<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>A folk shaped by water at display at Nature Centre Siida’s new exhibition — Siida</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2015</year><wordcount>743</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/a-folk-shaped-by-water-at-display-at-nature-centre-siida2019s-new-exhibition</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="veehisten-vki-esill-luontokeskus-siidan-uudessa-nyttelyss.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="ziid-veahka-ovdan-luondduguovdd-siidda-oa-jhusas.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
<p type="listitem">in English |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
</list><p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
<p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Sections</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Collections |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Nature services |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Restaurant |</p>
<p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
<p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
</list><p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
<p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p>Info</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">/</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
<p>A folk shaped by water at display at Nature Centre Siida’s new exhibition</p>
<p type="title">A folk shaped by water at display at Nature Centre Siida’s new exhibition</p>
<p>May 04, 2015 08:17 AM</p>
<p>The new exhibition of the Northern Lapland Nature Centre Siida, <span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">“A Folk Shaped by Water”</span>, consists of figures outlined in wood. During his canoeing trips in the wilderness of Vätsäri, Petri Nevalainen has collected, from the shores of Lake Inari, pieces of driftwood in which the eye can detect a range of figures. <span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">“A Folk Shaped by Water”</span>, a photography document on such pieces of wood, takes us on a trip to the wild world in which Nature keeps creating stories.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="fin">(c) Petri Nevalainen</p>
<p>Petri Nevalainen has been photographing all his life. He comes from the region of Pirkanmaa, and he has had exhibitions both in cities in the south of Finland and abroad. "A Folk Shaped by Water” exhibition has never been displayed before, but the choice of the exhibition venue was clear for the photographer all along.</p>
<p>- <span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">“A Folk Shaped by Water”</span> can really only start in Inari and Siida, Nevalainen says. He has worked on the exhibition for several years: he has looked for material on Lake Inari in summer and done the photographing in his studio. As a photographer, he is motivated among other things by the goal of producing good photographs that have a deeper aspect.</p>
<p>- I feel that a photo is a good one when it is intensive, Petri Nevalainen says. In the exhibition room, the audience will see intensive black-and-white photographs, some of which are bigger than a square metre.</p>
<p>From the very beginning, Petri Nevalainen has aimed at taking a stand through his exhibition.</p>
<p>- In our society, Nature is only considered as a storehouse of resources, and I wanted to bring forth my point of view, Nevalainen says. This is definitely an exhibition that takes a stand for Nature.</p>
<p>Nevalainen adds that, with his exhibition, he would like to have people wake up and have a moment of reflection.</p>
<p>People forget so easily all the things that there are in Nature. If we had time to stop for a while, we could see the world in a different way, Petri Nevalainen says.</p>
<p>Reflection does not demand very much in the beginning: one can, for example, start with the small and secure step of having a look at the exhibition. Looking at the figures, one can get new ideas and become interested in observing one’s own environment in a new way. The exhibition <span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">“A Folk Shaped by Water”</span> is available for the public at the Northern Lapland Nature Centre Siida from 1 May to late September.</p>
<p>More information: Northern Sámi Nature Centre, siida(a)metsa.fi, 0205 64 7740</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Metsähallitus Nature Centre, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)206 39 7740, siida@metsa.fi , www.siida.fi , www.luontoon.fi</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Document Actions</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Send this</p>
<p type="listitem">Print this</p>
</list><p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Contents</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
<p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="olo">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
<p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
<p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
<p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
<p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
<p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
<p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
<p>&gt; opening hours</p>
<p>&gt; tickets</p>
<p>&gt; contact information</p>
<p>&gt; location</p>
<p>&gt; guided tours</p>
<p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">|</p>
<p>photo gallery</p>
<p>tourist info</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
<p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">|</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
<p>Open original size in new window</p>
</body></document>
