<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>A Mapuche evening at Siida on Wednesday 14 March 2012  — Siida</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2012</year><wordcount>630</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/a-mapuche-evening-at-siida-on-wednesday-14-march-2012</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="mapuche-eahket-siiddas-gaskavahku-14.3.2012.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
<p type="listitem">in English |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
</list><p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
<p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Sections</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Collections |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Nature services |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Restaurant |</p>
<p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
<p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
</list><p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
<p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p>Info</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">/</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
<p>A Mapuche evening at Siida on Wednesday 14 March 2012</p>
<p type="title">A Mapuche evening at Siida on Wednesday 14 March 2012</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Mar 09, 2012 10:13 AM</p>
<p>Welcome to Siida to learn more about the life of the biggest indigenous population of Chile. Sirpa Kerman, the Executive Director of a Finnish child welfare association Parasta Lapsille ry, will tell about the conditions and everyday life of the Mapuche, an indigenous people in Chile. In 2007, 2008 and 2011, Kerman visited the area in which the association runs a campaign called <span type="quote">“Help a Mapuche Child”</span>.</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p><em type="italic">Parasta Lapsille ry </em>has worked in Chile for 30 years, helping – through Finnish sponsors – make it possible for children to go to school. From the year 2007 on, the aid has been directed at the Mapuche children of the county Tirua. The work is supported by the Foreign Ministry of Finland, but individual citizens, too, contribute through sponsoring children. </p>
<p>The Mapuche Evening is connected with the following exhibitions at Siida: <span type="quote">“Mapuche – The Seeds of Chile”</span> and the photography exhibition <span type="quote">“South of Biobío”</span> by Adolfo Vera.</p>
<p>The Mapuche are an indigenous people of approximately one million members in Southern Chile and Argentine. The name <span type="quote">“Mapuche”</span> comes from the words <em type="italic">mapu </em>(earth) and <em type="italic">che </em>(people). The Mapuche have their own language, Mapudungun, which has no official status. The Mapuche want to be recognized as a people and, thus, get their rights included in the constitution. They also want back their ancient lands and waters in order to manage them with respect for Nature. In addition, they want to participate in the development of society and to have their voice heard. At present, the Mapuche are struggling with both national and multinational companies. The struggle has led to serious confrontations and conflicts. Many Mapuche activists have got long prison sentences pursuant to a law on terrorism that was passed during the Pinochet Regime. </p>
<p>The Mapuche Evening is free for everyone, and it is arranged by the Sámi Museum Siida.</p>
<p>Further information: Sari Valkonen, Cultural Interpreter, +358 40 767 1052</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida - Sámi Museum and Nature Centre, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)400 898 212, www.siida.fi , siida@samimuseum.fi , siida@metsa.fi</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Document Actions</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Send this</p>
<p type="listitem">Print this</p>
</list><p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Contents</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
<p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="olo">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
<p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
<p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
<p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
<p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
<p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
<p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
<p>&gt; opening hours</p>
<p>&gt; tickets</p>
<p>&gt; contact information</p>
<p>&gt; location</p>
<p>&gt; guided tours</p>
<p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">|</p>
<p>photo gallery</p>
<p>tourist info</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
<p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">|</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
<p>Open original size in new window</p>
</body></document>
