<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>An exhibition of the Sámi Museum Siida to Naryan-Mar — Siida</title>
    <genre code="facta"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <year>2012</year>
    <wordcount>671</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <license type="standard"/>
    </availability>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/an-exhibition-of-the-smi-museum-siida-to-naryan-mar</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="saamelaismuseo-siidan-nyttely-narjan-mariin.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="smemusea-siidda-jhus-narjan-marii.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
      <p type="listitem">in English |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
    <p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Sections</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Collections |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Nature services |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Restaurant |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
    </list>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
    <p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Info</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">/</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
    <p>An exhibition of the Sámi Museum Siida to Naryan-Mar</p>
    <p type="title">An exhibition of the Sámi Museum Siida to Naryan-Mar</p>
    <p xml:lang="deu">Sep 05, 2012 02:50 PM</p>
    <p>The touring exhibition on Sámi handicraft produced by the Sámi Museum Siida will be displayed at Nenets Regional Museum in Naryan-Mar from September to the beginning of next year. Nenets culture, in turn, will be exhibited at Siida from February on.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>The exhibition <em type="italic">Sámi Duodji </em>of the Sámi Museum Siida will be opened at the Regional Museum of Nenets Autonomous Okrug on September 14th. The exhibition consists of today’s handicraft, or artefacts of <em type="italic">duodji </em>, that are part of the collections of the Sámi Museum. It displays, for example, handicrafts made from wood, root, antler and reindeer fur and skin as well as dresses, costumes and clothing accessories. The exhibition also contains a film produced by the Sámi Education Institute on how the Sámi wooden cup is made. <em type="italic"></em></p>
    <p>This exhibition exchange between two arctic museums that present two different nomadic cultures is realized as part of the project <em type="italic">Néda Ordym – Culture Tourism Project of the Indigenous Peoples of the North. </em>The Néda Ordym project that is coordinated by the Sámi Education Institute is implemented, in addition to the Sámi area, in two regions in the Russian Federation. The Néda part is carried out in Nenets Autonomous Okrug, wheras the Ordym part takes place in the Komi Republic. Both the word <em type="italic">néda </em>in the Nenets language and <em type="italic">ordym </em>in Komi mean a path, the migration route of reindeer. </p>
    <p>In the Néda Ordym project, tourism and cultural services are, through networking, product development and training, created, developed and marketed on an ethnically, ethically and ecologically sustainable basis from the perspective and the starting-points of indigenous peoples themselves. The Nenets part of the project has been funded by the European Union Kolarctic ENPI CBC programme; the activities in Komi, again, are part of Finland’s cooperation with neighbouring areas that is financed by the Finnish Foreign Ministry.</p>
    <p>The exhibition of the Sámi Museum Siida will be opened in Naryan-Mar on 14 Septemper, and it will be available for the public until 17 February 2013. An exhibition on Nenets culture from Nenets will be at display at Siida from 8 February to 26 May.</p>
    <p><em type="italic">Further information: </em>Arja Jomppanen, Head Curator, Sámi Museum Siida, arja.jomppanen(at)samimuseum.fi, tel. +358 (0)40 579 3313. </p>
    <p xml:lang="sme">Sámi museum, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)400 898 212, siida@samimuseum.fi , www.siida.fi</p>
    <p type="title">Document Actions</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">Send this</p>
      <p type="listitem">Print this</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Contents</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
    <p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
    <p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
    <p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="fin">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
    <p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
    <p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
    <p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
    <p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
    <p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
    <p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
    <p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
    <p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
    <p>&gt; opening hours</p>
    <p>&gt; tickets</p>
    <p>&gt; contact information</p>
    <p>&gt; location</p>
    <p>&gt; guided tours</p>
    <p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
    <p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">|</p>
    <p>photo gallery</p>
    <p>tourist info</p>
    <p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
    <p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
    <p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
    <p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">|</p>
    <p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
    <p>Open original size in new window</p>
  </body>
</document>
