<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Beaivváš. Beaivváš Sámi Našunálateáhter Teáhterbiktasat. Čájáhuslogahallan.</title><genre code="facta"/><author><person firstname="Veli-Pekka" lastname="Lehtola" sex="m" born="" nationality="FI"/></author><author><person firstname="Sigga-Marja" lastname="Magga" sex="f" born="" nationality="FI"/></author><year>2011</year><wordcount>3585</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual><language xml:lang="sme"/><language xml:lang="fin"/></multilingual><origFileName>https://www.veli-pekkalehtola.fi/UserFiles/files/Beaivvas_katalogi110508.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="beaivvas_biktasat.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="beaivvas_biktasat.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 161400 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>The first spark of interest to organize an exhibition display-ing the theatre costumes of Beaivváš Sámi National Theatre kindled in spring 2008 when Beaivváš performed Nils-Aslak</p>
<p>Valkeapää’s play <em type="italic">The Frost Haired and the Dream-seer </em>at the </p>
<p>Oulu City Theatre.</p>
<p>The costumes used in the play formed an impressive com-bination of the designs of traditional Sámi costumes and Ja-panese kimonos. The costumes shimmered with rich colours and appeared to be made out of heavy and expensive silk, the kind of fabric one would imagine to be used in an emperor’s court. The main character, the Frost Haired, had in the front of his costume a figure of a bear, embroidered with leather strips, taking one’s thoughts to the old bear mythology of the</p>
<p>Sámi. For a short moment, the performance opened up a view into the heart of the verbal and visual world of the Sámi, into the heart of theatre art.</p>
<p>The costume exhibition at the Siida Sámi Museum presents an overview of the significance of the theatre as a visual form of art, in which the costume designer acts as a mediator bet-ween the theatre performance and the audience.</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sigga-Marja Magga</p>
<p>Preface7</p>
<p>A group of young idealists formed a theatre company called Beaivváš in the winter of 1980–1981. Their aim was to produce one play, the <span type="quote" xml:lang="fin">”rock-yoik ope-ra”</span> <em type="italic">Min duoddarat </em>(Our Highlands) as an artistic uptake on the then ongoing dispute about the harnessing of the </p>
<p>Alta River for energy production. In the same way as the political strife, the play united ”us” and gave like-minded people a sense of solidarity and com-munity. At the same time, the Sámi were able to prove their strength also on stage, by means of an art form that was novel to them.</p>
<p>Two successful versions of the play</p>
<p><em type="italic">Min duoddarat </em>were made (1981 and 1983), establishing the group of per-formers as a theatre company and making it possible for them to produce a host of new plays. The theatre com-pany was awarded regular state fund-ing at the beginning of 1987, with a so-called trial period ( <em type="italic">proveperiod </em>) to see whether Beaivváš would qualify as a kind of regional theatre. In terms of art, the 1980s presented a productive pe-riod that was characterized by a search for <span type="quote" xml:lang="sme">”Sámi drama”</span>, the most appropriate forms of expression in art for the Sámi. </p>
<p>The primary aim of Beaivváš was to strengthen the Sámi language and iden-tity but, as in the production of <em type="italic">Min duoddarat </em>that was partly performed in two languages, Beaivváš also paid at-tention to its non-Sámi audience in its attempts to convince decision-makers of the necessity and proficiency of the theatre company. Music provided an obvious starting point simply because many of the actors had a background in music. Another point of departure was a pursuit of visuality, rather than drama dialogue. </p>
<p>Initially, the development of an ap-propriate form of theatrical expression was based on the ideal that only mate-rials produced by the Sámi themselves could convey what it means to be Sámi.</p>
<p>For example, <em type="italic">Vaikko čuođi stálu </em>(Even if a Hundred Ogres… 1985 and 1994–1995) depicted a thousand years of Sámi history, relying on the oral tradition and mythical characters. The musical <em type="italic">Luohti gomuvuođa salas </em>(A Yoik Nestled in </p>
<p>Infinity 1988) was based on the music skills of the Sámi (starring Mari Boine</p>
<p>Persen) and on a spectacular dance performance in a visually impressive setting. The children’s play <em type="italic">Máidnasat </em>(Sámi Fairytales 1989) transferred the rendering of a traditional tale to a new environment, outdoors on an icy lake. It was a presage of how the use of natural settings was to become a key compo-nent in the visual imagery of Beaivváš. </p>
<p>By the end of 1990, the theatre had pro-duced 19 plays in total.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Hamlet in a theatre of ice </em>In 1991, the state of Norway began to support Beaivváš financially as a per-manent theatre ( <em type="italic">fast teater </em>) and, a little later, Beaivváš was awarded the status of a national institution in Norway, al-beit the funding that it received never reached the level of even the smallest </p>
<p>Norwegian regional theatres. The es-tablishment of a full-time directorship reflected the growing professionalism of the theatre, leading to a sharp increase in the amount of productions. In the fol-lowing 15 years, Beaivváš had a total of 59 premieres—three times the amount that it produced in its first ten years.</p>
<p>The increase in the amount of pro-ductions was one explanation for why</p>
<p>Beaivváš began to gain a more diverse appearance. Sámi themes were no longer enough, and Beaivváš began to produce various drama classics, from Bertolt Brecht to Anton Chek-hov. Harriet Nordlund’s <em type="italic">Varraheajat </em>(Blood Wedding, 1989) was a pioneer: it presented a version of Federico Gar-cia Lorca’s classic that was only mildly adapted to the Sámi environment.11 </p>
<p>The Sámi theatre sought influences from other parts of the world, too. In</p>
<p xml:lang="sme"><em type="italic">Narukámi </em>(1991), director Haukur J. </p>
<p>Gunnarsson brought together Japa-nese drama and Sámi actors to create a new form of visual expression that was characterized by stylized movement and pantomime. In the same vein, Nor-dlund directed a version of <em type="italic">Boaresbárt-nit </em>(Batchelors 1995) that dealt with the relationships between men and women by means of Japanese popular comedy and Sámi storytelling. Japa-nese influence has later been strongly present in, for instance, the production of the plays <em type="italic">Ridn’oaivi ja nieguid oaidni </em>(The Frost Haired and the Dream-seer 2007) and <em type="italic">Nikio </em>(2008). </p>
<p>In the 1990s, the visual appearance of</p>
<p>Beaivváš was also increasingly shaped by the setting that was provided by its northern surroundings, i.e. the use of natural settings as an important part of set design and even of the dramatic development of a play. A joint produc-tion of <em type="italic">Sezuan </em>(The Good Person of </p>
<p>Szechwan) by several theatres in the</p>
<p>North was performed in a theatre of ice, setting Bertolt Brecht’s critical re-flection on the wretchedness of people into an arctic community and into the harsh cold. Artist Aage Gaup designed a stage setting of ice, parts of which had already sunk before the perform-ance could be finalized.</p>
<p>In plays written by Sámi, the juxta-position of the Sámi and the majority population were gradually set aside.</p>
<p>More attention was given to problems within the Sámi community. Inger</p>
<p>Margrethe Olsen’s plays, for example, often addressed sensitive issues of the</p>
<p>Sámi community, such as prejudice against homosexuality ( <em type="italic">Earalágan </em>- </p>
<p>Different 1992), or the mechanisms of violence ( <em type="italic">Skoavdnji </em>- Bogey 1994). </p>
<p>History became another focus of</p>
<p>Sámi writers’ literary production in the 1990s. Their plays explored the his-tory of civilization in the Sápmi area ( <em type="italic">Gumpegoddi </em>- Wolf Hunter, <em type="italic">Prinsen of </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Lappland </em>- Prince of Lapland, Okto - </p>
<p>Alone), political history ( <em type="italic">Eatni váibmu vardá </em>– The Mother’s Heart Bleeds), the impacts of war on the Sámi com-munity ( <em type="italic">Kiögg kå´kke / Giegat guhkket </em>- Cuckoos Call 1994) or the traumatic recent past of the Sámi ( <em type="italic">Internáhtta </em>– </p>
<p>Dormitory 2003). Additionally, there were cabarets, which were particularly common during Alex Scherpf’s term as director. The cabaret <em type="italic">Giđđadulvi </em>(Spring Flood) became a popular se-ries that pondered local and global is-sues in the form of a café theatre. </p>
<p>Theatrical performances involving snow and ice became even more of a trademark for the Sámi theatre as</p>
<p><em type="italic">Vølundda muitalus </em>(The Lay of Vol-und, 2000) continued the series of monumental outdoor performances. </p>
<p>The zenith of such development can be considered to be the collaborative ef-forts of Beaivváš and the Sámi theatre in Kiruna that presented Shakespeare’s</p>
<p><em type="italic">Macbeth </em>and later <em type="italic">Hamlet </em>on a stage made out of snow and ice on the shore of Lake Jukkasjärvi. It was built accord-ing to Shakespeare’s Globe Theatre. </p>
<p>Outstanding works in world literature were subjected to various adaptations in the 1990s. In addition to adaptations of texts by Anton Chekhov, Nikolai Gogol and F. G. Lorca, Beaivváš drew on the</p>
<p>Bible to present Job, who complained to a (female!) God about his troubles, as well as on Ludvig Holberg to introduce the drunkard Jeppe, whose misadven-tures seemed to be written for the grand old man of Sámi actors, Nils Utsi, as his bravura pieces. J. W. Goethe’s <em type="italic">Faust </em>(2004), who devours experience and knowledge of the world, was brought to the modern day and the arctic environ-ment with the help of visually impres-sive costume and set design. </p>
<p>Under Scherp’s direction, Shake-speare’s characters from Romeo and</p>
<p>Juliet to Macbeth dashed onto the Sámi stage — as clowns! Instead of the Capu-let and Montague families, Sámi sports clubs faced each other in mortal battle, or at least tried to: the battle was dis-tracted by the fact that the opponents were clowns who wore silly costumes, moved jerkily, spoke with a shrill voice and made vain attempts at hitting one another. Once again, Beaivváš was contested in the press: what was appro-priate for Sámi theatre?</p>
<p>The literary classics were counter-balanced by <span type="quote">”authentic”</span> forms of Sámi theatre, musicals that were largely based on the works of well-known 17</p>
<p>Sámi artists. They combined yoik with techno and didgeridoos with synthe-sizers; produced yoik and dance con-certs under the northern lights and brought music into pubs and cafés.</p>
<p>Another long-standing genre was chil-dren’s plays in which the Sámi tradi-tion of fairy tales and stories continued to have a firm hold. The myths of other indigenous peoples were also drawn upon, for example, in the play <em type="italic">Allaq </em>(2010) written by Cecilia Persson. </p>
<p><em type="bold">Polyphony of influences </em>It is possible to detect in the develop-ment of Beaivváš features that are also characteristic to other forms of Sámi art. The first decade presented a phase of nationality during which the topics and themes were to a great extent tied together with the development of a na-tional identity. The contrast between <span type="quote">”us” and ”the others”</span> ran through the plays. Theatre, among other things, set a scene for struggles concerning Sámi identity and self-image. </p>
<p>Nevertheless, drama, by its nature, speaks with many voices. Theatre workers see themselves as heirs to a lively storytelling tradition. In addition to the Sámi background, Beaivváš has gathered strength in world literature, theatre traditions of indigenous peoples and oriental drama. Multiculturalism has been present in the theatre’s staff, which has included members of Sámi origin who have come from across the</p>
<p>Sámi area as well as representatives of the majority population.</p>
<p>Beaivváš Sámi National Theatre has always addressed two audiences. It has attracted both Sámi and non-Sámi au-diences, spectators who know Sámi as well as those who do not understand the language spoken on stage but who can nonetheless empathize with the emotional atmosphere of a play. This double communication has been neces-sary because the theatre has been faced with the task of not only constructing</p>
<p>Sámi identity but also influencing the image that outsiders have of the Sámi.</p>
<p>A more practical aim has been to con-vince decision-makers of the necessity of a Sámi theatre.</p>
<p>Throughout its history, Beaivváš Sámi</p>
<p>National Theatre has had to struggle with challenges of a small institutional-ized theatre. The financial support pro-vided by the state is barely enough for the production of 2–3 premieres a year and for the running of a tour. Only 4–5 actors have a permanent contract with the theatre, and it is hard to organize enough training for them. The theatre has difficulties in getting young people interested in theatre and in recruiting new actors. Nevertheless, the theatre should be able to develop, to uphold a lively and interactive connection to the audience.</p>
<p>Especially in the case of young spec-tators, the theatre has to compete with many influential forms of art, such as documentary films at present. Beaivváš 21</p>
<p>Along with staging and lighting, theat-re costumes form an integral part of the visual narrative of theatre that unders-cores the time and place in which the play is set as well as the disposition of the characters. Theatre costumes may be inconspicuous so that spectators do not pay any special attention to them.</p>
<p>In a sense, they may then blend in with the setting, although every single gar-ment in a play is usually chosen with great care and a particular purpose in mind. Theatre costumes may also stand out and sometimes even steal the show, so that visual storytelling takes prece-dence over verbal drama. At their best, however, theatre costumes carry the spectators into the depths of the story and lead them into the inner world of the characters in the play.</p>
<p>Theatre costumes are an illusion. A costume may not necessarily be what it seems to be in the eyes of the audi-ence. The glimmer and glitter may not originate in brocade or silk adorned with golden threads, but in quite ordi-nary materials that turn into diamonds and spangles when caught in a certain light. A shimmering silver crown may be made out of silver-painted door handles, as was the elder’s crown in the play Allaq. It may also seem that putting on an impressive, voluminous costume takes a lot of time, but it may in effect be put on with one pull of a zipper. An actor may have many roles in one play and the costumes may dif-fer greatly from one role to another.</p>
<p>There may thus be another perform-ance taking place behind the stage, as costumers and their assistants dress and undress actors during a play.</p>
<p>Many theatres struggle with finan-cial issues and visuality has to give way to economy. On the other hand, that is characteristic of theatre because theatre is the art of passing moments . Every play is a unique event although the details have been polished to create an effec-tive whole. Creativity in coming up with technical solutions also gives freedom and forms part of the theatre’s charm; how easy it all seems and how extremely inventive theatre workers can be.</p>
<p>Beaivváš Sámi National Theatre is known for its impressive and appeal-ing theatre costumes, which have been created by costume designer Berit</p>
<p>Marit Hætta. She is a <em type="italic">duojár </em>(Sámi craftsmaker), an artist, an illustrator and a designer of theatre costumes. </p>
<p>Since 1980, Hætta has illustrated doz-ens of Sámi-language children’s books, schoolbooks and collections of poems; designed covers and produced other graphic materials. She has worked as a freelance costume designer for</p>
<p>Beaivváš Sámi Teahter since 1993. She has also designed theatre costumes for Hålogaland Theatre, the regional theatre in Tromsø. In 2000, Berit Marit</p>
<p>Hætta and sculptor, set designer Aage</p>
<p>Gaup received the Hedda Award, the</p>
<p>Norwegian theatre award, for best cos-tume and set design, for their work in the Beaivváš Sámi Teahter outdoor production <em type="italic">The Lay of Volund </em>. </p>
<p><em type="bold">Gákti suits the stage </em>Beaivváš Sámi National Theatre finds its inspiration not only in the Sámi culture but also in the cultures of ot-her indigenous peoples and ethnic mi-norities. Nonetheless, traditional Sámi clothing forms the foundation of cos-tume design for Beaivváš. Through the use of costumes, classic drama can be transferred into a Sámi setting or, vice versa, Sámi themes can be set in count-ries far away, even beyond dreams. The costume designer is involved in the production of a play throughout the process. She acquaints herself with the script and constructs the mood of the play and the disposition of the charac-ters together with the director, set de-signer, lighting designer and costume maker. Costumes develop into their final form during the rehearsals, where the functionality of the costumes is put into test when they are actually worn by the actors, and when viewed in rela-tion to the setting. </p>
<p>The ways in which Sámi garments are designed and cut date back to times when clothing materials consisted mainly of reindeer skin in its different forms. The same patterns and cuts that were used when winter garments were still made out of reindeer hide are now used in garments that are made out of woven fabric and are known as the tra-ditional Sámi costume, gákti. The Sámi clothing tradition has not broken off at any point in history but has carried over centuries, simply taking on new forms.</p>
<p>The natural shape of reindeer hide and reindeer leg skins determines how they are best cut to make fur coats, gaiters and shoes. In former times, and also today, the cut and sewing is measured by spans and by the eye be-cause every material and every piece of clothing is unique. Berit Marit Hætta says that as a duojár she feels that it is 27natural first to make test pieces of her own designs. In this way, she is able to make sure that every costume is feasi-ble in practice. It is also important that the costume makers and the designer have a common understanding of a costume at all stages of its production.</p>
<p>Sámi garments have been made for everyday and work use and, because of their practicality, they form a sound basis for theatre costumes. It is easy to make the back, front or sleeves of a fur coat or a gákti wider or narrower to fit an actor’s build. Performances that contain a lot of moving about or danc-ing call for light, loose and breathable costumes. Plays that are performed in a theatre of ice make it necessary that the costumes used are warm and water-repellent, and that enough many ther-mal layers can be worn under the outer garments. For instance, the play <em type="italic">Hamlet </em>was performed outdoors in mid-winter, when the temperature dropped to near-ly -30 Celsius degrees, so the costumes had to be well insulated. </p>
<p>In addition to their practicality, Sámi garments are easily adaptable to other cultures, as Berit Marit Hætta points out. Good examples of that adaptability are <em type="italic">The Frost Haired and the Dream-seer </em>, in which the costumes were de-signed to fit Japanese culture, and </p>
<p><em type="italic">Hamlet </em>, in which the costumes were used to set the story in Mongolia. In-deed, theatre costumes gain even more meaning when considered in the light of the dual purpose that Beaivváš Thea-tre typically serves. From the very be-ginning, the aim of the Sámi theatre has been to strengthen Sámi language and identity, with an additional aim of in-forming others about the Sámi culture and mindset. In using the Sámi lan-guage, Beaivváš has acquainted Sámi with various theatre traditions from across the world, such as the European and Japanese traditions. In using strong visual imagery, it has created a form of expression that appeals also to those who do not understand Sámi. </p>
<p>According to Berit Marit Hætta, adapting classic drama to the Sámi culture is easier than one would first imagine. Classics in world literature and drama usually deal with universal human themes and emotions, such as love and hate, that are common to all cultures and touch people all over the world. Sometimes the themes of a play deal with topics that may seem foreign to the costume designer, in which case it may be better to set the events away from Sámi culture. For example, in</p>
<p><em type="italic">Hamlet </em>, Hætta set the themes of malice and violence as far away from the Sámi as possible, all the way to Asia. </p>
<p><em type="bold">Costumes comment and communicate </em>Theatre-goers observe the performan-ce, movement and dialogue of the ac-tors as well as the functioning of the set design. Even if they would not under-stand a word of the language spoken in the play, spectators are able to empat-hize with the characters. The costumes used in a theatre performance may help in interpreting the main story, or they may narrate a story of their own. </p>
<p>Stories told by the costumes may, for example, comment on the problems of poverty, as can be seen in the costumes of the play <em type="italic">Allaq </em>. </p>
<p>Berit Marit Hætta reports how the costumes of the characters in <em type="italic">Allaq </em>were sometimes criticized for being so clean and decorative although the sto-ry was set after a natural disaster and the characters had lost everything that they had had. Hætta tells that on her travels across the world she also vis-ited countries in great material need. </p>
<p>She noticed that people nonetheless wanted to dress well and wear beauti-ful clothes, so as to show that they were not giving into poverty although there was not much that they could do about it. What they could do was to maintain their dignity and pride, their only pos-sessions in extreme poverty.</p>
<p>Sometimes Sámi craftspeople may come to see a performance simply to wonder at the new creations of the cos-tume designer. Their interest is based on the fact that Berit Marit Hætta has the ability to design costumes that highlight distinct elements of different cultures and make them visible even to those sitting on the back row of the auditorium. The impact of theatre on the development of the Sámi culture is indisputable. It has especially influ-enced the identity and self-esteem of</p>
<p>Sámi youth. The costumes of Beaivváš</p>
<p>Sámi Teahter, which draw extensively on the cultures of other arctic peoples, can be considered a form of art that unites indigenous peoples. The theatre mediates between different cultures and encourages people to learn from one another, develop themselves and sometimes even distance themselves from their traditions.</p>
<p>Berit Marit Hætta is of the opin-ion that young people have found the courage to play with different materials and designs. They are increasingly test-ing the boundaries between tradition and modernity. She notes, however, that the cultural heritage of the Sámi is such that it cannot be mixed with our illusions. That heritage is fragile and vulnerable to outside influences and should therefore be cherished with care. On the other hand, she admits that the theatre is free to paint new landscapes and create new images of our culture and, therefore, it also has the possibility to provide us with al-ternative interpretations of the reality around us.</p>
</body></document>
