<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Far Away in the North - A journey into nature with pictures and music — Siida</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2014</year><wordcount>766</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/far-away-in-the-north-a-journey-into-nature-with-pictures-and-music</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="kaukana-pohjoisessa-kuvakonsertin-ennakkolipunmyynti-on-alkanut.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="guhkkin-davvin-govvakonseartta-ovdabileahtaid-vuovdin-lea-lgn.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
<p type="listitem">in English |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
</list><p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
<p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Sections</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Collections |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Nature services |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Restaurant |</p>
<p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
<p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
</list><p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
<p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Info</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">/</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
<p>Far Away in the North - A journey into nature with pictures and music</p>
<p type="title">Far Away in the North - A journey into nature with pictures and music</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Sep 02, 2014 07:40 AM</p>
<p>Two traditional Inari events, Camera Borealis and Kaamosjazz, have joined forces to organise a picture concert at the Saami Cultural Centre Sajos in November. The concert <span type="quote">“Far away in the North – a journey into nature with pictures and music”</span> features a performance in which photographs by nature photographer Martti Rikkonen are shown to the accompaniment of live music by the Saami artist Niillas Holmberg. The concert kicks off with a treat in the form of excerpts from the repertoire of Simon Lynge, an Inuit musician from Greenland.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Niillas Holmberg is a Sámi poet, musician and actor from Utsjoki. His ensemble consists of multi-instrumentalists Roope Mäenpää, Linda Fredriksson and Teho Majamäki. The concert will feature Arctic folk music in the Northern Sámi language. Niillas Holmberg Kvarteahtta's music reflects the beauty and roughness of Northern nature, the Sámi beliefs and philosophy of life, and astonishment at the endless need of Western people to own things.</p>
<p>Martti Rikkonen is a distinguished nature photographer and nature expert, who has put down roots in Inari. For him, nature photography was initially a young boy's hobby that evolved over the years into a profession. Today, Rikkonen is a renowned master of nature photography, who has won acclaim in various arenas including two wins in the Nature Photograph of the Year contest. Rikkonen has been the artistic director of the Camera Borealis event throughout its history. The picture concert displays fantastic photographs of Northern nature taken through the course of his diverse career.</p>
<p>The concert begins at 17:30 on Saturday November 22 nd , 2014 in the Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos in Inari. Advance tickets are available from Siida, Sajos and the www. lipputoimisto.fi service, and also from Metsähallitus’ Customer Services Saariselkä and Ivalo. Ticket prices: €25 in advance and €30 at the entrance. Transport will be provided from Saariselkä and Ivalo. To be sure of a seat, please buy your ticket in advance at Metsähallitus' Saariselkä Customer Service Kiehinen or Ivalo Customer Service. Transport price €10.</p>
<p>The concert Far away in the North – a journey into nature in pictures and music, will also be broadcast in livestream to the Finnish Nature Centre Haltia in Espoo.</p>
<p>After the picture concert, the evening will continue at Kultahovi in Hotel Inari with the Camera Borealis &amp; Greenland Eyes Jam Session featuring Simon Lynge's melodies. The Greenland Eyes film festival brings Lynge, a superstar in his native Greenland, to Inari. Entrance to The Jam Session is free of charge.</p>
<p>The Camera Borealis event is organised by Metsähallitus Northern Lapland Nature Centre Siida and Inari-Saariselkä Tourism Ltd is responsible for the Kaamosjazz event.</p>
<p>For further information, please contact: Kirsi Ukkonen, kirsi.ukkonen(a)metsa.fi or +358 400 479 986</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Metsähallitus Nature Centre, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)206 39 7740, siida@metsa.fi , www.siida.fi , www.luontoon.fi</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Document Actions</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Send this</p>
<p type="listitem">Print this</p>
</list><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Contents</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
<p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="fin">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
<p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
<p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
<p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
<p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
<p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
<p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
<p>&gt; opening hours</p>
<p>&gt; tickets</p>
<p>&gt; contact information</p>
<p>&gt; location</p>
<p>&gt; guided tours</p>
<p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">|</p>
<p>photo gallery</p>
<p>tourist info</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
<p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">|</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
<p>Open original size in new window</p>
</body></document>
