<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Gállok Protest Art – Protest Art from Kallak 13.6.–21.9.2014  — Siida</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2014</year><wordcount>709</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/gllok-protest-art-2013-protest-art-from-kallak-13.6.201321.9.2014</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="gllok-protest-art-protestitaidetta-kallakista-siidassa-13.6.-21.9.2014.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="gllok-protest-art-2013-proteastadidda-gllokis-oaidninlhkai-siiddas-13.6.-21.9.2014.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
<p type="listitem">in English |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
</list><p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
<p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Sections</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Collections |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Nature services |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Restaurant |</p>
<p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
<p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
</list><p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
<p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Info</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">/</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Gállok Protest Art – Protest Art from Kallak 13.6.–21.9.2014</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="deu">Gállok Protest Art – Protest Art from Kallak 13.6.–21.9.2014</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Jun 10, 2014 02:44 PM</p>
<p>Art is a means of being in contact with and taking a stand on what is going on. The latest temporary exhibition of the Sámi Museum Siida, Gállok Protest Art, presents the audience with Sámi protest art. Gállok Protest Art consists of art that has been produced at the road blockade on the way to a mining site in Gállok, Sweden. The paintings, signs, installations and banderols of the exhibition take a stand and deal with a topical theme.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Artists participated actively in a demonstration against mining at Camp Gállok in the neighbourhood of Jokkmokk, Sweden, in the summer of 2013. The camp was set up when the mining company JIMAB began logging in the area where test drilling for a mine would be done. With the logging operations, the first activists arrived at the site.</p>
<p>The camp grew into an international meeting place where the opponents of the mine, conservationists and Sámi fought together against the planned mining operations. In July and August, several cultural events were arranged at Kamp Gállok; they included, for example, an art workshop. It was attended by Sámi artists such as Anders Sunna, Jenni Laiti and Lena Viltok, and activists from the camp. The paintings, signs and installations by the blockade on the road to the mine in Gállok evolved into a big work of art.</p>
<p>When Kamp Gállok was taken down in the autumn, the artist collective tucked away the signs, banderols and installations; the road blockade by the camp was on its way from the forest road to galleries. Prior to Siida, Gállok Protest Art has been exhibited in Jokkmokk, Umeå, Luleå and Nikkaluokta. The Sámi artist Anders Sunna said at the opening of the exhibition in Jokkmokk in September 2013: <em type="italic"><span type="quote">“This is a way of fighting back, this is what our creative resistance looks like.”</span> </em></p>
<p>The struggle over Gállok is one of the most important fights over Sámi rights today. It has given more force to Sámi culture and art, and we can also see this in the Gállok Protest Art exhibition. In the spheres of art and culture, Sámi resistance against mining continues to be strong. Several new cultural events will be arranged in Gállok in the summer of 2014.</p>
<p>Gállok Protest Art – Protest Art from Kallak is open for the public in Siida from 13 June to 21 September 2014. Siida is open in summer from 9 a.m. to 8 p.m.</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sámi museum, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)400 898 212, siida@samimuseum.fi , www.siida.fi</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Document Actions</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Send this</p>
<p type="listitem">Print this</p>
</list><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Contents</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
<p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="fin">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
<p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
<p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
<p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
<p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
<p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
<p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
<p>&gt; opening hours</p>
<p>&gt; tickets</p>
<p>&gt; contact information</p>
<p>&gt; location</p>
<p>&gt; guided tours</p>
<p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">|</p>
<p>photo gallery</p>
<p>tourist info</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
<p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">|</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
<p>Open original size in new window</p>
</body></document>
