<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>"I Will Fly So Far" - Merja Aletta Ranttila's Art — Siida</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2012</year><wordcount>760</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/i-will-fly-so-far-merja-aletta-ranttilas-art</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="201cniin-kauas-min-lennn201d-merja-aletta-ranttilan-taidenyttely.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="201cnu-guhks-mun-girddn201d-merja-aletta-ranttila-diddajhus.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
<p type="listitem">in English |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
</list><p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
<p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Sections</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Collections |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Nature services |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Restaurant |</p>
<p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
<p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
</list><p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
<p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p>Info</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">/</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><span type="quote">"I Will Fly So Far"</span> - Merja Aletta Ranttila's Art</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fin"><span type="quote">"I Will Fly So Far"</span> - Merja Aletta Ranttila's Art</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Oct 12, 2012 10:40 AM</p>
<p>Merja Aletta Ranttila is a Sámi artist, printmaker and illustrator. On Friday 12 October, a solo exhibition by Ranttila will be opened at the Sámi Museum Siida in Inari in honour of her 30th anniversary as an artist. The exhibition in Inari is special also because Ranttila lives in Inari and is, as an artist, known and well appreciated in the area.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Merja Aletta Ranttila: <span type="quote">"I will Fly so Far"</span>. Siida.</p>
<p>Merja Aletta Ranttila was born into a Sámi family of five children in Karigasniemi, Utsjoki, in 1960. Going to a residential school where she was bullied and the Laestadian religion that made her feel guilty left their mark on a girl about to turn into a young woman. In 1980, Ranttila was accepted into and began studying at the Art School of Lapland in Tornio. After graduating, she continued her studies at Rovaniemi Arts and Crafts College, studying graphic design from 1982 to 1986.</p>
<p>At the beginning of her career, Merja Aletta Ranttila got her income from illustrations to textbooks, children’s books and novels and collections of short stories. Ranttila was especially commissioned to make illustrations on Sámi themes. She found her own artistic expression in the early 1990s when she began using lino cutting. The technique enabled her to make, on white, stylised and pitch black silhouette forms that she complemented by painting colour surfaces on them.</p>
<p>Ranttila’s breakthrough into public awareness took place in 1993, when her work was presented at the Aine Art Museum in connection with the triennal art exhibition of the Shaman Summer in Tornio in the south-western corner of Lapland. The devils that haunted pained female figures were disapproved by the clergymen of the north, and the artist was accused of Satanism and shamanism.</p>
<p>After the gloomy works of her initial years as an artist, Merja Aletta Ranttila has started to give her works lighter tones, too, but – even then – there is often a dark shadow flickering in the background. Her art also shows humoristic and mischievous features. The many self-portraits of the artist reflect the soul-searching Ranttila has done in her life.</p>
<p>In recognition of her work, Merja Aletta Ranttila has received, for example, the State Award in Children’s Culture (1993), the Art Prize of Urpo and Maija Lahtinen Foundation (1994) and the Cultural Prize of the Sámi Parliament (2000). Her works of art are included in many distinguished collections, and her art has been displayed in numerous exhibitions both in Finland and abroad. Ranttila lives and works in Inari.</p>
<p>Exhibition will be open from oct 12, 2012 until jan 27, 2013.</p>
<p xml:lang="smn"><em type="italic">Further information: </em>Merja Aletta Ranttila, aletta(at)mbnet.fi, and Senior Curator Arja Jomppanen, Sámi Museum Siida, tel. +358 40 579 3313, arja.jomppanen(at)samimuseum.fi </p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sámi museum, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)400 898 212, siida@samimuseum.fi , www.siida.fi</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Document Actions</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Send this</p>
<p type="listitem">Print this</p>
</list><p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Contents</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
<p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="olo">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
<p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
<p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
<p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
<p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
<p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
<p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
<p>&gt; opening hours</p>
<p>&gt; tickets</p>
<p>&gt; contact information</p>
<p>&gt; location</p>
<p>&gt; guided tours</p>
<p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">|</p>
<p>photo gallery</p>
<p>tourist info</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
<p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">|</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
<p>Open original size in new window</p>
</body></document>
