<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Sámi Museum Siida was after all granted a subsidy for its activities by the municipality of Inari  — Siida</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2013</year><wordcount>722</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/smi-museum-siida-was-after-all-granted-a-subsidy-for-its-activities-by-the-municipality-of-inari</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="saamelaismuseo-siida-sai-takaisin-inarin-kunnan-toiminta-avustuksen.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="smemusea-siida-oaui-ruovttoluotta-anra-gieldda-doaibmadoarjaga.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
<p type="listitem">in English |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
</list><p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
<p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Sections</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Collections |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Nature services |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Restaurant |</p>
<p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
<p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
</list><p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
<p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p>Info</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">/</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
<p>Sámi Museum Siida was after all granted a subsidy for its activities by the municipality of Inari</p>
<p type="title">Sámi Museum Siida was after all granted a subsidy for its activities by the municipality of Inari</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Sep 12, 2013 08:15 PM</p>
<p>In its meeting on Thursday, the municipality council of Inari amended the budget proposal for 2014 so that the Sámi Museum Siida will be granted a subsidy for its activities. The personnel of the Sámi Museum are happy about the strong backup and support that the local community has given to the museum. The personnel also promise to work with a will in future for the subsidy.</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p>The municipal executive board proposed that the annual subsidy granted to the Sámi Museum be halved in 2014 and axed totally in 2015 as part of the municipality’s programme for a controlled increase of the municipality’s expenses. However, the council voted against the board’s proposal in its meeting on 12 September. Thus, the Sámi Museum will at least next year get a subsidy that is of the same size as the one granted to it in recent years.</p>
<p>Tarmo Jomppanen, the Director of the Sámi Museum Siida, and the personnel of the museum are delighted by the positive decision. – Getting the subsidy in future, too, encourages and motivates us to continue working effectively for Sámi culture and tourism, Jomppanen says. The employees of the museum are above all happy about the strong support that the museum got from the local community in this issue; this support is thought to have influenced the opinion of the decision-makers.</p>
<p>The subsidy of 50,000 euros for the activities of the museum that the municipality has granted every year is very important for the Sámi Museum, as it makes it possible for the museum to run a number of local activities. For example, through the subsidy the museum can continue to run the Skolt Sámi Heritage House in Sevettijärvi, provide pedagogic services for children under school age and schoolchildren at the museum, and offer cultural stimuli for people of all ages.</p>
<p>Before the council meeting, there was a lively public discussion on the significance of the Sámi Museum Siida and on how necessary the subsidy is for it. After following the discussion, Director Jomppanen sees that there is also room for self-criticism at the museum. The discussion showed that not everyone in the area knows enough about the variety of activities the museum runs. In future, the Sámi Museum is going to invite employees and elected officials of the municipality to come to Inari and acquaint themselves with the activities and events taking place at the museum.</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sámi museum, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)400 898 212, siida@samimuseum.fi , www.siida.fi</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Document Actions</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Send this</p>
<p type="listitem">Print this</p>
</list><p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Contents</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
<p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="olo">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
<p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
<p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
<p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
<p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
<p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
<p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
<p>&gt; opening hours</p>
<p>&gt; tickets</p>
<p>&gt; contact information</p>
<p>&gt; location</p>
<p>&gt; guided tours</p>
<p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">|</p>
<p>photo gallery</p>
<p>tourist info</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
<p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">|</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
<p>Open original size in new window</p>
</body></document>
