<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Sámi Museum Siida Gets the Green Year Medal — Siida</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2016</year><wordcount>640</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/smi-museum-siida-gets-the-green-year-medal</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="saamelaismuseo-siidalle-on-mynnetty-vihervuoden-mitali.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
<p type="listitem">in English |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
</list><p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
<p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Sections</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Collections |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Nature services |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Restaurant |</p>
<p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
<p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
</list><p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
<p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p>Info</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">/</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Siida Gets the Green Year Medal</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Siida Gets the Green Year Medal</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Jun 02, 2016 11:10 AM</p>
<p>The main event of the Green Year, a thematic year arranged by the Ministry of the Environment, will take place on 2 June 2016 in Hämeenlinna, which spotlights nature and water this year. The day begins with a seminar with invited guests; the themes of the seminar are the relationship between the private and the public in a sustainable landscape, strategies on cultural environments, future urban cultivation, as well as local topics. After the seminar, the audience will be introduced to the subthemes of the Green Year in parks, and there will be a summer celebration for the public at the Market Place.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p>This year, the Green Year Medal is awarded to the Sámi Museum Siida from Inari. The decision about the recipient is made by the Medal Committee, presently chaired by former president Tarja Halonen. The medals have been donated by the group Asuntosäätiö, and they are granted during each Green Year. The first medals were awarded in 1985, the first Green Year.</p>
<p><em type="bold">The Committee’s grounds for granting the medal to Siida are: </em></p>
<p>The Green Year 2016, Medal No.215</p>
<p>The Sámi Museum Siida has worked for Sámi cultural heritage in a determined and praiseworthy way. Through its varied research, information and exhibition activities, Siida has succeeded in increasing appreciation for Sámi culture to a great extent as well as raising the general awareness of matters concerning this culture everywhere in Finland.</p>
<p>The surveys on nationally valuable landscape areas carried out by Siida in Northern Lapland make Sámi cultural landscapes an important part of the diversity of Finnish cultural landscapes.</p>
<p>At the same time, the Sámi Museum Siida has successfully opened up and renewed the entire concept of cultural landscape even internationally by establishing concretely and extensively the cultural and spiritual meaning of the nature-based indigenous livelihoods and their connection to landscapes.</p>
<p>More information:</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Seppo Närhi, Head secretary, Vihreäympäristöliitto ry, tel. +358(0)400 41908</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sari Valkonen, Museum Director Sámi Museum Siida, tel. +358(0)40 767 1052</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Päivi Magga, researcher Sámi Museum Siida, tel. +358(0) 40 180 1501</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">www.vihervuosi.fi/content/fi/1030/21981/</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sámi museum, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)400 898 212, siida@samimuseum.fi , www.siida.fi</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Document Actions</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Send this</p>
<p type="listitem">Print this</p>
</list><p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Contents</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
<p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="olo">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
<p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
<p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
<p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
<p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
<p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
<p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
<p>&gt; opening hours</p>
<p>&gt; tickets</p>
<p>&gt; contact information</p>
<p>&gt; location</p>
<p>&gt; guided tours</p>
<p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">|</p>
<p>photo gallery</p>
<p>tourist info</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
<p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">|</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
<p>Open original size in new window</p>
</body></document>
