<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>The Sámi Museum starts with exhibitions in Utsjoki — Siida</title>
    <genre code="facta"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <year>2012</year>
    <wordcount>619</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <license type="standard"/>
    </availability>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/the-smi-museum-starts-with-exhibitions-in-utsjoki</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="saamelaismuseo-aloittaa-nyttelytoiminnan-utsjoella.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="smemusea-lggaha-jhusdoaimma-ohcejogas.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
      <p type="listitem">in English |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
    <p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Sections</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Collections |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Nature services |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Restaurant |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
    </list>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
    <p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Info</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">/</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
    <p>The Sámi Museum starts with exhibitions in Utsjoki</p>
    <p type="title">The Sámi Museum starts with exhibitions in Utsjoki</p>
    <p>Apr 19, 2012 06:15 PM</p>
    <p>The Ailigas Science and Art Centre in Utsjoki will have its doors open for the public two days a week from 19 April 2012 on. On 19 April, facilities for the Sámi Museum Siida’s changing exhibitions will also be opened in the Ailigas Centre. The exhibitions of the Sámi Museum will begin with <span type="quote" xml:lang="sme">“A Sámi – That’s It!”</span>, an exhibition which introduces the audience to the results of the Nordic Sámi Youth project.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>The Ailigas Science and Art Centre – located in an old, cultural-historically valuable school building in Utsjoki – contains exhibition facilities for the Sámi Museum Siida, an exhibition of educational material produced by the Sámi Parliament, facilities for crafting and other activities, and three offices that can be rented. The other building on the premises, on the other side of the yard, still needs repairing. There are plans to have, for example, activities of a Sámi language centre and a handicraft shop in it.</p>
    <p>In line with the exhibition policy of the Sámi Museum Siida, the exhibitions in the Ailigas Centre, too, will focus on displaying Sámi culture. The first exhibition, <span type="quote" xml:lang="sme">“A Sámi – That’s It!”</span> , is based on a documentation project that Nordic Sámi museums ran together with Sámi young people. Siida contributed to the project by engaging Sámi young people who lived outside the official Sámi area in the documentation. In the exhibition, the young tell about their lives and attitudes to being Sámi through texts, pictures and films that they have made themselves.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">From 19 April 2012 on, the Ailigas Science and Art Centre is open for the public on Tuesdays and Thursdays from 2 to 6 p.m. Entrance to the exhibition is free. </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="vep">Welcome!</p>
    <p><em type="bold">More information: </em>Eeva-Maarit Aikio, Development and Business Manager, Utsjoki Municipality, tel. +358 (0)400 151 294, eeva-maarit.aikio(at)utsjoki.fi </p>
    <p><em type="bold">Inquiries about exhibition space: </em>Arja Jomppanen, Head Curator, Sámi Museum Siida, tel. +358 (0)40 579 3313, arja.jomppanen(at)samimuseum.fi </p>
    <p xml:lang="sme">Sámi museum, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)400 898 212, siida@samimuseum.fi , www.siida.fi</p>
    <p type="title">Document Actions</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">Send this</p>
      <p type="listitem">Print this</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Contents</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
    <p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
    <p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
    <p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="fin">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
    <p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
    <p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
    <p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
    <p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
    <p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
    <p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
    <p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
    <p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
    <p>&gt; opening hours</p>
    <p>&gt; tickets</p>
    <p>&gt; contact information</p>
    <p>&gt; location</p>
    <p>&gt; guided tours</p>
    <p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
    <p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">|</p>
    <p>photo gallery</p>
    <p>tourist info</p>
    <p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
    <p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
    <p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
    <p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">|</p>
    <p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
    <p>Open original size in new window</p>
  </body>
</document>
