<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Web Exhibition The Use of Wild Plants Has Been Launched — Siida</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2015</year><wordcount>742</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/web-exhibition-the-use-of-wild-plants-has-been-launched</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="eatnanaddu-2013-luonnonkasvien-kytt-verkkonyttely-avattu-1.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="eatnanaddu-2013-luondduattuid-geavaheapmi-neahttajhus-rahppojuvvon.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
<p type="listitem">in English |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
</list><p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
<p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Sections</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Collections |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Nature services |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Restaurant |</p>
<p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
<p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
</list><p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
<p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p>Info</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">/</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
<p>Web Exhibition The Use of Wild Plants Has Been Launched</p>
<p type="title">Web Exhibition The Use of Wild Plants Has Been Launched</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Mar 25, 2015 11:17 AM</p>
<p>The Sámi Museum Siida has created a web exhibition on the use of wild plants, and the website is now available for the public. The web exhibition Eatnanšaddu – The Sámi and the Use of Wild Plants is based on the plant exhibition of the same name that the Sámi Museum and the Northern Lapland Nature Centre produced together a few years ago.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p>Web Exhibition The Use of Wild Plants Has Been Launched</p>
<p>Would you like to know more about the Angelica? Are you familiar with dyeing, or healing with tinder fungus? On the website at www.samimuseum.fi/eatnansaddu we introduce the audience to wild plants used by the Sámi and their habitats and uses. In addition to a comprehensive information package, the website also contains a plant database with the data of approximately 50 wild plants; there is also a task section in which visitors can check how much they know about the wild plants of the north.</p>
<p>The exhibition has been realised as part of the Sápmi Miehtá project that was financed by the European Social Fund and Lapland’s Centre for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment. The project was run by the Sámi Education Institute, and its purpose was to create a virtual development and learning environment for the Sámi language and culture. The project, which lasted until the end of 2014, created an operations scheme for how to realise distance learning in the Sámi language and culture nationally and how to make use of the Sámi materials of museums and libraries in learning. During the project, the Sámi Museum and Nature Centre Siida created material that can be used in virtual education. Eatnanšáddu – The Use of Wild Plants is one of the learning environments that were published as part of the project; it is also an information website that everyone can access.</p>
<p>– The exhibition <em type="italic">Eatnanšaddu </em>that was displayed in Siida some years ago was very popular among the visitors. It contained a lot of information that we can use even today, Museum Director Sari Valkonen says. – Thanks to the project, the knowledge of the exhibition is now available for everyone. </p>
<p>– Now we can all study the data of the website, and, with spring almost here, look at the theme more closely and get ready to collect useful plants already this summer, Valkonen says.</p>
<p>The web exhibition <em type="italic">Eatnanšaddu </em>is available in three languages: Finnish, English and North Sámi. </p>
<p>Further information:</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sámi Museum Siida, Museum Director Sari Valkonen, sari.valkonen@samimuseum.fi , +358 40 767 1052</p>
<p>Northern Lapland Nature Centre Siida, Nature Centre Manager Kirsi Ukkonen, kirsi.ukkonen@metsa.fi , +358 400 479 986</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sámi museum, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)400 898 212, siida@samimuseum.fi , www.siida.fi</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Document Actions</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Send this</p>
<p type="listitem">Print this</p>
</list><p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Contents</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
<p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="olo">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
<p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
<p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
<p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
<p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
<p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
<p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
<p>&gt; opening hours</p>
<p>&gt; tickets</p>
<p>&gt; contact information</p>
<p>&gt; location</p>
<p>&gt; guided tours</p>
<p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">|</p>
<p>photo gallery</p>
<p>tourist info</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
<p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">|</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
<p>Open original size in new window</p>
</body></document>
