<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>283</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/><multilingual><language xml:lang="swe"/><language xml:lang="eng"/></multilingual><origFileName>http://www.lansstyrelsen.se/dalarna/En/manniska-och-samhalle/manskliga-rattigheter/Pages/default.aspx</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="manniska-och-samhalle-manskliga-rattigheter.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="manniska-och-samhalle-manskliga-rattigheter.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="swe">Human rights - Länsstyrelsen i Dalarna</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
</list><p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Human rights</p>
<p>The County Administrative Board's staff should have good knowledge of human rights. Therefore, the County Administrative Boards have developed a joint action plan for equal rights and opportunities.</p>
<p>The goal is to work for equal rights and opportunities and for this to permeate the County Administrative Board's organizations and activities and for this common approach to be shared by all County Administrative Boards. The County Administrative Board's action plan is based on the Discrimination Act and the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.</p>
<p type="title">Human rights apply to all</p>
<p>All human beings are born free and equal in value and rights. Human rights are universal. They apply throughout the world, regardless of country, culture or context.</p>
<p type="title">Discrimination Act</p>
<p>In accordance with the Discrimination Act, it is prohibited to discriminate against people on the grounds of sex, ethnicity, religion or other belief, sexual orientation, disability, age transgender identity or expression.</p>
<p>The new Discrimination Act entered into force in 2009 and covers more areas than the previous legislation. With the new Act, it has become easier to combat discrimination more effectively. At the same time as the Act came into force, a joint ombudsman's authority was formed, the Equality Ombudsman. It replaces the four previous anti-discrimination ombudsmen, the Disability Ombudsman (HO), the Equal Opportunities Ombudsman (JämO), the Ombudsman against Ethnic Discrimination (DO), and the Ombudsman against Discrimination because of Sexual Orientation (HomO).</p>
<p type="title">Contact us</p>
<p>County Administrative Board of Dalarna</p>
<p xml:lang="swe">dalarna snabela lansstyrelsen punkt se¤dalarna snabela lansstyrelsen punkt se</p>
<p>Send message</p>
<p>Hide form</p>
<p>Your email address (optional)</p>
<p>Send a copy of the message to the email address specified</p>
<p>Message</p>
<p>Enter the code below to send your message</p>
<p>Generate new image</p>
</body></document>