<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title/>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <wordcount>229</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/>
    <multilingual>
      <language xml:lang="swe"/>
      <language xml:lang="eng"/>
    </multilingual>
    <origFileName>http://www.lansstyrelsen.se/dalarna/En/samhallsplanering-och-kulturmiljo/skyddad-bebyggelse/Pages/default.aspx</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="samhallsplanering-och-kulturmiljo-skyddad-bebyggelse.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="samhallsplanering-och-kulturmiljo-skyddad-bebyggelse.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>Protected buildings - Länsstyrelsen i Dalarna</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="swe"></p>
    <p type="title">Protected buildings</p>
    <p>Photo: Anders Gottberg</p>
    <p><em type="italic">The County Administrative Board may decide that cultural and historical buildings and environments should be protected as listed buildings. </em></p>
    <p>The Heritage Conservation Act (SFS1988:950) specifies that particularly valuable buildings, settlements, church sites, parks, gardens or similar can be protected as a listed building. Buildings may also be protected under the Planning and Building Act, which is a task for the municipalities.</p>
    <p><em type="italic">The County Administrative Board </em></p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">investigates and decides whether an object should become a listed object</p>
      <p type="listitem">carries out supervision of listed buildings, churches and cemeteries grants permission for alterations to listed buildings, churches and cemeteries</p>
    </list>
    <p type="title">Protection of church sites</p>
    <p>In accordance with the Cultural Heritage Act (SFS 1988.950), all church buildings and church sites belonging to the Swedish Church, and all cemeteries should be preserved and maintained so that their cultural historic value is not reduced. Church buildings erected, and church sites constituted, before the end of 1939 may not be altered in any significant respect without permission from the County Administrative Board. The provisions concerning application of permission also apply concerning a church building or a church site that came into being after 1939 and is remarkable owing to its cultural historic value. Ecclesiastical furnishings of cultural and historical value shall be properly kept and preserved and every parish is to keep a list of such furnishings.</p>
  </body>
</document>
