<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Her Royal Highness Crown Princess Mette-Marit  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>626</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/artikkel.html?tid=28772</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="artikkel.html_tid=27663.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="artikkel.html_tid=76578_sek=76449.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Her Royal Highness Crown Princess Mette-Marit</p>
<p>Crown Princess Mette-Marit was born Mette-Marit Tjessem Høiby on 19 August 1973. Her engagement to His Royal Highness Crown Prince Haakon was announced on 1 December 2000, and they were married in Oslo Cathedral on 25 August 2001.</p>
<p>There are three children in the Crown Prince and Crown Princess’s family: Marius Borg Høiby, Her Royal Highness Princess Ingrid Alexandra and His Highness Prince Sverre Magnus.</p>
<p type="title">Education</p>
<p>The Crown Princess completed her upper secondary education at Kristiansand Katedralskole in 1994. During her time at upper secondary school, she spent a year abroad as an exchange student at Wangaratta High School in Australia.</p>
<p>Later the Crown Princess attended Bjørknes Private School, and in 1997 she took Examen philosophicum (the preliminary university examination) as well as examinations in chemistry and information technology at Agder University College. In 2000 - 2002 she studied ethics at the Faculty of Social Science and the Faculty of Humanities at the University of Oslo.</p>
<p>In 2003 the Crown Princess followed courses at the School of Oriental and African Studies at the University of London, where she took examiniations in Development-Experience, Theories of Development, HIV/AIDS and Development and The Global Refugee Crisis. The Crown Princess also spent three months as an observer at the Norwegian Agency for Development Cooperation (Norad), where she focused on HIV/AIDS issues.</p>
<p>In autumn 2008 the Crown Princess began studying part-time at BI Norwegian School of Management in Oslo, where she completed her Master of Management in 2012.</p>
<p type="title">Official duties</p>
<p>The Crown Princess is deeply committed to a broad range of national and international issues. Literature, young leadership, entrepreneurship, sustainability, mental health and global health issues are some of them. Social inclusion, mental health, young leadership, global health issues, entrepreneurship and environmental issues being some of them. Crown Princess Mette-Marit is the patron of the Norwegian Red Cross and several other organisations. Through the Crown Prince and Crown Princess’s Foundation, the Crown Princess contributes to projects supporting young people at risk. On her many visits representing Norway, the Crown Princess actively promotes Norwegian trade and industry, culture, architecture and design.</p>
<p>Since 2001, the Crown Princess she has been actively involved in HIV/AIDS-related work. In April 2006 she was appointed Special Representative for UNAIDS. In this capacity she has travelled to Nicaragua, Ukraine and Mali, and on several occasions led the Norwegian delegations to the biennial  International AIDS conference. A main focus for the Crown Princess is to strengthen youth leadership and form international partnerships in the AIDS response.</p>
<p>In 2015 the Crown Princess and Kate Roberts, senior vice-president at the global health non-profit Population Services International (PSI) established Maverick Collective. Melinda Gates shared their vision and joined as co-chair. The Maverick Collective was launched during the conference Women Deliver in Copenhagen in May 2016 and is an initiative that aims to engage other women to use their voice, intellectual and financial resources, to improve women’s health worldwide and help end extreme poverty.</p>
<p>In 2010 Crown Princess Mette-Marit was appointed Young Global Leader under the World Economic Forum, and in 2012 she became a member of the international Foundation Board of the Global Shapers Community. The Crown Princess was named a Leading Global Thinker by Foreign Policy Magazine in 2016. The same year she was also named one of the most creative people in business by Fast Company.</p>
<p type="title">Leisure interests</p>
<p>The Crown Princess’s leisure interests include outdoor recreational activities, physical exercise, literature, film and theatre. The Crown Prince and Crown Princess have an active family life and spend a great deal of time with their children enjoying outdoor recreational activities, from skiing in the winter to sailing and hiking at other times of the year.</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">15.01.2017</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
</body></document>
