<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>Focus: UNDP  - The Royal House of Norway</title>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <wordcount>772</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <license type="standard"/>
    </availability>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/artikkel.html?tid=84163</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="artikkel.html_tid=84120_sek=76440.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
    <p>The Royal House of Norway</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Focus: UNDP</p>
    <p>In 2003, Crown Prince Haakon was appointed Goodwill Ambassador for the United Nations Development Programme - UNDP. In this capacity he has travelled to Timor-Leste, Zambia, Haiti, Nepal, Botswana, Tanzania, Cambodia, Sierra Leone, Guatemala, Burundi and Mongolia.</p>
    <p>The Crown Prince has been particularly committed to the effort to end poverty, first through  the UN Millennium Development Goals and then through the 17 Sustainable Development Goals decided on in September 2015.</p>
    <p type="title">The Sustainable Development Goals</p>
    <p>25 September 2015, the world's countries decided on the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development, to  end poverty,  protect the planet, and  ensure prosperity for all. The agenda is supported by 17 goals for sustainable development and 169 sub goals with spesific targets.</p>
    <p>The 17 target areas are:</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">No poverty</p>
      <p type="listitem">Zero hunger</p>
      <p type="listitem">Good health and well-being</p>
      <p type="listitem">Quality education</p>
      <p type="listitem">Gender equality</p>
      <p type="listitem">Clean water and sanitation</p>
      <p type="listitem">Affordable and clean energy</p>
      <p type="listitem">Decent work and economic growth</p>
      <p type="listitem">Industry, innovation and infrastructure</p>
      <p type="listitem">Reduced inequalities</p>
      <p type="listitem">Sustainable cities and communities</p>
      <p type="listitem">Responsible consumption and production</p>
      <p type="listitem">Climate action</p>
      <p type="listitem">Life below water</p>
      <p type="listitem">Life on land</p>
      <p type="listitem">Peace, justice and strong institutions</p>
      <p type="listitem">Partnerships for the goals</p>
    </list>
    <p>Please find a more detailed description of the goals in the fact box.The sustainable development goals replaced the Millennium Development Goals from 1990 - 2015.</p>
    <p type="title">The Millennium Development Goals</p>
    <p>In 2000 all the countries in the world agreed to establish common goals to eradicate poverty, and eight Millennium Development Goals (MDG) were formulated.</p>
    <p>The general goal – MDG 1 – was to eradicate extreme poverty and hunger. The first of three targets under the goal was to halve, between 1990 and 2015, the proportion of people whose income is less than USD 1 a day.</p>
    <p>The eight MDG were to:</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">Eradicate extreme poverty and hunger</p>
      <p type="listitem">Achieve universal primary education</p>
      <p type="listitem">Promote gender equality and empower women</p>
      <p type="listitem">Reduce child mortality</p>
      <p type="listitem">Improve maternal health</p>
      <p type="listitem">Combat HIV/AIDS, malaria and other diseases</p>
      <p type="listitem">Ensure environmental sustainability</p>
      <p type="listitem">Develop a global partnership for development</p>
    </list>
    <p>At the end of 2015, significant progress had been made in all eight areas. For further information, please visit UN.org.</p>
    <p type="title">Human Development Report</p>
    <p>Crown Prince Haakon has provided input to two of the Human Development Reports that are published on an annual basis by UNDP:</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">The 2006 report <span type="quote">“Beyond scarcity: Power, poverty and the global water crisis”</span></p>
      <p type="listitem">The 2007/2008 report <span type="quote">“Fighting climate change: Human solidarity in a divided world”</span></p>
    </list>
    <p>The report series is put together by a group of independent experts whose task is to examine and analyse critical issues for human development worldwide.</p>
    <p type="title">Human Development Awards</p>
    <p>Crown Prince Haakon sat on a panel of judges for the 2007 Human Development Awards. The award honours the best regional, national and sub-national reports on progress made in and obstacles to combating poverty and inequality.</p>
    <p type="title">Kapuscinski lectures</p>
    <p>In 2011 the Crown Prince was a main speaker at the UNDP <span type="quote">“Kapuscinski lectures”</span> at the University of Warsaw, Poland. Crown Prince Haakon gave a lecture on the UN millenium goals for students and staff at the University.</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">30.09.2016</p>
    <p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Crown Prince Haakon visited Zambia on behalf of UNDP October 2013, and comments on his work as a UNDP goodwill ambassador and the UN Development Goals. (Photo: Christian Lagaard, The Royal Court of Norway)</p>
    <p>Facts</p>
    <p><em type="italic">The 17 UN Sustainable Development Goals </em></p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">End poverty in all its forms everywhere</p>
      <p type="listitem">End hunger, achieve food security and improved nutrition and promote sustainable agriculture</p>
      <p type="listitem">Ensure healthy lives and promote well-being for all at all ages</p>
      <p type="listitem">Ensure inclusive and equitable quality education and promote lifelong learning opportunities for all</p>
      <p type="listitem">Achieve gender equality and empower all women and girls</p>
      <p type="listitem">Ensure availability and sustainable management of water and sanitation for all</p>
      <p type="listitem">Ensure access to affordable, reliable, sustainable and modern energy for all</p>
      <p type="listitem">Promote sustained, inclusive and sustainable economic growth, full and productive employment and decent work for all</p>
      <p type="listitem">Build resilient infrastructure, promote inclusive and sustainable industrialization and foster innovation</p>
      <p type="listitem">Reduce inequality within and among countries</p>
      <p type="listitem">Make cities and human settlements inclusive, safe, resilient and sustainable</p>
      <p type="listitem">Ensure sustainable consumption and production pattern</p>
      <p type="listitem">Take urgent action to combat climate change and its impacts</p>
      <p type="listitem">Conserve and sustainably use the oceans, seas and marine resources for sustainable development</p>
      <p type="listitem">Protect, restore and promote sustainable use of terrestrial ecosystems, sustainably manage forests, combat desertification, and halt and reverse land degradation and halt biodiversity loss</p>
      <p type="listitem">Promote peaceful and inclusive societies for sustainable development, provide access to justice for all and build effective, accountable and inclusive institutions at all levels</p>
      <p type="listitem">Strengthen the means of implementation and revitalize the global partnership for sustainable development</p>
    </list>
    <p>Source: the UN</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">Please find more information at UNDP.org</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">UNDP.org</p>
      <p type="listitem">Human Development Awards</p>
      <p type="listitem">UN.org on the Sustainable Development Goals</p>
    </list>
  </body>
</document>
