<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>Diversity and innovation   - The Royal House of Norway</title>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <wordcount>524</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <license type="standard"/>
    </availability>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=139126</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyhet.html_tid=139126.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=139126_sek=74887.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
    <p>The Royal House of Norway</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Diversity and innovation</p>
    <p>Canada is a promising market for Norwegian companies. It is also an extremely culturally diverse country. Their Royal Highnesses attended seminars on several interesting topics on Wednesday.</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">10.11.2016</p>
    <p>Crown Prince Haakon and Crown Princess Mette-Marit participated in seminars on the strengths of diversity, innovative health technology, and Norwegian-Canadian cooperation on tunnelling on Wednesday, accompanied by Minister of Trade and Industry Monica Mæland.</p>
    <p type="title">Stronger through diversity</p>
    <p>Canada is said to be the most culturally diverse country in the world and Toronto the most culturally diverse city. Prime Minister Justin Trudeau has stressed that this diversity is one of Canada’s greatest strengths: <span type="quote">“Canadians are of every possible colour, culture, and creed and continue to celebrate and revel in our diversity.”</span></p>
    <p>The Diversity Institute at Ryerson University works with diversity in large organisations, helping them to use the potential inherent in their employees’ differences. The participants at Wednesday’s seminar listened to representatives of world-leading companies discuss the advantages of diversity for the organisations themselves as well as for market opportunities. One of the participants was the Norwegian organisation MAK, which works to increase Norway’s competitiveness by promoting intercultural competence. The focus of the seminar was on diversity as a resource for society, companies and individuals.</p>
    <p type="title">Norwegian health technology in Canada</p>
    <p>After the diversity seminar, the next item on the agenda for the Crown Prince and Crown Princess was innovative Norwegian technology. Innovation Norway and FRAM Medtech assist Norwegian companies seeking to enter the Canadian health market. The event provided Norwegian start-ups with an opportunity to make important contacts with representatives of the authorities, financial institutions, research groups and end-users.</p>
    <p>Crown Prince Haakon and Crown Princess Mette-Marit had the chance to look at several innovative products that Norwegian companies are hoping to launch in Canada.</p>
    <p>They also took advantage of the opportunity to visit an ongoing seminar on tunnel technology before attending a luncheon with representatives of Norwegian and Canadian trade and industry.</p>
    <p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Little Norway Park</p>
    <p>A visit to Little Norway Park rounded off the visit to Toronto. The park commemorates the training base for Norwegian fighter pilots that was located here during the Second World War. His Majesty King Harald visited Little Norway several times as a young boy. A total of over 3 000 pilots, navigators and mechanics were trained at the base during the course of the war. The troops’ barracks were located at the site where the park lies today.</p>
    <p>The Crown Prince and Crown Princess laid a bouquet of flowers at the base of the monument marking the site.</p>
    <p>Many Norwegians living in Toronto came to attend the ceremony, and Crown Prince Haakon and Crown Princess Mette-Marit took the opportunity to greet them as well as speak with the children who had brought flags and drawings.</p>
    <p>The Crown Prince and Crown Princess then travelled from Toronto to St John’s, where the final part of their visit will take place.</p>
    <p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">Official visit to Canada (News article)</p>
      <p type="listitem">Promoting culture in Toronto (News article)</p>
      <p type="listitem">Visit concluded in St John’s (News article)</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Canada 2016 (Photo album)</p>
    </list>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">Innovation norway</p>
    </list>
  </body>
</document>
