<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Presented the King with their own legislation  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>374</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=120119</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyhet.html_tid=120119.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=120119_sek=74887.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Presented the King with their own legislation</p>
<p>Today children from Kapellveien child-care centre presented King Harald with a specially drawn up constitution, in which Article 1 states: <span type="quote">“We shall use our hands kindly”</span>.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">14.03.2014</p>
<p>In this bicentennial year of the Norwegian Constitution, democracy and the right to vote have been important topics of discussion at Kapellveien child-care centre. The adults and children have talked about what these involve and the children have even held an election; using secret ballots and ballot box, the children voted on whether they would prefer a warm lunch or make-your-own sandwiches.</p>
<p>Discussions about the Constitution and other legislation, including why Norway has a statutory framework and who made the first laws, led the children to draw up their own constitution.</p>
<p type="title">Audience with the King</p>
<p>The children were granted an audience by the King to mark national <em type="italic">Barnehagedagen </em>(<span type="quote">"pre-school day"</span>), which takes place on 18 March. Emrik, Jessica, Agnes, Lars Kasander, Mari and Hennie were accompanied to the Royal Palace today by the director of their child-care centre, Ms Berit Kragebøl, and educational supervisor Ms Heidi Ruud Brabrand. </p>
<p>The children were greeted by the King in the Cabinet Parlour. There they presented their constitution to King Harald, and explained the various articles and the thinking behind these.</p>
<p>The young guests were treated to refreshments during their visit, enjoying juice and buns baked in the kitchen of the Royal Palace.</p>
<p><em type="italic">We shall use our hands kindly… </em></p>
<p>Here is the insightful constitution proposed by the children at Kapellveien child-care centre:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">We shall use our hands kindly: - We shall not hit, kick, push or bite one another.</p>
<p type="listitem">We shall use our words kindly: - We shall not bully, threaten or tease one another.</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">The older children shall be helpful to the younger children.</p>
<p type="listitem">Every child shall have the opportunity to play every day.</p>
<p type="listitem">We shall play together.</p>
<p type="listitem">All adults shall listen to what the children have to say.</p>
<p type="listitem">All the people on Earth shall take care of our planet.</p>
<p type="listitem">All children shall have the chance to go to pre-school.</p>
<p type="listitem">All children shall have a safe place to live and toys.</p>
<p type="listitem">All children shall be able to take a holiday with their family.</p>
</list><p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
</body></document>