<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Seminar on indigenous peoples  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>379</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=77641</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyhet.html_tid=77541.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=77678_sek=74887.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Seminar on indigenous peoples</p>
<p>On Wednesday, 18 March, Their Royal Highnesses The Crown Prince and Crown Princess attended the opening of a seminar on indigenous peoples at the National Museum of Anthropology in Mexico City.</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">22.03.2009</p>
<p>Afterward they travelled to the port city of Veracruz, where their official visit continued on Thursday.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="isl">Seminar</p>
<p>Crown Princess Mette-Marit officially opened a seminar on indigenous peoples at the National Museum of Anthropology in Mexico City. She began her opening speech in the Sámi language and talked about the position of the Sámi people in Norway in the past and present.</p>
<p>The Crown Princess explained that in modern times both Norway and Mexico have worked within the UN to advance the rights of indigenous peoples. Norway and Mexico have a long tradition of cooperation on issues relating to indigenous peoples, particularly in international organisations like the UN. Both our countries worked hard to negotiate and promote the UN Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples, she stated.</p>
<p>Following the seminars opening, the Crown Prince and Crown Princess were given a guided tour of the museum.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="ron">Museo de la Antropologia</p>
<p>The National Museum of Anthropology in Mexico City is among the most extensive and highly acclaimed in the world. The museum contains Mexicos largest collections and exhibitions on the Maya and Aztec civilisations as well as many other less known indigenous groups.</p>
<p>In honour of the Crown Prince and Crown Princesss visit, photographs and sound clips of Carl Sofus Lumholtz were put on display. Lumholtz was a Norwegian discoverer, ethnographer and author who travelled to Mexico in 1890 and lived among the indigenous people in the north-western part of the country. His book Unknown Mexico, published in 1902, is based on his experiences there.</p>
<p type="title">On to Veracruz</p>
<p>The Crown Prince and Crown Princess departed Mexico City in the afternoon and travelled to Veracruz, a vital port city visited by many Norwegian ships.</p>
<p>In the evening, the Crown Prince and Crown Princess attended an official banquet at Museo de la Ciudad (City Museum) hosted by the Governor of the state of Veracruz, Mr Fidel Herrera.</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Official visit to Mexico (News article)</p>
<p type="listitem">A busy day in Mexico (News article)</p>
<p type="listitem">Final day in Mexico (News article)</p>
</list></body></document>
