<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>385</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/><multilingual><language xml:lang="swe"/><language xml:lang="eng"/></multilingual><origFileName>http://www.1177.se/Other-languages/Engelska/Barn/Barnsakerhet-0---3-man</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="barnsakerhet-0---3-man1.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="barnsakerhet-03-man.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="swe">Child safety, 0-3 months / Barnsäkerhet 0 - 3 mån - 1177 Vårdguiden - sjukdomar, undersökningar, hitta vård, e-tjänster</p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p type="title">Child safety, 0-3 monthsBarnsäkerhet 0 - 3 mån</p>
<p></p>
<p type="title">Tips and advice</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Keep one hand on the child if you have to turn away from the changing table.</p>
<p type="listitem">When you give the child a bath, put your arm behind the child’s neck and hold your hand firmly around its upper arm.</p>
</list><p type="title">To prevent fall-related injuries:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">always keep the child in view when it is on the changing table</p>
<p type="listitem">always try to keep one hand on the child if you have to turn away from the changing table</p>
<p type="listitem">make sure that the changing table is stable even if the child kicks about and moves</p>
<p type="listitem">always put the baby bouncer on the floor. It is also a good idea to strap slightly older children into the baby bouncer, because the chair can fall over if the child leans forward and is not wearing the belt.</p>
</list><p type="title">To prevent burns:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">avoid drinking hot coffee or tea with the child on your lap</p>
<p type="listitem">measure the water temperature in the bath so it is not too hot. You can use a thermometer or dip your elbow in</p>
<p type="listitem">make sure the child spends as much time as possible in the shade on sunny days.</p>
<p type="listitem">For safe car trips:</p>
<p type="listitem">make sure that the child is always strapped into an approved baby seat</p>
<p type="listitem">if buying a used baby seat, make sure it is not damaged in any way</p>
<p type="listitem">check that there are no loose objects that could be thrown around the car if you have to brake hard.</p>
</list><p>There are baby seats that are approved to be installed in both the front and back seat. Always follow the installation instructions carefully.</p>
<p type="title">To protect hearing</p>
<list><p type="listitem">avoid loud volume, for example loud music or sudden, loud noises</p>
<p type="listitem">make sure that toys do not make loud, shrill noises – try them before you buy them.</p>
</list><p type="title">To prevent other accidents</p>
<p>To prevent other accidents you can regularly check the child's equipment and toys, for example the brakes on the pram and the rubber teats on dummies.</p>
<p type="title">Passive smoking</p>
<p>Passive smoking exposes the child to health risks. If you cannot stop smoking completely, change your smoking habits and stop smoking at home. A completely smoke-free environment is best for the child.</p>
</body></document>
