<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>331</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/><multilingual><language xml:lang="swe"/><language xml:lang="eng"/></multilingual><origFileName>http://www.1177.se/Other-languages/Engelska/Symtom_sjukdom/Cellforandringar-i-livmoderhalsen</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="cellforandringar-i-livmoderhalsen.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="rus" location="cellforandringar-i-livmoderhalsen.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="cellforandringa.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="swe">Cell changes in the cervix / Cellförändringar i livmoderhalsen - 1177 Vårdguiden - sjukdomar, undersökningar, hitta vård, e-tjänster</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Cell changes in the cervixCellförändringar i livmoderhalsen</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Overview</p>
<p type="title">General</p>
<p>The cervix is the lower part of the uterus. The very bottom part of it is called the ectocervix. It is here that cell changes can take place. These do not usually mean that you are ill, but, in rare cases, cell changes can develop into cancer – something that usually takes several years. If you have regular Pap tests, these changes can be detected and you can be treated in good time.</p>
<p>Cell changes that can lead to cancer are normally caused by a virus contracted during sex. You can partly protect yourself by using condoms. You can also be vaccinated against two of the most common types of virus that can cause cancer. For the protection to be as effective as possible, you should have the vaccine before you start having sex.</p>
<p>There is some hereditary risk for cell changes in the cervix, and smoking also increases the risk.</p>
<p type="title">Symptoms</p>
<p>Cell changes do not cause any symptoms or discomfort; they can only be detected by taking cell samples with a Pap test.</p>
<p type="title">Treatment</p>
<p>Most cell changes go away by themselves. If they need to be treated, they are removed by means of a small operation. They can also be removed by using heat, cold or a laser beam. You will be given a local or general anaesthetic during the treatment, which will be done at a hospital or gynaecological clinic. Patients can normally return home the same day.</p>
<p>Following treatment, you will feel as normal, but you should avoid having sex for three or four weeks.</p>
<p type="title">When should you seek medical care?</p>
<p>Since cell changes do not cause any discomfort, it is important to cooperate with the Pap test programme offered by the council.</p>
<p>You should always call the medical care hotline for advice on where to go for a Pap test.</p>
</body></document>
