<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>835</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/><multilingual><language xml:lang="swe"/><language xml:lang="eng"/></multilingual><origFileName>http://www.1177.se/Other-languages/Engelska/Barn/Feber--vad-kan-man-gora-sjalv</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="feber-hos-barn--vad-kan-man-gora-sjalv.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="fit" location="feber-hos-barn---vad-kan-man-gora-sjalv.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="feber-hos-barn---vad-kan-man-gora-sjalv.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="feber-hos-barn---vad-kan-man-gora-sjalv.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smj" location="feber-hos-barn---vad-kan-man-gora-sjalv.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="feber-hos-barn-vad-kan-man-gora-sjalv.html"/><parallel_text location="feber-hos-barn---vad-kan-man-gora-sjalv.html" xml:lang="rmy-rka"/><parallel_text location="feber-hos-barn---vad-kan-man-gora-sjalv.html" xml:lang="rmn"/><parallel_text location="feber-hos-barn---vad-kan-man-gora-sjalv.html" xml:lang="rmu"/><parallel_text location="feber-hos-barn---vad-kan-man-gora-sjalv.html" xml:lang="yid"/><parallel_text location="feber-hos-barn---vad-kan-man-gora-sjalv.html" xml:lang="rmy-rlo"/><parallel_text location="feber-hos-barn---vad-kan-man-gora-sjalv.html" xml:lang="rmf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="swe">Fever in children – what can I do myself? / Feber – vad kan man göra själv? - 1177 Vårdguiden - sjukdomar, undersökningar, hitta vård, e-tjänster</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Fever in children – what can I do myself?Feber – vad kan man göra själv?</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">A high temperature is part of the body's defence system</p>
<p>A fever isn't dangerous in itself, it is part of the body's defence against infections. Children can easily get a fever, and high temperatures are often caused by viral infections like colds, coughs and sore throats that cause the body temperature to rise. The child's temperature can also rise if he or she plays very energetically or moves around a lot. In rare cases a fever can be a sign of a serious illness.</p>
<p>You can often tell when a child has a fever. If you are unsure you can take the child's temperature, but it is most important to monitor the child's general health. If you are going to contact the healthcare services it is a good idea to have taken the child's temperature first. The most accurate way to take the the child's temperature is rectally. Children have a fever if their temperature is over 38 degrees in the morning or after resting for half an hour.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Let the child rest and drink lots of fluids</p>
<p>A child who has a fever needs to stay home from school or preschool to rest and recover. The child does not have to stay in bed, but should avoid physical exertion. It is best to let the child decide whether to stay in bed or not.</p>
<p>When you have a fever you need to drink more fluids than usual. That is why it is a good idea to offer the child something to drink regularly. Give the child what he or she likes and wants, for example ice cream, fruit drinks or porridge. If the child is not hungry he or she does not have to eat ordinary food. It is OK if he or she eats a little less for a few days. If the child does not pee very often and is tired he or she may need to drink more fluids.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Make the child as comfortable as possible</p>
<p>If the child finds it more comfortable, he or she can sleep under a thin sheet or sleep in his or her underwear. If the child appreciates it, you can also bathe his or her forehead with a cool, moist towel. But if the child is shivering and is cold, which is common when their temperature goes up, you can add another blanket and make the child as comfortable as possible.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Non-prescription medicines</p>
<p>A fever does not usually have to be treated with antipyretic medicines. Most children have a fever that last a few days; this is not necessarily of sign of a serious illness. You can give the child antipyretic medicine if he or she is suffering as a result of the fever, with symptoms including aches and pains, whining, lack of thirst and appetite, having trouble sleeping and settling down at night.</p>
<p>You should not treat children under six months of age without contacting the health services first. For children over three months of age there are medicines that contain paracetamol, for example Alvedon or Panodil. From the age of six months children can take Ipren, which is non-prescription and contains ibuprofen. These medicines are available as solutions or as suppositories with the right dosage for small children. For older children there are also tablets. Follow the instructions on the packaging carefully. Do not combine different medicines. Children under the age of 18 who have a fever should not use antipyretic medicines containing acetylsalicylic acid, for example Magnecyl, Treo or Albyl.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">You may need to contact the healthcare services</p>
<p>A fever is not serious, but the infection that causes it could be. It is above all by monitoring the child's general health that you can assess whether you need to contact your local healthcare centre. If the child has enough energy to be active and play then the fever is probably just a sign of a mild infection.</p>
<p>However, you should always contact the healthcare services if the child:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Is under three months old and has a temperature of more than 38 degrees.</p>
<p type="listitem">Is between three and six months old and has a temperature of more than 39 degrees.</p>
</list><p>Regardless of the child's temperature, you should contact the healthcare services if the child isn't as alert as usual, is lethargic and does not want to eat or drink. Also contact the healthcare services if the child still has a fever after four days.</p>
<p>Some children can experience cramps, called fever cramps, when their temperature rises. When this happens for the first time you should either go to a hospital or a healthcare centre. There you will receive advice and support so you know what to do next time the child has a fever.</p>
<p>You can always phone the healthcare helpline for advice.</p>
</body></document>