<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>296</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/><multilingual><language xml:lang="swe"/><language xml:lang="eng"/></multilingual><origFileName>http://www.1177.se/Other-languages/Engelska/Regler-och-rattigheter/Second-opinion-en-andra-lakarbedomning</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="second-opinion-en-andra-lakarbedomning.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="fit" location="second-opinion-en-andra-lakarbedomning.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="second-opinion.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="second-opinion-en-andra-lakarbedomning.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smj" location="second-opinion-en-andra-lakerbedomning.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="second-opinion-en-andra-lakarbedomning.html"/><parallel_text location="second-opinion-en-andra-lakarbedomning.html" xml:lang="rmy-rka"/><parallel_text location="second-opinion-en-andra-lakarbedomning.html" xml:lang="rmn"/><parallel_text location="second-opinion-en-andra-lakarbedomning.html" xml:lang="rmu"/><parallel_text location="second-opinion-en-andra-lakerbedomning.html" xml:lang="yid"/><parallel_text location="second-opinion-en-andra-lakarbedomning.html" xml:lang="rmy-rlo"/><parallel_text location="second-opinion-en-andra-lakarbedomning.html" xml:lang="rmf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="swe">New medical evaluation, second opinion / Ny medicinsk bedömning, second opinion - 1177 Vårdguiden - sjukdomar, undersökningar, hitta vård, e-tjänster</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">New medical evaluation, second opinionNy medicinsk bedömning, second opinion</p>
<p>If you are facing a difficult medical decision as the result of a diagnosis that you have received from a doctor, you may be entitled to a new medical evaluation, a second opinion, from another doctor. The purpose of a new medical evaluation is to make sure that you will be obtaining the care and treatment that is most suitable for you.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>You have the right to a new medical evaluation if you for example have been diagnosed with cancer, a disorder of the nervous system, or another illness or injury that is life-threatening or highly serious.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">How to apply</p>
<p>If you would like to apply for a second opinion, you can ask your doctor or another representative of the surgery where you received your first medical opinion about who you should go to with your request. If you wish to go to a certain doctor or clinic within Sweden, your county council is obligated to try and arrange things so that you can get there. Your county council is also obligated to pay for a new medical evaluation, even if it means that you need to travel to another county in order to get it. Your county council will also usually pay your travel costs.</p>
<p>You have the right to receive any alternative treatment that the second doctor recommends. However, the treatment must be</p>
<list><p type="listitem">justified on the basis of scientific evidence and clinical experience</p>
<p type="listitem">reasonably priced in view of the particular illness or injury involved</p>
</list><p>You can also contact your county council’s patient’s ombudsman or the patient’s board (patientnämnden) help in getting a second medical evaluation.</p>
</body></document>
