<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>488</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/><multilingual><language xml:lang="swe"/><language xml:lang="eng"/></multilingual><origFileName>http://www.1177.se/Other-languages/Engelska/Regler-och-rattigheter/Vard-i-Sverige-om-man-ar-asylsokande-gomd-eller-papperslos</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="vard-i-sverige-om-man-ar-asylsokande-gomd-eller-papperslos.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="vard-i-sverige-om-man-ar-asylsokande-gomd-eller-papperslos.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="vard-i-sverige-om-man-ar-asylsokande.html"/><parallel_text location="vard-i-sverige-om-man-ar-asylsokande-gomd-eller-papperslos.html" xml:lang="rmy-rlo"/><parallel_text location="vard-i-sverige-om-man-ar-asylsokande-gomd-eller-papperslos.html" xml:lang="rmn"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="swe">Care in Sweden if you are seeking asylum, in hiding or undocumented / Vård i Sverige om man är asylsökande, gömd eller papperslös - 1177 Vårdguiden - sjukdomar, undersökningar, hitta vård, e-tjänster</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Care in Sweden if you are seeking asylum, in hiding or undocumentedVård i Sverige om man är asylsökande, gömd eller papperslös</p>
<p>If you are seeking asylum or are undocumented, you are entitled to both health and dental care in Sweden. Children under 18 usually have the right to receive care free of charge.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Persecution and danger</p>
<p>You may apply for asylum (the chance to receive a residence permit) in Sweden if you need protection as a refugee because you have been persecuted in your native country. You may also apply for asylum based on other reasons.</p>
<p>Being in hiding or undocumented means that you are in Sweden without a permit, perhaps because there is a court order for you to be deported.</p>
<p type="title">Health check-ups</p>
<p>All adults and children who are seeking asylum have the right to a free health check-up. The check-up is to be performed as soon as possible after you arrive in Sweden. If you are in hiding or undocumented, you are to be offered a check-up when you see a caregiver.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Children who are seeking asylum, in hiding or undocumented</p>
<p>Children under 18 are to receive health and dental care on the same terms as all others who are living in the county. Most county councils and regions do not charge for care below the age of 18.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Adults who are seeking asylum, in hiding or undocumented</p>
<p>As an adult (age 18 or older), you are entitled to health and dental care that cannot wait. Maternity and abortion care, as well as contraceptive counselling, are also included.</p>
<p>You will be charged SEK 50 for an appointment at a health centre or for medical care based on a referral. An appointment with a counsellor or other non-medical professional costs SEK 25.</p>
<p>You can make an appointment at a health centre or outpatient specialist clinic in any county council you like. If you are seeking asylum, you will need a referral whenever the particular county council requires it.</p>
<p>Treatment provided by the Swedish Dental Service costs SEK 50.</p>
<p>The charge for prescription medicine is also SEK 50. Your travel expenses to receive health care are covered after the first SEK 40. However, you must pay any travel expenses to receive care in another county.</p>
<p>Preventive paediatric and maternity care, and prenatal and childbirth care are free of charge. Nor do you pay anything if you have an infectious disease and need protective care.</p>
<p>If you are seeking asylum, make sure to show your LMA card from the Migration Board any time you receive health care. LMA is an abbreviation for the Reception of Asylum Seekers and Others Act. The card is a temporary ID that will remain valid as long as you are seeking asylum.</p>
</body></document>