<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>667</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/><multilingual><language xml:lang="swe"/><language xml:lang="eng"/></multilingual><origFileName>http://www.1177.se/Other-languages/Engelska/Regler-och-rattigheter/Vardgaranti</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="vardgaranti.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="fit" location="vardgaranti.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="vardgaranti.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="vardgaranti.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smj" location="vardgaranti.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="vardgarantier.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="rmy-rka" location="vardgaranti.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="rmn" location="vardgaranti.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="rmu" location="vardgaranti.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="yid" location="vardgaranti.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="rmy-rlo" location="vardgaranti.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="rmf" location="vardgaranti.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="swe">Health Care Guarantee / Vårdgaranti - 1177 Vårdguiden - sjukdomar, undersökningar, hitta vård, e-tjänster</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Health Care GuaranteeVårdgaranti</p>
<p>A health care guarantee means that a patient shall receive health care within a certain period of time. This is a statutory part of the health care and medical treatment code. The health care guarantee indicates the frame of time within which a patient shall be offered care from the county council or the region. However, it does not regulate whether care shall be provided or what type of care a patient shall receive.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>Emergency care is not tied to the health care guarantee. A patient who has become acutely ill or injured shall receive treatment as quickly as possible.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">How it works</p>
<p>From the time it is decided that a patient should be seen by a physician for a first visit at the district health care clinic, or alternatively, make a visit or receive a treatment within specialized care, the health care guarantee indicates how long, at the longest, a patient shall be required to wait. If it is not possible to receive care or treatment at the health care facility where a patient has sought care within the designated time frames, a patient shall be offered an appointment or treatment at another health care facility.</p>
<p>It is possible that a patient can be referred to another health care facility in another region or under the jurisdiction of another county council.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Valid only in your county/region</p>
<p>The health care guarantee applies only in the county council or region in which the patient is registered. If a patient decides to seek care outside the county council of residence, the patient is not guaranteed care within a specific period of time.,</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">National Health Care Guarantee 0–7–90–90</p>
<p>According to the health care guarantee, a patient has the right to:</p>
<list><p type="listitem"><em type="italic">0 – Contact with primary health care the same day </em>The same day that a patient seeks help, contact with primary health care shall be provided, for example, contact with a district health care clinic or the medical treatment advisement line (a telephone-based service). This initial contact can take place via telephone or through a personal visit. </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">7 – Visit with a physician within primary health care within seven days </em>If health care personnel determines that a patient needs to see a physician, a patient shall be seen by a physician within seven days at the longest, at a district health care clinic or with a family doctor, for example. </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">90 – Visit with specialised care within 90 days </em>If a patient obtains a referral to specialised care, the specialised care unit shall see the patient within 90 days. This applies even if the patient has sought treatment without a referral. </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">90 – Treatment begun within 90 days </em>Upon a decision for treatment, for example an operation, the patient shall be seen within 90 days. </p>
</list><p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">When does the health care guarantee not apply?</p>
<p>The health care guarantee does not apply</p>
<list><p type="listitem">to follow-up visits</p>
<p type="listitem">if, for medical reasons, the patient should wait longer than the time frame provided by the health care guarantee</p>
<p type="listitem">to medical services, for instance laboratory or x-ray examinations</p>
<p type="listitem">to investigations and examinations</p>
<p type="listitem">to the provision of means of assistance, with the exception of the trial of hearing aids</p>
<p type="listitem">if the patient chooses to refuse an offer of treatment with another health care facility (if the patient later changes his/her mind, he/she can accept the offer of treatment)</p>
<p type="listitem">if the patient chooses to seek care at a health centre or clinic under the jurisdiction of a county council other than where the patient is registered.</p>
</list><p>The guarantee does not determine if you are to receive care, what kind of care you will receive or how long an assessment will take.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Waiting lists in health care</p>
<p>There is a national website for the follow-up of health care guarantees and waiting lists, www.vantetider.se. On the website, patients can find information about waiting lists within the region and the county council's area of jurisdiction.</p>
</body></document>
