<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Timetable for the gradual lifting of restrictions</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="helsenorge.no" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>873</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>https://helsenorge.no/SiteCollectionDocuments/korona/korona-tidsplan-engelsk.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="korona_tidsplan_nordsamisk.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 180635 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p type="listitem">Timetable for the gradual lifting of restrictions    The following changes are being introduced with effect from 7 May:</p>
<p type="listitem">The recommended size of groups in private settings will increase from five to a maximum of 20 people, provided everyone is able to remain at least one metre apart.</p>
<p type="listitem">This also means that exercise and other organised sports may take place involving up to 20 people provided they remain at least one metre apart. In this area, it is the  Directorate of Health's recommendations and the sport's own guidelines that apply.  These recommendations and guidelines should be followed.</p>
<p type="listitem">Sports centres can re-open. There is a ban on the use of changing rooms at sports centres.</p>
<p type="listitem">Events with up to 50 participants will be permitted in public spaces, provided participants are able to remain at least one metre apart and there is a responsible  organiser. This applies to all types of events, including sports events such as  tournaments, cup competitions and matches. Employees and contractors who are  responsible for managing events in public spaces will not be considered part of the  event. Their role should be laid down in specific industry standards.</p>
<p type="listitem">The ban on international travel by health professionals is lifted. However, international travel should still be avoided where possible. Anyone who has been  abroad must go into quarantine upon returning to Norway.</p>
<p type="listitem">The population must be prepared for travel quarantines to continue throughout the summer.</p>
<p type="listitem">The duration of enforced quarantine is reduced from 14 to 10 days. Anyone who has been in close contact with a person who has been confirmed as being infected up to  48 hours before they developed their first symptoms must go into quarantine. People  should still go into quarantine if they have been within two metres of an infected  person for more than 15 minutes. A six-month exception from the obligation to go into  quarantine is granted for anyone who has already been infected with SARS-CoV-2.</p>
<p type="listitem">Employers should ensure that employees are able to remain at least one metre apart throughout their entire working day. In areas of the country where employees depend  on public transport, employers are encouraged to facilitate home office working  and/or electronic meetings wherever possible, with physical presence at the  workplace only when necessary. This particularly applies in the Oslo area and in  other towns and cities where there is pressure on public transport.      The following changes will be introduced with effect from 11 May:</p>
<p type="listitem">All primary and secondary schools will re-open for all year groups during the week commencing 11 May 2020 (calendar week 20). The infection control rules must be  followed, which may mean that not all pupils can be in school at the same time.</p>
<p type="listitem">Adult education and training programmes for refugees under the Introduction Act can also re-open during week 20.</p>
<p type="listitem">Folk high schools (Folkehøgskoler) must remain closed throughout the academic year, with the exception of short courses.</p>
<p type="listitem">Driving schools can re-open. They must comply with the infection control requirements that apply to other businesses with one-to-one contact.</p>
<p type="listitem">It is an intention to enable bingo halls and similar establishments to re-open.</p>
<p type="listitem">Universities, university colleges and technical colleges must continue to provide distance learning. Students who are required to be on campus in order to maintain  their study progression will be able to gain access to their campus. Educational  institutions must follow the applicable requirements regarding infection control.</p>
<p type="listitem">Courses being run by an adult education association or Kompetansepluss must continue to provide distance learning. Students who are required to be on campus in  order to maintain their study progression will be able to gain access to their campus.  Educational institutions must follow the applicable requirements regarding infection  control.</p>
<p type="listitem">A guide for sports is being published, with an emphasis on children's and youth sports which involve physical contact, such as football. The aim is to enable children  and young people to participate in their sport in a way which is more normal than at  present, e.g. playing matches against other players in their team. This must take  place in a way which is safe in terms of infection protection.</p>
<p type="listitem">Plans are being drawn up to implement the following changes with effect from  1 June:</p>
<p type="listitem">Cafés and bars that do not serve food will be able to re-open, provided they are able to follow the social distancing rule of at least one metre. Requirements concerning  seating and table service will be laid down in a regulation.</p>
<p type="listitem">Amusement parks can re-open.</p>
<p type="listitem">Organised swimming, including school swimming, will be permitted.</p>
<p type="listitem">The Directorate of Health and the National Institute of Public Health will publish revised recreational travel advice by no later than 15 May. This advice will apply from  1 June.      Plans are being drawn up to introduce the following changes with effect from  15 June:</p>
<p type="listitem">Events with up to 200 people will be permitted.</p>
<p type="listitem">It is an intention to allow gyms to re-open, provided that the health authorities agree on appropriate infection control measures with the industry.</p>
<p type="listitem">It is an intention to allow water parks and swimming pools generally to re-open to the public, provided that the health authorities agree on appropriate infection control  measures with the industry.</p>
<p type="listitem">League matches in elite football will be permitted from 16 June, under an exemption in the COVID-19 Regulation.</p>
</body></document>
