<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Life in the time of corona</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="helsenorge.no" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>1032</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://helsenorge.no/coronavirus/life-in-the-time-of-corona?redirect=false</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="raad_for_koronahverdagen.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="ravvagat_koronadilis.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 180635 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p>Life in the time of corona - helsenorge.no</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedmeny</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til innholdet</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Min helse</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="rmn">helsenorge.no</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="pol">Meny</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Søk</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Søk...</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Søk...</p>
<p type="title">Life in the time of corona</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nno">Norsk bokmål</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">Sámi</p>
</list><p>The present unprecedented daily life situation with Covid-19 is gradually turning into a new normal. Even if we now see a gradual resumption of public life, we need for a good while to adjust to the abnormal being the new normal.</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sidebilde</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Helsedirektoratet / Eva Rustad de Brisis</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Sideinnhold</p>
<p>​To keep a distance to others and mainly stay at home can be quite demanding. Some people feel lonely, while others find it challenging to stay in close quarters with their family over time. Life can be stressful for those working from home and for those temporarily laid off. We can all benefit from proactively looking after of our psychological as well as our physical health.</p>
<p type="title">Tips to maintain good habits during the coronavirus epidemic</p>
<p type="title">Social support and staying connected is important</p>
<p xml:lang="olo">K</p>
<p>eep in touch with family and friends via the phone or digital channels.</p>
<p type="title">Do more of what makes you happy</p>
<p>Take time to do things you enjoy doing – either alone, with a friend or with your family. It can be anything from watching a film, going for a walk or decluttering a closet. Take the opportunity to learn something new.</p>
<p>Read more about tips to boost mental health and quality of life</p>
<p>(in Norwegian).</p>
<p type="title">Go for a walk or engage in other outdoor activities</p>
<p>Pick an activity that you enjoy and that can easily be carried out. Let the activity become a part of your daily routine, as this will make it easier to follow through. If you keep a distance of one meter and avoid public transport as far as possible, you can team up with a friend or neighbour.</p>
<p>Here are some tips for increasing physical activity</p>
<p>(in Norwegian).</p>
<p type="title">Keep a daily meal plan with food that is healthy and varied</p>
<p>A healthy and varied diet is important for your health and well-being, as it will contribute to a well-functioning immune system. Try to eat lots of vegetables, fruits and berries, whole grains and fish, while limiting the amount of processed meat, red meat, salt and sugar.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p>For more info on a healthy and varied diet:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Dietary advice from the Norwegian Directorate of Health (pdf in English)</p>
<p type="listitem">How to build a healthy meal (in Norwegian)</p>
</list><p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p>In Norway, many now enter the month of ramadan.</p>
<list><p type="listitem">R  ead more about Health advice in connection with fasting during Ramadan for concrete advice related to the coronavirus disease covid-19.</p>
</list><p type="title">Be critical to miracle cures and carefully evaluate the source of information</p>
<p>In times of fear and uncertainty it is easy to be tempted by stories about some magical food or supplement that claims to cure or relieve the disease. No food, drink, supplement or diet can protect against or cure a covid-19 infection. Be critical to the source of information and turn to reliable sources for up-to-date information from the authorities. The Norwegian Food Safety Authority has written an article on how</p>
<p>supplements will not stop the coronavirus</p>
<p>(in Norwegian).</p>
<p type="title">Maintain your daily rhythm and bedtime routines</p>
<p>Getting up at roughly the same time every day is a good idea, even during weekends. Try to get at least 30 minutes of daylight every day.</p>
<p>Here you can find</p>
<p>additional advice for a better night's rest</p>
<p>(in Norwegian).</p>
<p type="title">Limit your intake of alcohol</p>
<p>Here you can read more about</p>
<p>alcohol and health</p>
<p>(in Norwegian).</p>
<p type="title">Do you consider quitting smoking?</p>
<p>Here you can read more about</p>
<p>help and advice on how to quit smoking (slutta.no)</p>
<p>(in Norwegian).</p>
<p type="title">Be kind to yourself and to others</p>
<p>We are now in an unpredictable and unusual situation that can be stressful to connections and relationships. Accept that these can be tough times both for you and those around you. Try not to set the expectations too high. Break up and organize your day and set goals along the way. Remember to include time for rest and to appreciate what you achieve.</p>
<p type="title">Seek support – do not be afraid to ask for help</p>
<p>When times are tough and you need someone to talk to, or if you are worried about someone who might not be doing well, there are places you can turn to. Here is an</p>
<p>overview of help lines and chat services that can help out</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">.</p>
<p type="title">What about sex and corona?</p>
<p>You can still have sex with your regular partner given that you are both healthy. If you are ill with signs of a respiratory infection, you should keep a distance also to those closest to you and not have sex. There is no evidence of the coronavirus being sexually transmissible. The coronavirus spreads mainly by droplet transmission and can be transmitted via kissing if you are infected by the virus. Contact transmission can occur if your hands have virus on them and you come into contact with mucous membranes of the nose or mouth. Washing your hands is therefore a good advice whether you are having sex with yourself or others.</p>
<list><p type="listitem">E  njoy your own body. You are your safest sexual partner - masturbation will not spread the coronavirus. Wash sex toys well before and after use.</p>
<p type="listitem">Enjoy sex with your regular partner.</p>
<p type="listitem">Stick to one partner and avoid random sexual contacts. If you are having sex with others, limit the number of sexual partners as much as possible. Avoid kissing and oral sex. If you choose to have oral sex, use a condom / dental dam to avoid saliva. Do not share sex toys.</p>
<p type="listitem">If you meet your sexual partners online, via dating apps etc, you can consider taking a break from meeting people in person. Video dating, sexting and chat rooms can be an exciting option. Be webwise!</p>
</list><p type="title">Follow the advice for infection control</p>
<p>We've grown accustomed to hearing them, but the following advice are still very valid to the present coronavirus situation:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Wash your hands often and thoroughly</p>
<p type="listitem">Keep a distance to others</p>
<p type="listitem">Stay at home if you are ill</p>
<p type="listitem">Follow the recommendations from the health authorities</p>
</list><p type="title">How to prevent transmission?</p>
<p>Good habits to prevent transmission of the coronavirus</p>
<p>(in Norwegian).</p>
</body></document>
