<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Gradual resumption of public life</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="helsenorge.no" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>2987</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://helsenorge.no/coronavirus/events-and-activities?redirect=false</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="omfattende_tiltak_for_aa_hindre_spredning_av_koronaviruset.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="doaibmabijut_eastadit_koronavirusa_njoammumis.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 180635 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p>Coronavirus in Norway: Measures to limit the transmission of the virus - helsenorge.no</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedmeny</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til innholdet</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Min helse</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="rmn">helsenorge.no</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="pol">Meny</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Søk</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Søk...</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Søk...</p>
<p type="title">Gradual resumption of public life</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nno">Norsk bokmål</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">Sámi</p>
</list><p>On Thursday May 7th, 2020 the Government presented a plan on how to further handle the covid-19 situation in Norway. A controlled and stepwise reopening of society and a plan for adjustments of the corona measures is proposed.</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sidebilde</p>
<p xml:lang="fit">Mostphotos</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Sideinnhold</p>
<p>The measures imposed have shown good effect. On this basis, the Government has decided on a plan for a stepwise reopening of society as we move closer to summer. Here's a timetable for the gradual lifting of restrictions in many different languages .</p>
<p>During week 20 (within May 15th, 2020) all levels of all primary and secondary schools shall reopen.</p>
<p>It is crucial that we continue to follow the advice of the health authorities on social distancing, good hand hygiene and staying at home when we are ill. In order to continue the reopening of society we need to take extra care to keep the situation under control.</p>
<p type="title">We need to keep our distance and practice good hand hygiene</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Seksjon 1 Innhold</p>
<p>Businesses that reopen are to follow industry standards for infection control. Outside of these businesses it is important that everyone continues to follow the basic advice for infection control, keeps a good distance to others and washes their hands frequently.</p>
<p>When we are together, we should not be more than 20 persons in a group and keep a distance of at least 1 metre between us, more if and where possible. This distance applies both to persons within the group and to other people. It does not apply to persons who live in the same household.</p>
<p type="title">Changes to closing and ban</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Seksjon 2 Innhold</p>
<p>Together we have managed to get the transmission of the coronavirus under control. Thus the Government chooses to ease the comprehensive measures. The goal is to allow as many as possible of the activities and businesses that have been closed to reopen before the summer holidays, provided the situation and spread is still under control.</p>
<p type="title">The following changes apply from May 7th</p>
<p>Public events with up to 50 people are allowed from May 7th. During the event, people should be able to keep a minimum distance of 1 metre to persons with whom they do not live in the same household. This applies only to events hosted by a responsible organiser who can keep a record of who is present, where good hygiene can be followed and who can ensure that people who are ill do not participate.</p>
<p>Read the full press release from the government on the new advice and guidelines for events here (in Norwegian).</p>
<list><p type="listitem">The size recommendations for groups gathering in private is increased from a maximum of five to a maximum of 20 persons, under the condition that it is possible to keep a distance of at least one metre or more between people.</p>
<p type="listitem">This also means that training and other organised sports activities can be carried out for up to 20 persons who can keep a physical distance of at least one metre. The guidelines from the Norwegian Directorate of Health and the specific sport's own guidelines apply.</p>
<p type="listitem">Sports halls can reopen. The use of changing rooms in sports halls is prohibited.</p>
<p type="listitem">Public events with up to 50 people are allowed, given that people can keep a minimum distance of 1 metre to others and where a responsible organiser can be held accountable. This applies to all types of events, including sports events such as shows, cups and matches. Employees or contractors responsible for the public event are not counted as part of the event. Their role should be defined according to the specific industry standard.</p>
<p type="listitem">The ban on international travels for healthcare personnel professionals is lifted. International travel is still discouraged. Quarantine rules are imposed to anyone arriving from abroad travels.</p>
<p type="listitem">The population should prepare for travel quarantine rules to be valid through summer.</p>
<p type="listitem">Quarantine time is now adjusted from 14 to 10 days. People who are a close contact of a person with a confirmed infection shall be in quarantine. You are considered a close contact if you have been near someone who then shows symptoms of covid-19 within 48 hours, and you were 2 metres or closer to them for 15 minutes or more. You are also considered a close contact if you have been in direct contact (e.g hugging or shaking hands) or been in contact with secretes such as saliva, sweat, snot, mucus and tears from someone who is ill. You will still be subject to quarantine if you have been in contact with an infected person by less than 2 metres for 15 minutes or more. A six months exception from quarantine rules applies to those who have themselves been subjected to covid-19. All persons who develop symptoms of covid-19 must, as all others, stay at home until they have been free from symptoms at least 24 hours.</p>
<p type="listitem">Employers should ensure that employees during work can keep a distance of at least one metre. In areas where employees are dependent on public transport, employers are encouraged to facilitate working from home offices with remote virtual meetings as far as possible, and with physical meetings at work being kept to a minimum. This applies to the Oslo area and other urban areas in particular, where there is a certain pressure on public transport.</p>
</list><p type="title">The following changes apply from May 11th</p>
<list><p type="listitem">All primary and secondary schools shall reopen for all levels during week 20 (within May 15th). Guidelines to control the transmission of infectious diseases should be followed, which implies that all pupils might not be able to attend school at the same time.</p>
<p type="listitem">Adult education and the introductory programmes for refugees can also open during week 20 (within May 15th).</p>
<p type="listitem">Folk high schools will stay closed for the remaining school year, except for short courses.</p>
<p type="listitem">Driver education and driver training can open. Infection control guidelines that apply to other businesses with one-to-one contact should be followed.</p>
<p type="listitem">The aim is to reopen bingo halls and similar venues.</p>
<p type="listitem">For universities, colleges and vocational schools distance education will continue. Students who need to be present at the teaching facility in order to secure their academic progression can get access. The teaching facility should follow guidelines to control the transmission of infectious diseases.</p>
<p type="listitem">For courses under the adult education association and Kompetansepluss distance education will continue. Student who need to be present at the teaching facility in order to secure their academic progression can get access. The teaching facility should follow guidelines to control the transmission of infectious diseases.</p>
<p type="listitem">Guidelines for sports activities will be published, with emphasis on children and youth sports that involve physical contact, such as football etc. The goal is for children and youth to be able to engage in their sport to a greater extent and in a more normal way than today, e.g. by playing internal matches with players from their own team. This must be done in line with guidelines for infection control.</p>
</list><p type="title">From June 1st, the aim is to make the following changes.</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Service and catering businesses that do not serve food can open, if they are able to adhere to the required distance of minimum one metre. Regulations on seating and tables apply.</p>
<p type="listitem">Organised swimming can open, including swimming in school.</p>
<p type="listitem">The Norwegian Directorate of Health and the Norwegian Institute of Public Health will prepare new leisure travel advice within May 15th. The advice will be valid from June 1st onwards.</p>
</list><p type="title">From June 15th, the aim is to make the following changes.</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Events with up to 200 people will be feasible.</p>
<p type="listitem">The aim is to open gyms, provided that the health authorities have established sound measures for infection control in collaboration with the industry.</p>
<p type="listitem">The aim is to open water park and swimming pools to the general audience, provided that the health authorities have established sound measures for infection control in collaboration with the industry.</p>
<p type="listitem">Top level football league matches will be allowed from June 16th onwards, exempt from the covid-19 regulations.</p>
</list><p type="title">Schools and kindergartens</p>
<p>Lower primary schools (levels 1st – 4th) and after school clubs reopened April 27th. By May 15th, all levels of all primary and secondary schools shall reopen.</p>
<p>Conditions are that this can be done in a safe manner and in compliance with regulations to control transmission of infectious diseases. Sending children to school must be safe, and it must be safe for the staff at school to go to work.</p>
<list><p type="listitem">You can find the guidelines for infection control for primary school levels 1st – 7th here .</p>
<p type="listitem">You can find the guidelines for infection control for lower secondary school (levels 8th – 10th) and upper secondary school here (in Norwegian).</p>
</list><p>Based on the precautionary principle and to minimize the risk of transmission some children might be advised not to go back to school. The Norwegian Society of Pediatricians (Norsk barnelegeforening) have in consultation with Norwegian Institute of Public Health prepared an overview of different diagnoses in children and youth, and whether any special considerations need to be taken into account (in Norwegian).</p>
<p>Kindergartens reopened from April 20th. Guidelines for preventing transmission of the virus in kindergartens (in Norwegian) have been prepared.</p>
<p>The goal is that all pupils and students, including those in upper secondary schools, will return to school before the summer holidays. Based on advice from the health authorities a plan will be put in place as to when the individual levels will start school. Announcements will be made well in advance, to allow schools to prepare for additional levels returning.</p>
<p type="title">Other businesses</p>
<p>Businesses with one-to-one contact - such as hairdressers, skin care and massage therapists – were allowed to reopen from April 27th, under the assumption that industry standards for infection control are met.</p>
<p>In order to stay open, businesses that offer e.g. hairdressing, skin care, tattoo and piercing services must be provided in a way that complies with infection control measures. Industry standard guidelines for infection control in businesses with one-to-one contact (e.g. hairdressers and skin/body care) have been developed. The guidelines provide advice on how businesses can adequately safeguard infection control and prevent transmission of covid-19. The goal is to protect customers and employees and limit the transmission.</p>
<p>Businesses where health personnel such as dentist, physiotherapists, psychologists and others with one-to-one contact can meet their patients face-to-face, under the assumption that industry standards for infection control are met.</p>
<p>Industry standards for infection control in health related businesses with one-to-one contact (in Norwegian). These guidelines also apply to personnel in the dental services, where additional guidelines for the dental health services have been developed (in Norwegian).</p>
<p type="title">Events, health services and alternative accommodation</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Seksjon 3 Innhold</p>
<p type="title">Cultural and sports events</p>
<p>School bands, choirs, bands and orchestras can perform music rehearsals in line with Guidelines for infection control at rehearsal (in Norwegian).</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Sports events and organised sports (both indoors and outdoors) where more than 5 people in a group meet and a physical distance of minimum 1 metre cannot be kept are prohibited.</p>
<p type="listitem">Sports activities can be carried out when the distance and groups recommendations from the Norwegian Directorate of Health are followed.</p>
<p type="listitem">The ban on events with over 500 participants has been extended through August 31st, 2020.</p>
</list><p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Health services</p>
<p>The Government will continue to build the capacity of the health services to be able to handle many patients – in particular patients in need of intensive care.</p>
<p>The health services should provide treatment not only to those who are sick because of the coronavirus. Persons who are diagnosed with cancer, chronic diseases or who are injured after an accident should also be given necessary treatment.</p>
<p>Hospitals can now prepare for regular management and planned treatments where possible. The municipalities can also begin to restore a more normal activity in the health and care services.</p>
<p type="title">Alternative accommodation</p>
<p>The municipalities are required to provide alternative accommodation to those in quarantine or isolation if their living conditions or family situation is such that isolation at home is challenging. This can be at a hotel or other accommodation arranged by the municipality.</p>
<p type="title">Other measures</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Seksjon 4 Innhold</p>
<p>Parents who cross borders in order to be with underage children are not required to stay in regular quarantine. This is implemented in the current Covid-19 regulations .</p>
<p>Hospitals have now prepared for normal operation.</p>
<p>The Norwegian Directorate of Health and the County Governors (fylkesmennene) will work with the municipalities to restore normal activity in the municipal health and care services.</p>
<p>The responsibilities of the municipalities for the care of vulnerable children are strengthened.</p>
<p type="title">Public transport and domestic travel</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Seksjon 5 Innhold</p>
<p>Limited leisure travel is still a good measure to prevent transmission. Avoid public transport if you can and avoid places where it will be difficult to keep sufficient distance to others.</p>
<p>The ban on overnight stays at holiday properties outside your own municipality was lifted April 20th.</p>
<p>Travels to a holiday property where you spend time mainly with your own family members or others that you would normally be in contact with at home does not pose a risk of transmission, given that you:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">avoid travels if you are ill or show symptoms.</p>
<p type="listitem">avoid round trips and plan your travels in order not to contribute to an increased risk of transmission from one location to another.</p>
</list><p type="title">Risk of infection and recommendations for public transport</p>
<p>Transmission can occur prior to (waiting area, bus-stop, boarding), during or after (disembarking, baggage claim) travels by public transport. The risk of infection increases with the number of contacts between persons, as well as the proximity and duration of people being restricted to confined areas.</p>
<p>Recommendations for public transport:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Do not travel if you are ill.</p>
<p type="listitem">Keep a minimum distance of one metre to your fellow passengers. If crowded, consider postponing your trip.</p>
<p type="listitem">No more than half of the available seats should be in use. Thus there should only be passengers in every other seat at the most. You can sit next to those who live in your own household.</p>
<p type="listitem">Avoid coughing or sneezing in the direction of your fellow passengers. If you need to cough or sneeze you should use a paper tissue that you then dispose of, or the crook of your elbow.</p>
<p type="listitem">Keep a good hand hygiene prior to, during and after travelling.</p>
<p type="listitem">Avoid unnecessary touching of surfaces.</p>
<p type="listitem">Be considerate of your fellow passengers and other who travel, elderly people in particular.</p>
<p type="listitem">If you take a taxi you should sit in the back seat.</p>
</list><p>Droplet transmission usually occurs within a one-metre distance. Keeping one metre between passengers is recommended in order to limit the risk of transmission. The longer the journey, the more important to keep good distance. The key measure for infection control is for people who are ill to stay at home.</p>
<p>Persons with an acute respiratory tract infection should stay at home , even if the symptoms are only mild. Persons in quarantine or home isolation should not travel by public transport. This applies both to passengers and employees. Good hand- and cough hygiene is also important.</p>
<p>Read the full Infection control guidelines for public transport (bus, train, tram, etc) (in Norwegian) .</p>
<p type="title">Risk of infection and recommendations for domestic flights</p>
<p>Transmission can occur prior to (waiting area, check-in, boarding), during or after (arrival, baggage claim) flights. The risk of infection increases with the number of contacts between persons, as well as the proximity and duration of people being restricted to confined areas. Movement and contact between people are reduced with good routines.</p>
<p>Keeping a good hand hygiene by disinfection or washing with soap and water is the most simple and effective measure to protect yourself and those around you from covid-19. In addition, it is recommended to keep a distance and not to cough or sneeze directly onto others, but rather use a paper tissue or the crook of your elbow if you do not have any tissue available.</p>
<p>Keeping one seat empty between each passenger in the cabin is recommended. Travelers living in the same household can sit next to each other.</p>
<p>As of today, face masks are not recommended for healthy persons in the population by the Norwegian Institute of Public Health . Neither during flights nor when traveling.</p>
<p type="title">People who are ill should stay at home</p>
<p>Persons with an acute respiratory tract infection should stay at home, even if the symptoms are only mild. Persons in quarantine or home isolation should not go to the airport or travel by air. This applies both to passengers and employees.</p>
<p>For more information, see the new guidelines for infection control in aviation connected to the covid-19 outbreak .</p>
<p type="title">International travel</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Seksjon 6 Innhold</p>
<p>All international travel that is not strictly necessary is discouraged. Quarantine rules are imposed to anyone arriving from abroad travels .</p>
<p type="title">Ban on international travels for healthcare personnel professionals who work in patient care</p>
<p>The Norwegian Directorate of Health has issued a ban prohibiting abroad travels for healthcare personnel who work in patient care. The ban applies both to business travel and leisure travel. Costs will be compensated for.</p>
<p>The ban is in accordance with the Covid-19 Regulations, and until further notice the ban thus applies until the regulations are repealed.</p>
<p>Health personnel who wants to take part in humanitarian efforts can be exempted from the travel ban for health personnel. Applications are sent to the Norwegian Directorate of Health who can grant an exemption.</p>
<p type="title">Entry control at health institutions</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Seksjon 7 Innhold</p>
<p>The Norwegian Directorate of Health will prepare guidelines for visits to health and care institutions and the reopening of day care and activity services. The guidelines will accommodate for residents and patients to receive visitors and that day care and activity services are available, while at the same time meeting the requirements for infection control. The guidelines will be made available shortly.</p>
</body></document>
