<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>Finnish Sámi Cultural Centre SAJOS gets its own stamp</title>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <translator>
      <unknown/>
    </translator>
    <translated_from xml:lang="fin"/>
    <year>2012</year>
    <wordcount>496</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index.php?option=com_docman&amp;task=doc_download&amp;gid=1720&amp;Itemid=10</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="sajos_postimerkki_09_01_2012.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="sajos_poastamearka_09_01_2012.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="sajos_frimarke_09_01_2012.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text location="sajos_briefmarke_09_01_2012.pdf" xml:lang="deu"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 134043 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p><em type="bold">Finnish Sámi Cultural Centre SAJOS gets its own stamp </em></p>
    <p>The Finnish  stamp year 2012 w ill start on January 23 w ith the release of a set of four publications. The Sámi  Cultural  Centre SAJOS opened today in Inari, Finland,  is celebrated w ith a miniature  sheet. Other January stamps depict the World Design Capital  Helsinki  2012 project, Helene Schjerfbeck’s 150th anniversary and Valentine’s Day.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">A floor plan gives shape to the stamp </em></p>
    <p>The <em type="italic">Sámi Culture</em> miniature  sheet of four stamps obtained its unusual shape from the floor plan of the Sámi  Cultural  Centre SAJOS. Opened today in Inari by Juutuanjoki River, SAJOS is a centre of Sámi  administration  and culture in Finland.  It also houses various events, congresses and meetings. </p>
    <p>The <em type="italic">Sámi Culture</em> sheet has been fully designed by Nordic efforts. The sheet w as illustrated by Sámi  artist <em type="bold">Merja Aletta Ranttila</em>. The layout has been produced by <em type="bold">Markku Virtanen</em> from Lapland.  </p>
    <p>The self-adhesive stamp sheet’s pattern imitates  leather, w ith a troll-drum being depicted in the middle  of the stamp. The sheet’s motif illustrates three Sámi Goddesses. <span type="quote">“Juksahkka protects hunters and guards boys throughout their lives. Sarahkka  protects w omen and girls from the very beginning  and regulates birth. Uksahkka  is the Goddess of the home  w ho protects houses and the nests of animals and birds,”</span> Merja  Aletta Ranttila  says, describing her design.</p>
    <p>In addition  to Goddesses and the troll-drum, the sheet depicts a w itch, reindeer village, reindeer and lean-tos. The self-adhesive stamps are shaped like mountains.</p>
    <p>The Sámi  Culture  miniature  sheet contains four first class stamps w ith an edition  of 300,000 copies.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Seven new  designers </em></p>
    <p>The <em type="italic">Future City</em> stamp booklet, w hich celebrates Helsinki’s  position as the World Design Capital,  presents seven new  stamp designers w ho w ere aw arded in the open design competition  organized online  in spring 2011.  </p>
    <p>The eight designs aw arded in the competition  w ere <em type="italic">Future City</em> by Chloe <em type="bold">Chapeaublanc</em>, <em type="italic">Onnela</em> by <em type="bold">Sini Henttonen</em>, <em type="italic">Citykani</em> by <em type="bold">Katja Hynninen</em>, <em type="italic">Kaupungin liike </em>by <em type="bold">Daniel Kallström </em>, <em type="italic">Asenne</em> by <em type="bold">Ville Korhonen</em>, <em type="italic">Tulevaisuus rohkeana</em> by <em type="bold">Elias Ollila</em>, and <em type="italic">Color Power</em> and <em type="italic">Mix</em> by <em type="bold">Varpu Kangas</em>.<em type="italic"> </em>All designs entered in the competition  can be view ed at the competition  site at w w w.futurecity.fi..  </p>
    <p>Design agency Kokoro &amp; Moi  turned the aw arded w orks into stamps.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Schjerfbeck’s four w orks in a stam p </em></p>
    <p>The year 2012 marks the 150th anniversary of the birth of artist <em type="bold">Helene Schjerfbeck</em> (1862–1946). In  honour of the anniversary, a booklet of four self-adhesive stamps depicting her w orks w ill be released. The booklet<em type="bold"> </em>designed by<em type="bold"> Teresa Moorhouse</em> includes the <em type="italic">School Girl II</em>,<em type="italic"> Green Apples and Champagne Glass</em>, <em type="italic">Self Portrait,</em> <em type="italic">Black</em> <em type="italic">Background</em> and <em type="italic">Silk Shoes </em>paintings. </p>
    <p><em type="bold">Six sym bols for friendship </em></p>
    <p>This year's Valentine's Day stamps w ere designed by <em type="bold">Päivi Unenge</em>, a Finnish illustrator living in Sw eden. The miniature  booklet called <em type="italic">I Heart You! </em>contains six selfadhesive stamps and motifs, including  little  girls, birds, pets, and, naturally, hearts.  </p>
    <p><em type="bold">Further information: </em></p>
  </body>
</document>
