<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Challenges of the nordic welfare model from the sámi perspective</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="fin"/><year>2011</year><wordcount>313</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index.php?option=com_docman&amp;task=doc_download&amp;gid=1625&amp;Itemid=10</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="nfhk2011_suom.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nfhk2011_saame.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 139793 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p><em type="bold">10. NORDIC PUBLIC HEALTH CONFERENCE </em><em type="bold">”Health Promotion on system level – How Does the Nordic welfare model cope with today’s challenges ? ” </em><em type="bold">24. - 26.8.2011 Turku/Åbo, Finland </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">CHALLENGES OF THE NORDIC WELFARE MODEL FROM THE SÁMI PERSPECTIVE -session </em></p>
<p>Wednesday 24th Aug 2011 at 15.45 – 17.15, University of Turku,</p>
<p>Moderator: Ristenrauna Magga, Executive director, SámiSoster NGO, Finland Language: North Sáme - English hrs 15.45</p>
<p><em type="italic">Opening </em>Prof. Antti Uutela, National Institute for Health and Welfare, Finland 15.50 </p>
<p><em type="italic">Culturally Adapted Health Care – Why and How? </em></p>
<p>Dr. Ole Mathis Hetta, MD, Senior adviser in Sámi Community Medicin, Norwegian Directorate of Health 16.15</p>
<p><em type="italic">Being a young Sámi in Sweden, living conditions, mental health and alcohol habits </em>Lotta Omma, Leg Psychologist, Leg psychotherapist, Dpt of Clinical Sciences, Division of Psychiatry, Umeå University 16.40 </p>
<p><em type="italic">The influence of welfare state and modern lifestyle on the health outcome of Sámi </em>Dr. Heidi Eriksen, MD PhD, Leading physician, Utsjoki Health Center <em type="italic"></em>17.05 </p>
<p>Discussion Dr. Lydia Heikkilä, Sámi Parliament, Northern Finland Social Centre of Excellence, Sámi dpt</p>
<p>Description of the session: The welfare state arrived in Sámi Home Area, in the Nordic countries, relatively late and at a rapid pace. Introduction of the welfare services together with the ongoing modernization processes challenged the traditional Sámi institutions, lifestyles and cultural conducts. The initial starting point of the welfare state ideology was based on production of equal services to everyone regardless of one’s background. The aim of equality functions well for the majority, when the needs and background are similar, but may result in inequalities for the minority with different needs. The complex matters and relationships involved to the question have until so far not been widely investigated. The presentations introduce reflexive Sámi angles of the topical problems related to this phenomenon both from the perspective of public health service production, health promotion and health outcome focusing especially on the cultural perspective. Convenors:</p>
</body></document>
