<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title/>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <wordcount>2591</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.udir.no/kl06/KRO1-03/Hele/Komplett_visning?lplang=eng&amp;read=1</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="laereplan_kroppsoeving.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="laereplan_kroppsoeving.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>Udir.no - Curriculum for physical education</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Hovedinnhold</p>
    <p type="title">Curriculum for physical education</p>
    <p>Laid down as a regulation by the Ministry of Education and Research on 13 June 2012.</p>
    <p>Applicable from: 01.08.2012</p>
    <p type="title">Purpose</p>
    <p>Physical education as a general study subject shall inspire physical activity in all aspects of life and inspire lifelong enjoyment of being physical active. Physical activity is important for everyone as this fosters good health. The physical activity culture, such as play, sports, dance and outdoor life is part of how we establish our identity in society and what we have in common. The subject shall stimulate physical use of the body to enhance individual sensing, experiencing, learning and creating. The social aspects of physical activities mean that physical education is important for promoting fair play and respect for one another.</p>
    <p>Teaching in the subject shall contribute to helping the pupils experience joy, inspiration and a sense of mastery by being physically active and by interacting with others. The subject shall also contribute to helping children and young people develop a sense of self awareness, a positive perception of the body and their own developing identity. It shall help pupils understand the ideas of an ideal body and healthy physical activity, which can influence their sense of self and ideas about health, nutrition, training and lifestyle. Pupils shall learn to understand how their own efforts can help them reach their goals, and what factors can motivate activity and training.</p>
    <p>Pupils shall develop competence through a wide selection of play and different kinds of activities, develop versatility and learn to value exercise and visiting to nature. The subject shall help pupils acquire knowledge about exercise and training, lifestyle and health, and motivate them to have an active life and continue physical training into adulthood. The subject shall provide pupils with physical challenges and the courage to test their own limits during spontaneous and organized activities. Learning in the subject of Physical Education shall attend to traditional and alternative physical activities in the subject and stimulate experimentation and creative development. Key elements of the subject are movement and play, versatile sports, fair play, dance and outdoor life.</p>
    <p>Learning in the subject shall provide pupils with a point of departure for lifelong enjoyment of physical activity and a sense of mastery based on own skills and ability levels. This subject is assessed using a special scheme that includes evaluating pupil effort as a part of basic subject assessment. Many of the competence aims for the subject take the pupils' own physical limitations and skills levels into consideration for assessment.</p>
    <p type="title">Main subject areas</p>
    <p>The subject has been structured into main subject areas for which competence aims have been formulated. The main subject areas complement each other, and should be viewed in relation to one another.</p>
    <p>Physical education is a common core subject for all the education programmes in upper secondary education. Learning in this subject shall therefore be as relevant as possible by adapting each subject to its education programme, as much as possible.</p>
    <p>Physical education has competence aims after the fourth, seventh and tenth year levels in primary and lower secondary school and after Vg1, Vg2 and Vg3 in upper secondary education.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Overview of the main subject areas: </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Year Level </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">The main subject area </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">1–4</p>
    <p>Physical activity in various environments and settings</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">5–7</p>
    <p>Sports activities</p>
    <p>Outdoor life</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">8–10</p>
    <p>Sports activities</p>
    <p>Outdoor life</p>
    <p>Exercise and lifestyle</p>
    <p xml:lang="deu">Vg1 – Vg3</p>
    <p>Sports activities</p>
    <p>Outdoor life</p>
    <p>Exercise and lifestyle</p>
    <p type="title">Physical activity in various environments and settings</p>
    <p>The main subject area Physical Activity in Various Environments and Settings covers development and automation of natural basic movements in different indoor and outdoor environments. Organized activities and spontaneous play in varied environments are key elements in the subject. The main subject area also includes basic knowledge about the body and personal hygiene.</p>
    <p type="title">Sports activities</p>
    <p>The main subject area Sports Activities covers a wide selection of sports, dance and alternative physical activities. Emphasis is placed on movement, play and creative activities that are adapted to the skill levels and aptitudes of each pupil. The selection will vary according to local conditions and individual interests. Participating and performing dances created by the individual and those from other cultures, including youth cultures, are integrated into the subject. Organized activities, free activities and experimentation are key elements in this main subject area. Fair play and common rules for participation are important parts of the subject. The concept of fair play involves showing respect for one another in different activities. Interaction and working together are key elements of this concept.</p>
    <p type="title">Outdoor life</p>
    <p>The main subject area Outdoor Life covers competence and skills needed to do things safely in nature and see the value of visiting natural environments. Attention must be paid to local outdoor traditions, using the local environment and how to orient and conduct oneself in nature during the different seasons.</p>
    <p type="title">Exercise and lifestyle</p>
    <p>The main subject area Exercise and Lifestyle focuses on various activities and how training and exercise can influence one's health. The relationship between physical activity and lifestyle based on individual interests and mastery are important topics in this area. The main subject area focuses on the knowledge, experience and reflection required to carry out various types of exercise and self-training as the basis for an active lifestyle and taking one's own and others skills levels and aptitudes into consideration. Other important topics are how to undertake health-promoting activities and work in an ergonomically correct way.</p>
    <p type="title">Teaching hours</p>
    <p>Teaching hours are given in 60-minute units:</p>
    <p>Primary school</p>
    <p>Year levels 1–7: 478 hours</p>
    <p>Lower secondary school</p>
    <p>Year levels 8–10: 223 hours</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">PROGRAMMES FOR GENERAL STUDIES, EXCEPT FOR</p>
    <p>THE PROGRAMME FOR MUSIC, DANCE AND DRAMA</p>
    <p>Vg1: 56 hours</p>
    <p>Vg2: 56 hours</p>
    <p>Vg3: 56 hours</p>
    <p xml:lang="deu">VOCATIONAL EDUCATION PROGRAMMES</p>
    <p>Vg1: 56 hours</p>
    <p>Vg2: 56 hours</p>
    <p type="title">Basic skills</p>
    <p>The basic skills are integrated in the competence aims where they contribute to development of the competence in the subject, while also being part of this competence. In Physical Education, the basic skills are understood as follows:</p>
    <p><em type="italic">Oral skills </em>in Physical Education involve creating meaning by listening, speaking and in conversation. This involves being able to present impressions from and perceptions of various physical activities. Expressing oneself orally is necessary when deciding on rules for play, various types of games and other kinds of interaction. It means being able to listen to others, respond to others and be aware of the person to whom one is speaking. The ability to communicate orally is also necessary when one is going to organize activities. </p>
    <p><em type="italic">Being able to write </em>in Physical Education deals primarily with written presentations about activities and assessing these. This skill becomes more relevant at higher year levels. </p>
    <p><em type="italic">Being able to read </em>in the Physical Education involves being able to find, interpret and understand information from specific texts dealing with the subject. This provides the basis for assessing important aspects of the subject's activities. This also includes interpreting maps and understanding symbols. </p>
    <p><em type="italic">Numeracy </em>in Physical Education means being able to measure lengths, times and forces. Understanding what these figures tell us is necessary when planning and carrying out training activities. </p>
    <p><em type="italic">Digital literacy </em>in Physical Education involves being able to use digital tools, different media and resources in a suitable and correct manner to solve practical tasks. This involves gathering and organizing information to plan and carry out activities and training, and communicating and documenting these. </p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Competence aims after Year Level 4</p>
    <p type="title">Physical activity in various environments and settings</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">play and participate in activities in various environments where senses, motor functions and coordination are put to the test</p>
      <p type="listitem">perform basic activities such as crawling, walking, jumping, hopping, sprinting, landing, turning and rolling in gymnastics and organized activities</p>
      <p type="listitem">feel safe in water and be able to swim</p>
      <p type="listitem">travel by and on water and explain the dangers</p>
      <p type="listitem">interact with others in different activities</p>
      <p type="listitem">know one's own physical limits and distinguish the difference between one's own skill levels and the skill levels of others</p>
      <p type="listitem">use simple aids and tools from traditional and alternative physical activities</p>
      <p type="listitem">play with others using different kinds of balls and participate in simple ball games</p>
      <p type="listitem">explore, play and express themselves with movement to different rhythms and music</p>
      <p type="listitem">take part in singing games and simple dances from various cultures</p>
      <p type="listitem">ski and skate when conditions allow</p>
      <p type="listitem">make and use simple maps for orientation in the local neighbourhood</p>
      <p type="listitem">use clothing, equipment and simple aids and tools when outdoors in a safe and functional manner</p>
      <p type="listitem">talk about rules that apply to being in a natural environment and being able to move in the countryside without leaving tracks</p>
      <p type="listitem">name the parts of the body and ways of moving</p>
      <p type="listitem">explain the importance personal hygiene has for health and enjoyment, for oneself and for others</p>
      <p type="listitem">comply with traffic rules for pedestrians and bicyclists</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Competence aims after Year Level 7</p>
    <p type="title">Sports activities</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">perform various physical activities that strengthen the body in different ways that promote stamina, coordination and other physical development</p>
      <p type="listitem">swim using basic techniques, including the breaststroke/crawl, the backstroke and under water</p>
      <p type="listitem">comply with rules and principles for interaction and respect the outcome of the game</p>
      <p type="listitem">use basic techniques and simple tactics in some selected individual sports, team sports and alternative physical activities</p>
      <p type="listitem">ski and skate using different techniques when conditions allow</p>
      <p type="listitem">experiment with physical expression and perform simple dances from different cultures</p>
      <p type="listitem">ride a bicycle safely as a means of transport</p>
      <p type="listitem">explain why physical activity is important in everyday life</p>
    </list>
    <p type="title">Outdoor life</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">use orienteering maps in familiar terrain</p>
      <p type="listitem">describe local traditions in outdoor life</p>
      <p type="listitem">participate in different outdoor activities and practice moving about safely in different kinds of weather</p>
      <p type="listitem">plan and carry out an overnight stay in the outdoors</p>
      <p type="listitem">practise some activities with roots in Sami traditions</p>
      <p type="listitem">perform simple first aid</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Competence aims after Year Level 10</p>
    <p type="title">Sports activities</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">train and use different skills in selected individual sports, team sports and alternative physical activities</p>
      <p type="listitem">swim the breaststroke/crawl and backstroke and dive</p>
      <p type="listitem">practice fair play by using own skills and knowledge in cooperation with others</p>
      <p type="listitem">perform dances from youth cultures and other cultures, and work with other pupils to compose basic dances</p>
      <p type="listitem">explain and perform rescue activities in water</p>
      <p type="listitem">explain and perform life-saving first aid</p>
    </list>
    <p type="title">Outdoor life</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">orient themselves using maps and a compass in varied terrain and elaborate on other ways of getting their bearings</p>
      <p type="listitem">practise various forms of outdoor life in different natural environments and explain access rights in Norway</p>
      <p type="listitem">plan and carry out trips in different seasons, including staying the night outdoors</p>
    </list>
    <p type="title">Exercise and lifestyle</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">use play and different kinds of training to develop one's own body and health</p>
      <p type="listitem">practice and explain the basic principles of exercise and training</p>
      <p type="listitem">elaborate on the relationship between different physical activities, lifestyles and health</p>
      <p type="listitem">explain how different ideal body types and different physical activity cultures influence training, nutrition, lifestyle and health</p>
      <p type="listitem">prevent and perform first-aid for sports injuries</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Competence aims after Vg1</p>
    <p type="title">Sports activities</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">practice and give an account of the basic rules for a selected number of sports and activities</p>
      <p type="listitem">practice fair play by including others in sports, regardless of the pupils' levels of skills, in a selected number of sports and activities</p>
      <p type="listitem">make functional use of different skills in selected individual sports, team sports and alternative physical activities</p>
      <p type="listitem">experiment with different kinds of dance and compose dances</p>
    </list>
    <p type="title">Outdoor life</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">practice outdoor life in different natural environments based on local traditions</p>
    </list>
    <p type="title">Exercise and lifestyle</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">give an account of the factors that influence motivating physical activity and training</p>
      <p type="listitem">practice training methods and exercises relating to training stamina, strength and coordination to develop one's own body and care for one's health</p>
      <p type="listitem">plan and carry out warming up exercises and stretching in connection with various training activities</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Competence aims after Vg2</p>
    <p type="title">Sports activities</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">use and instruct others in the principles of fair play during physical activity</p>
      <p type="listitem">practice training to improve techniques, tactics and the ability to interact with others in team sports</p>
      <p type="listitem">practice different methods to improve skills in selected individual sports, dance and alternative physical activities</p>
    </list>
    <p type="title">Outdoor life</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">use nature for recreation, training and outdoor life</p>
    </list>
    <p type="title">Exercise and lifestyle</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">plan, execute and evaluate training to develop one's own body and care for one's own health</p>
      <p type="listitem">use basic principles for training stamina, strength and physical activity in general</p>
      <p type="listitem">exercise in ways that prevent injury and strain injuries, and give an account of the principles for good working techniques and ergonomics</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Competence aims after Vg3</p>
    <p type="title">Sports activities</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">show knowledge and different kinds of skills in sports, dance and other physical activities through functional participation in activities, training and play</p>
      <p type="listitem">evaluate one's own competence in and show how one can develop further in sports, dance or other physical activities</p>
      <p type="listitem">discuss and elaborate on how one's own fair play can influence others in activities, exercise and play</p>
    </list>
    <p type="title">Outdoor life</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">plan, carry out and asses trips in the countryside with map and compass as aids, and elaborate on other ways of getting one's bearings</p>
    </list>
    <p type="title">Exercise and lifestyle</p>
    <p>The aims of the studies are to enable pupils to</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">practise and explain activities and exercises that are relevant for promoting good health, and discuss and elaborate on the possible negative aspects of training</p>
      <p type="listitem">plan, carry out and assess a personal exercising plan based on basic principles of exercising which is relevant for the skills, aptitudes and goals of the pupil</p>
      <p type="listitem">give an account of the relationship between regular physical activity, lifestyle and health, and explain what it means to care for one's own health</p>
    </list>
    <p type="title">Assessment</p>
    <p>Provisions for final assessment:</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Overall achievement assessment </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Year Level </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Provision </em></p>
    <p>10th year level</p>
    <p>The pupils shall receive an overall achievement mark.</p>
    <p>Vg1 programmes for special pathway subjects in vocational education programmes</p>
    <p>Vg2 vocational education programmes</p>
    <p>Vg3 programmes for general studies and vocational education programmes in schools</p>
    <p>Vg3 supplementary programme for general university admissions certification</p>
    <p>The pupils shall receive an overall achievement mark 1</p>
    <p>1 When the subject is taught over several years, only the overall achievement mark from the highest level the pupil has in this subject shall be entered on the competence certificate or school leaving certificate.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Examinations for pupils </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Year Level </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Provision </em></p>
    <p>10th year level</p>
    <p>The pupils have no final examination.</p>
    <p>Vg1 programmes for special pathway subjects in vocational education programmes</p>
    <p>Vg2 vocational education programmes</p>
    <p>Vg3 programmes for general studies and vocational education programmes in schools</p>
    <p>Vg3 supplementary programme for general university admissions certification</p>
    <p>The pupils have no final examination.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Examinations for external candidates </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Year Level </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Provision </em></p>
    <p>10th year level</p>
    <p>There is no provision for external candidates in this subject.</p>
    <p>Vg2 vocational education programmes</p>
    <p>Vg3 programmes for general studies and vocational education programmes in schools</p>
    <p>External candidates shall sit for an oral-practical examination that is prepared and graded locally.</p>
    <p>The general provisions on assessment have been laid down in the Regulations relating to the Norwegian Education Act.</p>
  </body>
</document>
