<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Saamelaisopetur Suomessa. Tutkomus saamelaisopettajien opetustyöstä suomalaiskouluissa.</title><genre code="science"/><author><person firstname="Rauna" lastname="Rahko-Ravantti" sex="f" born="" nationality="FI"/></author><year>2016</year><wordcount>323</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>http://lauda.ulapland.fi/bitstream/handle/10024/62576/Rahko-Ravantti_ActaE_200_pdfA.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="rahko-ravantti_phd.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="rahko-ravantti_phd.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 161400 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p>Sámi education in Finland – Research on Sámi teachers’ work in Finnish schools Rauna Rahko-Ravantti Doctoral dissertation, University of Lapland</p>
<p>Sámi education has a strong history of assimilation, and the Sámi school culture is colored with colonization. The educational project of folk education, schooling and school system has efficiently assimilated indigenous peoples within the mainstreaming society for centuries. In this sense, the Sámi people’s situation is, in many ways, similar to other indigenous peoples’ situation. Sámi languages are endangered and the Sámi traditions, skills, and knowledge differ from the mainstream culture. During the past decades, the pursuit has been to change the influence of assimilation through school systems so that schools could strongly support, maintain, and revitalize the Sámi language and culture alongside socioeconomic and other societal factors. The Finnish constitution defines that the Sámi people have the right to maintain and develop their own language and culture. Teachers are core agents in indigenous education and fulfill the legislative goals in practice. Their work is important when heading from colonization to decolonization.</p>
<p>Sámi education and Sámi teachers, who implement Sámi education in</p>
<p>Finnish basic schools, form the core of this study. The purpose was to research Sámi teachers’ work in Finnish schools and their agency as teachers. In addition, their perceptions of the development and change of Sámi education and its future development were studied. Previous studies have been conducted mainly in Norway, and therefore this study is the first doctoral thesis about the state of Sámi education in Finland from the Sámi teachers’ perspective.</p>
<p>This was a qualitative study investigating Sámi teachers’ perceptions. Sámi teachers (N=10) whose mother tongue was Sámi were interviewed. The data were analyzed with the so-called sacred circle or medicine wheel that is widely used in indigenous research. According to it, Sámi teachers’ perceptions could be grouped by doors opening to four cardinal points. The West Door described the influence of the history of colonialism on today’s teachers’</p>
</body></document>
