<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>”Dat ii leat dušše dat giella” – ”Se ei ole vain se kieli”.  Tapaustutkimus saamenkielisestä kielipesästä saamelaisessa varhaiskasvatuksessa</title>
    <genre code="science"/>
    <author>
      <person firstname="Rauni" lastname="Äärelä" sex="f" born="" nationality="FI"/>
    </author>
    <year>2016</year>
    <wordcount>636</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <license type="standard"/>
    </availability>
    <origFileName>http://lauda.ulapland.fi/bitstream/handle/10024/62619/Äärelä_Rauni_ActaE_203pdfA.pdf</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="rauni_aarele_phd.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="rauni_aarele_phd.pdf"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 161400 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>The research results comprise language nest practices that were divided into primary and secondary practices. The primary practices were necessary activities that formed a part of everyday child care, such as dining, language support in everyday situations (e.g., arrival and departure from the child care, dressing, cleaning), nap time, and outdoor time. The secondary practices were special features of the everyday life in the language nest. They were divided into following categories: themed work in the language nest; guided morning circles; narration and the world of fairytales; plays and tasks that enhance language knowledge; visitors adding to cultural learning contents; and seasonal activities. According to the findings, the primary and secondary practices were Sámi-speaking activities that were based on the Sámi culture. Cultural values of Sámi upbringing could be recognized in the everyday life of the language nest. As a whole, the everyday life appeared as a socio-cultural basis for growth, raising children as a part of Sámi culture and language community. The language nest operated and transformed in a liminal state. In order to turn into an established form of operation, language nests have to be further developed. According to this study, the language nest teachers developed their work actively in collaboration with the surrounding community. They tried to develop and renew it even though the continuation and availability of resources of the language nest were uncertain. Language nests do not have common national guidelines and there are no learning materials based on the language immersion method to be used in language nests. Furthermore, Sámi-speaking language nest teachers do not have any structured education that would be based on the language immersion method. The language nest employees practiced based on their own expertise and strong experience. They reported that they would need additional education and opportunities of sharing information about good practices with their colleagues. According to the language nest teachers, the Sámi language nest would need a common framework, including a curriculum and guidelines. In addition, it would need premises, learning environments, and materials that are based on the Sámi culture. The language nest teachers also wanted to create stronger networks with other language nests. Likewise, they wished to strengthen collaboration with the immediate surrounding community and other partners.</p>
    <p>Based on the research, the concept of <span type="quote">“language nest pedagogy”</span> was created. The model of language nest pedagogy was constructed in the form of Sámi cradle ball (<em type="italic">šiella</em> in North-Sámi). The rings illustrate the principles of language nest pedagogy that are the practices through which children learn language in the language nest. The main Sámi colors in the background highlight the Sámi framework of language learning: the revitalization of the Sámi language, Sámi culture, Sámi education, and Sámi language learning. This doctoral research is the first one to describe the practices of a Sámi language nest. As a pioneering work, it provides first-hand information about the operation of the language nest and the implementation of language immersion in the revitalization of the Sámi language in early childhood education. Even though language nests have operated already almost three decades, they still have to fight for their existence. This study showed how a language nest can provide a meaningful and stimulating learning environment to revitalize the Sámi language and culture and how manifold are the solutions that the language nest teachers have created to revitalize the Sámi language. Furthermore, the language nest teachers are strongly committed to the development of language nests and its success. Their way of working sets an example of the operation of a language nest. The study provided grounds for the establishment of language nests and attested that language nests have a first-rate and far-reaching importance for the revitalization of the Sámi language. </p>
    <p>Key words: the Sámi language, language immersion, language nest, revitalization of the Sámi language, case study, Sámi early childhood education</p>
  </body>
</document>
