<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>AgustaWestland lea ožžon fálaldaga skáhput ođđa gádjunhelikopteriid - regjeringen.no</title>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <person firstname="" lastname="Ministry of Justice and Public Security" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/>
    </author>
    <year>2013</year>
    <publChannel>
      <publication>
        <publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher>
      </publication>
    </publChannel>
    <wordcount>288</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/jd/press-center/pressemeldinger/20131/agustawestland-awarded-contract.html?id=747342</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="agustawestland-tildelt-kontrakt-om-lever_id_747342.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="agustawestland-lea-oon-falaldaga-skahput_id_747342.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 64438 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>AgustaWestland awarded contract - regjeringen.no</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>AgustaWestland AW 101 – the new Norwegian search and rescue helicopter (Photo: AgustaWestland)</p>
    <p><em type="italic">The Ministry of Justice and Public Security has awarded AgustaWestland Ltd. the contract for the delivery of new search and rescue helicopters to replace the current Sea King. </em></p>
    <p>AgustaWestland was on the 4 th December awarded the contract for delivery of 16 new search and rescue helicopters to Norway. The contract will provide a significant strengthening of the public search and rescue service and ensure emergency readiness throughout the country.</p>
    <p>- I am very pleased that we soon will be signing the contract with AgustaWestland. This will insure a significantly improved safety for people at sea, along the coast and in remote areas around the country, says the Minister of Justice and Public Security, Anders Anundsen.</p>
    <p>The new helicopters will be able to relieve significantly more people in distress, be noticeably faster and with longer range than today - under virtually all weather conditions. Additionally, search capability and the possibility for medical treatment are significantly improved.</p>
    <p>AgustaWestland AW 101 is the candidate that in total, after intensive negotiations, best meets the demands for Norway's future SAR helicopter. On 7 November 2013 the Government gave the Ministry of Justice and Public Security the authorization to finalize the negotiation and sign the contract for the new rescue helicopter .</p>
    <p>The acquisition process started on 21. October 2011 with the announcement of prequalification. Tender documents were released on12. July 2012 and the offers was received from four bidders on 18. December the same year. The intention is to sign the contract with AgustaWestland after the standstill period of fourteen days has expired.</p>
    <p>NAWSARH – New All Weather Search and Rescue Helicopters in Norway</p>
  </body>
</document>
