<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>Departemeantta birra - regjeringen.no</title>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <person firstname="" lastname="Ministry of Children, Equality and Social Inclusion" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/>
    </author>
    <translator>
      <unknown/>
    </translator>
    <translated_from xml:lang="nob"/>
    <year>2006</year>
    <publChannel>
      <publication>
        <publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher>
      </publication>
    </publChannel>
    <wordcount>192</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/bld/BLD-arbeider-for-at.html?id=303</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="om-departementet_id_303.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="dep_id_303.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="departemeantta-birra_id_303.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>About the ministry - regjeringen.no</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">The Ministry of Children, Equality and Social Inclusion seeks:</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">to allow children and young people to grow up safely and to participate in public decision-making processes</p>
      <p type="listitem">to promote economic and social security for families</p>
      <p type="listitem">to promote full equality of status between men and women</p>
    </list>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">to strengthen consumer rights, interests and safety</p>
    </list>
    <p>The Ministry’s activities affect the daily lives of most people in the country, and its decisions and judgments can have a major impact on individuals.</p>
    <p>Most of the Ministry’s budget goes toward benefits for families with children. The three main benefit types are called child benefits, maternity/paternity benefits and cash benefits to the parents of young children. Among social welfare services, the largest budgetary items are for child welfare and protection.</p>
    <p><em type="italic">The Ministry of Children and Equality. Photographer: Roger Holmsen </em></p>
    <p>Specialist departments within the Ministry uphold laws and administer support programmes while performing additional functions related to planning, reporting, incentive measures, counselling, and information dissemination to the general public and affected groups. The Ministry’s departments also support research, testing and programme development in their speciality areas as well as collaboration in international arenas.</p>
    <p>Last updated: 08.07.2014</p>
  </body>
</document>
