<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Olmmošvuoigatvuođat - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="Ministry of Foreign Affairs" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="nob"/><year>2007</year><publChannel><publication><publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher></publication></publChannel><wordcount>815</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/ud/selected-topics/human-rights.html?id=1160</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="menneskerettigheter_id_1160.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="mr_samisk_id_1160.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p>Human rights - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Human rights</p>
<p>The promotion of human rights and democratic principles is at the heart of Norwegian foreign policy. This policy is implemented both at the multilateral level – in forums such as the UN, the OSCE and the Council of Europe – and at country level.</p>
<p>Issues relating to human rights and democracy are a high priority in both foreign and development policy. Whether we are supporting human rights defenders, promoting freedom of speech, fighting the death penalty, or supporting the development of democratic constitutions and free elections, safeguarding human rights is the guiding principle. Priority target groups for Norwegian human rights efforts are human rights defenders, minorities, women, children and indigenous peoples.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway’s human rights dialogues</p>
<p>Norway has started to cooperate more closely with countries where there are human rights challenges but at the same time potential for improvement through dialogue and contact. Currently, Norway is engaged in formal human rights dialogues of this kind with China, Indonesia and Vietnam.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Indigenous peoples in development cooperation</p>
<p>One of the aims of Norwegian development cooperation is to increase the focus on indigenous peoples, while taking an integrated approach to cooperation on indigenous issues.</p>
<p type="title">Norway condemns violation of freedom of expression and other human rights in Egypt</p>
<p>[Press release, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 23.06.2014]</p>
<p>‘I am deeply concerned about the trials that are taking place in Egypt and the sentences that are being imposed. Monday’s judgment against three journalists is shocking and unacceptable. In addition, 183 death sentences that were pronounced earlier have been upheld,’ said Minister of Foreign Affairs Børge Brende.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway condemns reported mass executions in Iraq</p>
<p>[Press release, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 16.06.2014]</p>
<p>Norway is deeply concerned about the situation in western and northern Iraq, where the authorities have lost control of large areas, including Mosul, Iraq’s second largest city.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Nordic Statement on Human Rights and Good Governance</p>
<p type="title">New York, 9 June 2014</p>
<p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 09.06.2014]</p>
<p>'The Nordic countries would like to see a stand-alone goal for good governance and the rule of law in the post-2015 agenda', said Foreign Minister Børge Brende in his nordic statement about the post-2015 agenda at the UN General Assembly 9 June.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway congratulates Ukraine on presidential election</p>
<p>[Press release, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 26.05.2014]</p>
<p>‘I would like to congratulate the people of Ukraine on a successfully conducted presidential election. Despite the fact that many Ukrainians in Donetsk, Luhansk and Crimea were prevented from participating, the preliminary statement of the election observers indicates that the election was conducted in an orderly manner,’ said Minister of Foreign Affairs Børge Brende.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Egypt in breach of international obligations</p>
<p>[Press release, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 06.05.2014]</p>
<p>‘The death sentences in Egypt in recent months are a clear breach of human rights and of Egypt’s international obligations. Norway condemns these sentences, and we have raised the matter directly with the Egyptian authorities,’ said Foreign Minister Børge Brende.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Opening address to the exhibition: The Path to Exclusion</p>
<p type="title">Center for Studies of Holocaust and Religious Minorities, 5 May 2014</p>
<p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 05.05.2014]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"Although the Constitution of 1814 is considered one of the most liberal of its time, its original paragraph 2 excluded Jews from entrance into Norway. (...) Under the occupation the paragraph was reinstated by Quisling in 1942 before it was finally abolished when Norway was liberated in 1945"</span>, said State Secretary Bård Glad Pedersen when he opened the exhibition.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New round of death sentences in Egypt</p>
<p>[Press release, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 28.04.2014]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“It is shocking and unacceptable that an Egyptian court has once again pronounced a summary judgment – this time passing 683 death sentences. We are now witnessing a situation where Egyptian courts are seriously undermining the country’s reputation internationally,”</span> commented Minister of Foreign Affairs Børge Brende.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New agreement on Norwegian support for UN human rights efforts</p>
<p>[Press release, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 28.04.2014]</p>
<p>In Geneva, Foreign Minister Børge Brende and UN High Commissioner for Human Rights Navi Pillay signed an agreement under which Norway will provide NOK 250 million to support the UN’s human rights efforts over the next three years.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Statement at the 19th Session of the Universal Periodic Review Working Group</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="ron">Geneva, 28 April 2014</p>
<p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 28.04.2014]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"It is an honour for me to be here in connection with Norway’s second Universal Periodic Review. Norway has strongly supported the UPR mechanism as an important pillar of the Human Rights Council"</span>, said Miniser of Foreign Affairs, Børge Brende, in his statement at the Universal Periodic Review in Geneva.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Violence and arrests in Venezuela</p>
<p>[News story, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 03.04.2014]</p>
<p>Since the beginning of February, Venezuela has been hit by a wave of protests and political unrest. More than 35 people are reported to have been killed. Many others have been injured. A number of protesters have also been arrested.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p>More documents about this subject</p>
</body></document>
