<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>Riikkaidgaskasaš fágaovttasbargu - regjeringen.no</title>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <person firstname="" lastname="Government.no" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/>
    </author>
    <translator>
      <unknown/>
    </translator>
    <translated_from xml:lang="nob"/>
    <year>2007</year>
    <publChannel>
      <publication>
        <publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher>
      </publication>
    </publChannel>
    <wordcount>569</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/topics/International-relations/International-cooperation.html?id=1166</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="internasjonalt-fagsamarbeid_id_1166.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="internasjonalt_fagsamarbeid_id_1166.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="riikkaidgaskasa-fagaovttasbargu_id_1166.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>International cooperation - regjeringen.no</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">International cooperation</p>
    <p>The Ministry of Foreign Affairs has an important coordinating and advisory role vis-à-vis other ministries since it is the Minister of Foreign Affairs who is responsible for the organisation, coordination and implementation of Norwegian foreign policy. On this page you will find news from the ministries relating to international cooperation. You can explore the topic in more detail by using the menu on the right.</p>
    <p>Subscribe to RSS feed</p>
    <p type="title">Norway working to remove fossil fuel subsidies</p>
    <p>[Press release, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 03.07.2014]</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Free trade agreement with Colombia</p>
    <p>[Press release, Ministry of Trade, Industry and Fisheries, 20.06.2014]</p>
    <p><span type="quote">“The free trade agreement will promote greater economic cooperation between Norway and Colombia,”</span> says Minister of Trade and Industry Monica Mæland.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Norwegian funding for polio eradication increased</p>
    <p>[Press release, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 02.06.2014]</p>
    <p>Norway is increasing its annual support for efforts to eradicate polio from NOK 50 million to NOK 240 million for the next six years. The funding will be channelled through the GAVI Alliance.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">National statement of Norway at the World Health Assembly</p>
    <p type="title">Minister of Health and Care services Mr. Bent Høie</p>
    <p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Health and Care Services, 20.05.2014]</p>
    <p>Minister of Health and Care services Mr. Bent Høie</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">NOK 10 million to girls’ education in northern Nigeria</p>
    <p>[Press release, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 13.05.2014]</p>
    <p>‘Boko Haram’s kidnapping of more than 200 schoolgirls is an unacceptable attack on girls’ right to education. The Government has therefore decided to allocate NOK 10 million to efforts to promote safe schooling for girls in northern Nigeria and help to the communities affected by the abductions. Norway will also consider providing humanitarian assistance for refugees and internally displaced people in the area,’ said Minister of Foreign Affairs Børge Brende.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">The Geopolitics of Energy. A Norwegian Perspective</p>
    <p type="title">Center for Strategic and International Studies (CSIS), Washington, 9 April 2014</p>
    <p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 09.04.2014]</p>
    <p><span type="quote">"The Norwegian approach to energy security is quite simple. We are a reliable and predictable provider of energy – and we will remain so. Making politics out of the energy markets will profit neither consumers – nor producers"</span>, Minister of Foreign Affairs, Børge Brende, said in his address.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">International seminar on air pollution and health</p>
    <p type="title">Oslo, Norad, 20 March 2014</p>
    <p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 20.03.2014]</p>
    <p>"The fight against air pollution and short lived climate pollutants in developing countries is a priority area for Norway. We want to see more attention given to this issue internationally, including by the world’s health authorities, State Secretary Hans Brattskar said in his opening statement at an international seminar on air pollution and health in Oslo on 20 March 2014.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">mHealth meeting with WHO and ITU</p>
    <p type="title">By State Secretary Cecilie Brein-Karlsen</p>
    <p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Health and Care Services, 18.03.2014]</p>
    <p>By State Secretary Cecilie Brein-Karlsen</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Global Health: The Global Burden of Cervical Cancer</p>
    <p type="title">Luncheon seminar at the Norwegian Storting, 17 March 2014</p>
    <p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 17.03.2014]</p>
    <p>State Secretary Hans Brattskar's intervention at a seminar at the Norwegian Storting on 17 March 2014.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">20,000 new seed samples deposited in Svalbard</p>
    <p>[News story, Ministry of Agriculture and Food, 27.02.2014]</p>
    <p>A new shipment of seeds from food plants has been deposited in the Svalbard Global Seed Vault for long-term storage. The shipment, that was transported to the seed vault in Longyearbyen this week, contains 20,000 seed samples from Japan, Brazil, Peru, Mexico and the USA.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>More documents about this subject</p>
  </body>
</document>
