<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Nyheter - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>311</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/nhd/Whats-new/News.html?id=718</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Nyheiter.html?id=718"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyheter.html?id=718"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyheter.html?id=718"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">News - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">3</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">4</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">5</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">6</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Out Of Office</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.09.2010]</p>
<p>Nearly all employees of The Ministry of Trade and Industry were out of the office on the same day recently. On September 7, they visited a total of 59 companies all over Norway – where they learned about everything from burger-flipping and salmon farming to shipbuilding and beer production.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway's pavilion at EXPO 2010 in Shanghai reaches one million visitors</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[25.06.2010]</p>
<p>On June 25th, the Norwegian Pavilion at EXPO in Shanghai welcomed visitor number one million.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The State's Ownership Report 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.06.2010]</p>
<p>- We have put behind us another demanding year for Norwegian business. In the midst of a global economic crisis, however, Norwegian companies have managed better than many dared to hope, Minister of Trade and Industry Trond Giske said.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Vietnam's Deputy Prime Minister Hoang Trung Hai Visits Norway</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[14.06.2010]</p>
<p>Following the invitation from Minister of Trade and Industry Trond Giske, Vietnam's Deputy Prime Minister Hoang Trung Hai has visited Norway this week. Economic relations between Vietnam and Norway was discussed at a meeting at the ministry today.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">One of of China's most powerful politicians on a visit to Norway</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.06.2010]</p>
<p>He Guoqiang is in Norway. He is one of nine members of the standing committee of the Chinese Communist Party's Politburo. He Guoqiang arrived in Norway with a delegation of over one hundred people, of whom about half are from the Chinese business community.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Minerals Act available in English</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[28.05.2010]</p>
<p>The Minerals Act and regulations issued pursuant to the act are available in English.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Discussing a trade agreement with Hong Kong</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[24.05.2010]</p>
<p>The ongoing negotiations on a trade agreement was the main topic when Minister of Trade and Industry, Mr. Trond Giske, had political conversations in Hong Kong this morning. - We expect to finish by the end of the year, Giske said.</p>
</body></document>
