<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Nyheter - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>996</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/smk/Whats-new/news.html?id=884</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Nyheiter.html?id=884"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyheter.html?id=884"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyheter.html?id=884"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">News - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">3</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">4</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">5</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">6</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">7</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">8</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">9</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">10</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">International breakthrough in efforts to improve the health of women and children</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[22.09.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“I am glad to see that so many UN members and organisations have pledged funding today to save women and children. The pledges now total more than USD 40 billion over the next five years. This is the greatest effort the world has seen to reduce child and maternal mortality,”</span> said Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Developing countries must do more to reach the Millenium Development Goals</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.09.2010]</p>
<p>In his statement to the UN high-level meeting on the Millennium Development Goals, Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg stressed that developing countries bear the main responsibility for reaching the Millennium Development Goals.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Treaty on maritime delimitation and cooperation in the Barents Sea and the Arctic Ocean signed today</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.09.2010]</p>
<p>Norway and Russia signed the treaty on maritime delimitation and cooperation in the Barents Sea and the Arctic Ocean in Murmansk today. It was signed by Foreign Ministers Jonas Gahr Støre and Sergei Lavrov in the presence of Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg and President Dmitry Medvedev.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Oslo Conference calls for cooperation and new growth to address global jobs crisis</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.09.2010]</p>
<p>13 September Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg hosted an international conference in Oslo on the challenges of growth, employment and social cohesion, bringing together heads of state and government, the heads of the ILO and the IMF, trade union leaders, academics and employers from around the world.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Treaty between Norway and Russia to be signed</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[06.09.2010]</p>
<p>Norway and Russia will sign the Treaty concerning Maritime Delimitation and Cooperation in the Barents Sea and the Arctic Ocean in Murmansk on 15 September.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Suspected preparations to commit terrorist acts</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.07.2010]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Police Security Service (PST) has apprehended three individuals suspected of having prepared terrorist acts. <span type="quote">“Terrorism creates fear and insecurity, and must be combated. We shall maintain and consolidate public security in Norway,”</span> says Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">State secretary to leave OED for HOD</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[25.06.2010]</p>
<p>In today’s session of the Council of State the King has honourably dismissed Mr. Robin Kåss from his office as state secretary to Minister of Petroleum and Energy Terje Riis-Johansen, and at the same time appointed him as state secretary to Minister of Health and Care Services Anne-Grete Strøm-Erichsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New political adviser</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[24.06.2010]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has from 25 June 2010 appointed Mr. Tord Dale (32), adviser, Oslo, as political adviser to Minister of Health and Care Services Anne-Grete Strøm-Erichsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Changes among the state secretaries</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.06.2010]</p>
<p>State State Secretary Espen Barth Eide has been transferred from the Ministry of Defence to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, while State Secretary Roger Ingebrigtsen has been transferred from the Ministry of Health and Care to the Ministry of Defence. The changes are effective as of 28 June 2010.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway’s Stoltenberg to co-chair climate group</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[06.06.2010]</p>
<p>Norway’s Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg will lead the UN High-level Advisory Group on Climate Change Financing in developing countries. He succeeds former British Prime Minister Gordon Brown. The group shall mobilise the resources promised at the Copenhagen Climate Summit last December.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="tur"><span type="quote">"A military attack against civilian activists is totally unacceptable"</span></p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[31.05.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">”A military attack against civilian activists is totally unacceptable. We are shocked at the news that Israeli naval forces have attacked ships bringing humanitarian aid to Gaza”</span>, says Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg in a comment to the Israeli boarding of the humanitarian convoy to Gaza.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Agreement on financing and quick-start measures to protect rainforest</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[27.05.2010]</p>
<p>Today heads of state and government, ministers and other representatives of some 50 countries concluded an agreement on reducing greenhouse gas emissions from deforestation. Around NOK 25 billion has been pledged for the period 2010–2012 for measures to reduce greenhouse gas emissions from deforestation and forest degradation in developing countries.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway and Indonesia in partnership to reduce emissions from deforestation</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.05.2010]</p>
<p>Norway and Indonesia agreed today to enter into a partnership to support Indonesia’s efforts to reduce emissions from deforestation and degradation of forests and peat lands. Indonesia will take immediate and decisive action to reduce its forest and peat related greenhouse gas emissions. Norway will support those efforts with one billion USD over the next few years.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Acting political adviser</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.05.2010]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has from 20 May 2010 appointed Mr. John Trygve Tollefsen (27), political adviser, Oslo, as acting political adviser at the office during Mr. Sindre Fossum Beyer’s leave of absence until 8 August.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Agreement reached between Norway and the Russian Federation in the negotiations on maritime delimitation</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[27.04.2010]</p>
<p>“Agreement has now been reached between the Norwegian and the Russian negotiating delegations on the bilateral maritime delimitation in the Barents Sea and the Arctic Ocean," said Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway's Stoltenberg receives Russian President</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.04.2010]</p>
<p>Bilateral trade relations are central when Russian President Dmitry Medvedev visits Norway. On 26 April the President participates with Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg at a major Norwegian-Russian trade and industry conference in Oslo.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway to contribute NOK 20 million to improve nuclear security</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.04.2010]</p>
<p>At the Nuclear Security Summit in Washington Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg today announced a total Norwegian contribution of NOK 20 million to the Nuclear Security Fund of the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA). The increased means will be spent on nuclear security efforts in developing countries in the years ahead.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Biodiversity and preservation of rain forests</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[10.04.2010]</p>
<p>Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg and Mexican President Felipe Calderón today visited the Montes Azules nature reserve in Chiapas in southern Mexico. Set in the heart of the Lacadon jungle, the Reserve de la Biósfera Montes Azules is the largest undivided rain forest north of the Amazonas.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Deeply saddened by news of President Kaczynski’s death</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[10.04.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“I was deeply saddened to hear of the tragic death of Polish President Lech Kaczynski. My thoughts are with the Polish people,”</span> Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg commented.</p>
<p type="title">Joint Statement by President Calderón and Prime Minister Stoltenberg</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.04.2010]</p>
</body></document>
