<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Aktuelt - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>639</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/fin/News.html?id=217</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Aktuelt.html?id=217"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="aktuelt.html?id=217"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="aktuelt.html?id=217"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">What's new - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">3</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">4</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">5</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">6</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">7</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">8</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">9</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">10</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p type="title">Fiscal Budget 2011: A modest fiscal tightening</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2010]</p>
<p>Several targeted policy measures helped mitigating the effects of the international financial crisis on the Norwegian economy. Following a decline in mainland output of 1.4 per cent in 2009, growth in the Mainland economy is now forecast at 1.7 per cent in 2010 and 3.1 per cent in 2011, the latter about half a percentage point above trend growth. Unemployment has been kept at low levels throughout the downturn and is forecast at 3½ per cent both in 2010 and 2011.</p>
<p type="title">Level playing field for suppliers of electronic services</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2010]</p>
<p>In a legislative proposal, the Government presents changes to the VAT Act making suppliers not established in Norway obligated to charge VAT when supplying electronic services to Norwegian consumers (B2C). Today, only suppliers established in Norway must charge VAT when such services are supplied to Norwegian consumers. The proposal will create a level playing field for operators established within and outside Norway, supplying electronic services to Norwegian consumers.</p>
<p type="title">New Strategy Council for the Government Pension Fund Global</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2010]</p>
<p>In the National Budget 2011 the Ministry today announced the establishment of a new Strategy Council with four external members. The Strategy Council has been asked to write a report on the long term investment strategy of the Government Pension Fund Global and present this no later than 1 December 2010.</p>
<p type="title">Oslo Conference calls for cooperation and new growth to address global jobs crisis</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.09.2010]</p>
<p>13 September Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg hosted an international conference in Oslo on the challenges of growth, employment and social cohesion, bringing together heads of state and government, the heads of the ILO and the IMF, trade union leaders, academics and employers from around the world.</p>
<p type="title">Webcast: ILO and IMF conference in Oslo on the labour market challenges in the wake of the economic crisis</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="est">Webcast</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.09.2010]</p>
<p>Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg will 13 September host a high-level conference on the international situation in the labour market, where millions of people are unemployed as a result of the global economic crisis. The conference is a joint event by the International Labour Organization (ILO) and the International Monetary Fund (IMF).</p>
<p type="title">IMF and ILO on the outlook for employment in the wake of the global financial crisis</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[02.09.2010]</p>
<p>IMF and ILO today launched a background paper on the <span type="quote">“Challenges of Growth, Employment and Social Cohesion”</span> for the upcoming high-level conference in Oslo.</p>
<p type="title">Long term challenges for fiscal policy</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.08.2010]</p>
<p>The Norwegian economy was also hit by the financial crisis. Even though Norwegian financial institutions were financially sound, the stress in international markets and economies also affected Norwegian banks and the economy but to a lesser extent than many other economies, said Mr. Sigbjørn Johnsen at the Arctic Securities conference today.</p>
<p type="title">Three companies excluded from the Government Pension Fund Global</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.08.2010]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance has excluded two Israeli companies and one Malaysian company from the portfolio of the Government Pension Fund Global (GPFG).</p>
<p type="title">ILO and IMF conference in Oslo to address ways of accelerating a job-rich crisis recovery</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.08.2010]</p>
<p>ILO and IMF announced a joint conference to be hosted by the Prime Minister of Norway, Jens Stoltenberg, on 13 September 2010, in Oslo, to explore new ways of forging a sustainable, job-rich recovery from the global economic crisis.</p>
<p type="title">The Ministry of Finance attends UN-Conference on Responsible Investment</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[24.06.2010]</p>
<p>The UN Global Compact Leader Summit 2010 concentrates on the need to elevate the role of responsible business and investment in bringing about the needed transformation to more sustainable and inclusive markets. At the summit, the UNGC will also present a new guide on responsible business in conflict-affected and high-risk areas. The Ministry of Finance has played an active part in the work to develop this guide.</p>
</body></document>
