<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Nyheter - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>1156</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/fad/whats-new/news.html?id=348</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="nyheiter.html?id=348"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyheter.html?id=348"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyheter.html?id=348"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">News - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New version of the Requirements specification for PKI in the public sector</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[06.07.2010]</p>
<p>The Norwegian ministry of government administration, reform and church affairs is launching a revised version of the Requirements specification for PKI in the public sector. The new version replaces the current version 1.02 from January 2005.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Every citizen now able to look public authorities in the cards</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.05.2010]</p>
<p>A public electronic post journal for the civil service (OEP) is launched as the first of its kind in the world. – From this day on everyone is able to get access to the documents of the central civil service. Until now, only journalists had the right to do so. OEP is democracy and openness in practice, reform minister Rigmor Aasrud says.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">eID success creates demand for more government funding</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.05.2010]</p>
<p>More than half of the adult Norwegian population has acquired the eID called <span type="quote" xml:lang="sma">"MinID"</span>, and the number of users and the extent of on-loggings are still rising. - MinID has developed into a formidable success; the use has doubled over the last year. This is why the government proposes an extra allocation of NOK 13 million, minister of government administration and reform, Ms Rigmor Aasrud, says.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">135 applications for more than NOK 28 million</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[10.05.2010]</p>
<p>- The response is overwhelming. This shows that the Norwegian web community is characterized by innovative power and will, creativity and knowledge, minister Rigmor Aasrud says.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Service for removal of web information launched</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.03.2010]</p>
<p>Anybody who finds unwanted information about oneself on the internet is now able to contact the Norwegian Data Inspectorate’s new service slettmeg.no (<span type="quote" xml:lang="sma">“deleteme.no”</span>) for advice.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Citizen survey shows satisfied users, but public services have room for improvement, minister says</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[14.01.2010]</p>
<p>86 per cent of the citizens of Norway think that their country is close to being a perfect country to live in. We are also satisfied with public services. These are conclusions from the nationwide Citizen Survey which measures how satisfied Norwegian citizens are with municipal, regional and government services.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Changes in the Ministry Structure</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[31.12.2009]</p>
<p>The Cabinet decided on 18 Dec 2009 that certain changes in the ministry’s structure be implemented from 1 January 2010. As a consequence, this website is being updated.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Inger-Anne Ravlum appointed State Secretary</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.10.2009]</p>
<p>Inger-Anne Ravlum today was appointed State Secretary in the Ministry of Government Administration and Reform. The Ministry’s name will from 01.01.2010 be Ministry of Reform and Church Affairs.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Rigmor Aasrud appointed Minister of Reform and Church Affairs</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.10.2009]</p>
<p>Rigmor Aasrud is appointed minister in charge of the Ministry of Government Administration and Reform, and of church affairs in the Ministry of Culture and Church Affairs and the Department of Sami and minority policy in the Ministry of Labour and Social Inclusion. Until 20 December 2009 she also has the political responsibility for the Ministry of Labour and Social Inclusion, with the exception of the department of immigration and the department of integration and cultural diversity.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New obligatory IT standards for the state sector adopted</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[02.07.2009]</p>
<p>The Norwegian government has adopted a series of new obligatory IT standards for the state sector. Now it will be easier for users to get access to information material offered by the government - whether it be graphics, videos, sound or picture material - regardless of which software and computer equipment is being used.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New report: The government must use the culture of sharing on the Internet</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[04.11.2008]</p>
<p>Web users wish to spread information from public sources through internet communities. However, there is a risk that the government is slowing down this process, according to the report eCitizen 2.0, received by Minister of Government administration and reform, Ms. Heidi Grande Røys, recently.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Transparency into government travel activities</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.08.2008]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Government Administration and Reform wants increased transparency into how government activities are affecting the environment. So for the first time, the government has prepared an overview over job related air travel by state employees. – The environmental challenges we are facing, necessitate more knowledge on how government activities are affecting the environment, says Mr Jørund Leknes, political adviser to the Minister.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">High level competition in Bergen</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.07.2008]</p>
<p>State aid and competition regulation were central topics of discussion when Minister of Government administration and reform, Ms Heidi Grande Røys, last Wednesday and Thursday met with European Competition Commissioner, Ms Neelie Kroes, in Bergen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Competition Law being enforced on Svalbard</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[25.06.2008]</p>
<p>While many complain about having to deal with too many laws and regulations, the inhabitants on Svalbard (Spitsbergen) are complaining that they have too few of them. For one thing, they would like to see the Norwegian Competition Law enforced on Spitsbergen as well. Now the Norwegian government is going to fulfill that wish.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">99.8 per cent will get broadband access in 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.04.2008]</p>
<p>At the end of this year, 99.8 per cent of the population will have one or more offers of a broadband internet connection, according to a new report. - The government’s broadband efforts are now yielding results. 96 000 households, which otherwise would have had no broadband access, are now connected. This has been made possible through public appropriations, Minister of Government Administration and Reform, Ms Heidi Grande Røys, says.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Magnificent opera building officialy handed over</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[04.04.2008]</p>
<p>– The building won’t be any obstacle, Minister of government administration and renewal, Ms Heidi Grande Røys, said as she last Friday handed over the key to Norway’s new opera house to Minister of culture and church affairs, Mr Trond Giske. She was referring to the Government’s stated intention that the new opera should offer opera and ballet of a high international standard to a broad audience.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Clearing the pin code chaos on public web sites</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.04.2008]</p>
<p>Users of public electronic services may look forward to a better future. The Norwegian government has decided to establish a public infrastructure – a common hub – for electronic ID (eID). This decision means that in the future citizens may use the same eID to log on to several public electronic services; the number of services will increase and the services themselves will become more advanced; there’s an end in sight to the existing pin code chaos.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norwegians on top in Europe in digital competence</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[25.02.2008]</p>
<p>Norwegians are more advanced users of the Internet than most other Europeans. Even though digital divisions still exist in Norway, according to new EU statistics the generation gap is smaller in Norway than in the European Union.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Open document standards to be obligatory for state information</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[19.12.2007]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Government has decided that all information on state-operated web sites should be accessible in the open document formats HTML, PDF or ODF. This means an end to the time when public documents are published in closed formats only.</p>
<p type="title">Reports on improving the performance of competition policy</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.12.2007]</p>
<p>The Ministry has received the reports from two external R&amp;D-projects being part of the work to improve the performance of the competition policy.</p>
</body></document>
