<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Norga jođiha davviriikkaid suodjalusovttasbarggu - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="Ministry of Defence" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><year>2014</year><publChannel><publication><publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher></publication></publChannel><wordcount>302</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/fd/press-centre/Press-releases/20141/norway-assumes-nordefco-chairmanship.html?id=748235</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="norge-leder-det-nordiske-forsvarssamarbe_id_748235.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="norga-joiha-davviriikkaid-suodjalusovtta_id_748235.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 64438 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p>Norway assumes NORDEFCO chairmanship - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p><em type="italic">As of 1st January 2014, Norway is the chair nation of the Nordic Defence Cooperation (NORDEFCO). </em></p>
<p>– Our goal is to further develop the practical side of the cooperation, says Norwegian Minister of Defence, Ine Eriksen Søreide.</p>
<p>– We want to ensure continued progress in NORDEFCO through result-oriented, efficient and relevant cooperation, the Minister continues.</p>
<p>During the chairmanship, Norway will emphasize the following objectives:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Enhanced security policy dialogue. Further develop NORDEFCO as a forum for useful dialogue on developments and trends affecting the Nordic countries.</p>
<p type="listitem">Strengthen the Nordic ability to deliver relevant military contributions to international peace operations.</p>
<p type="listitem">Ensure further progress on training and exercises. Extend existing cooperation on training and facilitate better coordination between Nordic, Nordic-Baltic and NATO exercise programs.</p>
<p type="listitem">Result-oriented approach to capability and armaments cooperation, directing efforts and resources towards projects with the highest potential for results.</p>
<p type="listitem">Strengthen cooperation on capacity building and security sector reform in post-conflict countries and young democracies, aiming to offer such contributions to NATO, UN and EU.</p>
<p type="listitem">Develop the dialogue between NORDEFCO and Nordic defence industry in order to ensure timely deliveries of materiel to the armed forces and maintain a competitive defence industrial base.</p>
<p type="listitem">Revitalise cooperation on Public-Private Partnerships (PPP). Further develop a common Nordic approach to PPP through exchange of experience and best practice between the nations and identify possible common PPP projects, in dialogue with industry.</p>
</list><p><em type="italic">Background </em>The Nordic Defence Cooperation (NORDEFCO) was established in 2009 and reorganised in 2013. It incorporates all bi- and multilateral cooperative activities related to security policy, operations, capability development and armaments in one single management structure on military and ministerial level. The prime objectives are improved cost-efficiency and increased operational effect. The chairmanship rotates on annual basis between Norway, Sweden, Denmark, and Finland. Iceland is also member of NORDEFCO. <em type="italic"></em></p>
</body></document>
