<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Etater og virksomheter - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>930</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/bld/BLD-arbeider-for-at/Offices-and-agencies-associated-with-the-Ministry-of-Children-and-Equality.html?id=115191</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Tilknytta-verksemder.html?id=115191"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="tilknyttede-virksomheter.html?id=115191"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="tilknyttede-virksomheter.html?id=115191"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p>Offices and agencies associated with the Ministry of Children and Equality: - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Allocation Committee for support to voluntary children's and youth organizations</p>
<p>The Allocation Committee it is an administrative body within the Ministry of Children and Equality whose primary responsibility is to distribute grants and subsidies to voluntary national children's and youth organizations in accord with regulations.</p>
<p>Website of Allocation Committee for support to voluntary children's and youth organizations</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">County Governors</p>
<p>Each county has a County Governor who represents the King and the government. The task of the County Governor’s office is to make sure the goals, guidelines and actions of the Storting are followed locally. On behalf of some of the national ministries, the office fulfils a variety of administrative functions related to municipalities and individuals. County Governors have both supervisory and appeal authority.</p>
<p>Website of County Governors</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">County social welfare boards</p>
<p>County social welfare boards are responsible for decision-making with regard to child welfare services. Today there are 12 such county boards; each one covers one or two counties. The boards comprise a national body which on matters of social welfare are independent of both the Ministry and the County Governor.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Ecolabelling Norway</p>
<p>In Norway there are two official environmental labels, the Swan and the Flower. Their use is overseen by Ecolabelling Norway, a foundation whose leadership board is made up of representatives from the Ministry of Children and Equality, environmental authorities, the Confederation of Norwegian Enterprise, the Federation of Norwegian Commercial and Service Enterprises, the Norwegian Confederation of Trade Unions, the Norwegian Consumer Council, commercial chains and environmental organizations.</p>
<p>Website of Ecolabelling Norway</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Market Council</p>
<p>The Market Council is a national authority. Its main task is to settle complaints regarding marketing. Such complaints must be handled first by the Consumer Ombudsman, the Directorate for Health and Social Affairs or the Norwegian Media Authority. Because the Market Council is an administrative organ, the Parliamentary Ombudsman for Public Administration can also review cases that the Market Council has had under consideration. The actions of the Market Council are final and can only be overridden by the ordinary courts.</p>
<p>Website of Market Council</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">National Institute for Consumer Research</p>
<p>The National Institute for Consumer Research (SIFO) is an independent, multidisciplinary centre for research, testing and reporting on consumer affairs. The institute shares its expertise with public authorities, political leaders, businesses and organizations. It conducts research for the Research Council of Norway as well as state agencies, businesses and a variety of other organizations.</p>
<p>Website of National Institute for Consumer Research</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norwegian Assay Office</p>
<p>The Norwegian Assay Office performs market surveillance and administrative duties in connection with the legally prescribed labelling of precious metals. The office monitors the quality of precious metals, ensuring that gold, silver and platinum items are labelled in accordance with the law and that information provided to consumers is both accurate and adequate.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norwegian Directorate for Children, Youth and Family Affairs</p>
<p>The task of the Norwegian Directorate for Children, Youth and Family Affairs is to provide appropriate supportive measures to children, youth and families in need of help anywhere in the country.</p>
<p>Website of Norwegian Directorate for Children, Youth and Family Affairs</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norwegian Labour and Welfare Organization (NAV)</p>
<p>The Norwegian Labour and Welfare Organization is composed of a central agency and elements of the municipal social service systems. The Norwegian Labour and Welfare Organization helps provide social and economic security while encouraging a transition to activity and employment.</p>
<p>Website of Norwegian Labour and Welfare Organization (NAV)</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Consumer Dispute Commission</p>
<p>The Consumer Dispute Commission is an arbiter of conflicts, particularly those related to goods and building-trade services in which consumers (perhaps with help from the Consumer Council of Norway) have tried and failed to reach an amicable settlement.</p>
<p>Website of The Consumer Dispute Commission</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Consumer Dispute Commission</p>
<p>The Consumer Dispute Commission is an arbiter of conflicts, particularly those related to goods and building-trade services in which consumers (perhaps with help from the Consumer Council of Norway) have tried and failed to reach an amicable settlement.</p>
<p>Website of The Consumer Dispute Commission</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Consumer Ombudsman</p>
<p>The Consumer Ombudsman is responsible, on behalf of consumers, for ensuring that goods and services are marketed in conformance with the Act relating to marketing and contracts. The office of the ombudsman and the businesses that it monitors are expected to negotiate their way to voluntary agreement. If agreement cannot be reached, the ombudsman can refer the case to the Market Council for resolution.</p>
<p>Website of The Consumer Ombudsman</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Equality and Anti-Discrimination Ombud</p>
<p>The Equality and Anti-Discrimination Ombud operates independently within his or her field of expertise but is administratively integrated within the Ministry of Children and Equality. The Ombud fights discrimination and promotes equality regardless of factors like gender, ethnicity, disability, sexual orientation and age.</p>
<p>Website of The Equality and Anti-Discrimination Ombud</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Equality and Anti-Discrimination Tribunal</p>
<p>The Equality and Anti-Discrimination Tribunal handles complaints and appeals regarding recommendations and actions by the Equality and Anti-Discrimination Ombud. The tribunal deals only with matters that first come before the Ombud.</p>
<p>Website of The Equality and Anti-Discrimination Tribunal</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Ombudsman for Children in Norway</p>
<p>The Ombudsman for Children in Norway is charged with promoting the interests of children in both the public and private spheres, and with paying close attention to changes in the conditions of childhood development. The Act relating to the Ombudsman for Children in Norway was adopted in 1981, and the first such ombudsman in the world was appointed the same year. The office of the ombudsman may initiate action on its own or respond to issues referred by others.</p>
</body></document>
