<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Pressemeldinger - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>1098</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/kd/press-contacts/Press-releases.html?id=605</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Pressemeldingar.html?id=605"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=605"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=605"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Press releases - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Prioritising knowledge and education</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2010]</p>
<p>In 2011, allocations to education and knowledge increase with the total of NOK 4.6 billion. -We are pleased that the government, within a tight budget, has chosen to prioritise the most important investment that we can make in our future – the education sector, say the ministers Kristin Halvorsen and Tora Aasland.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Kavli Prizes to eight scientists</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.06.2010]</p>
<p>The names of the 2010 Kavli Prize Laureates was announced by the President of the Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters, Nils Christian Stenseth, on June 3 in Oslo, Norway.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Agreements on cooperation with Russia</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[27.04.2010]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Ministry of Education and Research and representatives of the Russian Federation has signed agreements on cooperation in higher education and meteorology.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Holberg International Memorial Prize 2010: Natalie Zemon Davis</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.03.2010]</p>
<p>Natalie Zemon Davis is one of the most creative historians writing today, an intellectual who is not hostage to any particular school of thought or politics according to the Holberg Prize Academic Committee.</p>
<p type="title">- Supporting the Norwegian knowledge economy</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.10.2009]</p>
<p>More lessons at primary school level and free homework assistance for the very youngest pupils. 5 600 extra higher education places and NOK 350 million for climate research. Public funding for research of almost one percent of gross national product.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">3800 new student places in higher education</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.05.2009]</p>
<p>The Government proposes the establishment of 3 800 new student places at universities and university colleges as of fall 2009. In addition, the Government also increases the funding for the higher education institutions with 80 million kroner. The measures are part of the Revised National Budget released today.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Climate for Research</p>
<p type="title">White paper on research</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[24.04.2009]</p>
<p>The new White paper on research <span type="quote">”Climate for Research”</span>, the government emphasises that public research spending will continue to increase. Furthermore, Norwegian research policy will be defined by nine research policy goals. The Government emphasizes that research should contribute to meet societal and global challenges like climate change.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">White Paper on Teacher Education</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[06.02.2009]</p>
<p>The Government is proposing a new teacher education programme for primary and lower secondary education with a stronger emphasis on subject knowledge and teaching skills, quality of studies and research orientation.</p>
<p type="title">National budget: Knowledge for the future</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.10.2008]</p>
<p>The red-green coalition government will continue to develop the Norwegian welfare state, through investment in kindergartens, education and research. Amongst other things, the government proposes spending a total of around NOK 2 billion on improving the quality of our schools in 2009. Priority will be given to measures to enhance the status of teachers, make the teaching profession more attractive and improve standards in our schools.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Holberg International Memorial Prize 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.09.2008]</p>
<p>Fredric R. Jameson has made outstanding contributions to the understanding of the relation between social formations and cultural forms in a project he himself describes as the <span type="quote">“poetics of social forms”</span>.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Thompson and Tits share the Abel Prize for 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[27.03.2008]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters has decided to award the Abel Prize for 2008 to John Griggs Thompson, University of Florida and Jacques Tits, Collège de France. This was announced by the Academy’s President, Ole Didrik Lærum, at a press conference in Oslo today. Thompson and Tits receives the Abel Prize <span type="quote">“for their profound achievements in algebra and in particular for shaping modern group theory”</span>.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">- A proactive budget for Norway’s knowledge economy</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2007]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Government intends to create 350 new fellowships to boost recruitment of scientists and academics. The Government also intends to increase the capital of the Research and Innovation Fund to NOK 66 billion in 2008. Total budget allocations to research and development will increase by NOK 1.2 billion. More student residences and increased student funding are also on the Government’s agenda for 2008.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Polish-Norwegian Research fund launched</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.09.2007]</p>
<p>Poland and Norway launch a joint research fund to encourage bilateral Polish-Norwegian research co-operation. The Polish-Norwegian research fund specifically earmarks the fields of environment and health.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway gets its first Kavli Institute</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[14.08.2007]</p>
<p>The Centre for the Biology of Memory at The Norwegian University of Science and Technology in Trondheim was proclaimed one of the world’s 15 Kavli Institutes. The Kavli Foundation, founded by Norwegian-American Fred Kavli, has previously established Kavli Institutes at elite institutions such as Harvard, Stanford and Cambridge, to mention a few.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway - A major contributor in the International Polar Year</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.03.2007]</p>
<p>Yesterday, 01 March, saw the kick-off of the International Polar Year (IPY) 2007-2009. The Norwegian government has granted NOK 80 million for polar research under the IPY in 2007 alone. – The IPY will boost international research on the Arctic and Antarctica regions. It will provide us with new knowledge about climate change, as well as other issues, Prime Minister of Norway, Jens Stoltenberg, said during the opening ceremony in Oslo.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">NOK 120 million allocated to Polish-Norwegian Research Fund</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[27.02.2007]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Ministry of Foreign Affairs has approved the establishment of the planned Polish-Norwegian Research Fund. The total budget for the fund in 2007 - 2009 is NOK 120 million (EUR 15 million). Of this amount, NOK 100 million will come from Norwegian EEA funds and the Polish government will contribute in the range of NOK 20 million.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Knowledge is at the core of the High North strategy</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.12.2006]</p>
<p>The Government’s High North strategy attaches great importance to developing knowledge and competence. – Our aim is for Norway to be at the top of the league in developing knowledge in and about the High North, said Minister of Education and Research Øystein Djupedal, when the strategy was presented today.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Big investment in kindergarten and education</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[04.10.2006]</p>
<p>The Government proposes to increase funding for preschool education by some NOK 3.2 billion in 2007. Of this, The Government also proposes to allocate over NOK 370 million to the introduction of free learning materials for students in upper secondary education. Additionally, the Government proposes to increase the capital of the Research and Innovation Fund by NOK 10 billion to NOK 60 billion. Total budget allocations to research and development will increase by almost NOK 900 million.</p>
<p type="title">Looking out! Bologna in a global setting!</p>
<p type="title">The Nordic Official Bologna Seminar in Oslo 28 -29 September 2006</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[27.09.2006]</p>
<p>Ministry of education and research is this week hosting an international seminar on higher education together with the Nordic countries and Nordic Council of Ministers. (27.09.06)</p>
<p type="title">Bilateral agreement on science and technology with USA</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.12.2005]</p>
<p>Norway has entered into a bilateral agreement on science and technology with the United States. The agreement was signed by the Minister of Education and Research, Mr. Oeystein Djupedal, in Washington D.C. on December 9 2005.</p>
</body></document>
