<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Pressemeldinger - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>875</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/fd/press-centre/Press-releases.html?id=399</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Pressemeldingar.html?id=399"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=399"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=399"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Press releases - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norwegian stockpiles of cluster munitions are history</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.07.2010]</p>
<p>On Friday the 16th of July at 2 p.m., the State Secretary for the Norwegian Ministry of Defence, Roger Ingebrigtsen, pushed the button to destroy Norway’s last batch of cluster munitions.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Norwegian Defence Budget 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.10.2009]</p>
<p>The Government proposes to allocate NOK 34.9 billion for defence in 2010. The Northern regions, international operations and the veterans are given priority.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Harald Sunde new Chief of defence</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[29.05.2009]</p>
<p>Lieutenant General Harald Sunde was appointed General and new Chief of Defence by the King in Council today.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norwegian frigate to join EU NAVFOR Atalanta</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[27.02.2009]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Government has decided to send a new Nansen-Class Frigate to the EU anti-piracy naval operation ATALANTA outside Somalia.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norwegian field hospital for UN operation in Chad</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.12.2008]</p>
<p>The Government has decided to offer the United Nations a field hospital for the UN operation in Chad and the Central African Republic (CAR), MINURCAT II, for up to a year from spring 2009. On 15 March the UN will take over from the current EU operation in the same area.</p>
<p type="title">The Joint Strike Fighter recommended to replace the F-16</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.11.2008]</p>
<p>The Minister of Defence recommends that the F-16 is replaced by the F-35 Lightning II Joint Strike Fighter (JSF).</p>
<p type="title">A clear investment in defence</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[28.03.2008]</p>
<p>The Government today presented the new long-term plan for the Armed Forces: A Defence for the protection of Norway’s security, interests and values. The Government wishes to give the Armed Forces a substantial financial boost. The Government also maintains its strategic focus on the northern regions and carries forward its policy for a Defence which has the deep-rooted and broadly based support of the Norwegian people.</p>
<p type="title">Nordic Battle Group on stand-by</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[28.12.2007]</p>
<p>The six month stand-by period for the Nordic Battle Group (NBG) commences at the beginning of the year. The NBG will stand ready to participate in a potential EU-led crisis management operation.</p>
<p type="title">Norwegian force contributions to ISAF in Afghanistan</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[06.11.2007]</p>
<p>The Government has decided to maintain the presence of Norwegian forces in the Faryab province in Northern Afghanistan through 2008, and will also strengthen the stabilization force (PRT) in Maymaneh with 2-3 helicopters, as well as an infantry unit consisting of about 100 personnel.</p>
<p type="title">Defence budget 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2007]</p>
<p>The Government proposes to allocate NOK 31.5 billion for defence in 2008. This is a continuation in real terms of last years level of defence funding and gives a 98 percent fulfilment of the funding allocation for the current long-term plan. The operating budget is NOK 300 million above the level anticipated in the current long-term plan.</p>
<p type="title">Norwegian–Swedish troop contribution welcomed by UN and AU</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2007]</p>
<p>Wednesday 3 October, the UN and the African Union (AU) notified Norway that they gratefully accept the offer by Norway and Sweden to provide an engineer unit for the UN/AU Hybrid Operation in Darfur (UNAMID). The UN and the AU will now notify the Sudanese authorities of the decision.</p>
<p type="title">Norway welcomes UN resolution on Darfur and plans to send troops</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.08.2007]</p>
<p>– We are very pleased that the Security Council unanimously has agreed on a peace operation in Darfur, says Norwegian Defence Minister Anne-Grete Strøm-Erichsen. – Norway and Sweden have been planning a joint contribution of military engineers to a potential UN force to Darfur.</p>
<p type="title">Defence Minister gives the all clear for JSF production phase agreement</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.01.2007]</p>
<p>Defence Minister Anne-Grete Strøm-Erichsen has decided to sign the production phase agreement for the Joint Strike Fighter Programme.</p>
<p type="title">The Government moves the combat aircraft acquisition into the next stage — Maintains three candidates</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.12.2006]</p>
<p>The Government has approved the so-called conceptual solution for the combat aircraft acquisition. The process towards a possible acquisition of new combat aircraft will now be intensified.</p>
<p type="title">Nordic and Nordic-Baltic defence ministers' meetings in Oslo, 7 — 8 November 2006</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.11.2006]</p>
<p>The ministers discussed in their meeting issues such as participation in international operations, SHIRBRIG, Nordic-Baltic support to security sector reform in Ukraine, and also topical NATO and EU questions, in particular related to the upcoming NATO summit in Riga.</p>
<p type="title">The Norwegian Defence Budget 2007 - Northern Area and UN Operations Given Priority</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[06.10.2006]</p>
<p>The Government has proposed a defence budget for 2007 amounting to NOK 31 billion. This represents a continued high budget level for the defence sector. Priority is given to the High North and international operations.</p>
<p type="title">Norwegian officer appointed to top UN post</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.05.2006]</p>
<p>Major General Per Arne Five has been appointed Deputy Military Adviser in the Department for Peacekeeping Operations (DPKO) at the UN headquarters in New York.</p>
<p type="title">Continued Norwegian participation in JSF</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.05.2006]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Government has today decided to continue participation in the Joint Strike Fighter programme. The decision came after Lockheed Martin presented an improved package for Norwegian industry.</p>
<p type="title">30.6 billion for defence</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[17.11.2005]</p>
<p>The Government will allocate NOK 30.6 billion to defence in 2006. This means that the high level of the defence budget recommended by the Bondevik II administration will be maintained. Modernisation of the Armed Forces will continue and more resources will be devoted to the northern regions and to UN operations.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">F-16s for ISAF in Afghanistan</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[14.11.2005]</p>
<p>Norway is to send 3 to 4 F-16 aircraft to Afghanistan for a period of three months in spring 2006.</p>
</body></document>
