<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Pressesenter - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>298</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/hod/press-center.html?id=424</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="pressesenter.html?id=424"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="pressesenter.html?id=424"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="pressesenter.html?id=424"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p>Press centre - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway’s WHO strategy</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.09.2010]</p>
<p>Norway has a seat on the Executive Board of the World Health Organization (WHO) from May 2010 to May 2013. In connection with this, the Norwegian Government has developed a WHO strategy.</p>
<p type="title">State Secretary Pledges Comprehensive Effort to Lead Tobacco Control Efforts in Europe</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[30.04.2010]</p>
<p>- State secretary Roger Ingebrigtsen in the Ministry of Health and Care Services today announced a commitment to a comprehensive strategy and plan to reduce tobacco use in Norway and to regain the leadership role it once had in fighting Norway’s leading cause of preventable illness and death. This announcement followed the completion of an in-country assessment completed this week by the World Health Organization (WHO) in cooperation with the Norwegian government.</p>
<p type="title">Russia takes over the chairmanship of the health collaboration under the Northern Dimension</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[25.11.2009]</p>
<p>November 25 Norway hosted the Northern Dimension Partnership in Public Health and Social Well-being’s Annual Conference. At the conference, Russia formally took over the chairmanship of the Partnership from Norway.</p>
<p type="title">Pictorial health warnings on tobacco products</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[12.10.2009]</p>
<p>By 1 July 2011 all cigarette packs in Norway shall carry a pictorial health warning. -Research shows that pictorial warnings are far more efficient than textual warnings. Pictorial warnings are easier to remember, communicate health risks more clearly and increase the motivation to quit smoking, says State Secretary Ellen Birgitte Pedersen at the Ministry of Health and Care Services.</p>
<p type="title">National strategy to reduce social inequalities in health</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.05.2007]</p>
<p>– Social inequalities in health are a public health concern and an expression of unacceptable systematic injustices, says Sylvia Brustad, Norwegian Minister of Health and Social Affairs. The Ministry of Health and Care Services has in Report No. 20 (2006–2007) to the Storting recommendations of a National strategy to reduce social inequalities in health.</p>
</body></document>
