<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Pressemeldinger - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>1051</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/sd/press-centre/Press-releases.html?id=810</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="pressemeldingar.html?id=810"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=810"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=810"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Press releases - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Invitation to tender on the helicopter route Værnes - Bodø</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.08.2010]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Ministry of Transport and Communications invites airlines in all EAA countries to an open tender procedure for regional scheduled air services on the helicopter route Værnes – Bodø during the period 1 August 2011 to 31 July 2014.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Fiscal budget 2010: Unprecedented spending on roads and railways</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.10.2009]</p>
<p>The fiscal budget proposed for 2010 brings a new substantial boost in spending on transport and communications. The total budget for this sector for 2010 comes to NOK 27 billion – up 21 per cent compared with the adopted budget for 2009. Spending on roads and railways is at a record-high level.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Invitation to tender: Scheduled regional air services in Finnmark and North-Troms – 1 April 2010 – 31 March 2013</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[17.09.2009]</p>
<p>Today the Norwegian Ministry of Transport and Communications has published a tender for scheduled regional air services in Finnmark and North-Troms.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New Air Service Agreements formally signed</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[10.06.2009]</p>
<p>New Air Services Agreements between Singapore and Norway, Denmark and Sweden, respectively, were formally signed today. Mr. Erik Lahnstein, State Secretary of the Royal Ministry of Transport and Communications, signed on behalf of Norway, while Mr. Raymond Lim, Minister for Transport and Vice Minister for Foreign Affairs, signed on behalf of Singapore. Representatives of the Danish and Swedish Embassies in Oslo signed on behalf of Denmark and Sweden, respectively.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Unprecedented boost for transport – nationwide</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.03.2009]</p>
<p>“In the decade ahead we intend to spend a total of NOK 321.9 billion via the fiscal budget on development, operation and maintenance of the road and rail networks and coastal shipping lanes. This is NOK 100 billion or 45 per cent more than in the previous National Transport Plan." This was stated by Transport and Communications Minister, Liv Signe Navarsete, when the Government today presented its White Paper on the National Transport Plan for the period 2010-2019.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Fiscal budget 2009: Historic focus on transport and communications</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.10.2008]</p>
<p>The Government proposes NOK 28 billion to transport and communications via the fiscal budget for 2009 for safer, more environment-friendly and efficient transport nationwide. This is an increase of NOK 3.2 billion compared with 2008.</p>
<p type="title">Invitation to tender: Regional air services in Norway</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[02.10.2008]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Transport and Communications invites all EEA air carriers to tender on scheduled regional air services within Norway, for the period 1 April 2009 – 31 March 2012. The deadline for submitting tenders is 3 November 2008.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Auction of the vacant licence to build and operate a third generation mobile communications systems (3G)</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.12.2007]</p>
<p>The Royal Ministry of Transport and Communications has received one bid in the auction over the vacant fourth licence to build and operate a third generation public mobile communication systems (3G) in Norway. The bid of 47 mill. NOK was made by Mobile Norway AS (formerly known as Automobil invest AS).</p>
<p type="title">Third generation mobile communications system in Norway: Sealed, first-price auction of the fourth licence</p>
<p type="title">Sealed, first-price auction of the fourth licence</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[14.11.2007]</p>
<p>The Royal Ministry of Transport and Communications has received an application for the vacant fourth licence to build and operate a third generation public mobile communication system (3G) in Norway, and announces today that the licence will be assigned in a sealed auction.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Fiscal budget 2008: Strong focus on transport and communications – NOK 24.7 billion</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2007]</p>
<p>The government proposes a NOK 24.7 billion appropriation to transport and communications via the 2008 fiscal budget. This is an increase of about NOK 1.1 billion or 4.7 per cent over the revised 2007 budget.</p>
<p type="title">Invitation to tender: Scheduled air services in Norway - 1 January 2008 – 31 March 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.09.2007]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Transport and Communications invites tenders to an open tender procedure for regional scheduled air services on the routes Andenes – Bodø v.v. and Andenes – Tromsø v.v. during the period 1 January 2008 to 31 March 2009.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Good transport and telecommunication services will promote development in the High North</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.12.2006]</p>
<p>Good transport and telecommunication services are necessary for trade and economic development,” said Minister of Transport and Communications Liv Signe Navarsete.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Auction over vacant license for third generation mobile communication system (3G) in Norway</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[31.10.2006]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Transport and Communications has not received bids in the auction of the vacant license to build and operate a 3G-network in Norway. The deadline to submit bids expired at 10 AM local time. Even though four companies in August 2006 notified their interest, no companies submitted bid in the actual auction.</p>
<p type="title">Third generation mobile communications system in Norway: Sealed, first-price auction of the fourth licence</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[17.10.2006]</p>
<p>The Royal Ministry of Transport and Communications announces today that the fourth licence to build and operate a third generation public mobile communication system (3G) in Norway will be assigned in a sealed auction. ( 17 Oct 06)</p>
<p type="title">Third generation mobile communications system — four companies interested in licence</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[24.08.2006]</p>
<p>Four companies are interested in competing for the vacant license to build and operate a third generation public mobile communication system (3G) in Norway.</p>
<p type="title">Invitation to tender: Scheduled air services in Norway - 1 April 2007 — 31 March 2010.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[24.08.2006]</p>
<p>The deadline for submitting tenders is 22 September 2006. (24.08.06)</p>
<p type="title">New licence for third generation mobile communications system</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.07.2006]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Transport and Communications now announces a vacant spectrum licence to operate a third generation public mobile communications system (3G). - I am pleased to facilitate for establishing a new mobile network and better infrastructure, says the Minister of Transport and Communications Liv Signe Navarsete. (05.07.06)</p>
<p type="title">Stronger Nordic-Baltic co-operation on transport policy after Balestrand meeting</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[21.06.2006]</p>
<p>The Nordic and Baltic Ministers of Transport met at Balestrand in Norway on June 20th and 21st 2006 (NB8-meeting). (21.06.06)</p>
<p type="title">Invitation to tender: Regional air services in Norway</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="sma">Press Release</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.07.2005]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Transport and Communications invites all EEA air carriers to tender on scheduled regional air services within Norway, for the period 1 April 2006 – 31 March 2009. (07.07.05)</p>
<p type="title">Digital terrestrial network for television broadcasting: Renewed invitation to tender</p>
<p type="title">Press release</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[30.06.2005]</p>
<p>Today, the Ministry of Transport and Communications and the Ministry of Culture and Church Affairs have renewed an invitation to tender for a licence to operate and build a digital terrestrial television network in Norway. (30.06.05)</p>
</body></document>
