<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Pressemeldinger - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>2425</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/oed/press-center/Press-releases.html?id=769</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Pressemeldingar.html?id=769"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=769"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=769"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Press releases - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">3</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Full steam ahead on the Norwegian Continental Shelf</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2010]</p>
<p>The activity level in the Norwegian petroleum industry is still high. Exploration activity has the last few years increased substantially and several new discoveries are being made. The Pension Fund is still growing, now approaching NOK 3000 billion. This is more than one million per family in Norway, says the Minister of Petroleum and Energy, Terje Riis-Johansen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">NOK 10 million to opening process in the Jan Mayen area</p>
<p type="title">National Budget 2011</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2010]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Government proposes ten million kroner for environmental studies in connection with the ongoing process to open the sea areas surrounding the island of Jan Mayen for petroleum activities.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">TCM Administration Complex opened</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.10.2010]</p>
<p>Today the Minister of Petroleum and Energy Terje Riis-Johansen opened the Administration Complex of Technology Centre Mongstad (TCM). TCM is the the world’s largest facility for testing and improving CO2 capture technologies.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Broad interest for mature areas on the Norwegian shelf</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Awards in Predefined Areas (APA) 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.09.2010]</p>
<p>By the deadline for applications in the Awards in Predefined Areas (APA) 2010 on the Norwegian continental shelf (NCS), the Ministry of Petroleum and Energy has received applications from 41 companies. The Ministry aims at award of new production licenses in APA 2010 late 2010 or early 2011.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">SDFI values of 865 billion kroner</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[06.07.2010]</p>
<p>The value of the State’s Direct Financial Interest (SDFI) as of 1 January 2010 is estimated at 865 billion kroner. This is the result of a valuation of the SDFI portfolio carried out by Wood Mackenzie on behalf of the Ministry of Petroleum and Energy.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Announcement – 21st Licensing Round</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.06.2010]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Petroleum and Energy hereby announces the 21st Licensing Round, which comprises 94 blocks or parts of blocks in the Norwegian Sea and the Barents Sea.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norm prices for Norwegian crude oil 1st quarter 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[22.06.2010]</p>
<p>The Petroleum Price Board (PPB) has set Norm Prices for Norwegian crude oil lifted in the 1st quarter of 2010. The Norm Prices are used as tax reference prices in the taxation of the crude oil producers on the Norwegian continental shelf and are set in arrears for every quarter.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">More knowledge before new awards</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.06.2010]</p>
<p>The Minister of Petroleum and Energy, Mr. Terje Riis-Johansen, spoke today on a conference concerning the Integrated Management plan of the Marine Environment of the Barents Sea and the Sea Areas off the Lofoten Islands. In light of the Deepwater Horizon accident in the Gulf of Mexico, the minister emphasized the need for more knowledge about the accident before awarding new areas for deep water exploration in the 21. licensing round.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">NOK 261 billion income from the petroleum industry</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.05.2010]</p>
<p>In the Revised National Budget for 2010 the average price of Norwegian crude oil is estimated at NOK 475 per barrel in 2010. This is an upward adjustment of NOK 50 per barrel compared to the National budget.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Sasol new partner in CO2 Technology Centre Mongstad</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.05.2010]</p>
<p>As of today, the South African company Sasol joined as partner in CO2 Technology Centre Mongstad (TCM). According to the agreement between The Norwegian State, represented by the Ministry of Petroleum and Energy and Sasol, the Norwegian State has agreed to sell and Sasol has agreed to buy 2, 44% of the participating interest in TCM.</p>
<p type="title">General Electric expands offshore wind power activity in Norway</p>
<p type="title">Joint press release from the Ministry of Trade and Industry and the Ministry of Petroleum and Energy</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[25.03.2010]</p>
<p>General Electric (GE) gives Norway a pivotal role in their strategy for offshore wind. The American company wants to create a new Offshore Technology Development Center in Oslo in addition to expanding its production of turbine demonstration units in Verdal.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norm prices for Norwegian crude oil 4rd quarter 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[24.03.2010]</p>
<p>The Petroleum Price Board (PPB) has set Norm Prices for Norwegian crude oil lifted in the 4rd quarter of 2009.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The State vs. Statoil ASA – payment under a guarantee declaration – settlement</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.03.2010]</p>
<p>The State, represented by the Ministry of Petroleum and Energy and Statoil ASA have today agreed to settle a case concerning payment under a guarantee declaration issued by Statoil ASA to the State in 1999.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New acrage in APA give new opportunitis in the north - announcement APA 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[19.02.2010]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Petroleum and Energy hereby announces Awards in Predefined Areas (APA) 2010. With this announcement prospective blocks for exploration activities in mature areas of the Norwegian Continental Shelf (NCS) are being made available to the industry.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway joins cooperation on energy grid in the North Sea</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[02.02.2010]</p>
<p>Today the Norwegian Minister of Petroleum and Energy, Terje Riis-Johansen, signed a political declaration on strengthening the regional cooperation on development of an offshore energy grid in the North Sea region.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">APA 2009 - Awards</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[19.01.2010]</p>
<p>The Government has decided to offer 38 production licenses in the awards in predefined areas 2009 (APA 2009).</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Norwegian State versus Statoil ASA – settlement under guarantee declaration – decision by Stavanger tingrett</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.01.2010]</p>
<p>Stavanger tingrett has today decided a case raised by the Norwegian State represented by the Ministry of Petroleum and Energy against Statoil ASA. The dispute concerns whether Statoil ASA is obliged to render a settlement to the State under a guarantee issued to the State in 1999, in connection with modifications of the terminal at Kårstø as part of the Åsgard development.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norm prices for Norwegian crude oil 3rd quarter 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[17.12.2009]</p>
<p>The Petroleum Price Board (PPB) has set Norm Prices for Norwegian crude oil lifted in the 3rd quarter of 2009. The Norm Prices are used as tax reference prices in the taxation of the crude oil producers on the Norwegian continental shelf and are set in arrears for every quarter.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Initiates 21st licensing round</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.11.2009]</p>
<p>Mr. Terje Riis-Johansen, Norwegian Minister of Petroleum and Energy, has invited oil companies to nominate blocks that ought to be included in the 21st licensing round on the Norwegian continental shelf. The invitations have been sent to all licensees on the shelf and pre-qualified companies.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The National Budget 2010: NOK Four billion to Norwegian Renewable Energy Partners</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.10.2009]</p>
<p>The Government proposes to support INTPOW – Norwegian Renewable Energy Partners – with four million NOK.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">High activity on the Norwegian Continental Shelf, but still demanding conditions in the supply industry.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.10.2009]</p>
<p>In a period of turmoil and uncertainty Norway’s oil- and gas revenues have enabled actions to limit the effects on employment, trade and industry. .</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Unprecedented allocation of funds toward carbon capture and storage</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.10.2009]</p>
<p>In the National Budget of 2010, the Norwegian Government proposes to allocate approximately NOK 3.4 billion toward`s CCS.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norm prices for Norwegian crude oil 2nd quarter 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2009]</p>
<p>The Petroleum Price Board (PPB) has set Norm Prices for Norwegian crude oil lifted in the 2nd quarter of 2009. The Norm Prices are used as tax reference prices in the taxation of the crude oil producers on the Norwegian continental shelf and are set in arrears for every quarter.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">APA 2009: Continued broad interest for mature areas on the Norwegian shelf</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.09.2009]</p>
<p>By the deadline for applications in the Awards in Predefined Areas (APA) 2009 on the Norwegian continental shelf (NCS), the Ministry of Petroleum and Energy has received applications from 44 companies. The Ministry aims at award of new production licenses in APA 2009 late 2009 or early 2010.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Opening of Hywind – the world’s first full-scale floating wind turbine</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.09.2009]</p>
<p>Today, the Minister of Petroleum and Energy, Mr. Terje Riis-Johansen, took part in the opening of Hywind; the world’s first full-scale floating wind turbine. Enova supports the project with NOK 59 mill.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Norwegian Government proposes new legislation on offshore renewable energy</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.06.2009]</p>
<p>-This is a historic day. Offshore wind energy may become the next adventure for the Norwegian industry and energy sector. Through the proposed act and the strategy for offshore renewable energy the Government establishes a framework and future possibilities for a new green industry, says the Norwegian Minister of Petroleum and Energy, Mr. Terje Riis-Johansen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norm prices for Norwegian crude oil 1st quarter 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.06.2009]</p>
<p>The Petroleum Price Board (PPB) has set Norm Prices for Norwegian crude oil lifted in the 1st quarter of 2009. The Porm Prices are used as tax reference prices in the taxation of the crude oil producers on the Norwegian continental shelf and are set in arrears for every quarter.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">CCS, market liberalisation and energy security dominate the agenda of the EC – Norway Energy Dialogue</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[28.05.2009]</p>
<p>Carbon capture and storage (CCS), energy security in Europe, liberalisation of energy markets and offshore wind were the main points on the agenda of the EC-Norway energy dialog that Energy Commissioner, Andris Piebalgs and Norwegian Minister of Petroleum and Energy, Terje Riis-Johansen held today in Bergen (Norway).</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Sustained activity on a high level in the Norwegian petroleum sector</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.05.2009]</p>
<p>- Over the last years, the Norwegian petroleum sector has shown a high level of activity, a high exploration rate, and good market conditions for the supply industry. We expect sustained activity on a very high level in 2009, but the outlook is less positive than only a few months ago, says Mr. Terje Riis-Johansen, Minister of Petroleum and Energy.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Carbon capture at Kårstø: The procurement process comes to a halt – integration is under consideration</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.05.2009]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Government has decided to halt the procurement process for the assignment of contracts to construct the CO2 capture and storage (CCS) facility at Kårstø, until the gas-fired power plant’s operational pattern becomes clearer or other solutions that ensure regularity of production and emissions of CO2 from the power plant become evident.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Goliat – an important part of the development in the High North</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.05.2009]</p>
<p>Today, the Norwegian Government has approved the plan for development and operation (PDO) for the Goliat field. The PDO is now being submitted to the Parliament.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">20th Licensing Round – Awards</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[30.04.2009]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Petroleum and Energy is today announcing the awards of 21 new production licenses in the 20th Licensing Round.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norm prices for Norwegian crude oil 4th quarter 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[17.04.2009]</p>
<p>The Petroleum Price Board (PPB) has set norm prices for Norwegian crude oil lifted in the 4th quarter of 2008.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Final norm prices for offshore-loaded Norwegian crude oil in 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[17.04.2009]</p>
<p>The Petroleum Price Board has set final norm prices for offshore-loaded Norwegian crude oil lifted in 2008.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Announcement - awards in predefined areas (APA) 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.03.2009]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Petroleum and Energy hereby announces Awards in Predefined Areas (APA) 2009. With this announcement prospective blocks for exploration activities in mature areas of the Norwegian Continental Shelf (NCS) are being made available to the industry.</p>
<p type="title">Norm prices for Norwegian crude oil 3rd quarter 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[17.02.2009]</p>
<p>The Petroleum Price Board (PPB) has set norm prices for Norwegian crude oil lifted in the 3rd quarter of 2008. The norm prices are used as tax reference prices in the taxation of the crude oil producers on the Norwegian continental shelf and are set in arrears for every quarter.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Norwegian State to take part in the Skanled-project</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.02.2009]</p>
<p>Today, the Norwegian Government has decided that Petoro can take part in the Skanled project with an interest of up to 30 %.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Legislation on offshore renewable energy production – consultation paper sent on public hearing</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.02.2009]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Minister of Petroleum and Energy, Mr. Terje Riis-Johansen forwarded 13 February a consultation paper which outline a new act on offshore renewable energy. The consultation paper is sent on public hearing. Comments are due 17 April 2009.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Skanled – one step closer to development</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[14.01.2009]</p>
<p>Today, Gassco and the partners of the Skanled project have decided to continue the project following a clarification of Ineos investment plans at Rafnes. The new concept does not include a separation plant, and it establishes sufficient capacity for the use of gas in Grenland in the future.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">APA 2008 - Awards</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.12.2008]</p>
<p>The Government has today decided to offer 34 production licenses in the awards in predefined areas 2008 (APA 2008).</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Facts 2008 - Energy and Water Resources in Norway</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[14.11.2008]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Petroleum and Energy launches today <span type="quote">“Facts 2008 - Energy and Water Resources in Norway”</span>. The English version of the publication is available both on the web site and as booklet.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Broad interest in the 20th licensing round on the Norwegian continental shelf</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.11.2008]</p>
<p>By today’s deadline for applications in the 20th licensing round on the Norwegian continental shelf the Ministry of Petroleum and Energy has received applications from 46 qualified companies.</p>
<p type="title">Norm prices for Norwegian crude oil 2nd quarter 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[21.10.2008]</p>
<p>The Petroleum Price Board (PPB) has set norm prices for Norwegian crude oil lifted in the 2nd quarter of 2008. The norm prices are used as tax reference prices in the taxation of the crude oil producers on the Norwegian continental shelf and are set in arrears for every quarter.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Nearly two billion NOK for Carbon Capture and Storage in 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.10.2008]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Government has ambitious goals for carbon capture and storage (CCS), and the work to reach these goals will continue as planned in 2009.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">High oil prices result in record-level income for the Norwegian State</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.10.2008]</p>
<p>The result is an expected increase in the State’s net cash flow from the petroleum sector of about NOK 100 billion this year.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">APA 2008 – broad interest for mature areas on the Norwegian shelf</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.10.2008]</p>
<p>By the deadline for applications in the awards in predefined areas (APA) 2008 on the Norwegian continental shelf, the Ministry of Petroleum and Energy has received applications from 47 companies. The Ministry aims to award new production licenses for APA 2008 early in 2009.</p>
<p type="title">ESA accepts public funding of carbon capture at Mongstad</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.07.2008]</p>
<p type="title">Announcement – 20th Licensing Round</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[27.06.2008]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Petroleum and Energy hereby announces the 20th Licensing Round, which comprises 79 blocks or parts of blocks in the Norwegian Sea and the Barents Sea. This will provide basis for awards during spring of 2009.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The value of the SDFI has been estimated to 834.8 billion kroner</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.06.2008]</p>
<p>The final value of the State’s Direct Financial Interest (SDFI) as at 1 January 2008 has been estimated to NKr 834.8 billion. This is the result of a valuation of the SDFI portfolio undertaken by Wood Mackenzie on behalf of the Ministry of Petroleum and Energy.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Mr. Terje Riis-Johansen appointed Norwegian Minister of Petroleum and Energy</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.06.2008]</p>
<p>Mr. Terje Riis-Johansen (40) was today appointed Norwegian Minister of Petroleum and Energy, representing the Centre Party in the coalition government headed by Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
</body></document>
