<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Pressemeldinger - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>1019</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/bld/Press-Center/Press-releases.html?id=317</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Pressemeldingar.html?id=317"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=317"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=317"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Press releases - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Lysbakken faces questions in Geneva</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[21.01.2010]</p>
<p>On Thursday, 21 January, Norway's Minister of Children, Equality and Social Inclusion, Audun Lysbakken, will be questioned by the UN Committee on the Rights of the Child.</p>
<p type="title">Commission on Child Welfare Experts is named</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.01.2010]</p>
<p type="title">Delay in transfer of care responsibility from immigration authorities to the child welfare service</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[29.06.2009]</p>
<p>Ministry of Children and Equality Ministry of Labour and Social Inclusion Contact: Ministry of Children and Equality, communications office: +47 97 77 36 34 Ministry of Labour and Social Inclusion, media and communications: +47 22 24 51 04 The government has decided to delay, until after 2010, the transfer of administrative responsibility for the care of unaccompanied asylum-seekers under the age of 15. The reason is that Norway in recent years has experienced a major increase in the arrival of asylum-seekers who declare themselves to be unaccompanied minors.</p>
<p type="title">Better protection of children's rights</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[24.04.2009]</p>
<p>Minister of Children and Equality Anniken Huitfeldt proposes changes to the Child Welfare Act that include a strengthening of follow-up care and clarifications designed to make sure children's interests come first in all evaluations that are undertaken. Cooperation between the child welfare service and other public bodies is to be improved. The goal is to provide vulnerable children and youths the same opportunities enjoyed by other young people in the community.</p>
<p type="title">Clear prohibition against child punishment</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[21.11.2008]</p>
<p>- There should be no more doubt over whether we've abolished with the right of parents to punish children physically and psychologically in Norway. Clarifications to the law are intended to remove all discussion about its provisions," says Minister of Children and Equality Anniken Huitfeldt. She's now seeking comments on a proposal for changes to the Children Act.</p>
<p type="title">Improved stability for state-funded foster homes</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[31.10.2008]</p>
<p>Families that agree to provide family or emergency homes on assignment for the state will now be given new rights. New standard contracts provide these families with increased economic security, including rights to occupational pensions, paid sick leave and reimbursement of expenses for work-related injury insurance.</p>
<p type="title">Strengthening anti-discrimination efforts</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.10.2008]</p>
<p>The government has increased the resources of the Equality and Anti-Discrimination Ombud in 2009 by NOK 9 million in order to combat discrimination of people with disabilities and to strengthen existing anti-discrimination provisions. An additional NOK 4 million has been allocated for a new action plan against ethnic discrimination.</p>
<p type="title">Women on parental leave are <span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">"forgotten"</span></p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.09.2008]</p>
<p>On 12 Sept. 2008, the Work Research Institute (Arbeidsforskningsinstituttet) submitted a research report titled <span type="quote">"Consequences of pregnancy and exercise of parental leave in Norwegian employment practice"</span> to the Minister of Children and Equality Anniken Huitfeldt.</p>
<p type="title">Stricter marketing act to prevent illegal marketing practices</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.05.2008]</p>
<p>The government today submitted a proposal for a new marketing act. Cross-border trade is increasing and goods and services are being marketed in new ways. As a result, a modern and efficient regulatory framework is required.</p>
<p type="title">Pre-natal support</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[14.11.2007]</p>
<p>"Children with parents who are mentally ill or who abuse alcohol or drugs must be followed closely from before birth to the start of school. We have initiated a major project in which specialized teams will guide and assist municipalities in their efforts to improve the lives of vulnerable children," says Minister of Children and Equality Manuela Ramin-Osmundsen.</p>
<p type="title">Comprehensive marriage proposal up for review</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.05.2007]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Children and Equality is sending out for review a proposal for a comprehensive marriage act. The proposal is for a single marriage law covering both same-sex and male-female couples.</p>
<p type="title">Immigrant of the Year 2006</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[27.09.2006]</p>
<p>The 2006 prize for Immigrant of the Year was presented today under the auspices of the Ministry of Children and Equality. The second annual award presentation took place at the Riverside Youth Centre.</p>
<p type="title">Comments sought on new marketing law</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[10.07.2006]</p>
<p>Marketing and business transaction techniques have evolved greatly in recent decades, and are increasingly international in character. That is the background for a proposed new marketing law for which the Ministry of Children and Equality began seeking comments today.</p>
<p type="title">Minister of Children and Equality Karita Bekkemellem acts to hinder human trafficking</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[29.06.2006]</p>
<p>Minister of Children and Equality Karita Bekkemellem today launched the campaign <span type="quote">"Stop Human Trafficking"</span> as a part of a Government action plan. The object is to change attitudes by casting light on the connection between the sex trade and human smuggling.</p>
<p type="title">Family and consumer policies changing on 1 July</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[28.06.2006]</p>
<p>Several legislative changes affecting the Ministry of Children and Equality are due to take effect on 1 July. Among them is an extension of the paid parental leave period reserved for fathers after a birth or adoption – the <span type="quote">“father quota”</span>.</p>
<p type="title">Anne Enger Lahnstein leads Equal Pay Commission</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.06.2006]</p>
<p>Minister of Children and Equality Karita Bekkemellem today presented the new Norwegian Equal Pay Commission. One task of the Commission will be to consider ways of narrowing the wage gap between women and men.</p>
<p type="title">European interest in Norwegian gender equality policies</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.05.2006]</p>
<p>European countries are worried about steadily sinking fertility rates. Norway is among the most fertile European countries, with a fertility rate of 1.84 children per woman.</p>
<p type="title">Youth, gender and equality: Nordic ministers meet today in Tønsberg</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[10.05.2006]</p>
<p>On behalf of the Nordic Council of Ministers for Gender Equality, Norway's Minister of Children and Equality, Karita Bekkemellem, received a White Paper yesterday outlining the view of young people toward gender equality.</p>
<p type="title">New instructional guide: Youths who sell or trade sex</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[10.04.2006]</p>
<p>A new instructional guide has been published for social service professionals who work with young people at risk for selling or trading sexual activity. This guide is the only resource of its kind in the world. While previous publications have focused to a large degree on legal issues, this one is practical in nature.</p>
<p type="title">Rules regarding gender balance within boards of Public Limited Companies</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.12.2005]</p>
<p>The Government has decided that the rules regarding gender representation in public limited companies shall be implemented as of January 1, 2006. Public limited companies registered before this time is given 2 years to comply with the requirements of sex representation. All new companies must follow the rules in order to be registered.</p>
</body></document>
