<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Pressemeldinger - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>2181</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/smk/press-center/Press-releases.html?id=894</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Pressemeldingar.html?id=894"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=894"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=894"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Press releases - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">3</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">4</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">5</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">International breakthrough in efforts to improve the health of women and children</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[22.09.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“I am glad to see that so many UN members and organisations have pledged funding today to save women and children. The pledges now total more than USD 40 billion over the next five years. This is the greatest effort the world has seen to reduce child and maternal mortality,”</span> said Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Developing countries must do more to reach the Millenium Development Goals</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.09.2010]</p>
<p>In his statement to the UN high-level meeting on the Millennium Development Goals, Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg stressed that developing countries bear the main responsibility for reaching the Millennium Development Goals.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Treaty on maritime delimitation and cooperation in the Barents Sea and the Arctic Ocean signed today</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.09.2010]</p>
<p>Norway and Russia signed the treaty on maritime delimitation and cooperation in the Barents Sea and the Arctic Ocean in Murmansk today. It was signed by Foreign Ministers Jonas Gahr Støre and Sergei Lavrov in the presence of Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg and President Dmitry Medvedev.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Oslo Conference calls for cooperation and new growth to address global jobs crisis</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.09.2010]</p>
<p>13 September Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg hosted an international conference in Oslo on the challenges of growth, employment and social cohesion, bringing together heads of state and government, the heads of the ILO and the IMF, trade union leaders, academics and employers from around the world.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Treaty between Norway and Russia to be signed</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[06.09.2010]</p>
<p>Norway and Russia will sign the Treaty concerning Maritime Delimitation and Cooperation in the Barents Sea and the Arctic Ocean in Murmansk on 15 September.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Suspected preparations to commit terrorist acts</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.07.2010]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Police Security Service (PST) has apprehended three individuals suspected of having prepared terrorist acts. <span type="quote">“Terrorism creates fear and insecurity, and must be combated. We shall maintain and consolidate public security in Norway,”</span> says Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">State secretary to leave OED for HOD</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[25.06.2010]</p>
<p>In today’s session of the Council of State the King has honourably dismissed Mr. Robin Kåss from his office as state secretary to Minister of Petroleum and Energy Terje Riis-Johansen, and at the same time appointed him as state secretary to Minister of Health and Care Services Anne-Grete Strøm-Erichsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New political adviser</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[24.06.2010]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has from 25 June 2010 appointed Mr. Tord Dale (32), adviser, Oslo, as political adviser to Minister of Health and Care Services Anne-Grete Strøm-Erichsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Changes among the state secretaries</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.06.2010]</p>
<p>State State Secretary Espen Barth Eide has been transferred from the Ministry of Defence to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, while State Secretary Roger Ingebrigtsen has been transferred from the Ministry of Health and Care to the Ministry of Defence. The changes are effective as of 28 June 2010.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway’s Stoltenberg to co-chair climate group</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[06.06.2010]</p>
<p>Norway’s Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg will lead the UN High-level Advisory Group on Climate Change Financing in developing countries. He succeeds former British Prime Minister Gordon Brown. The group shall mobilise the resources promised at the Copenhagen Climate Summit last December.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Agreement on financing and quick-start measures to protect rainforest</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[27.05.2010]</p>
<p>Today heads of state and government, ministers and other representatives of some 50 countries concluded an agreement on reducing greenhouse gas emissions from deforestation. Around NOK 25 billion has been pledged for the period 2010–2012 for measures to reduce greenhouse gas emissions from deforestation and forest degradation in developing countries.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway and Indonesia in partnership to reduce emissions from deforestation</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.05.2010]</p>
<p>Norway and Indonesia agreed today to enter into a partnership to support Indonesia’s efforts to reduce emissions from deforestation and degradation of forests and peat lands. Indonesia will take immediate and decisive action to reduce its forest and peat related greenhouse gas emissions. Norway will support those efforts with one billion USD over the next few years.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Acting political adviser</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.05.2010]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has from 20 May 2010 appointed Mr. John Trygve Tollefsen (27), political adviser, Oslo, as acting political adviser at the office during Mr. Sindre Fossum Beyer’s leave of absence until 8 August.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Agreement reached between Norway and the Russian Federation in the negotiations on maritime delimitation</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[27.04.2010]</p>
<p>“Agreement has now been reached between the Norwegian and the Russian negotiating delegations on the bilateral maritime delimitation in the Barents Sea and the Arctic Ocean," said Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway to contribute NOK 20 million to improve nuclear security</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.04.2010]</p>
<p>At the Nuclear Security Summit in Washington Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg today announced a total Norwegian contribution of NOK 20 million to the Nuclear Security Fund of the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA). The increased means will be spent on nuclear security efforts in developing countries in the years ahead.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Deeply saddened by news of President Kaczynski’s death</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[10.04.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“I was deeply saddened to hear of the tragic death of Polish President Lech Kaczynski. My thoughts are with the Polish people,”</span> Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg commented.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway welcomes new nuclear arms treaty</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.04.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">”The signing of a new nuclear arms treaty between the USA and Russia is an important step on the road towards a world without nuclear arms”</span>, says Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Change of political adviser</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.03.2010]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has appointed Mr. Ivar Vigdenes (25), acting political adviser, Hegra, as political adviser in the Ministry of Petroleum and Energy from 28 March 2010. He succeeds Mr. Jarand Felland, who will leave his post on 15 April.</p>
<p type="title">Norway’s Stoltenberg to give advice on financing effort against climate change in developing countries</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[04.03.2010]</p>
<p>Norway’s Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg has become member of the UN High-level Advisory Group on Climate Change Financing. The group was recently appointed by the UN Secretary-General, to mobilise the financing promised for efforts against climate change during the UN Climate Change Conference in Copenhagen last December.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Acting political adviser</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.01.2010]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has appointed Mr. Ivar Vigdenes (25), political secretary, Hegra, as acting political adviser in the Ministry of Petroleum and Energy for the period 21 January-1 March 2010, during Mr. Jarand Felland’s leave of absence.</p>
<p type="title">Haiti quake a humanitarian disaster – Norway to contribute</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[14.01.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“The earth quake in Haiti is a humanitarian disaster striking a people living in poverty. Locals have made major life-saving efforts, but it is now decisive that we see a broad and coordinated international relief operation. Norway will contribute NOK 40 million to imminent relief efforts”</span>, says Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Acting political adviser in KUD</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.01.2010]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has appointed Ms. Kjersti Stenseng (35), manager, Vinstra, as acting political adviser in the Ministry of Culture for the duration of Mr. Roger Solheim’s service as acting state secretary.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Changes among the state secretaries</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.01.2010]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has appointed Ms. Lotte Grepp Knutsen, state secretary, as acting state secretary at the Office of the Prime Minister for the duration of Ms. Rita Skjærvik’s maternity leave.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway’s Stoltenberg initiates climate group on forests</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[22.12.2009]</p>
<p>Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said in Oslo today that he will initiate a climate group consisting of the most important forest countries.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Changes among the state secretaries</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.12.2009]</p>
<p>In today’s session of the Council of State, the King has made two changes among the state secretaries from 4 January 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Ministry changes from 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.12.2009]</p>
<p>In the 18 December session of the Council of State some changes were undertaken in the structure of ministries as of 1 January 2010. The changes were announced when Government changes were made on 20 October this year.</p>
<p type="title">Norway steps up Amazon contribution after proven results in reducing deforestation</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.12.2009]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“Our financing of the fund is resultsbased and given the reduction, we will increase our contribution to the Amazon Fund to USD 150 million for 2010. It’s very encouraging that deforestation continues to decline in the Amazon,”</span> says Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p type="title">Norway and Mexico launch joint model for Climate Funding in Copenhagen</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[12.12.2009]</p>
<p>Today, Norway and Mexico launched a joint model for climate funding at the negotiations in Copenhagen. The model will establish a Green Fund for financing of climate actions in developing countries. Contributions to the Green Fund should come both from public budgets and from auctioning of allowances. The size of the fund is likely to reach around USD 30-40 billion by 2020.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Climate change and Afghanistan topics at Obama – Stoltenberg meeting</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[10.12.2009]</p>
<p>The need for a strong political climate agreement in Copenhagen and the military and civilian efforts in Afghanistan were important topics in today's talks in Oslo between Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg and US President Barack Obama. Stoltenberg announced that Norway will increase its financial contribution to the Afghan National Army and Police to a total of USD 110 million for the period 2010 to 2014.</p>
<p type="title">President Barack Obama visits Prime Minister Stoltenberg</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.12.2009]</p>
<p>Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg will receive President Barack Obama at the Office of the Prime Minister on Thursday 10 December. The meeting will take place at 10 am.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New political adviser</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[30.11.2009]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has from 30 November appointed Ms. Anja Kristin Salte Hjelseth (25), student and county politician, Ulefoss, as political adviser to Minister of Local Government and Regional Development Liv Signe Navarsete.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New state secretaries</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.11.2009]</p>
<p>In today’s session of the Council of State, the King has appointed three new state secretaries.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New political adviser</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[12.11.2009]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has from 23 November appointed Ms. Sigrid Brattabø Handegard (45), mayor, Jondal, as political adviser to Minister of Transport and Communications Magnhild Meltveit Kleppa.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New political adviser</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.11.2009]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has from 2 November appointed a new political adviser in the Ministry of Trade and Industry.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New political advisers</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[02.11.2009]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has appointed new political advisers.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New state secretary</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[30.10.2009]</p>
<p>In today’s session of the Council of State, the King has appointed Ms. Gina Lund (45), assistant director general, Oslo, as state secretary to Minister of Labour Rigmor Aasrud until 20 December 2009, and from 21 December 2009 to Minister of Labour Hanne Bjurstrøm.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New political advisors</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[28.10.2009]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has from 29 October appointed new political advisers.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New political advisers</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.10.2009]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has from today appointed new political advisers.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Changes among the political advisers</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.10.2009]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has as of today appointed several political advisers.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Changes among the state secretaries</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.10.2009]</p>
<p>In today’s session of the Council of State, the King has appointed several state secretaries.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New political adviser</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[22.10.2009]</p>
<p>The Office of the Prime Minister has from 22 October appointed Mr. Trond Blattmann, adviser, Kristiansand, as political adviser to Minister of Reform and Church Affairs and Minister of Labour Rigmor Aasrud.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Changes among the political advisers</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.10.2009]</p>
<p>Due to today’s changes in the Government, changes have been made among the political advisers.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="tur"><span type="quote">”An excellent team for safe governance”</span></p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.10.2009]</p>
<p>Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg today presented a number of changes in the Government. Seven ministers have been given new fields of responsibility while six new ministers have been appointed.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Changes among the state secretaries</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.10.2009]</p>
<p>Due to today’s changes in the Government, a number of state secretaries have been honourably discharged from their posts and many have been appointed.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Changes in the Government</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.10.2009]</p>
<p>In today’s session of the Council of State, several changes in the Government were made. New ministers are Grete Faremo, Sigbjørn Johnsen, Karl Eirik Schjøtt-Pedersen, Rigmor Aasrud, Hanne Bjurstrøm, Lisbeth Berg-Hansen and Audun Lysbakken. Other ministers have got new fields of responsibility.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Changes among the state secretaries</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.10.2009]</p>
<p>In today’s session of the Council of State the King has honourably dismissed Mr. Jan-Erik Larsen and Mr. Per J. Jordal from their posts as state secretaries to Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Prime Minister praises inspiring, far-sighted Nobel award</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.10.2009]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“The award of this year’s Nobel Peace Prize to President Barack Obama is both inspiring and far-sighted. It is an important award because it may serve as an added stimulus in efforts to achieve the President’s visions,”</span> says Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New policy platform for the red–green coalition Government</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.10.2009]</p>
<p>Continued focus on solidarity, value creation and social justice. This was how Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg, Finance Minister Kristin Halvorsen and Minister of Transport and Communications Liv Signe Navarsete summed up the majority Government’s new policy platform at Soria Moria today. Employment, education, welfare and climate change were singled out as priority areas for the next four years.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Changes among the political advisors</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[02.10.2009]</p>
<p>As Ministers Dag Terje Andersen and Helga Pedersen in today’s session of the Council of State have been honourably discharged from their posts, changes have been made among the political advisors.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Changes among the state secretaries</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[02.10.2009]</p>
<p>As Minister of Labour and Social Inclusion Dag Terje Andersen and Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Helga Pedersen in today’s session of the Council of State have been honourably discharged from their posts, changes have been made among the state secretaries.</p>
</body></document>
