<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Preassadieđáhusat - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="nob"/><year>2006</year><publChannel><publication><publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher></publication></publChannel><wordcount>3611</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/fkd/Press-Centre/Press-releases.html?id=276</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="pressemeldingar_id_276.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="pressemeldinger_id_276.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="preassadieahusat_id_276.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Press releases - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Ban on landings of mackerel from Faroese and Icelandic vessels</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[29.07.2010]</p>
<p>- The irresponsible fishing for mackerel which Iceland and the Faroe Islands have initiated as an attempt to secure future quota shares is a serious threat to the mackerel stock, and undermines the cooperation to secure the necessary conservation measures. I consider this situation very seriously, and it has been the topic of discussions between myself and the European Commissioner for Fisheries and Maritime Affairs, Norwegian Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Lisbeth Berg-Hansen says in a comment.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Very good results in combating illegal fishing</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.04.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“A concerted effort by the Norwegian and Russian authorities has halted illegal, unreported and unregulated (IUU) catches of cod in the Barents Sea, which were estimated at more than 100 000 tonnes a year. Last year, no IUU fishing of cod was detected. The Government has given high priority to combating IUU fishing in the Barents Sea, and the results speak for themselves,”</span> said Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Lisbeth Berg-Hansen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Further review of salvage of German submarine U-864</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.03.2010]</p>
<p>The Government commissioned an external quality assurance report on the proposal for raising the wreck of the German submarine U-864 off the west coast of Norway. This has now been presented, and identifies a number of uncertainties. An accident involving release of the mercury cargo would be a threat to the marine and coastal environment. It has therefore been decided to commission an in-depth review to ensure that any salvage operation is properly planned, takes full account of environmental concerns, and has an acceptable level of risk.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway and the EU have concluded a bilateral fisheries agreement for 2010 and a long-term agreement on management of North East Atlantic mackerel</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.01.2010]</p>
<p>- I am very content that these agreements have now been concluded, and that a difficult period of negotiations with the EU is over. We can now look forward with the view of finding joint solutions to new challenges. We had many rounds of negotiation with the EU last autumn, but the challenges were so difficult that we had to resume negotiations in January. It is of major importance for the fishing industry in Norway and the EU that we now have agreements in place. The industry can now continue their important value creation within a stable framework, said Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Lisbeth Berg-Hansen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Breakdown in the fisheries negotiations between Norway and the EU</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.12.2009]</p>
<p>- I am very disappointed about the EU’s lack of willingness and determination to arrive at a mutually satisfactory agreement for 2010, says Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs, Lisbeth Berg-Hansen.</p>
<p type="title">Quota for the minke whale hunt in 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.12.2009]</p>
<p>The Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs has set a quota of 1286 animals for the minke whale hunt in 2010.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">North Atlantic ban on discards in international waters</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[19.11.2009]</p>
<p>The 28th annual meeting of the Northeast Atlantic Fisheries Commission (NEAFC) adopted a ban on discards in international waters on the major stocks regulated by NEAFC. The adoption is a major contribution in the work towards sustainable and responsible management of fisheries in the high seas. NEAFC also adopted several adjustments of the NEAFC Scheme of Control and Enforcement related to port state control, surveillance of fisheries and catch reporting. These are all important tools in the work of combating IUU-fishing.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway requests WTO consultations on EU ban on trade in seal products</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.11.2009]</p>
<p>Norway has today formally requested WTO dispute settlement consultations, because the Government views the EU ban on trade in seal products as being in contravention of WTO rules. <span type="quote">“In our view, the EU decision is contrary to WTO rules on a number of key points. We will not let this go uncontested. We have therefore requested formal WTO dispute settlement consultations today,”</span> said Foreign Minister Jonas Gahr Støre.</p>
<p type="title">Agreement on Norwegian-Russian fisheries for 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.10.2009]</p>
<p>Norway and Russia have today entered into an agreement on management of the joint stocks in the Barents Sea for 2010. The stock situation is very good and quotas for both cod and haddock have been increased. The long term collaboration on responsible management, research and control provides great benefits for both Norwegian and Russian fishermen and coastal communities.</p>
<p type="title">New strategy for marine bioprospecting</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.09.2009]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“Norway has a long tradition of harvesting the sea and has developed a high level of competence in the marine sector and bioprospecting. Through this new strategy, we are facilitating an exploitation of our marine resources that can provide us with new knowledge and new jobs from the treasure chest of the sea,”</span> said Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Helga Pedersen when she presented the government’s strategy for marine bioprospecting in Tromsø today.</p>
<p type="title">Scotland and Norway sign memorandum</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[17.08.2009]</p>
<p>- Scotland and Norway have signed a Memorandum of Undersanding (MoU) on aquaculture today. - We can learn from each other, and develop our industries even further, says the Norwegian Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Helga Pedersen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Overfishing reduced by 84%</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[28.05.2009]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“Once again, overfishing of cod in the Barents Sea has been substantially reduced in 2008. This means that unreported fishing has been reduced by as much as 84% from 2005 to 2008 and that resources to the value of 1.1 billion kroner are now benefiting the coastal communities,”</span> says Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Helga Pedersen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway proposes new international guidelines for by-catch management and discards</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.03.2009]</p>
<p>"Up to 20 million tons of fish are discarded in the sea worldwide every year. This is a waste of fish which could have been a valuable food resource. Norway has therefore put forward a proposal on developing international guidelines for by-catch management and reduction of discards to the UN's Food and Agriculture Organisation (FAO)," says Norway's Minister for Fisheries and Coastal Affairs, Helga Pedersen.</p>
<p type="title">U-864 is to be raised</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[29.01.2009]</p>
<p>On 29 January the Norwegian Government decided that the wreck of German submarine U 864 is to be raised and the polluted seabed covered by a layer of clean sand and gravel. In 2007 and 2008, the Norwegian Coastal Administration (NCA), assisted by Det Norske Veritas, a private company on technical evaluations and risk assessments, undertook a more detailed study of the feasibility of raising the wreck with its cargo of mercury, and compared this measure against that of covering both the wreck and the contaminated seabed. <span type="quote">“This work has identified the different risk factors in the two options. The decision of raising U-864 is the result of an overall evaluation; key aspects in this regard are the identified risks and the concerns that the coastal population and the fishing industry have over a capping of the wreck”</span>, says Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs, Helga Pedersen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Protective measures for Norwegian coastal cod during 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[19.12.2008]</p>
<p>According to marine scientists, stocks of Norwegian coastal cod have declined since 1994. After a long process, the Norwegian Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs therefore introduced various protective measures to limit the professional fishing of Norwegian coastal cod, effective from 1 May 2004. With some adjustments, these measures have been kept in force from 2005 to 2008. The protective measures will remain in force in 2009 with certain restrictions.</p>
<p type="title">Quota agreement between Norway and the EU for 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[10.12.2008]</p>
<p>Norway and the EU have concluded a bilateral fisheries agreement for 2009. For both parties discard of fish has been the main issue during this year’s negotiations. Norway and EU have agreed on a number of measures directed at the reduction of discard.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New licences for the farming of salmon, trout and rainbow trout</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.11.2008]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs has 7 November 2008 brought before Parliament Bill no. 1 annex no. 4, relating to new licences for farmed salmon, trout and rainbow trout. The Government will allocate 65 new licences in 2009 as follows: Finnmark 7, Troms 8, Nordland 15, Nord-Trøndelag 7, Sør-Trøndelag 8, Møre og Romsdal 5, Sogn og Fjordane 5 and Hordaland 5. Of these, 5 licences will be reserved for applicants who wish to engage in organic aquaculture-production. The licences will be granted at a fixed cost and applicants will be prioritised on the basis of certain defined criteria.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Agreement on Norwegian-Russian quotas for 2009</p>
<p type="title">Secretary General Mr. Jørn Krog, mobile 900 24 447</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.10.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“The stock situation in the Barents Sea is very encouraging, and this will benefit Norwegian and Russian fishermen and coastal communities. Cod and haddock quotas will increase, and will be higher in 2009 than for many years. We see that our long-term cooperation on responsible management, research and control is reaping great rewards,”</span> says Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Helga Pedersen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The wreck of the <span type="quote" xml:lang="vep">“Murmansk”</span></p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.08.2008]</p>
<p>- The Government takes seriously the concerns of the inhabitants of Sørvær about the wreck of the Murmansk. The Government will therefore continue surveying the wreck with the objective of removing it, confirmed Norwegian Fisheries and Coastal Minister Helga Pedersen. On Thursday the Minister is visiting Sørvær to listen to the local community and inform them about the on-going work.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Requirement that all fish that are caught in Norwegian waters, also by foreign vessels, must be landed</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[12.08.2008]</p>
<p>Discard is currently one of the most serious threats against sustainable management. This is in particular the case for those fish stocks we co-manage with the EU in the North Sea. We therefore want a further tightening of the rules governing discard of fish caught by foreign vessels in the Norwegian Exclusive Economic Zone, says Minister for Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Helga Pedersen. I want a requirement that all fish that are caught in Norwegian waters, also by foreign vessels, must be taken to port, regardless of which final port is used, says the Minister for Fisheries and Coastal Affairs.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New Act on Ports and Fairways</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[27.06.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“With its proposed new Act on Ports and Fairways, the Government will facilitate the safety of navigation, efficient transport at sea and sustainable use and management of fairways. The Act also contributes to the efficiency and safety of port operations, which in turn improves the competitiveness of sea transport,”</span> said Helga Pedersen Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs after the Government presented its proposal to the Storting.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">A good cooperation between Norwegian and Russian fisheries authorities</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[14.04.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“The meeting confirms that Russian and Norwegian fisheries authorities still are in a position to cooperate well. We have discussed the positive developments in the illegal fishing in the Barents Sea, Norwegian-Russian cooperation on research, and cooperation in international forums such as NEAFC and FAO,”</span> said Helga Pedersen, Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs following political discussions with the leader of the Russian government fisheries committee, Andrej Krajnij, in Oslo today.</p>
<p type="title">Quota agreement between Norway and the EU for 2008</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nno">Assistant Director General Ann Kristin Westberg,  tel.  +47 916 95 372</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.11.2007]</p>
<p>Norway and the EU have concluded a bilateral fisheries agreement for 2008. The parties have also come to an agreement on fishing in the Skagerrak for next year.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">WTO panel rules in Norway’s favour in the salmon case</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.11.2007]</p>
<p>The WTO Panel’s report finds that the EU anti-dumping measure against Norwegian salmon is inconsistent with WTO rules on 22 separate grounds. According to the Norwegian Government, the EU measure contains such fundamental and serious errors that the measure must be revoked.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Agreement on Norwegian-Russian quotas for 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.10.2007]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“We are delighted that the quotas for cod in the Barents Sea will be higher in 2008 than would have been the case if overfishing had continued unchanged. The quota size is a direct result of the reduction in overfishing and shows that efforts to combat illegal fishing are working. This will benefit the law abiding fishermen along the coast,”</span> says Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Helga Pedersen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Strategy: Towards a competitive Norwegian aquaculture industry</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[14.08.2007]</p>
<p>- The aquaculture industry is doing well and contributes to development and activity along the coast. In its strategy for a competitive Norwegian aquaculture industry, the government is focusing on the industry’s need for framework conditions which contribute to maintaining the Norwegian aquaculture industry’s international leading position as producer and exporter of seafood,” says Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs, Helga Pedersen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">WWF-Norway is awarded the Lighthouse Prize for 2007</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.06.2007]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“The Lighthouse Prize (Fyrtårnprisen) for 2007 is awarded to WWF-Norway for this organisation’s indefatigable and thorough involvement in the fight against illegal fishing. This work is especially important for ensuring a sustainable marine resource basis,”</span> says political advisor Kari-Anne Opsal in the Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs.</p>
<p type="title">Third annual Kystens dag (Coast Day)</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.06.2007]</p>
<p>Kystens dag (Coast Day) will be held this year for the third year in a row. <span type="quote">“It is inspiring to see how coastal Norway comes together in a volunteer effort to celebrate its coast,”</span> said political adviser Kari-Anne Opsal. She will open Kystens dag in Bergen, which this year coincides with the 30th anniversary of Torgdagen (Market Square Day).</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="tur"><span type="quote">“A breakthrough in combating illegal fishing”</span></p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[29.04.2007]</p>
<p>1 May 2007 will stand as a milestone in combating illegal, unreported and unregulated (IUU) fishing in the North-East Atlantic. That is the day the North-East Atlantic Fisheries Commission (NEAFC) introduces the new port-state control regime. <span type="quote">“This is a breakthrough in combating illegal fishing in our maritime areas. Port-state control of fisheries will give us a far better overview of the total volume of fish removed. Henceforth it will be difficult for vessels engaging in illegal fishing to land their booty,”</span> says the Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs, Helga Pedersen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Preparing for a broader assessment of the alternatives for raising the submarine wreck off Fedje</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[17.04.2007]</p>
<p>- Based on hearings in the Norwegian Parliament where several players have presented new proposals on how the submarine could be raised, more time is needed in order to consider the alternatives for raising the submarine wreck, says Helga Pedersen, the Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs.</p>
<p type="title">Welcome decline in overfishing in the Barents Sea</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[21.03.2007]</p>
<p>The 2006 report on Russian fishing of cod and haddock presented today by the Directorate of Fisheries states that Russian fishing in excess of quota in 2006 fell by 23% (equivalent to 23,000 tonnes) for cod, and by fully 55% (equivalent to 20,000 tonnes) for haddock. Estimating overfishing involves great uncertainty and poses many methodological challenges.</p>
<p type="title">Successful meeting between Spanish and Norwegian fisheries authorities</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.03.2007]</p>
<p>Representatives of the Spanish Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food and the Norwegian Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs met in Oslo on 12 March to discuss fisheries issues of common interest. Measures against illegal fishing were central during the constructive talks. The delegations were led by Director General Fernando Curcio and Secretary General Jørn Krog. <span type="quote">“I view this meeting as a major step forward with regard to Spanish-Norwegian fisheries relations,”</span> says State Secretary Vidar Ulriksen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Pollution hazard from the submarine wreck off Fedje to be eliminated</p>
<p type="title">Contact person: Director General Kirsten Ullbæk Selvig, +47 22 24 64 37 / +47 91 54 42 35</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.02.2007]</p>
<p>Following discussions by the Government, the Acting Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs, Dag Terje Andersen, has decided that the submarine wreck and the contaminated areas around it are to be entombed. A sarcophagus will isolate the mercury from the marine environment, thereby eliminating the pollution hazard. Subsequent annual inspections are to ensure that the sarcophagus protects the environment in the long term.</p>
<p type="title">Media contact line</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.02.2007]</p>
<p>Beginning on Monday, 12 February, the Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs will staff a media contact line during working hours. The press must exclusively use the telephone number +47 22 24 66 99 between 8.00 and 15.45 on weekdays.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New vessel traffic centre (VTS) for North Norway in Vardø</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.01.2007]</p>
<p>The new vessel traffic centre (VTS) for North Norway will be opened today in Vardø by State Secretary Vidar Ulriksen of the Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs. <span type="quote">“The new vessel traffic centre will monitor and guide shipping traffic along the coast of North Norway and will substantially help to improve maritime safety in northern areas,”</span> Ulriksen says. The vessel traffic centre will also play a key role in Norway’s maritime safety cooperation with Russia.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Five-party agreement on management of the Norwegian spring-spawning herring stock</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.01.2007]</p>
<p>On 18 January 2007, the EU, the Faroe Islands, Iceland, Norway and Russia concluded an agreement on the management of the Norwegian spring-spawning herring fish stock. Norway has been allocated 61% of the total allowable catch (TAC) for the herring stock, which gives Norway a quota of 780 800 tonnes for 2007.</p>
<p type="title">Quota agreement between Norway and the EU for 2007</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.12.2006]</p>
<p>Norway and the EU have agreed to a bi-lateral fisheries agreement for 2007. The Parties have also reached agreement on fishing in the Skagerrak next year. The long-term management plan for haddock stocks has been revised with a view to achieving higher yields in the long term.</p>
<p type="title">Focus on knowledge for sustainable growth and increased value creation in the marine sector</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.12.2006]</p>
<p>Norway is the responsible for managing extensive, rich seas in the High North. The Government has set the principle that the management of living marine resources is to take place within a sustainable framework, and must be based on sound knowledge of the ecosystems. This will ensure the maximum sustainable yield from these resources. The Government’s ambition is for Norway to be a leading nation in marine research and management.</p>
<p type="title">Improving maritime safety around Svalbard</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.12.2006]</p>
<p>A number of measures have already been or are being implemented to improve maritime safety along the coast of mainland Norway. An important element of the Government’s High North strategy is to enhance maritime safety in the waters around Svalbard. In this way, the Government will take a comprehensive approach to safety in the High North.</p>
<p type="title">Transport corridors</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.12.2006]</p>
<p>Good infrastructure is essential for trade and economic activity. The development of safe and efficient transport corridors in the High North therefore figures prominently on the Government’s agenda. The Government supports the initiative for the establishment of the Northern East–West Freight Corridor (the NEW Corridor) between China and North America through the port of Narvik.</p>
<p type="title">New, ice-class research vessel</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.12.2006]</p>
<p>The Government will assess the need for a new, ice-class research vessel capable of operating in the far north. An ice-class research vessel would be useful in obtaining information needed for making political and management decisions in the High North, for example in connection with the development of the petroleum and fisheries sectors. It would also be used in monitoring to improve our understanding of the environment, climate and resources in the north.</p>
<p type="title">Quota for the minke whale hunt in 2007</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.12.2006]</p>
<p>The Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs has set a quota of 1052 animals for the minke whale hunt in 2007.</p>
<p type="title">International agreement to combat illegal fishing reached in London</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.11.2006]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“This is an important milestone for the Norwegian Government’s international efforts to prevent illegal, unreported and unregulated (IUU) fishing,”</span> says State Secretary in the Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Vidar Ulriksen. In the negotiations in London this evening, full agreement was reached among all of the countries in the NEAFC regarding the measures that will enter into force starting in May of next year.</p>
<p type="title">Agreement on Norwegian-Russian quotas for 2007</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[04.11.2006]</p>
<p>Implementing measures to stop illegal fishing in the Barents Sea was the main topic at the 35 th&gt; session of the Joint Norwegian-Russian Fisheries Commission. - The Fisheries Commission has decided to give priority to this work this year as well. Norway and Russia agreed on a number of measures last year, and much has been achieved. <span type="quote">“This year focus has been on speeding up implementation of these measures,”</span> says Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Helga Pedersen.</p>
<p type="title">EU and Norway agree on closer collaboration on fisheries</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[04.10.2006]</p>
<p>Today EU and Norway will sign a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) on monitoring, control and surveillance of fisheries. The text sets out a framework for mutual control and enforcement between EU Member States and Norway which will not only facilitate the management of shared fish stocks, but also make a major contribution to both parties' fight against illegal, unregulated and unreported (IUU) fishing.</p>
<p type="title">Norwegian authorities react to Russian demands</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.09.2006]</p>
<p>Norwegian authorities received a letter on 7 September from the Russian veterinary authorities, which sets out requirements for seafood exports that may jeopardise all fish exports from Norway to Russia. These requirements apply to both fresh and frozen fish, and will enter into force 1 October.</p>
<p type="title">Agreed on actions against IUU fishing</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.08.2006]</p>
<p>We have agreed that we all must improve our vigilance by improving control at sea, control of transport and transhipment of fish, landings of fish as well as processing and sale of fish products. I am very pleased that we all take such interest in the question of how to combat the illegal, unreported and unregulated fishing (IUU-fishing), said the Norwegian minister of fishery and coastal affairs, Helga Pedersen, when the round table Conference on measures against IUU-fishing finished in Trondheim Monday.</p>
<p type="title">Programme for the ministerial conference on illegal fishing in Trondheim on Monday 7 August, 2006</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.08.2006]</p>
<p type="title">Ministerial conference on illegal fishing</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[02.08.2006]</p>
<p>Six countries will be sending their fisheries ministers to the international roundtable conference on illegal, unreported and unregulated (IUU) fishing in Trondheim on 7 August. The conference host is Helga Pedersen, the Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs. Programme for the ministerial conference</p>
<p type="title">Invitation to attend a round table discussion of ministers on IUU (illegal, unregulated and unreported) fishing</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.07.2006]</p>
<p>The media are welcome to follow the round table discussions and will be given an opportunity to ask questions of the ministers at a subsequent press conference.</p>
</body></document>
