<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Pressemeldinger - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>3015</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/fin/press-center/Press-releases.html?id=235</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Pressemeldingar.html?id=235"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=235"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="pressemeldinger.html?id=235"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Press releases - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Fiscal Budget 2011: A modest fiscal tightening</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2010]</p>
<p>Several targeted policy measures helped mitigating the effects of the international financial crisis on the Norwegian economy. Following a decline in mainland output of 1.4 per cent in 2009, growth in the Mainland economy is now forecast at 1.7 per cent in 2010 and 3.1 per cent in 2011, the latter about half a percentage point above trend growth. Unemployment has been kept at low levels throughout the downturn and is forecast at 3½ per cent both in 2010 and 2011.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Level playing field for suppliers of electronic services</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2010]</p>
<p>In a legislative proposal, the Government presents changes to the VAT Act making suppliers not established in Norway obligated to charge VAT when supplying electronic services to Norwegian consumers (B2C). Today, only suppliers established in Norway must charge VAT when such services are supplied to Norwegian consumers. The proposal will create a level playing field for operators established within and outside Norway, supplying electronic services to Norwegian consumers.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New Strategy Council for the Government Pension Fund Global</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.10.2010]</p>
<p>In the National Budget 2011 the Ministry today announced the establishment of a new Strategy Council with four external members. The Strategy Council has been asked to write a report on the long term investment strategy of the Government Pension Fund Global and present this no later than 1 December 2010.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Three companies excluded from the Government Pension Fund Global</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.08.2010]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance has excluded two Israeli companies and one Malaysian company from the portfolio of the Government Pension Fund Global (GPFG).</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Revised National Budget 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.05.2010]</p>
<p>The Norwegian economy has performed better than most other industrial countries during the financial crisis and global recession. Expansionary monetary and fiscal policies, along with extensive credit and liquidity measures, have helped to mitigate the effects of the crisis on the Norwegian economy.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Report on the management of the Government Pension Fund in 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.03.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"Strong performance in 2009 shows that the Government Pension Fund has fared well through the financial crisis. Key in this respect is a strong adherence to the long-term investment strategy of the fund"</span>, says Minister of Finance Sigbjørn Johnsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">OECD economic survey of Norway 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.03.2010]</p>
<p>The Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) presented its economic survey of Norway today. The survey gives a comprehensive and insightful analysis of the Norwegian economy.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Regulation of payment services - Simpler rules for hawala-systems and other money remittance systems</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.03.2010]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance has today put forward a proposal for regulation of payment services, including proposal for simpler rules for <span type="quote" xml:lang="som">“hawala”</span> business and other money remittance companies. – This should contribute to that simple money remittance businesses can operate in legal forms, says Finance Minister Sigbjørn Johnsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New guidelines for responsible investment practices in the Government Pension Fund Global (GPFG)</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[02.03.2010]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance today adopted two new guidelines for responsible investment practices in the Government Pension Fund Global. <span type="quote">“The new guidelines represent follow-up of the evaluation of the ethical guidelines for the Fund that was completed in 2009,”</span> says Minister of Finance Sigbjørn Johnsen. <span type="quote">“We retain several important elements from the ethical guidelines, as well as introducing a number of new measures.”</span></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Government Pension Fund set to invest in real estate</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.03.2010]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance has adopted rules for real estate investments in the Government Pension Fund Global.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Government takes action to prevent VAT fraud in connection with trading of emissions allowances</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.02.2010]</p>
<p>In a draft legislation proposal, the Government recently presented changes to the VAT Act in order to prevent VAT fraud in connection with trading of emissions allowances.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Finance minister Johnsens's comment on the supreme court verdict</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[12.02.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"I take into account that the supreme court has concluded that latent tax from the old shipping tax scheme not can be collected according to the transitional regulations from 2007"</span>, says finance minister Sigbjørn Johnsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Tobacco producers excluded from Government Pension Fund Global</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[19.01.2010]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance has decided to exclude 17 companies that produce tobacco from the Government Pension Fund Global (GPFG), based on a recommendation from the Fund’s Council on Ethics. The divestment of shares in these companies has now been completed.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">IMF presents its views on the Norwegian economy</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.11.2009]</p>
<p>A mission from the International Monetary Fund (IMF) has today presented its views on the Norwegian economy and Norwegian economic policy. The mission is in Oslo as part of its article IV-consultation with Norway. <span type="quote">"The mission’s statement is an important contribution to the domestic debate on economic policies. IMF notes that the economic policies implemented by the Norwegian Government have been effective in counteracting the financial crisis"</span>, says finance minister Sigbjørn Johnsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Authorisations to borrow in 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[06.11.2009]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance today presents a proposition to the Storting (Parliament) concerning authorisation for central government borrowing in 2010.</p>
<p type="title">Measures to counter the effects of the financial crisis are working – 2010 budget to support the positive economic development</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.10.2009]</p>
<p>The Norwegian economy has been affected by the global recession, but the downturn seems to be less severe than in most other countries. The implementation of extensive liquidity and credit policy actions, as well as expansionary fiscal and monetary policy measures, has stabilised the economy and provided stimulus to domestic demand. The economy has performed better than expected only a few months ago, and the outlook has improved.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Supplier of surveillance equipment for the separation barrier in the West Bank excluded from the Government Pension Fund – Global</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.09.2009]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance has excluded the Israeli company Elbit Systems Ltd. from the Government Pension Fund – Global, on the basis of the Council on Ethics’ recommendation. The Council on Ethics has found that investment in Elbit constitutes an unacceptable risk of contribution to serious violations of fundamental ethical norms as a result of the company’s integral involvement in Israel’s construction of a separation barrier on occupied territory. <span type="quote">“We do not wish to fund companies that so directly contribute to violations of international humanitarian law,”</span> says Minister of Finance Kristin Halvorsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Thales SA and DRD Gold Limited to be reinstated in the Government Pension Fund – Global’s portfolio</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.09.2009]</p>
<p>On the basis of the Council on Ethics’ recommendation, the Ministry of Finance has decided to reverse its previous decisions to exclude the companies Thales SA and DRD Gold Limited from the investment universe of the Government Pension Fund – Global. The reason for their reinstatement is that the companies are no longer involved in the activities that formed the basis for their exclusion.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">A broad evaluation of active management of the Norwegian Government Pension Fund - Global</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[31.08.2009]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance has appointed an international group with specialist expertise to evaluate the experiences in active management in Norges Bank.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Government Pension Fund: Assessing the impact of climate change on strategic asset allocation decisions</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.06.2009]</p>
<p>- I can now make public that we, together with the consulting firm Mercer, are taking a leading role in launching a comprehensive research project aimed at assessing the impact of climate change on financial markets, as well as implications for strategic asset allocation, said the Norwegian Minister of Finance Ms Kristin Halvorsen at the Government Pension Fund’s Investment Strategy Summit <span type="quote">“Investing for the long run”</span>.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norwegian Ministry of Finance to sell EU Emission Allowances through Barclays Capital</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.05.2009]</p>
<p>Norway is linked to the EU Emissions Trading Scheme - ETS. The allocation plan for Phase II of ETS (2008-2012) was adopted in March 2009. The total volume to be added to ETS by Norway is about 75 million EUAs (tons of C02), which is about 15 million EUAs annually. A total of 39 million EUA is allocated to Norwegian installations and 4.2 million to a New Entrants Reserve. The balance of 31.8 million EUAs will be sold in the market. In 2009 about 12.7 million EUAs will be offered in the market by the Ministry of Finance.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Revised National Budget 2009: Continued expansionary policies</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.05.2009]</p>
<p>The Norwegian economy is affected by the international financial crisis, but the downturn is not expected to be as severe in Norway as in many other industrial countries. To curb growth in unemployment, the Government proposes to increase the spending of oil revenues by a further NOK 9.5 billion to a total of NOK 130 billion during the 2009 fiscal year.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Regulations for the Norwegian State Finance Fund</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.05.2009]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance has today laid down regulations for the State Finance Fund. - I am pleased with the fact that the EFTA Surveillance Authority (ESA) now has approved the State Finance Fund as an allowed state aid measure, says Minister of Finance Kristin Halvorsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Government Pension Fund: Long-term management in turbulent times</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.04.2009]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“The financial crisis has meant that the return on the Government Pension Fund’s investments in 2008 was very poor. However, we have a robust and long-term investment strategy that we have chosen because it will serve us well over time,”</span> says the Norwegian Minister of Finance Ms Kristin Halvorsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Government will strengthen Norges Bank’s management and control system</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.04.2009]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“The Government has submitted a bill today with proposals that will strengthen Norges Bank’s management and control system in line with the best international practices and recognised principles for sound central bank management,”</span> says the Norwegian Minister of Finance Ms Kristin Halvorsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Government Pension Fund: Broad review of Norges Bank’s active management</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.04.2009]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“We are working on new guidelines for active management that will limit the risk. In addition, we will conduct a new external review of Norges Bank’s risk management and active management. This will provide a basis for a broad assessment in the spring of 2010 of whether or to what extent active management is to be continued,”</span> says the Norwegian Minister of Finance Ms Kristin Halvorsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Government Pension Fund: Developing and strengthening the ethical guidelines</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.04.2009]</p>
<p>After a broad evaluation of the ethical guidelines for the Government Pension Fund – Global, the Government is now planning a more active and more cohesive perspective on the ethical management: consideration of environmental and social aspects and good corporate governance are going to be integrated to a greater extent as relevant factors in all aspects of the management of the Fund.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Government Pension Fund: Climate on the agenda</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.04.2009]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“We take climate change seriously. Today the Government presented a Report to the Storting detailing its plan to establish a new investment programme pertaining to environmental issues and initiating a broad climate-change study. We also want to strengthen the focus on issues related to climate change in Norges Bank’s work on engaging with companies,”</span> says the Norwegian Minister of Finance Ms Kristin Halvorsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway offers to make financial resources available to the IMF</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[28.03.2009]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Minister of Finance Kristin Halvorsen Friday sent a letter to the Managing Director of the International Monetary Fund (IMF) offering to make additional financial resources available to the Fund.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Regulations relating to Management of the Government Bond Fund</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.03.2009]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance laid down regulations relating to Folketrygdfondet’s management of the Government Bond Fund today. The Fund has been established with a ceiling of NOK 50 billion.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Siemens under observation in corruption case</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.03.2009]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance has decided to place the German company Siemens AG under observation due to the gross and systematic corruption the group has been involved in over many years. Gross corruption can be grounds for exclusion from the Government Pension Fund – Global.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Supplier of military materials to Burma excluded from Government Pension Fund – Global</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.03.2009]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance has excluded the Chinese company Dongfeng Motor Group Co. Ltd from the Government Pension Fund - Global, based on advice from the Council on Ethics. The company sells military trucks to Burma. <span type="quote">“We cannot finance companies that support the military dictatorship in Burma through the sale of military materials,”</span> says Minister of Finance Kristin Halvorsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Government Pension Fund - Global: 2008 is the worst year in the history of the fund</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.03.2009]</p>
<p>- The results of the Pension Fund – Global, which were presented by Norges Bank today, show that the Fund in 2008 was strongly influenced by the global financial crisis, says the Norwegian Minister of Finance, Ms Kristin Halvorsen.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Appointment of the Board of Directors of the Norwegian State Finance Fund</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[06.03.2009]</p>
<p>The King in Council has today appointed the Board of Directors for the Norwegian State Finance Fund.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norway presents new measures for industry and households</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.02.2009]</p>
<p>The Government proposes to establish two new funds with a total capital of NOK 100 billion. The funds will ease the access to loans for companies and households, and contribute to stabilise the financial market", says Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p type="title">Mining company excluded from the Government Pension Fund – Global due to contribution to serious environmental damage</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[30.01.2009]</p>
<p>Based on a recommendation from the Council on Ethics for the Government Pension Fund – Global, the Ministry of Finance has excluded the Canadian mining company Barrick Gold Corporation from the Fund.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Cluster weapons manufacturer excluded from the Government Pension Fund – Global</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[30.01.2009]</p>
<p>Based on a recommendation from the Council on Ethics for the Government Pension Fund – Global, the Ministry of Finance has excluded the American company Textron Inc. Corporation from the Fund.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Fiscal Measures to Limit the Economic Downturn</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.01.2009]</p>
<p>In a proposition to the Storting (Parliament) the Norwegian Government proposes amendments to the 2009 Fiscal Budget. The proposed measures amount to NOK 20 billion, of which NOK 16¾ billion is an increase in budget expenditures and NOK 3¼ billion is targeted tax relief for the business sector. The structural non-oil deficit will increase by an additional NOK 7 billion as a consequence of revised estimates for some budget items.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Norwegian Government Presents Measures to Secure Employment</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.01.2009]</p>
<p>- Employment for all is our main priority. That is why the Norwegian Government today presents measures to secure existing jobs and create new jobs. We are proposing changes in the Fiscal Budget for 2009 that will reduce the effects of the international economic setback, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg says.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Long-Term Perspectives for the Norwegian Economy</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.01.2009]</p>
<p>- The White Paper on long-term perspectives addresses key challenges facing the Norwegian economy in coming decades, including global warming, globalisation and an ageing population. The paper also presents the Government’s strategy to meet these challenges that includes further enhancement of our welfare model and continued support of strong global institutions. It is important not to lose sight of the challenges to long-term sustainable development in the midst of the current economic turmoil, says Minister of Finance Kristin Halvorsen.</p>
<p type="title">Joint statement from the Ministers of Finance in Denmark, Finland, Norway and Sweden regarding help to Iceland</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.11.2008]</p>
<p>The IMF Executive Board has today approved a financial package for Iceland. This is a first step to get Iceland out of its current serious financial and economic situation. The banking crisis in Iceland is of unprecedented proportions and has serious implications for the country’s economy.</p>
<p type="title">Exchange of government securities for covered bonds</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[24.10.2008]</p>
<p>The Storting (Norwegian parliament) has today authorised the Ministry of Finance to exchange government securities with collateral in or in return for Norwegian covered bonds in amounts up to a total of NOK 350 billion.</p>
<p type="title">350 Billion Kroner Government Bond Swap Facility, Authorisations to Borrow</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[17.10.2008]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance presents to the Storting (Parliament) a proposition on an authorization to implement a 350 billion kroner facility with banks, where Government Bonds are swapped for covered bonds.</p>
<p type="title">The Norwegian Government has decided to guarantee for deposits in the Norwegian branch of Kaupthing Bank</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.10.2008]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Government has today decided to guarantee for deposits in the Norwegian branch of Kaupthing Bank up to the amount to be covered by the Icelandic deposit guarantee scheme. The Icelandic deposit guarantee scheme shall cover up to an amount corresponding to appr. 20 000 euro per depositor. The total amount of the guarantee is 400 million NOK.</p>
<p type="title">Norway endorses the Santiago principles</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.10.2008]</p>
<p>Norway supports the Generally Accepted Principles and Practices (GAPP) for Sovereign Wealth Funds which have now been made public.</p>
<p type="title">350 billion Kroner Government Bond Swap Facility</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[12.10.2008]</p>
<p>The Government and Norges Bank present two targeted initiatives to enhance confidence in the financial market. Through the issuance of government bonds amounting to 350 billion kroner the Government will provide collateral that may be used in banks’ funding operations. Norges Bank will on its side provide liquidity loans of two year maturity targeted at smaller banks. Norwegian authorities are prepared to implement necessary measures to maintain confidence in the Norwegian banking system, says Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p type="title">Supporting Stable Development of the Norwegian Economy</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.10.2008]</p>
<p>The Norwegian economy has in the past four years experienced its strongest expansion since the 1950s. Recent developments, however, suggest that the cyclical peak has been passed, and the international financial turmoil has increased the uncertainty about the outlook for the economy. In accordance with the fiscal guidelines, the Government proposes a Fiscal Budget for 2009 with a structural, non-oil budget deficit of NOK 92 billion.</p>
<p type="title">The Government Pension Fund Global: Prudent and long-term management</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.10.2008]</p>
<p>The investment strategy for the Government Pension Fund is robust, long-term and well-equipped to deal with financial market turmoil.</p>
<p type="title">Active ownership pays off</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.09.2008]</p>
<p>Active ownership activities in Monsanto Co. have contributed to a significant reduction in the use of child labour in the company’s hybrid cotton seed production in India. Norges Bank can still play an important role in achieving further improvements. The Ministry of Finance has therefore decided not to exclude Monsanto Co. from the portfolio of the Government Pension Fund - Global.</p>
<p type="title">The Government Pension Fund divests its holdings in mining company</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.09.2008]</p>
<p>The Ministry of Finance has decided to exclude the company Rio Tinto from the Government Pension Fund - Global due to a risk of contributing to severe environmental damage. There are no indications to the effect that the company's practises will be changed in future, or that measures will be taken to significantly reduce the damage to nature and the environment.</p>
</body></document>
