<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Taler og artikler - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>2080</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/smk/Whats-new/Speeches-and-articles.html?id=886</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Talar-og-artiklar.html?id=886"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="taler_og_artikler.html?id=886"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="taler_og_artikler.html?id=886"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nno">Speeches and articles - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p type="title">The Speech from the Throne by His Majesty The King on the occasion of the opening of the 155th session of the Storting</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[02.10.2010]</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">UN High-Level Summit on The Millennium Development Goals</p>
<p type="title">UN General Assembly, New york, 20 September 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[21.09.2010]</p>
<p>- The Millennium Development Goals cannot be seen in isolation from climate change, armed conflict and women’s empowerment, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said in his speech.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Accelerating the achievement of the MDGs through decent work</p>
<p type="title">New York, 20 September 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.09.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"I commend the ILO for following up from Oslo to discuss the Millennium Development Goals and decent work"</span>, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said in hiss speech at the ILO conference in New York.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at UN side-event: <span type="quote">"The Case for More Outcome Orientation and Empowerment"</span></p>
<p type="title">New York, 20 September 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.09.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"Through our work in the Vaccine Alliance GAVI, we have demonstrated the effectiveness of results-based financing in an ambitious immunisation programme"</span>, Prime Minister Stoltenberg said at a side-event hosted by Chancellor of Germany, Angela Merkel.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at the IMF/ ILO Conference The Challenges of Growth, Employment and Social Cohesion</p>
<p type="title">Oslo, 13 September 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.09.2010]</p>
<p>- Today, world leaders face a great responsibility. We have to succeed in our joint efforts to create more jobs and economic development, the Prime Minister said.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Speech at Offshore Northern Seas</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Stavanger, 24 August 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[24.08.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"We are facing major challenges in the energy sector. If we are to meet our energy needs and achieve our environmental goals, both the energy industry and the government must do their part"</span>, the Prime Minister stated at the ONS conference in Stavanger.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at the Conference on the Convention on Cluster Munitions</p>
<p type="title">Santiago, Chile, 7 June 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.06.2010]</p>
<p>By State Secretary Mina Gerhardsen.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at Official Ceremony at Los Pinos</p>
<p type="title">Mexico City, 9 April 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.04.2010]</p>
<p type="title">Speech at the National Museum of Anthropology</p>
<p type="title">Mexico City, 9 April 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.04.2010]</p>
<p type="title">Speech at Delhi Sustainable Development Summit</p>
<p type="title">Dehli, 5 February 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.02.2010]</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Prime Minister's New Year's Address 2010</p>
<p type="title">Broadcast by NRK and TV2 1 January 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.01.2010]</p>
<p type="title">Speech at COP15</p>
<p type="title">Copenhagen</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[17.12.2009]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"We are now at a critical stage in the conference. We must now all take the responsibility for reaching a successful agreement here in Copenhagen. If we don’t succeed, the most vulnerable countries will suffer the most"</span>, Prime Minister Stoltenber said in his speech</p>
<p type="title">Operationalizing deliveries of interventions for MDG4,5,6 combined</p>
<p type="title">by State Secretary Mina Gerhardsen</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[24.11.2009]</p>
<p type="title">The speech from the throne by His Majesty The King on the occasion of the opening of the 154th session of the Storting</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.10.2009]</p>
<p type="title">HM The King’s Report to the Storting on the State of the Realm and the Administration of Government during the Period since the Previous Report</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.10.2009]</p>
<p type="title">Investing in our Common Future: Healthy Women, Healthy Children</p>
<p type="title">UN General Assembly, New York</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.09.2009]</p>
<p type="title">Fighting climate change with carbon capture and storage</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[28.05.2009]</p>
<p>Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg's speech at the CCS Conference in Bergen, May 27 2009.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at the NATO Parliamentary Assembly</p>
<p type="title">Oslo, 26 May 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.05.2009]</p>
<p>Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg's speech at the NATO Parliamentary Assembly.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at NATO Summit 2009</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Strasbourg, France 4 april 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[04.04.2009]</p>
<p type="title">Speech at  Prince of Wales' meeting on rainforests</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">St. James's Palace, London 1 April 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.04.2009]</p>
<p type="title">Speech at the Progressive Governance Summit</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">Viña del Mar, Chile</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[27.03.2009]</p>
<p>Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg's speech at the Progressive Governance Summit.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Prime Minister's New Year's Address 2009</p>
<p type="title">Broadcast by NRK and TV2 1 January 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.01.2009]</p>
<p>Broadcast by NRK and TV2 1 January 2009.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Speech at Education for All - High level Group Meeting</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Oslo City Hall, 16 December 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.12.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"Since the turn of the century the number of children who have received education has increased by around 40 million. However, 75 million children are still not in school. To reach the UN Millennium Development Goal on education it is estimated that 9 billion dollars a year will be needed"</span>, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said at the Education for All High level Group Meeting in Oslo.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at The Oslo Signing Conference for the Convention on Cluster Munitions</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.12.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"It is a pleasure for me to welcome you to Oslo on this historic occasion. Today we confirm that cluster munitions are banned forever. That we, a partnership of states, international organisations and civil society, have moved the world forward. This convention will make the world a safer and better place"</span>, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said at The Oslo Signing Conference for the Convention on Cluster Munitions today.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The financial crisis: Someone has to lead the way</p>
<p type="title">Article in the Norwegian daily newspaper Dagbladet 8 November 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[10.11.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"Our most important task is to combat unemployment and prevent an economic crisis. As we know from experience, the people who are hit hardest by such problems are those who are already in a financially vulnerable situation"</span>, writes Poul Nyrup Rasmussen, President of the Party of European Socialists (PES), and Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The speech from the throne by His Majesty the King on the occasion of the opening of the 153rd session of the Storting</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[02.10.2008]</p>
<p type="title">Speech at Scandinavian Renewable Energy Forum</p>
<p type="title">Lillestrøm, Norway 1 October 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.10.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"Over the last three years my Government has doubled the funding for investments in renewable energy. Next year we will double the capital in the Fund for Renewable Energy from 10 billions kroner to 20 billions"</span>, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg told the Scandinavian Renewable Energy Forum, at Lillestrøm today.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at Global Campaign press conference</p>
<p type="title">UN Building, New York, 25 September 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.09.2008]</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Speech to UN General Assembly</p>
<p type="title">UN Building, New York, 25 September 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.09.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"I believe we face not only a food crisis, an energy crisis, a climate crisis, a trade talk crisis, but a larger, decision-making crisis. We have great institutional capacity. But we are too often unable to decide"</span>, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg told the UN General Assembly in New York on 25 September.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at the Prime Minister's visit to Minneapolis</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.09.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"There are more Norwegian Americans in the US than there are Norwegians in Norway. With the exception of Ireland, no single country saw a larger share of its population emigrate to America. A fifth of Minnesota’s inhabitants are of Norwegian descent"</span>, Prime Minister Stoltenberg said at a reception in Minneapolis monday.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at the Prime Minister's official visit to Chile</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="deu">19 September 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[19.09.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"To meet the challenges that our planet is facing, we need strong bilateral partnerships between like-minded countries. Countries like Norway and Chile. Even though we are at opposite ends of the world, we share the same fundamental beliefs and values"</span>, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said at a luncheon in Santiago de Chile today.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at a Millennium Development Goals event</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Santiago de Chile 19 September 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[19.09.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"Every year, close to 10 million children die of diseases for which there are inexpensive and effective remedies. Every year, more than half a million women die during childbirth. More than fifty million women suffer serious complications related to pregnancy or childbirth. Nearly all of these deaths and injuries are preventable. By simple means"</span>, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said at an event in Santiago de Chile today.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at the 25th anniversary of the Norwegian Indigenous Peoples Programme</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="deu">Brasilia 16 September 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.09.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"Every state has a responsibility to protect and promote their indigenous populations. And the international community has a common responsibility to ensure that they do"</span>, Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenbeg said at the 25th anniversary of the Norwegian Indigenous Peoples Programme in Brasilia today.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at the Prime Minister's luncheon with President Lula</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="deu">Brasilia 16 September 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[16.09.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"Mr. President, Combating climate change is a crucial global task. Brazil has become the global leader in the fight to save the rain forest. The Amazon plan and the Amazon Fund are ambitious and necessary tools. I am impressed by your dedication and political will to stop deforestation. I am proud that Norway has today pledged one billion dollars to the Amazon Fund, and that we can be part of this historic process"</span>, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said at a luncheon in Brasilia today.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at technology seminar in Rio</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.09.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"The main challenges mankind face today are poverty and climate change. But we are confronted with a dilemma: to reduce emissions of CO2 at the same time as the use of fossil fuels increases. This challenge can only be met by political determination and technological innovation"</span>, Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenbeg told a conference in Rio de Janeiro today.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at Rio Oil and Gas</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Rio de Janeiro 15 September 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.09.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"Rio Oil and Gas is the most important oil and gas event in the southern hemisphere. Brazil has been a petroleum producer for decades. And with its latest discoveries in the deep sub-salt layers, Brazil will become a major energy power"</span>, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said at Rio Oil and Gas today.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at visit to Aker Yards</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Rio de Janeiro 15 September 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.09.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"The Norwegian supply industry is a truly globalised industry. And it reminds us that through international competition, new technology is born. The cooperation between Norway and Brazil in the offshore sector is thriving"</span>, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said at a visit to Aker Yards in Rio de Janeiro today.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="tur"><span type="quote">”Norway-Brazil: Tradition, Trade and Technology Cooperation”</span></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Rio de Janeiro 15 September 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.09.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"Norway and Brazil are different countries, but there are many things that link us together. More than 70 Norwegian companies have established subsidiaries in Brazil in all kinds of sectors"</span>, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said at a networking luncheon in Rio de Janeiro today.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Speech at Offshore Northern Seas 2008</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Stavanger 26 August 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.08.2008]</p>
<p type="title">Speech at launch of Congo Basin Forest Fund</p>
<p type="title">London, Lancaster House 17 June 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[17.06.2008]</p>
<p type="title">Speech at the SADC Summit</p>
<p type="title">Mauritius 20 April 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.04.2008]</p>
<p type="title">Speech at The NATO-Russia Counsil</p>
<p type="title">Bucharest Summit 04 April 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[04.04.2008]</p>
<p>We welcome this opportunity to meet with president Putin in the NATO Russia Council. This is an important forum for dialogue and practical cooperation. It has already produced increased trust and confidence. The NRC should be a venue for frank discussion between strategic partners on issues of common concern.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at the Bucharest Summit</p>
<p type="title">Bucharest 03 April 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.04.2008]</p>
<p>The need for NATO and the strong transatlantic security relationship is greater than ever. NATO must adopt to new challenges. We must respond to increasing demands. We must continue to modernize. We must continue to develop our individual and collective capabilities.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at Point Carbon conference 2008</p>
<p type="title"><span type="quote">"Carbon Market Insights"</span> - Copenhagen 12 March 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[12.03.2008]</p>
<p>This year, I have visited all three poles – the Arctic, the Antarctic and the Himalayas. I have been struck by the magnificence and the strong forces of nature in these remote parts of the world. But I have also been alarmed by the potential consequences of climate change.</p>
<p type="title">Opening of Svalbard Global Seed Vault</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Longyearbyen, Svalbard</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.02.2008]</p>
<p>We are standing deep in the mountains of Svalbard. For thousands of years, this remote place has been in the grip of permafrost. But now, because of the vision, the courage and the initiative of scientists and politicians, these harsh conditions will now serve humanity - by providing secure storage for the seeds of the world.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Speech at Delhi Sustainable Development Summit</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[07.02.2008]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"The world cannot choose between development and environment. We need both. India has a key role in securing a sustainable future"</span>, Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg told the Delhi Sustainable Development Summit in New Delhi today.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Speech Kirstenbosch Institute, Cape Town</p>
<p type="title">Cape Town 18 January 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.01.2008]</p>
<p>Panel discussion on climate change and Africa.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">New Year's Address 2008</p>
<p type="title">Broadcast by NRK and TV2 1 January 2008</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[01.01.2008]</p>
<p>In his New Year's Address Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said the Government in 2008 will meet with parents and school workers for dialogue on the quality of schooling.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Speech at UN Climate Change Conference in Bali</p>
<p type="title">Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.12.2007]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"The response from Bali must be: We have the will; we have the means; and we have the determination to act"</span>, Norway's Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said in his speech to the UN Climate Change Conference in Bali today.</p>
<p type="title">The Prime Minister's opening speech, Klima X</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Teknisk Museum, Oslo, 11th December</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.12.2007]</p>
<p>Nobel Laureate Dr. Pachauri, ladies and gentlemen, school children. I am delighted to be here today to open this spectacular exhibition about climate change.</p>
</body></document>
