<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Sártnit ja artihkkalat - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="Government.no" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="nob"/><year>2007</year><publChannel><publication><publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher></publication></publChannel><wordcount>611</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/whatsnew/speeches_articles.html?id=1334</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="taler_artiklar_id_1334.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="taler_artikler_id_1334.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="sartnit_artihkkalat_id_1334.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nno">Speeches and articles - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">3</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">4</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">5</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">6</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">7</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">8</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">9</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">10</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p type="title">Responding to the Nexus – The Case for NATO</p>
<p>[Ministry of Defence, 17.09.2014]</p>
<p>Speech by Minister of Defence Ine Eriksen Søreide at the conferende <span type="quote">"A New Nexus of global Threats? Concepts and Response"</span> in Oslo Sept. 17 2014. The title of her speech was <span type="quote">"Responding to the Nexus – The Case for NATO"</span>.</p>
<p type="title">NATO Wales Summit – Revitalizing the Trans-Atlantic Bond</p>
<p>[Ministry of Defence, 16.09.2014]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Minister of Defence Ine Eriksen Søreide held this speech at The Rīga Conference 2014 September 12. The title of the speech was <span type="quote">"NATO Wales Summit – Revitalizing the Trans-Atlantic Bond"</span>.</p>
<p type="title">Introductory speech at EU Heads of Mission meeting</p>
<p type="title">Oslo, 9th September 2014</p>
<p>[Ministry of Finance, 09.09.2014]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"I am very glad to be here because European cooperation is so important to us, both economically and politically. The EU and EU member countries are among our closest partners. The geopolitical crisis in Ukraine has reminded us how important it is to stay together and defend our values"</span>, said Minister of Finance, Siv Jensen.</p>
<p type="title">Address at the Estonian–Norwegian Business Forum</p>
<p type="title">Oslo, 3 September 2014</p>
<p>[Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 03.09.2014]</p>
<p>- The synergy that can be achieved by bringing together Estonian ICT expertise and Norwegian experience in the field of green technology makes us confident that we can develop successful solutions not only for Estonia and Norway, but also for third markets, said Minsiter Vidar Helgesen in his address at the forumt.</p>
<p type="title">Europe – 25 year after the fall of the Berlin Wall</p>
<p>[Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 02.09.2014]</p>
<p>'This year – 2014 – is a year of anniversaries. A year in which to commemorate events of pivotal importance for Europe, as both a geographical and a political entity', said Minister Vidar Helgesen in his opening address at the Europe Conference 2014 in Oslo 2 September.</p>
<p type="title">EU: Time to stand up for the liberal society</p>
<p type="title">Letter in Financial Times, 28 August 2014</p>
<p>[Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 28.08.2014]</p>
<p>'As we approach the 25th anniversary of the fall of the Berlin Wall, the EU should demonstrate in no uncertain terms that it will not accept the re-establishment of an illiberal state within its borders', writes Minister Vidar Helgesen in a letter in Financial Times - about today's political situation in Hungary.</p>
<p type="title">Perspectives on the future of the Norwegian Continental Shelf</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="est">ONS: Hovedtale 26.august</p>
<p>[Ministry of Petroleum and Energy, 26.08.2014]</p>
<p>We have the resources, we have world class suppliers and we have a predictable and stable framework. After more than 40 years of petroleum production, the NCS is still attractive - with a promising future.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at Offshore Northern Seas 2014</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Stavanger, 25 August 2014</p>
<p>[The Office of the Prime Minister, 25.08.2014]</p>
<p type="title">About the Conflict in Eastern Congo</p>
<p type="title">The Christian Council of Norway's conference, 22 August 2014</p>
<p>[Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 22.08.2014]</p>
<p>'Norway closely follows the development in Eastern Congo. Though demanding challenges remain, especially with regard to prevailing insecurity, human rights violations and the dire conditions of internally displaced persons, we acknowledge that important progress has been achieved', said State Secretary Brattskar in his address at the Christian Council of Norway's conference.</p>
<p type="title">How to Prevent Total Disaster in South Sudan</p>
<p type="title">Argument in Foreign Policy on 21 August 2014 by  Rajiv Shah, Valerie Amos, Kristalina Georgieva and Børge Brende</p>
<p>[Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 21.08.2014]</p>
<p>'After half a year of fighting, the world's newest country is barreling toward calamity. But its leaders can pull it back from the brink -- if they choose to do so', write Rajiv Shah, Valerie Amos, Kristalina Georgieva and Børge Brende in an argument in Foreign Policy on 21 August 2014.</p>
</body></document>