<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Stáhtačálli Terje Moland Pedersen - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="Ministry of Justice and the Police" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="nob"/><year>2007</year><publChannel><publication><publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher></publication></publChannel><wordcount>694</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/jd/About-the-Ministry-of-Justice-and-the-Po/Other-political-staff/State-Secretary-Terje-Moland-Pedersen.html?id=1695</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="statssekretar-terje-moland-pedersen_id_1695.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="statssekretar_terje_moland_pedersen_id_1695.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="stahtaalli-terje-moland-pedersen_id_1695.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">State Secretary Terje Moland Pedersen - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p><em type="italic">General </em>I was born in Fredrikstad in 1952. I have been married to Kirsen since 1975. We have two children (Idar (1981) and Line (1983)). I did my compulsory military service in 1973 and have served in the police force since 1974. Since 1995 I have been in local politics full-time, and for that reason I have been on a leave of abcence from the police. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Professional experience </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob">1972 to 1974 Scaffolder at Fredrikstad Mekaniske Verksted (shipyard)</p>
<p>1974 to 1975 Appointed to Fredrikstad Police Headquarters as temporary police constable</p>
<p>1975 to 1976 Police trainee at Oslo Police Headquarters, Majorstua police station 1977 Permanent appointment, Fredrikstad Police Headquarters 1977 to 1979 Served in the uniformed branch</p>
<p>1979 to 1989 Served in the Police Headquarters’ criminal investigation department, drugs office</p>
<p>1989 to 1993 Served in the Police Headquarters’ planning department as a trainee supervisor in the service office, and had partial responsibility for an organisational review of the Police Headquarters. Participated also in several analysis assignments such as the Office Committee, the EDP Committee and so on. Had the responsibility for all follow- up from Police Headquarters in connection with the planning and building of a new police station in Fredrikstad.</p>
<p>1990 Temporary appointment as Police Chief Inspector.</p>
<p>1993 Permanent appointment as Police Chief Inspector, Fredrikstad Police Headquarters 1993 to 1994 Main supervisor for the Police College in Østfold.</p>
<p>1994 Appointed as group leader of the investigation section of the economic crime office. 1991 The Ministry of Justice’s personnel planning project. Participated in the working party that prepared the proposal for a personnel evaluation system and proposals for holding of performance appraisal interviews.</p>
<p>1992 The Police College project. Participated in a working party that prepared proposals for curricula for the practical training year.</p>
<p>1992 Project leader for the Norwegian Police Federation. Prepared a strategy plan for how the Association should work on salary and status questions until the year 2000.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Political experience </em></p>
<p>1991 to present Elected representative, Fredrikstad District Council</p>
<p>1991 to 1993 Deputy chair of Main Committee for Education, and on the Board for Day-Care Centres in Fredrikstad. 1990 to 1994 Chairman of the Board for Ambjørnrød Centre 1993 to 1996 Chairman of the Board of Borg Havn IKS 1995 to 1999 Chairman of precinct committee for Centre precinct, Fredrikstad Municipality 1999 to the present Member of the Executive Committee of Fredrikstad Municipality 1999 to the present Group leader for the Norwegian Labour Party 1999 to 2003 Chairman of Main Technical Committee 1999 to 2003 Chairman of the Board of Borg Havn IKS 1999 to 2005 Chairman of the Board of Fredrikstad parkering A/S 2003 to 2005 Member of the Board of Viken havneselskap A/S (company now wound up) 2003 to the present Chairman of the permanent planning committee in Fredrikstad 2004 to the present Chairman of Norwegian Ports Federation 2005 to the present State Secretary in the Ministry of Justice and the Police</p>
<p><em type="italic">Organisational experience </em>1976 to 1977 Chief union representative at the Police Academy 1978 to 1987 Member of the Board of Fredrikstad police association 1987 to 1993 Chairman of Fredrikstad police association 1992 to 1996 Member of the supervisory board of the Norwegian Police Federation 1996 to the present Member of the Board of Fredrikstad Labour Party In addition to this, I have held a number of other offices of trust and leading offices. <em type="italic">Education </em>1972 Eksamen atrium (high school leaving exam) Frydenberg gymnas 1974 Eksamen Philosophicum (matriculation exam), University of Oslo 1977 Graduated from the Police Academy 1977 Course in drugs investigation, the Police Academy 1982 Seminar in crime prevention, Ministry of Justice and Social Affairs 1986 The Police Academy’s post-qualification education course 1990 Seminar in crime prevention, Ministry of Justice 1990 Course in expertise development, Ministry of Consumer Affairs and Government Administration 1991 Seminar for trainee supervisors, the Police Academy 1991 Seminar in project work 1993 Course for trainee supervisors, the Police College 1996 Course in negotiation technique, KS bedrift. Miscellaneous IT courses Miscellaneous courses for union representatives under the aegis of the Norwegian Police Federation Miscellaneous courses for elected politicians, and for political leaders Miscellaneous courses /consultation through the Norwegian Bar Association </p>
</body></document>
