<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Birasdepartemeanta 코add치 D치lkk치dat- ja birasdepartemeantan - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="Ministry of Climate and Environment" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><year>2013</year><publChannel><publication><publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher></publication></publChannel><wordcount>208</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/kld/press-centre/Press-releases/2013/the-ministry-of-the-environment-becomes-.html?id=748447</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="departementet-skiftar-namn_id_748569.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="miljoverndepartementet-blir-til-klima--o_id_748447.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="birasdepartemeanta-adda-dalkkadat--ja-bi_id_748447.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 64438 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p>The Ministry of the Environment becomes the Ministry of Climate and Environment - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p><em type="italic">In order to clarify the Ministry's responsibilities, on 1 January 2014 the Ministry of the Environment will change its name to the Ministry of Climate and Environment. </em></p>
<p>"The Government intends to pursue an ambitious climate and environmental policy. Following the change of government, the Ministry was given new responsibilities and a more distinct role in climate policy. It was therefore natural to change the name. Among other things, the Ministry of Climate and Environment will have full responsibility for the climate and forestry initiatives, quota purchases and the CO2 compensation scheme," says Tine Sundtoft, Minister of Climate and Environment.</p>
<p>The Government will pursue an aggressive climate policy and strengthen the climate accord by increasing efforts in public transport, new, climate-friendly technology and establishing a green tax commission. It should pay to be environmentally friendly, and the point is to turn taxes in an environmentally friendly direction.</p>
<p>At the same time, the Ministry retains responsibility for other important areas. Both nature management and the protection of cultural monuments will be focus areas going forward.</p>
<p>"We will continue work on protecting Norwegian nature and safeguarding our cultural monuments," Sundtoft says.</p>
<p>Your browser does not support iframes.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
</body></document>