<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Biras - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="Government.no" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="nob"/><year>2007</year><publChannel><publication><publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher></publication></publChannel><wordcount>561</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/topics/The-environment.html?id=925</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="miljo_id_925.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="miljo_id_925.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="biras_id_925.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>The environment - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">The environment</p>
<p>It is <em type="italic">the Ministry of Climate and Environment </em>that has chief responsibility for the Government’s environmental policy. Environmental policy cuts across ministerial boundaries and involves issues that are the responsibility of several different ministries. </p>
<p>On this page you will find general information and documents relating to the environment. You can explore this topic in more detail by using the menu on the right.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Subscribe to e-mail alert</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Subscribe to RSS feed</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Norway’s fifth national report to the Convention on Biological Diversity</p>
<p>[Report, Ministry of Climate and Environment, 10.07.2014]</p>
<p>The report presents information on status and trends for biodiversity in Norway, measures undertaken to implement the Convention since 2009, successes and remaining Challenges.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Norway working to remove fossil fuel subsidies</p>
<p>[Press release, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 03.07.2014]</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">NEFCO to close first Call for Proposals for NorCaP</p>
<p>[Press release, Ministry of Climate and Environment, 30.06.2014]</p>
<p>Nordic Environment Finance Corporation has as the Facility Manager of the NEFCO Norwegian Carbon Procurement Facility (NorCaP) decided to close its procurement of CERs under the first Call for Proposals.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Resource mobilisation for the Green Climate Fund</p>
<p type="title">Oslo, 30 June 2014</p>
<p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 30.06.2014]</p>
<p>'We have to reduce greenhouse gas emissions and adapt to the inevitable consequences of climate change. This is costly, and climate finance must be made available to developing countries so that they can address these needs', Foreign Minister Børge Brende said in his opening statement at the Green Climate Fund meeting in Oslo on 30 June 2014.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Remarks at the Our Ocean Conference</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Washington DC, 16-17 June 2014</p>
<p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 17.06.2014]</p>
<p>'We depend on the ecosystems of the world for our survival. We need to ensure that the oceans of the world are managed responsibly. This conference is an important step in that direction,' Foreign Minister Børge Brende said in his remarks at the Our Ocean Conference in Washington DC on 17 June 2014.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">A future-oriented Government Building Complex</p>
<p>[Press release, Ministry of Local Government and Modernisation, 25.05.2014]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“History will unite with the future. We will change, but also preserve. The new Government Building Complex will be modern, stimulate vibrant and safe urban spaces and create good jobs, while also preserving our history,”</span> says Prime Minister Erna Solberg.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">The team</p>
<p>[Article, Ministry of Climate and Environment, 02.05.2014]</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">New evaluation of Norway's International Climate and Forest Initiative</p>
<p>[News story, Ministry of Climate and Environment, 24.03.2014]</p>
<p>Norway has created the political space needed to improve forest governance. This is one of the conclusions in a new evaluation of Norway's International Climate and Forest Initiative (NICFI).</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Norway’s sixth National Communication under the Framework Convention on Climate Change</p>
<p type="title">Status report as of January 2014</p>
<p>[Report, Ministry of Climate and Environment, 10.03.2014]</p>
<p>This report is Norway’s sixth national communication on national circumstances, polices and measures related to climate change under the Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC). The previous national communications were submitted in 1994, 1997, 2002, 2006 and 2010 respectively.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Ethiopia</p>
<p>[Article, Ministry of Climate and Environment, 25.02.2014]</p>
<p>As the first large country in Africa, Ethiopia launched in 2011 an ambitious and green national development plan called the Climate Resilient Green Economy (CRGE). The country wishes to maintain its strong economic growth in the decades ahead and become a so-called middle-income country by 2030, but without increasing national greenhouse gas emissions.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>More documents about this subject</p>
</body></document>
