<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Vuollásaš ásahusat - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="Ministry of Finance" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="nob"/><year>2006</year><publChannel><publication><publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher></publication></publChannel><wordcount>544</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/fin/The-Ministry/Underliggende-etater.html?id=115192</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="etatar-og-verksemder_id_115192.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="underliggende_etater_id_115192.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="vuollasa-asahusat_id_115192.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Subordinate Agencies - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">National Insurance Scheme Fund</p>
<p>The National Insurance Scheme Fund was established in 1966 when the National Insurance Act was adopted. The Fund is separate from the National Insurance Scheme, and the capital managed by the Fund is not earmarked for any specific purpose.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Statistics Norway</p>
<p>Statistics Norway prepares and publishes all official statistics covering virtually all areas of life in Norway. It is also responsible for the national accounts and other important economic statistics used in preparing the National Budget and the Government's long-term program. Statistics Norway engages in extensive research and also co-ordinates and collates statistics collected by other institutions, and participates in international co-operation on statistics.</p>
<p>Website of</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Customs and Excise Authorities</p>
<p>The main objective of the Customs and Excise Authorities is to ensure that customs and excise duties are correctly levied and paid on time. In addition, they are responsible for preventing the illegal import and export of goods in Norway. The customs and excise authorities set and collect customs duties, value-added tax on imports and special duties payable to the Treasury.</p>
<p>Website of</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Financial Supervisory Authority</p>
<p>The Financial Supervisory Authority of Norway supervises banks, insurance companies and other financial institutions to ensure that they comply with the legislation pertaining to financial markets. The Authority assesses, for example, management and control arrangements established by an enterprise and reviews company accounts and documents. When the Ministry of Finance considers a matter involving the financial market, the Authority is usually consulted before a decision is taken.</p>
<p>Website of</p>
<p type="title">The Government Pension Fund</p>
<p>The inflow in the Government Pension Fund Global consists of all state petroleum revenues as well as the return on the fund’s investments. The operational management of the Pension Fund Global is carried out by Norges Bank, which invests the fund’s capital in bonds and equities outside of Norway in accordance with guidelines issued by the Ministry.</p>
<p>Website of</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Norwegian Government Agency for Financial Management</p>
<p>The Norwegian Government Agency for Financial Management has an important role in initiating, promoting and coordinating reforms within performance management and financial management within government. Some of the agencys main tasks are to give advice to the Ministry of Finance concerning establishing principles and norms for government finance management, prepare advisory material, methods and tools for finance management and conduct consultative functions, training and information tasks.</p>
<p>Website of</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Norwegian National Collection Agency</p>
<p>The Norwegian National Collection Agency (Statens innkrevingssentral) has been given restricted authority to act as a government enforcement office on their portfolio of claims, in accordance with the Norwegian law of enforcement. In addition to this it collects numerous governmental fees, charges, and debts and it has been given the responsibility for developing and introducing new financial computer systems for the entire Norwegian police force.</p>
<p>Website of</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Tax Administration</p>
<p>The Tax Administration ensures that taxes are set and collected in the correct manner and are responsible for updating the national population register. It issues tax cards, collect advance tax and check the tax-return forms that are required to be submitted each year. The Tax Administration also determines and monitors national insurance contributions, and value-added tax and are responsible for providing professional guidance and instruction to local tax collection offices that collect direct taxes.</p>
<p>Website of</p>
</body></document>
