<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Aktuelt - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>554</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/krd/Whats-new.html?id=505</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Aktuelt.html?id=505"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="aktuelt.html?id=505"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="aktuelt.html?id=505"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">What's new - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">3</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">4</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">5</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">6</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">7</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p type="title">New theme page on research on local governments and regions, dwellings, buildings and the environment</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[24.09.2010]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Ministry of Local Government and Regional Development is responsible for areas of expertise that include local government administration and the implementation of elections, regional and district policy and housing and building policy</p>
<p type="title">Norway signs cooperation agreement with India</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.09.2010]</p>
<p>Today, Norway’s Minister of Local Government and Regional Development Liv Signe Navarsete and Indian minister Dr. C. P. Joshi signed a Memorandum of Understanding for mutual cooperation on local governance in the two countries.</p>
<p type="title">Response to OSCE'S EAM report of 27 November 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[31.05.2010]</p>
<p>At the invitation of the Norwegian Government, OSCE/ODIHR carried out an Election Assessment Mission in Norway during the General Election of September 2009. OSCE’s report from the visit was presented on 27 November 2009. This report gives an overview of the requests contained in the OSCE report and the planned follow up to them.</p>
<p type="title">More rental housing for people in difficulties</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.05.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“A lot of people have applied for funding in order to set up rental housing this year. We are increasing funding for rental housing by NOK 88.8 million in 2010 in a revised national budget. This means that Husbanken (The Norwegian State Housing Bank) can provide funding for around 1150 homes this year,”</span> says Liv Signe Navarsete, Minister of Local Government and Regional Development.</p>
<p type="title">New rental funding for regulated housing tenants in Trondheim</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.05.2010]</p>
<p>Rental regulation for pre-war housing was phased out in the New Year. In a revised national budget, the Government issues a bill on new housing rental funding for occupants who are unable to pay current rents for such housing in Trondheim. This funding will be means-tested.</p>
<p type="title">Fairer distribution of income between the municipalities</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.05.2010]</p>
<p>The Government proposes a fairer distribution of income between the municipalities. <span type="quote">“In this way we will ensure that municipalities all over the country can offer their residents equal welfare services,”</span> says Minister of Local Government and Regional Development Liv Signe Navarsete.</p>
<p type="title">The municipalities will receive more income next year</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[11.05.2010]</p>
<p>The municipalities will receive between four and five billion kroner more in total income next year. <span type="quote">“In spite of the tighter economic climate, the Government is prioritising more money to the municipalities to ensure good welfare services,”</span> says Minister of Local Government and Regional Development Liv Signe Navarsete.</p>
<p type="title">Workshop on the observation of e-enabled elections, part 2</p>
<p type="title">Webcast - The E-vote 2011-project</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[19.03.2010]</p>
<p>The Council of Europe and the Norwegian Ministry of Local government and Regional Development organized a workshop on the observation of e-enabled elections 18. og 19. March 2010 in Oslo. See broadcast from the second day: 19.03.2010.</p>
<p type="title">Workshop on the observation of e-enabled elections, part 1</p>
<p type="title">Webcast - The E-vote 2011-project</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.03.2010]</p>
<p>The Council of Europe and the Norwegian Ministry of Local government and Regional Development organized a workshop on the observation of e-enabled elections 18. og 19. March 2010 in Oslo. See broadcast from the first day: 18.03.2010.</p>
<p type="title">11 municipalities to try out e-voting in 2011</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[21.01.2010]</p>
<p>The government has decided that voters in Bodø, Bremanger, Drammen, Hammerfest, Mandal, Radøy, Re, Tynset, Vefsn, Ålesund and a district in Oslo can take part in an electronic voting trial for the municipal and county council elections in 2011.</p>
</body></document>
