<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Aktuelt - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>1262</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/fkd/Whats-new.html?id=258</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Aktuelt.html?id=258"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="aktuelt.html?id=258"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="aktuelt.html?id=258"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">What's new - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">3</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">4</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">5</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">6</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">7</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">8</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p type="title">Facts about Fisheries and Aquaculture 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[23.08.2010]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs has published a booklet containing facts on Norwegian seafood production – consumption and export, fisheries and catches, aquaculture and research and innovation. The booklet was published in August 2010.</p>
<p type="title">Ban on landings of mackerel from Faroese and Icelandic vessels</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[29.07.2010]</p>
<p>- The irresponsible fishing for mackerel which Iceland and the Faroe Islands have initiated as an attempt to secure future quota shares is a serious threat to the mackerel stock, and undermines the cooperation to secure the necessary conservation measures. I consider this situation very seriously, and it has been the topic of discussions between myself and the European Commissioner for Fisheries and Maritime Affairs, Norwegian Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Lisbeth Berg-Hansen says in a comment.</p>
<p type="title">Farmed salmon</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[28.06.2010]</p>
<p>Food safety, environmental considerations and work associated with the health and welfare of fish are given high priority in the management of Norway’s aquaculture industry. The Strategy for an Environmentally Sustainable Norwegian Aquaculture Industry prioritises the environmental aspects of sustainability in aquaculture. A sustainable aquaculture industry is an industry that is run in an environmentally responsible way and which is adapted to take particular account of the marine environment and its biological diversity. The strategy identifies the issues, sets goals and clarifies what is required to achieve them.</p>
<p type="title">The Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs given responsibility for setting up BarentsWatch</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[25.06.2010]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Government has decided to give the Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs the responsibility for setting up a new, full-spectrum monitoring and information system for the Northern sea and coastal areas (<span type="quote" xml:lang="deu">“BarentsWatch”</span>). The work will be headed up by the Norwegian Coastal Administration (NCA). The Norwegian Mapping Authority, the Norwegian Meteorological Institute and many other specialist bodies will be involved in the work.</p>
<p type="title">The Norwegian Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs  meets the Fisheries Committee of the European Parliament</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[22.06.2010]</p>
<p>The Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs met the Fisheries Committee of the European Parliament 22 June 2010, where the Norwegain Minister presented Norwegian fisheries management and expressed the need for close cooperation between the EU and Norway.</p>
<p type="title">Speech before the the European Parliament, 22 June 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[22.06.2010]</p>
<p type="title">Norwegian perspectives on maritime safety – by the Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[06.05.2010]</p>
<p>State Secretary Vidar Ulriksen's speech during MajorEvent in Ålesund 5. May 2010.</p>
<p type="title">Very good results in combating illegal fishing</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.04.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“A concerted effort by the Norwegian and Russian authorities has halted illegal, unreported and unregulated (IUU) catches of cod in the Barents Sea, which were estimated at more than 100 000 tonnes a year. Last year, no IUU fishing of cod was detected. The Government has given high priority to combating IUU fishing in the Barents Sea, and the results speak for themselves,”</span> said Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Lisbeth Berg-Hansen.</p>
<p type="title">Further review of salvage of German submarine U-864</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.03.2010]</p>
<p>The Government commissioned an external quality assurance report on the proposal for raising the wreck of the German submarine U-864 off the west coast of Norway. This has now been presented, and identifies a number of uncertainties. An accident involving release of the mercury cargo would be a threat to the marine and coastal environment. It has therefore been decided to commission an in-depth review to ensure that any salvage operation is properly planned, takes full account of environmental concerns, and has an acceptable level of risk.</p>
<p type="title">Moderation in times of greed</p>
<p type="title">Secretary General Jørn Krogs speech at the opening of the North Atlantic Seafood Forum, Lillestrøm March 3rd, 2010.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[04.03.2010]</p>
<p>Secretary General Jørn Krogs speech at the opening of the North Atlantic Seafood Forum, Lillestrøm March 3rd, 2010.</p>
<p type="title">Norway and the EU have concluded a bilateral fisheries agreement for 2010 and a long-term agreement on management of North East Atlantic mackerel</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[26.01.2010]</p>
<p>- I am very content that these agreements have now been concluded, and that a difficult period of negotiations with the EU is over. We can now look forward with the view of finding joint solutions to new challenges. We had many rounds of negotiation with the EU last autumn, but the challenges were so difficult that we had to resume negotiations in January. It is of major importance for the fishing industry in Norway and the EU that we now have agreements in place. The industry can now continue their important value creation within a stable framework, said Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Lisbeth Berg-Hansen.</p>
<p type="title">Breakdown in the fisheries negotiations between Norway and the EU</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.12.2009]</p>
<p>- I am very disappointed about the EU’s lack of willingness and determination to arrive at a mutually satisfactory agreement for 2010, says Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs, Lisbeth Berg-Hansen.</p>
<p type="title">Quota for the minke whale hunt in 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.12.2009]</p>
<p>The Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs has set a quota of 1286 animals for the minke whale hunt in 2010.</p>
<p type="title">North Atlantic ban on discards in international waters</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[19.11.2009]</p>
<p>The 28th annual meeting of the Northeast Atlantic Fisheries Commission (NEAFC) adopted a ban on discards in international waters on the major stocks regulated by NEAFC. The adoption is a major contribution in the work towards sustainable and responsible management of fisheries in the high seas. NEAFC also adopted several adjustments of the NEAFC Scheme of Control and Enforcement related to port state control, surveillance of fisheries and catch reporting. These are all important tools in the work of combating IUU-fishing.</p>
<p type="title">Norway requests WTO consultations on EU ban on trade in seal products</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[05.11.2009]</p>
<p>Norway has today formally requested WTO dispute settlement consultations, because the Government views the EU ban on trade in seal products as being in contravention of WTO rules. <span type="quote">“In our view, the EU decision is contrary to WTO rules on a number of key points. We will not let this go uncontested. We have therefore requested formal WTO dispute settlement consultations today,”</span> said Foreign Minister Jonas Gahr Støre.</p>
<p type="title">Agreement on Norwegian-Russian fisheries for 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[09.10.2009]</p>
<p>Norway and Russia have today entered into an agreement on management of the joint stocks in the Barents Sea for 2010. The stock situation is very good and quotas for both cod and haddock have been increased. The long term collaboration on responsible management, research and control provides great benefits for both Norwegian and Russian fishermen and coastal communities.</p>
<p type="title">New strategy for marine bioprospecting</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[08.09.2009]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“Norway has a long tradition of harvesting the sea and has developed a high level of competence in the marine sector and bioprospecting. Through this new strategy, we are facilitating an exploitation of our marine resources that can provide us with new knowledge and new jobs from the treasure chest of the sea,”</span> said Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Helga Pedersen when she presented the government’s strategy for marine bioprospecting in Tromsø today.</p>
<p type="title">Facts about Fisheries and Aquaculture 2009</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[03.09.2009]</p>
<p>The Norwegian Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs has published a booklet containing facts on Norwegian seafood production – consumption and export, fisheries and catches, aquaculture and research and innovation. The booklet was published in August 2009.</p>
<p type="title">Opening speech Aqua Nor 2009</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Trondheim Tuesday 18 August</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[18.08.2009]</p>
<p>Opening speech Aqua Nor 2009 Minister of Fisheries and Coastal affairs Helga Pedersen Trondheim Tuesday 18 August</p>
<p type="title">Scotland and Norway sign memorandum</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[17.08.2009]</p>
<p>- Scotland and Norway have signed a Memorandum of Undersanding (MoU) on aquaculture today. - We can learn from each other, and develop our industries even further, says the Norwegian Minister of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs Helga Pedersen.</p>
</body></document>
