<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Aktuelt - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>499</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/smk/Whats-new.html?id=876</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="Aktuelt.html?id=876"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="aktuelt.html?id=876"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="aktuelt.html?id=876"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">What's new? - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">1</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">2</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">3</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">4</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">5</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">6</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">7</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">8</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">9</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="vep">10</p>
<p type="listitem">Next &gt;</p>
</list><p type="title">The Speech from the Throne by His Majesty The King on the occasion of the opening of the 155th session of the Storting</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[02.10.2010]</p>
<p type="title">International breakthrough in efforts to improve the health of women and children</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[22.09.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">“I am glad to see that so many UN members and organisations have pledged funding today to save women and children. The pledges now total more than USD 40 billion over the next five years. This is the greatest effort the world has seen to reduce child and maternal mortality,”</span> said Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p type="title">UN High-Level Summit on The Millennium Development Goals</p>
<p type="title">UN General Assembly, New york, 20 September 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[21.09.2010]</p>
<p>- The Millennium Development Goals cannot be seen in isolation from climate change, armed conflict and women’s empowerment, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said in his speech.</p>
<p type="title">Accelerating the achievement of the MDGs through decent work</p>
<p type="title">New York, 20 September 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.09.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"I commend the ILO for following up from Oslo to discuss the Millennium Development Goals and decent work"</span>, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg said in hiss speech at the ILO conference in New York.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at UN side-event: <span type="quote">"The Case for More Outcome Orientation and Empowerment"</span></p>
<p type="title">New York, 20 September 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.09.2010]</p>
<p><span type="quote">"Through our work in the Vaccine Alliance GAVI, we have demonstrated the effectiveness of results-based financing in an ambitious immunisation programme"</span>, Prime Minister Stoltenberg said at a side-event hosted by Chancellor of Germany, Angela Merkel.</p>
<p type="title">Developing countries must do more to reach the Millenium Development Goals</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[20.09.2010]</p>
<p>In his statement to the UN high-level meeting on the Millennium Development Goals, Norwegian Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg stressed that developing countries bear the main responsibility for reaching the Millennium Development Goals.</p>
<p type="title">Treaty on maritime delimitation and cooperation in the Barents Sea and the Arctic Ocean signed today</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[15.09.2010]</p>
<p>Norway and Russia signed the treaty on maritime delimitation and cooperation in the Barents Sea and the Arctic Ocean in Murmansk today. It was signed by Foreign Ministers Jonas Gahr Støre and Sergei Lavrov in the presence of Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg and President Dmitry Medvedev.</p>
<p type="title">Speech at the IMF/ ILO Conference The Challenges of Growth, Employment and Social Cohesion</p>
<p type="title">Oslo, 13 September 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.09.2010]</p>
<p>- Today, world leaders face a great responsibility. We have to succeed in our joint efforts to create more jobs and economic development, the Prime Minister said.</p>
<p type="title">Oslo Conference calls for cooperation and new growth to address global jobs crisis</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[13.09.2010]</p>
<p>13 September Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg hosted an international conference in Oslo on the challenges of growth, employment and social cohesion, bringing together heads of state and government, the heads of the ILO and the IMF, trade union leaders, academics and employers from around the world.</p>
<p type="title">Treaty between Norway and Russia to be signed</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">[06.09.2010]</p>
<p>Norway and Russia will sign the Treaty concerning Maritime Delimitation and Cooperation in the Barents Sea and the Arctic Ocean in Murmansk on 15 September.</p>
</body></document>
