<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>SÁM Introductory Sámi language in practical situation – Part II | Sámi University of Applied Sciences</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>204</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://samas.no/en/studier/sam-introductory-sami-language-practical-situation-part-ii</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="sam-nordsamisk-i-praktisk-laeringssituasjon-innforingsstudium-2-del.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="sam-nordsamisk-i-praktisk-laeringssituasjon-innforingsstudium-2-del-sam-davvisamegiella.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>Sámi language introduction course</p>
<p type="title">SÁM Introductory Sámi language in practical situation – Part II</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Language of instruction  : Northern Sámi</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">Study place: Guovdageaidnu</p>
<p type="listitem">15 credits</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Semester plan</p>
</list><p>This study is a continuation course to North Sami in practical learning situation-introduction program part I.</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Course fee: 1200 NOK material fee and 400 NOK semester fee (semester fees are payed once each semester)</p>
<p type="listitem">Scholarship opportunity from the Sami Parliament</p>
</list><p>The course emphasizes on communication and interaction between students in Sami. Students receive training through communication in various situations in everyday life. New words, speaking and writing exercises and language exercises are adapted for various topics. All topics include verbal tasks, role plays and simple texts.</p>
<p>The course also includes short and overnight excursions. The study concludes with an oral presentation of a project.</p>
<p>This course can be compared with European language portfolio A3-A4 (Davvin 3 and 4)</p>
<p><em type="italic">Further education: </em></p>
<p>Sami in practical situations, introductory part 1 and 2 provide a basis to study Semester Course in North Sami language.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Job Opportunities </em><em type="italic">: </em></p>
<p>Are you working in areas located in the Sami administrative area, it may require you to have Sami language skills. Therefore, this study fit for those who are preparing to work in Sami areas.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
</body></document>