<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Samediggi - Saamelaiskäräjät - Sámi handicraft flea market and Sámi handicraft market at Sajos 12th –13th of December 2014</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="fin"/><wordcount>289</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Børre Gaup" email="albbas@gmail.com"/><multilingual><language xml:lang="fin"/><language xml:lang="eng"/></multilingual><origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index2.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=958&amp;lang=english.html</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=958_lang=finnish.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=958_lang=davvi.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=958_lang=anaras.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p>Sámi handicraft flea market and Sámi handicraft market at Sajos 12th –13th of December 2014</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p>Sámi Duodji association organizes in cooperation with the Youth Council of Sámi Parliament and the Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos Sámi handicraft flea market and market at Sajos, Inari 12 th – 13 th of December 2014.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Sámi handicraft flea market on Friday 12 th of December at 12-17.  </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p>Come to the flea market for bargains! Sámi traditional dress (gákti), brooch (risku), earrings or other handicraft that is no longer needed for someone, can be a treasure for you. You can also find Sámi handicraft materials such as fabrics, threads, silk, skins and so on. At the flea market there is also a group table if you don’t have enough stuff for your own table. During the flea market performs Tiina Aikio from Vuotso and her accompanist Tony Brandtberg at 2 pm.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p>Remember, that one man's trash is another man's treasure and retro is in right now!</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p>Psst, the 4 th Club night of Sajos starts at 8 pm.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p><em type="italic">Sámi handicraft market on Saturday 13th of December at 10–17  </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p>Saturday is the market day and sellers all around the Sámi land gather to the lobby of Sajos. Markets are a brilliant place to explore the latest trends of Sámi handicrafts as well as make Christmas shopping.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p>During the market day at 1 pm performs a group called Ravggon, they play folk-rock music in Northern Sámi.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p>Also kids are very welcome to the markets! Sámi children’s center Mánnu organizes a handicraft workshop at 10-12.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p>When you get hungry, Restaurant Lyeme offers market food for smaller and bigger hunger.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p><em type="italic">There is still time to register as a seller to the markets!  </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p><em type="italic">More information and registration:  </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p>By e-mail</p>
</body></document>