<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>Samediggi - Saamelaiskäräjät - The Anniversary Exhibition of Petteri Laiti open until the end of September</title>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <translator>
      <unknown/>
    </translator>
    <translated_from xml:lang="fin"/>
    <wordcount>325</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index2.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=1115&amp;lang=english</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=1115_lang=finnish.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=1115_lang=davvi.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>The Anniversary Exhibition of Petteri Laiti open until the end of September</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>The Anniversary Exhibition of Petteri Laiti can be visited at the Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos until the end of September. The exhibition is open on weekdays 9 a.m. – 5 p.m.</p>
    <p>65 years old artist Petteri Laiti belongs to the pioneers of Sámi handicrafts.   Laiti has received the proficiency of craftsmanship as a heritage of his family. Petteri Laiti tells, that he has grown with woodchip pile as his father made functional handicrafts and his mother textile work.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Laiti is one of the best known Sámi artisans in Finland and he masters a variety of traditional Sámi crafts. Laiti has specialized in gnarl- and horn-work and in knives, but he has also developed handicraft use for different materials of reindeer. His silver work is known for the way he combines silver with the materials and shapes of traditional Sámi handicraft, creating something new. His gnarl- and Sámi silver-work have been at display in numerous exhibitions in Finland and abroad.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Laiti graduated as a silversmith in 1984 and after that he founded atelier/shop Samekki in Inari. Now when the master will retire, his son Sami Laiti will continue his work.  Sami has studied the field at Sámi Education Institute in Inari.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos opened exhibition facilities for Sámi artists. Exhibition of Petteri Laiti opened the facilities for public. The aim of the exhibitions is to bring addition to the activities of Cultural Centre and create an ideal settings for Sámi artists and artisans to show their work. The hopes are that in the future people get to admire the work of several Sámi artists and artisans.</p>
    <p>More information:</p>
    <p xml:lang="sme">Riitta Orti-Berg, Cultural Secretary, The Sámi Parliament, riitta.orti-berg(at)samediggi.fi, tel. + 358 (0)10 839 3103, www.samediggi.fi</p>
    <p xml:lang="smn">Johanna Alatorvinen, ma. Marketing Manager, Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos, johanna.alatorvinen(at)samediggi.fi, tel. +358 (0)10 839 3109, www.sajos.fi</p>
    <p>Photo: The opening ceremony of the exhibition of Petteri Laiti, Sajos/ Terhi Tuovinen</p>
  </body>
</document>
