<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Samediggi - Saamelaiskäräjät - Sámi handicraft workshops will be organised for the second summer at Sajos</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="fin"/><wordcount>378</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index2.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=861&amp;lang=english.html</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=861_lang=finnish.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=861_lang=davvi.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=861_lang=anaras.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=861_lang=nuortta.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p>Sámi handicraft workshops will be organised for the second summer at Sajos</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>Located in the heart of Inari, the Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos will be arranging now for second time traditional and modern Sámi handicraft workshops this summer. Visitors have opportunity to make their own Sámi souvenirs to take back home and at the same time learn about the history and traditions of Sámi handicrafts.</p>
<p>Visitors get to choose from variety of materials and techniques, and create their own handicraft souvenir with the help of workshop instructor. Besides offering work instructors, the instructor will also tell visitors about the history of Sámi arts and crafts, and about their own handicraft techniques.</p>
<p>Handicraft workshops are part of the development of cultural content production at Sajos. The purpose of the Sámi handicraft workshops is to enhance the recognition of Sámi handicrafts and thereby raise awareness of the Sámi as indigenous people. Workshops are produced in cooperation with Duodji Shop in Sajos, which sells authentic Sámi handicrafts.</p>
<p> <em type="italic">A wide range of handcrafted items  </em> </p>
<p>Sámi handicrafts have long traditions and generally by Sámi handicraft is meant functional items, such as clothing, tools, household supplies, traps and jewelry, which are made by hand. Also today the traditions of handicrafts are in natural materials. Handicrafts are made by following the old tradition but at the same time applying the new working methods and new use by regions.</p>
<p>Depending on how much time they can spend, visitors can make a tin or pearl bracelet, woven belt, a bag for smartphone or tablet and a reindeer leather pouch. Arts and crafts workshops are arranged in the main foyer at Sajos for a fee. Groups should book their workshops in advance in case additional instructors are needed.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Sajos arts and crafts workshops are organized on weekdays from 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. between 1 July and 15 August 2014.  </em> </p>
<p><em type="italic">Summer opening times at Sajos:   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Sajos info:   mon-fri 9 a.m. - 5 p.m.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Duodji shop:  mon-fri 10 a.m. – 5 p.m.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Sámi library:  mon-tue 1 p.m. - 7 p.m., wed-thu 10 a.m. – 5 p.m., fri 10 a.m. -4 p.m.</p>
<p>More information:</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Johanna Alatorvinen, Marketing Manager, Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos,    , tel. +358  10 839 3109,  www.sajos.fi</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aune Musta, Managing Director, Duodji Shop,    , tel. +358 400-637178,  www.samiduodji.com</p>
</body></document>