<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The Animals and Plants of Inari Hiking Area - Nationalparks.fi</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>663</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>http://www.nationalparks.fi/en/inari/nature/theanimalsandplantsofinarihikingarea?inheritRedirect=true</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="elaimistojakasvillisuus.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="anaravanddardanguovllueallitjasattut.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="aanaarvandardemkuavluelleevaljejasadolasvuota.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>Skip to Content</p>
<p>Open Menu</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Suomeksi</p>
<p type="listitem">På svenska</p>
<p type="listitem">Anarâškielâ</p>
<p type="listitem">Davvisámegiella</p>
<p type="listitem">中文</p>
<p type="listitem">По-русски</p>
</list><p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p type="title">Inari</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Activities</p>
<p type="listitem">Directions and Maps</p>
<p type="listitem">History</p>
<p type="listitem">Instructions and Rules</p>
<p type="listitem">Nature <list><p type="listitem">The Animals and Plants of Inari Hiking Area</p>
</list> </p>
<p type="listitem">Services</p>
<p type="listitem">Sights</p>
<p type="listitem">Trails</p>
<p type="listitem">More Information</p>
</list><p type="title">Destinations</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Top Natural Attractions</p>
<p type="listitem">National Parks</p>
<p type="listitem">World Heritage Sites</p>
<p type="listitem">National Hiking Areas</p>
<p type="listitem">Wilderness Areas</p>
<p type="listitem">Other Nature Sites</p>
<p type="listitem">Hiking Trails</p>
<p type="listitem">Huts</p>
<p type="listitem">Historical Sites</p>
<p type="listitem">Nature Centres</p>
<p type="listitem">Accessible Destinations</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">Arctic Circle</p>
<p type="listitem">Evo</p>
<p type="listitem">Hossa</p>
<p type="listitem">Inari</p>
<p type="listitem">Iso-Syöte</p>
<p type="listitem">Kylmäluoma</p>
<p type="listitem">Oulujärvi</p>
<p type="listitem">Ruunaa</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">Activities</p>
<p type="listitem">Directions and Maps</p>
<p type="listitem">History</p>
<p type="listitem">Instructions and Rules</p>
<p type="listitem">Nature</p>
<p type="listitem">Services</p>
<p type="listitem">Sights</p>
<p type="listitem">Trails</p>
<p type="listitem">More Information</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">The Animals and Plants of Inari Hiking Area</p>
</list><p>Inari Menu</p>
<p type="title">Inari</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Activities</p>
<p type="listitem">Directions and Maps</p>
<p type="listitem">History</p>
<p type="listitem">Instructions and Rules</p>
<p type="listitem">Nature <list><p type="listitem">The Animals and Plants of Inari Hiking Area</p>
</list> </p>
<p type="listitem">Services</p>
<p type="listitem">Sights</p>
<p type="listitem">Trails</p>
<p type="listitem">More Information</p>
</list><p type="title">The Animals and Plants of Inari Hiking Area</p>
<p type="title">Animals</p>
<p>Ten fish species live naturally in Lake Inarijärvi: the Whitefish <em type="italic">(Goregonus lavaretus), </em>the Trout <em type="italic">(Salmo trutta), </em>the Arctic Char <em type="italic">(Salvelinus alpinus), </em>the Grayling ( <em type="italic">Thymallus thymallus), </em>the Perch <em type="italic">(Perca fluviatilis), </em>the Pike <em type="italic">(Esox lucius), </em>the Burbot <em type="italic">(Lota lota), </em>the Three-spined stickleback <em type="italic">(Gasterosteus aculeatus), </em>Nine-spined stickleback <em type="italic">(Pungitus pungitus), </em>and the Minnow <em type="italic">(Phoxinus phoxinus). </em>There are also planted fish species living in the lake: the Lake trout <em type="italic">(Salvelinus namaycush), </em>the Vendace <em type="italic">(Coregonus albula), </em>and the Lake salmon <em type="italic">(Salmo salar). </em>The nesting bird species of the lake are typical for a barren lake. Species of the Arctic Sea, such as the Great Cormorant <em type="italic">(Phalacrocorax carbo) </em>can also be seen.Especially during the summer, LakeInarijärvi is a good destination, because on the windy islands, there are lessmosquitoes and black flies than on the mainland. </p>
<p>The pine forests of Inarijärvi area provide a rugged, rocky habitat. The Western Capercaillie <em type="italic">(Tetrao urogallus), </em>the Willow Grouse <em type="italic">(Lagopus lagopus), </em>the Pine Grosbeak <em type="italic">(Pinicola enucleator), </em>or the Merlin <em type="italic">(Falco columbarius) </em>can be seen in the forests. The Teal <em type="italic">(Anas crecca), </em>the Black-throated Diver <em type="italic">(Gavia arctica), </em>the Mallard <em type="italic">(Anas platyrhynchos), </em>and the Red-breasted Merganser <em type="italic">(Mergus serrator) </em>nest on the lake. </p>
<p>In the winter, the White-throated Dipper <em type="italic">(Cinclus cinclus) </em>lives in the unfrozen places of Juutuanjoki River, and in the summer, the riverbanks are lush in places, providing nesting sites for different bird species, the number of which is greater there than generally in Inari area. In addition to the bird species already mentioned, you can see the European Wigeon <em type="italic">(Anas penelope), </em>the Smew <em type="italic">(Mergus albellus), </em>the Rough-legged Buzzard <em type="italic">(Buteo lagopus) </em>and the Osprey <em type="italic">(Pandion haliaetus). </em>On the leafy riverbanks, also the Moose <em type="italic">(Alces alces) </em>can be seen. </p>
<p type="title">Vegatation</p>
<p>In the wilderness-like surroundings of Lake Inarijärvi, the soil is low in nutrients, and the climate is harsh, which affects the vegetation. The pine and birch forests on the lake shores are swept by the wind, and in the field layer grow twigs which can tolerate dryness, such as the Marsh tea <em type="italic">(Ledum palustre), </em>the Crowberry <em type="italic">(Empetrum nigrum), </em>Lingonberry <em type="italic">(Vaccinium vitis-idaea), </em>and the Bog Bilberry <em type="italic">(Vaccinium uliginosum). </em></p>
<p>Generally, the rocky pine forests do not make a good habitat for plants. However, a hiker may be surprised finding some unusually luxuriant places. For example, on the banks of Juutuanjoki River it is possible to find the Erect Primrose <em type="italic">(Primula stricta), </em>the Marsh Lousewort <em type="italic">(Pedicularis palustris) </em>and the Moor-King <em type="italic">(Pedicularis sceptrum-carolinum). </em>Especially herb-rich forests, dominated by Aspens <em type="italic">(Populus tremula), </em>are lush places compared to their surroundings. For example, the Wood Millet <em type="italic">(Milium effusum), </em>the Arctic Blackberry <em type="italic">(Rubus arcticus) </em>and the One-sided Wintergreen <em type="italic">(Orthilia secunda) </em>grow there. </p>
<p>The top of Otsamotunturi Fell is above the limit of tree growth. First the pine forests turn into alpine birch forest, and then into open fell field. A special rare plant growing on Otsamotunturi Fell is the Yellow oxytropis <em type="italic">(Oxytropis campestris). </em>Other fell plants can also be found on the top of the fell, such as the Alpine Azalea <em type="italic">(Loiseleuria procumbens), </em>the Lapland Diapensia <em type="italic">(Diapensia lapponica), </em>the Blue Heath <em type="italic">(Phyllodoce caerulea), </em>the Dwarf Willow <em type="italic">(Salix herbacea) </em>and the Alpine bearberry <em type="italic">(Arctostaphylos alpina). </em></p>
<p>© Metsähallitus 2017</p>
<list/><p>Share This Page</p>
<p>Open Menu</p>
</body></document>
