<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Sami Statistics Data Sources</title><genre code="science"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>3163</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>http://samilogutmuitalit.no/sites/default/files/publications/2._sami_statistics_data_source.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="8_datagrunnlag_samisk_statistikk.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="8_datavuoddu_sami_statistihkkii.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p><em type="bold">  Sami Statistics Data Sources </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Recommendations based on articles in Samiske tall forteller 1-8 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Jon Todal</em>, leader, Expert Analysis Group for Sami Statistics </p>
<p><em type="italic">Summary </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">The most frequently used information sources for articles in Samiske tall forteller  have been based  on  data  from  so-called  STN-areas  (Sami  Parliament  subsidy  schemes  for  business development areas). These geographically based statistics have proided a lot of knowledge on Sami  society.  In  a  number  of  social  areas,  however,  ethnicity  based  statistics  would  have provided more relevant information than geographically based ones but there is no data source that  can  be  used  to  make  ethnicity-based  statistics  in  Norway.  The  article  recommends  that Statistics Norway continue to produce Sami statistics based on data from STN-areas. Further, it recommends a report on how to best chart Sami-speakers in Norway. A number of Sami social areas lack statistics. We must assess what information can be obtained from the data.  </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">The Expert Analysis Group for Sami Statistics has completed its second four-year appointment, and the group has published eight issues of scientific papers, Samiske tall forteller 1 – 8. Based on available statistics, authors have commented and analyzed changes in Sami society. Many of the authors in Samiske tall forteller have also commented and assessed the data they based their articles on. The summaries in this article are based on these comments and assessments.  </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">2.1  Two Types of Data </em></p>
<p>The first article in <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller</em> <em type="italic">1</em> is about data sources for Sami statistics. In this article, Paul  Inge  Severeida  points  to  two  types  of  data  for  this  type  of  statistics,  geographical  and ethnic.  </p>
<p>Statistics Norway has geographically based data for traditionally Sami communities. However, Norway  has  no  registry  of  ethnic  Samis  which  can  be  used  to  make  individual  based  Sami statistics.</p>
<p>In his article, Severeide discusses where one nonetheless can find individual-based Sami data, and how this can be used to establish what he calls a <span type="quote">“statistical Sami population”</span> to compile statistics applicable to Samis as an ethnic group in Norway. We will come back to this later.</p>
<p>Every second year since 2006, Statistics Norway has published a book called <em type="italic">Samisk Statistikk </em>(Sami Statistics). Statistics in this publication area based on data from STN-areas. An STN-area is a geographical area made up of counties and parts of counties in which businesses receive economic support from the Sami Parliament. These areas are comprised of traditionally Sami communities north of Saltfjellet and a large portion of the Sami population lives there.  </p>
<p>Severeide  point  out  that  a  portion  of  Samis  in  Norway  live  outside  of  STN-areas  and  are therefore not included in such statistics. A number of ethnic Norwegians and immigrants also live in STN-areas; they are included in the statistics. How much they affect the data depends on what theme is being analyzed.</p>
<p><em type="bold">2.2  Sami Demographic Data </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller</em> has had five articles on demographic changes in Sami communites.  </p>
<p>In 2008, Svanhild Andersen and Torunn Pettersen went through population developments in STN-areas (at that time called SUF-areas). Andersen and Pettersen characterised the changes in  these  areas  as  <span type="quote">“catastrophic”</span>.  However,  not  all  the  demographic  changes  were  equally negative everywhere. The authors recommended studying the statistics in further detail in order to  make  conclusions  about  the  reasons  for  the  variations.  The  recommendations  included  a more active use of existing statistics; they did not make any proposal regarding the collection of other data.</p>
<p>A demographic article by Øivind Rustad in 2010 showed how population decreases in STNareas  were  continuing.  This  article  contained  no  statistical  recommendations.  The  three demographic scientific papers in the 2012  issue of <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller</em>  did not contain any recommendations about the collection of other types of data either.  </p>
<p>Based on this, we can say that despite being aware of weaknesses in the statistics (weaknesses already pointed out by Paul Inge Severeide in <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller 1</em>, see above), the authors of  demographic  articles  consider  existing  statistics  with  data  from  STN-areas  to  be  a  sound basis for making analyses.  </p>
<p><em type="bold">2.3  Data Sources for Sami Health Information </em></p>
<p>The 2009, 2010 and 2015 issues all contained articles on health. Magritt Brustad wrote the first two  articles,  while  the  last,  from  2015,  was  co-authored  by  Magritt  Brustad  and  Torhil Lauritsen. The 2015 article was about dental health. The authors of this article did not discuss any special statistical challenges.</p>
<p>Lack  of  information  regarding  an  individual’s  ethnicity  can  make  it  difficult  to  design approriate policies and plans within the public sector. Brustad discussed this theme in her 2010 article  about  disability  and  social  security  benefits.  She  wrote  that  <span type="quote">“in  order  to  describe  the causal  relationships  between  the  environment  or  living  conditions  and  disability  and  social security  in  the  Sami  populations,  it  is  necessary  to  study  how  ethnic  information  on  the individual is included.”</span> Such information does not systematically exist.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, several large health studies have tried to survey the relationship between health and Sami ethnicity, and Magritt Brustad’s 2009 article was a summary based on such studies. Data for these studies was based on participants’ responses to questions regarding ethnicity.</p>
<p>Brustad  did  not  have  any  direct  recommendations  concerning  future  data  sources  but  she explained how <span type="quote">“Sami”</span> was defined in the various surveys. There is no <span type="quote">“official”</span> definition of the term <span type="quote">“Sami”</span> but statistics needs categories and categories were definied.</p>
<p>We face a Sami statistics problem here. If each instance of data collection uses its own definition of categoires, comparison of the results becomes difficult.</p>
<p><em type="bold">2.4  Data  Sources  for  Information  on  Industry  in  Traditionally Sami Areas  </em></p>
<p>Svanhild Andersen wrote an article in 2009 about primary industry in traditionally Sami areas. She built on Statistics Norway’s data from STN-areas and found the data useful when one kept to each specific industry within the area.</p>
<p>People  who  work  in  STN-areas  do  not  necessarily  work  in  only  one  industry  however.  The combination of different industris has a long tradition in Sami society. In the article, Andersen pointed out that further study on this aspect of industry in Sami areas was needed.</p>
<p>The ethnicity dimension is already discussed in the article on health and demographics above. The comments regarding lack of information on ethnicity applies for statistics on industry as well.  One  can  ask  what  provides  the  best  picture  of  Sami  society.  Is  it  figures  on  industry changes in traditionally Sami areas or is it information about the ethnicity of people who work there? The answer to the question is maybe that articles need to build on both types of data to  provide the best picture.</p>
<p>Industry was the main theme of the 2014 <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller</em> and four articles were about this theme. Else Grete Broderstad and Einar Eythórson wrote about fisheries and Jan Åge Riseth wrote about reindeer herding. Sigrid Skålnes analysed the development of industry within STNareas in the 2000s and Gunnar Claus analyzed employment statistics for STN-areas. </p>
<p>A shortcoming of the statistics, the authors pointed out, was that no information was available about  those  who  did  not  work  or  study.  These  fell  outside  of  the  statistics.  The  was  little information about people who lived in the country for only the short term. This last group is important for industry in Sami areas today. The authors also wanted information on people who left declining industries.</p>
<p>Authors on articles on business in the 2014 report, like Svanhild Andersen in 2009, also wanted more information on job-combining and part-time work.</p>
<p>Except  for  the  article  on  reindeer  herding,  all  the  industry  articles  were  about  specific geographical areas in the north. Reindeer herding is practiced in a larger part of the country, and  for  this  industry,  more  comprehensive  statistics  have  been  compiled  that  apply  to  all  of Norway. Since it is very clear which part of the industry is run by Samis and which part is run by Norwegian tame reindeer herders, ethnic based industry statistics were available. The author then compared Sami reindeer herding and Norwegian tame reindeer herding.</p>
<p><em type="bold">2.5  Data Sources for Infomation on Sami Language in Sociey </em></p>
<p>Six of the eight published reports of <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller</em> contained articles about developments in  the  number  of  students  chosing  Sami  as  the  language  of  instruction  at  school  and  those chosing to study Sami as a school subject. Only the reports from 2013 and 2014 did not include such  articles.  In  2015,  Torkel  Rasmussen  wrote  the  aricle  on  language  choice  at  school, otherwise these articles were written by Jon Todal. </p>
<p>Statistics are available on how many student  choose instruction in  Sami  as  a  first  or second language at the primary and lower secondary level. The figures are presented each year by GSI (<em type="italic">Grunnskolens  informasjonssystem</em>  –  the  primary  and  lower  secondary  school  information system). It is therefore easy to track developments and trends.  </p>
<p>The statistics also show the distribution of students for each of the three Sami languages taught in the country. Even though the discussion has never been very detailed in <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller, </em>it is possible to see the distribution of students geographically, down to the school district level.  </p>
<p>The quality of Sami instruction is difficult to quantify. Nontheless, it would be useful to know more than just the fact that Sami is taught as a first and second language. To gage the quality of Sami education, it is necessary, for example, to know how many hours of instruction <em type="italic">in</em> Sami schools  offer, not  just  <em type="italic">of</em> Sami.  We lack such data. We also  don’t know  how much of Sami instruction  is  carried  out  outside  of  regular  school  hours.  These  conditions  affect  students’ attitudes to the subject.       </p>
<p>Kaisa Rautio Helander and Yngve Johansen wrote an article in <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller 6</em> about Sami place names on public road signs within  administrative areas for Sami language (areas where Sami has the same status as Norwegian). Norway has an official language policy with binding laws and regulations that the state, counties and municipalities must follow. The article showed that in many cases, the laws were not followed and that statistics were lacking on the implementation of these language policies. The authors themselves needed to collect data and set up the necessary statistics in order to say something about the implementation of the Place Names Act on road signs. </p>
<p>In the 2015 issue of <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller,</em> Tore Johnsen wrote an article on Sami language in the Norwegian church. The church has itself compiled statistics on the use of Sami in its work. As long as the church is part of the state, it is required to use Sami in accordance with the Sami Act.  This  requirement  will  lapse  when  the  church  soon  separates  from  the  state.  Since  the Norwegian church’s standing in Sami society is strong, it is hoped that the church continues to use Sami and compiles statistics that could reveal possible changes in the use of the language. </p>
<p>The other articles on language in <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller</em> have few recommendations regarding statistical data sources. However, it has been pointed out that statistics to monitor the use of Sami in the public sector are needed, and that we know little about the transfer of language from generation to generaton at home. The last-mentioned statistics will be challenging to compile; the first should be easy. </p>
<p><em type="bold">2.6  School, Higher Education and Research </em></p>
<p>Beyond the school-related articles already mentioned (articles on language at primary and lower secondary school), <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller</em> has had eight other articles regarding school, higher education and research. </p>
<p>For five out of the eight articles, the authors had to collect data from various sources themselves in order to assemble the statistics. This applied to the following areas: the production of doctoral degrees  with  Sami  themes  (Else  Grete  Broderstad  2011),  adult  education  in  Sami  language (Lene  Antonsen  2015),  production  of  study  credit  points  in  Sami  (Kevin  Johansen  2013), distance learning in Sami (Kevin Johansen 2015) and Sami research projects (Kari Morthensen 2015).</p>
<p>Furthermore, in her 2015 article about adult education in Sami language, author Lene Antonsen called for consolidated statistics on the resources used on this type of education.</p>
<p>The three other school articles were written by Yngve Johansen and concerned the level of education among Samis. Johansen based these articles on data from STN-areas.</p>
<p><em type="bold">2.7  Political Participation among Samis </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller</em> has had two articles on political participation. The first was about voting participation in Sami Parliament elections  and was written by Torunn Pettersen. The second article  was  written  by  Per  Selle  and  Kristin  Strømsnes  and  was  about  political  participation among Samis, but not limited to Sami politics.   </p>
<p>The basis for the article on Sami Parliament elections was data that the author acquired from Statistics  Norway  and  the  Sami  Parliament.  Prior  to  2005,  finding  quality  assured  data  was difficult and figures were not available electronically. These problems were resolved from 2005 onwards.</p>
<p>It goes without saying that the electoral register of the Sami Parliament is the best registry to use when making quantitative analyses of Sami Parliament elections.</p>
<p>The other articles on political participation were based on three sample surveys: the national <em type="italic">Medborgerundersøkelsen</em>,  the  <em type="italic">Borgerrolleundersøkelsen</em>  conducted  in  five  municipalites  in Finnmark and the <em type="italic">Sametingsvalgundersøkelsen</em> conducted after the Sami Pariliament elections in 2009. Participants in the last survey were randomly selected among those registered in the Sami Parliament electoral register.   </p>
<p>The response rates for these surveys varied. The lowest was for the <em type="italic">Sametingsvalgundersøkelsen</em>. </p>
<p><em type="bold">2.8  Data on Sami Media </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Samiske  tall  forteller</em>  has  had  one  article  on  media.  The  article,  written  by  JohanJohan  Ailo Kalstad, was about the popularity, extent and general conditions of Sami media. The author used yearly statistics from the media, user surveys and annual reports from NRK (especially from NRK-Sápmi) and data from the Norwegian Media Authority. The author could study his findings  in  light  of  Eli  Skogerbø’s  report  on  Sami  media  from  2000,  which  was  based  on  a sample survey. Other sample surveys could also have been used.   </p>
<p><em type="bold">2.9  Environment and Resource Administration </em></p>
<p>There  has  been  only  one  article  on  the  theme  of  environment  and  resource  administraton  in Sami areas, written by Ole Bjørn Fossbakk. The author wrote extensively and informatively on  the  availability  of  various  data.  <em type="italic">Rovviltforvaltninga</em>  (the  agency  responsibe  for  predator management) and <em type="italic">Finnmarkseiendommen</em> (Finnmark Estate Agency) play a central role here. Figures  on  hunting  and  fishing  are  available  from  Statistics  Norway.  The  author  criticized <em type="italic">Finnmarkseiendommen </em>for making their figures especially difficult to acquire.   </p>
<p>In  addition  to  data  from  STN-areas,  Fossbakk  has  also  included  data  from  the  South  Sami reindeer grazing districts. The use of data from reindeer grazing districs has allowed him to hit on Sami interests outside of STN-areas as well.</p>
<p><em type="bold">2.10  Overview Articles </em></p>
<p>Paul  Inge  Severeide  has  written  three  articles  called  <em type="italic">Samiske  tall</em>  (Sami  numbers).  These articles present statistics for a range of social arenas. Commentary on statistics is brief and the main objective of the articles is to allow the reader to follow changes from year to year, also in social arenas not discussed in the longer articles.  </p>
<p>Most  of  the  statistics  used  area  based  on  data  from  Statistics  Norway  for  STN-areas.  The exceptions are reindeer herding statistics and school language statistics.</p>
<p><em type="bold">2.11  Summary </em></p>
<p>Statistics Norway’s figures for STN-areas appear to work well as a basis for analysis of Sami society, especially for analysis of demographics and industry. In total, 14 articles in  <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller</em> build largely on Statistics Norway’s data from STN-areas. Without such numbers, it would be much more  difficult  to  analyse  changes in  Sami society  in  Norway. The Expert Analysis group for Sami Statistics recommends that Statistics Norway continue to produce this type of statistics.   </p>
<p>Articles in <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller</em> show that there is no centrally collected data for a range of Sami social areas. There is reason to look closer at what can be done to improve the situation in the future.  </p>
<p>Ethnicity based statistics is needed in addition to statistics from STN-areas in order to analyze matters such as Sami health and transfer of Sami language between generations. As we have seen, Paul Inge Severeide has already considered this in the first <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller</em> in 2008. Severeide discussed whether it was possible to establish a <span type="quote">“statistical Sami population”</span> based on existing registries  such as  the 1970 census,  the registry of reindeer herders and the Sami Parliament’s electoral register.  </p>
<p>The establishment of such a Sami statistical  population  has  been evaluated but  has  been put aside. One reason for this was that it was not certain if the available material would represent all ethnic Samis. In the end, it was concluded that a large portion of Samis would most likely be excluded. Another reason to reject the proposal was the legal and privacy challenges tied to establishing such a population. These aspects must be carefully investigated before establishing a statistical Sami population.</p>
<p>We  in the Expert Analysis  Group for Sami Statistics  know that  other parties  have contacted Statistics  Norway  with  the  goal  of  compiling  statistics  on  Sami  speakers  in  Norway.  Better knowledge on the language situation will be useful for future public language planning. The methods used to accomplish this will be the same as for the establishment of a Sami statistical population, but with language as the central marker, not ethnicity.</p>
<p>Before one can establish the basis for such Sami language statistics, it is necessary to have a thorough  account  of  the  methodology  and  a  clarification  of  any  legal  issues.  The  Expert Analysis Group for Sami Statistics advises that work on such an account of the methodology begin and that any leagal questions around this be clarified.</p>
<p><em type="bold">2.12 Recommendations </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">On the Register </em></p>
<p type="listitem">  Statistics Norway should continue to produce statistics based on data from STNareas.</p>
<p type="listitem">  It  should  be  assessed  whether  it  is  methodologically  possible  to  establish  a <span type="quote">“statistical  Sami language population”</span> (not based on ethnicity, but  on language). The legal aspects of this should also be investigated.</p>
<p type="listitem">  Privacy  concerns  regarding  the  possible  establishment  of    a  <span type="quote">“statistical  Sami population”</span> (based on ethnicity) should be examined.</p>
<p><em type="italic">On Permanent Statistics </em></p>
<p>Statistics should be available on:</p>
<p type="listitem">  changes in Samis’ combination of different industries</p>
<p type="listitem">  what happens to people who leave declining industries</p>
<p type="listitem">  foreigners with temporary residence in Sami areas</p>
<p type="listitem">  the amount of Sami language instruction in primary and lower secondary school</p>
<p type="listitem">  the amount of Sami instruction conducted outside of regular school hours</p>
<p type="listitem">  changes  in  the  use  of  distance  learning  in  Sami  instruction  and  what  type  of languagea instruction distance learning is combined with</p>
<p type="listitem">  changes in use of Sami language in the public sector</p>
<p type="listitem">  the use of Sami in church (also after the separation of church and state)</p>
<p type="listitem">  the implementation of existing legislation, for example how the Place Names Act is being implemented on public signs</p>
<p type="listitem">  the  development  of  Sami-related  research  and  higher  education  (such  as  course study point production, number of PhDs, number of research projects financed by the Research Council of Norway and others)</p>
<p>In  addition  to  this,  statistics  of  great  interest  to  society,  such  as  statistics  on <em type="italic">Finnmarkseiendommen</em>, should be more readily available.   </p>
<p><em type="bold">Survey  </em></p>
<p>Discussions  should  begin  on  whether  it  is  possible  to  agree  on  Sami  ethnicity  definitions. Researchers could use these definitions to better compare results in the future.</p>
</body></document>