<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Self-Reported Experience of Discrimination against Samis in Norway</title><genre code="science"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>5054</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>http://samilogutmuitalit.no/sites/default/files/publications/9_self.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="7_selvopplevd_diskriminering.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="7_vasihan_vealaheapmi.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p><em type="bold">9  Self-Reported Experience of Discrimination against Samis in Norway </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Ketil Lenert Hansen</em>, PhD, Associate Professor, Regional Centre for Child and Youth Mental Health and Child Welfare North (RKBU North), UiT The Arctic University of Norway, Tromsø.<em type="bold"> </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Summary </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">New research shows that many Samis report experiencing various forms of discrimination. The aim of this chapter is to give updated information on the challenges of discrimination Samis face  in  Norway.  We  will  survey  the  occurrence  of  self-reported  incidents  of  discrimination among adult Samis between the age of 18 and 69 years, study where discrimination happens, identify who discriminates and how an individual might respond to being discriminated against.  </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">The figures are based on qualitative data collected in 2012 from 11,600 individuals (both Sami and majority Norwegians), from 25 municipalities in the five northernmost counties in Norway. The  study  is  part  of  a  health  and  living  conditions  investigation  in  areas  with  Sami  and Norwegian communities, called the SAMINOR 2 survey, which was a questionnaire sent out to municipalities in Northern Norway and Trøndelag.  </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">In the sample, approximately one in five experienced discrimination. About a third of those who had been discriminated  against,  say that the incident  happened in  the last  two years.  Samis experience discrimination much more frequently than majority Norwegians. Samis with strong Sami ties report the highest incidence of discrimination, both in the last two years and earlier. </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">The  most  common  form  of  discrimination  reported  by  Samis  was  ethnic  discrimination, followed by discrimination based on gender and geographical affiliation. Sami women reported the highest rates of gender discrimination.     </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Samis experience discrimination in several arenas. The most common is at school, work and in the local community. Additionally, many Samis report discrimination in public, on the internet and at stores or restaurants. Samis, to a greater extent than majority Norwegians, have and still experience discrimination from fellow students, teachers and other employees at school, work colleagues, public sector employees, other ethnic groups (majority population), strangers and other Samis. Even though many Samis experience discrimination, few file reports with The Equality and Anti-Discrimination Ombudsman (LDO- Likestillings- og diskrimineringsombudet). </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">9.1 Introduction </em></p>
<p>The Sami population is in a unique position compared to other minorities in Norway. On the one hand, they have a long history as a discriminated minority, especially when the Norwegian state had a Norwegianization policy aimed at assimilating Samis into the Norwegian majority culture  (Minde,  2005).  Conversely,  Samis  today  hold  the  status  of  indigenous  people  with strong legal standing in Norway (Midtbøen, 2015).</p>
<p>Nonetheless, the Samis’ legal status does not protect them from facing discrimination. Adult Samis  much  more  frequently  report  being  discriminated  against  than  majority  Norwegians (K.L. Hansen, Melhus, Hogmo &amp; Lund, 2008). In addition, discrimination is associated with poor somatic and mental health (K. L. Hansen, 2015; K. L. Hansen, Melhus &amp; Lund, 2010; K. L. Hansen &amp; Sørlie, 2012).</p>
<p>Sami policies from the middle of the 1800s until after the Second World War in Norway were based on assimilation. For Samis, this meant that their cultural traditions and language were to be  replaced  with  the  corresponding  majority  culture  and  language  (Josefsen,  2006;  Minde, 2005).  These  policies  had  an  ideological  foundation  in  Social  Darwinism,  nationalism  and security policy (Jensen, 2005). Within the educational system, this was expressed by policies such as instruction only in Norwegian, and the use of the Norwegian cultural identity as the basis of interaction between Samis and ethnic Norwegians (Høgmo, 1986). However, after the Second World War, the Norwegian government changed the direction of its policies on Sami minorities. This change became clear in connection with the steering of Samis’ legal rights at the end of the 1980s and beginning of the 1990s (ILO-169 and wording in paragraph 108 of the constitution), and the creation of the Sami Parliament.</p>
<p>Even though Norwegianization policies are a part of Norwegian history and former policy, their negative  effects  are  long  lasting.  It  will  take  time  to  change  the  general  framework  of Norwegian policies, legislation and organization, not to mention myths and attitudes, so that Sami  culture,  language,  traditions  and  needs  are  sufficiently  considered  in  fields  such  as education, work and public service.</p>
<p>Little  research  has  been  done  on  the  long-term  effects  of  the  Norwegianization  process  and structural discrimination. Certainly, Norwegianization has had many victims. Colonialization has stolen many Samis’ language, culture, and self-esteem and has been the cause of personal trauma (Nergård, 2011). Many researchers and politicians have spoken up to form a truth and reconciliation  commission  about  the  political  and  cultural  injustices  that  Samis  have experienced.  Norwegianization  and  discrimination  on  the  grounds  of  ethnicity  has  led  to significant  consequences  in  the  living  conditions,  quality  of  life  and  health  of  many  Sami families and individuals in a range of local communities in Norway, likely more than previously thought.  We  need  to  know  more  about  how  this  has  affected  and  still  affects  the  Sami population.</p>
<p><em type="bold">9.1.1 Chapter Objectives</em> </p>
<p>Updated information on the status of discrimination against Samis is needed to promote equality and  hinder  ethnic  discrimination.  This  information  can  also  be  used  to  develop  effective measures to prevent discrimination. The aim of this chapter is to give updated information on the challenges of discrimination Samis in Norway face.</p>
<p>Which challenges do Samis face at work, school, in the local community and public sector? Do they  face  the  same  challenges  with  equality  and  discrimination  as  majority  Norwegians? Alternatively, do Samis and non-Samis face different challenges?</p>
<p><em type="bold">9.1.2 The Concept of Discrimination </em></p>
<p>This article focuses on personal experiences with discrimination of Samis in Norway. In this article, discrimination is defined as occurring <span type="quote">“when a person or group of people is treated less favourably than others  because of,  for example,  ethnicity, religion,  beliefs,  disability, age or sexual orientation”</span>. ‘Discrimination’ is a form of unequal treatment which is unfairly justified and is not related to positive discrimination or affirmative action.</p>
<p>Discrimination can be defined as acts and practices which lead to injustice and inequality in power, resources and opportunities across people and groups in society and serves to support systems  of  privilege  and  repressive  structures  (Ferdinand,  Paradies  &amp;  Kelaher,  2015). Discrimination  can  manifest  itself  from  subtle  forms  of  exclusion  and  verbal  statements  to physical acts of violence. Current data suggests that discrimination is an increasing social issues in many countries (Paradies et al., 2015).</p>
<p>In this study, we have taken a broad approach to self-reported experience of discrimination and included ethnicity, gender, age and geographic affiliation, as well as discrimination based on illness, learning disabilities, religion or faith, physical disability, nationality, sexual orientation and others.</p>
<p>Discrimination can occur at school, work, in the local society, the public sector, other public settings such as shops and restaurants or in the family. The type of discrimination and setting in which it occurs can overlap and mutually reinforce. Samis may therefore face several types of discrimination in several settings at the same time. Discrimination can occur on three levels: <em type="italic">internalized  at  an  individual  level</em>  (for  example  incorporation  racist  attitudes,  beliefs  or ideologies in  an individual),  <em type="italic">interpersonal</em> (face to  face in  interactions  between individuals), and at the <em type="italic">structural</em> level (inherent discriminatory effects of social structures) (K. L. Hansen, 2015). In this chapter, we mainly study self-reported interpersonal discrimination (face-to-face interactions) among adult Samis and non-Samis.  </p>
<p><em type="bold">9.1.3 About the Study </em></p>
<p>The figures are based on data collected in 2012 from 11,600 individuals between the ages of 18 and  69  years  (both  Sami  and  majority  Norwegian),  from  25  municipalities  in  the  five northernmost  counties  in  Norway.  The  study  is  a  part  of  SAMINOR  2-survey,  which  was  a questionnaire  sent  out  to  municipalities  with  Sami  and  Norwegian  communities  in  Northern Norway  and  Trøndelag.  See  map  9.1  for  research  area.  The  research  is  described  earlier  in another publication (Brustad, Hansen, Broderstad, Hansen &amp; Melhus, 2014). <em type="italic">Datatilsynet </em>(The Data Inspectorate) and <em type="italic">REK nord </em>(The Regional Committees for Medical and Health Research Ethics, North) have approved the study.  </p>
<p><em type="bold">Map 9.1 Municipalities Involved in the Study</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">9.1.4 Sample Characteristics  </em></p>
<p>Demographic characteristics of the sample are presented in table 9.1. The majority in the sample were women. The average age was 50 years old, and the majority of participants had an average income, an education at the college or lower university degree level and lived in <em type="italic">Distrikts-Norge </em>(rural  Norway)<em type="italic">.</em>  The  study  is  therefore  most  representative  of  individuals  with  these characteristics. A third of participants had a Sami affiliation. </p>
<p><em type="bold">9.1.5 Definition of Ethnicity </em></p>
<p>Ethnicity refers to a group of individuals with a common identity related to a common origin, perceived by others to be a distinguishable by a common language, culture, history and so on. The term entails both subjective and objective aspects. Sami as an indigenous group is included in the term <em type="italic">ethnicity</em>. </p>
<p>Since there is no Sami registry in Norway, and since this information cannot be collected in a census, the survey included 11 different questions about ethnicity in order to define who was Sami and who not. In addition, this survey wanted to make a differentiated ethnicity variable that could categorize <em type="italic">Saminess</em>. </p>
<p><em type="bold">Figur 9.1 The figure comes from the questionnaire used by the SAMINOR 2 study. It shows how the questions on ethnicity were posed.</em> </p>
<p>The  first  question  group  concerns  which  home  language  you,  your  parents  and  your grandparents  have/had.  The  next  question  concerns  your  father’s,  mother’s  and  your  ethnic background.  The  last  question  is:  What  do  you  consider  yourself  to  be?  For  all  of  these questions, the answer alternatives were ‘Norwegian’, ‘Sami’, ‘Kven’, or ‘other’. Respondents could cross off one or more of the categories for each of the questions.</p>
<p>From these 11 questions, it is possible to make various categories of ethnicity. In this case, we chose to categorize as Sami any participant who crossed off one of the boxes marked Sami. The others  were  categorized  as  non-Sami.  (For  the  most  part,  these  participants  crossed  off Norwegian ethnicity with some also crossing off Kven or other ethnicity.)</p>
<p><em type="bold">We further constructed three categories of Sami ethnicity: </em></p>
<p>(i) <em type="italic">Strong Sami ties </em>(ii) <em type="italic">Self-reported Sami </em>(iii) <em type="italic">Sami family background </em></p>
<p>Category 1:’Strong Sami ties’ was made up of people who answered YES to all of the three following questions: ‘I use Sami as my home language’, ‘my ethnic background is Sami’ and ‘I consider myself to be Sami’. This group is marked in green as category 1 in figure 9.2.</p>
<p>Category 2: ‘Self-reported Sami’ were those who answered YES to one or two (but not all three) of the questions mentioned above in category 1. This group is shown in figure 9.2 all within the circles, except for the innermost circle which is category 1.</p>
<p>Category 3: ‘Sami family background’ was defined as those who reported Sami family background with either language or ethnicity for parents or grandparents, but did not define themselves as Samis. More concretely, these respondents reported Sami as a home language either for their parents or grandparents and/or that their parents had a Sami ethnic background, but they did not view their own ethnicity as Sami, or did not feel themselves to be Sami, and did not speak Sami at home. This group is marked as the white areas inside the quadrangle in the figure.</p>
<p>The categories are mutually exclusive and show a graduated ethnicity variable, where category 1 shows most  Sami  markers  and  a  strong  connection  to  a  Sami  background,  Sami  self-perception  and  home language. There are 1,372 respondents in this category. Category 2 is the largest category in terms of number  of  respondents  (N=1,459).  In  this  category,  most  have  said  that  they  have  both  a  Sami background and perceive themselves as Sami (55%), but only 8% in this category have Sami as a home language. In category 3, 1,097 reported a Sami family  background without perceiving themselves as Sami,  defining  their  own  background  as  Sami  or  speaking  Sami.  Figure  9.2  shows  a  graphic representation of the different ethnicity categories.</p>
<p><em type="bold">9.1.6 Sami Area </em></p>
<p>We defined the municipalities of Kautokeino, Karasjok, Nesseby, Tana and Porsanger as <em type="italic">Sami majority areas</em>.  In these  areas, over 50% of the population  reported  a Sami connection. The municipalities  of  Røros,  Snåsa,  Røyrvik,  Namsskogan,  Narvik,  Alta,  Grane,  Hattfjelldahl, Tysfjord,  Evenes,  Skånlang,  Lavangen,  Lyngen,  Storfjord,  Kåfjord,  Kvænangen,  Loppa, Kvalsund, Lebesby and Sør-Varanger were defined as <em type="italic">Sami minority areas</em>. The reason for this was that in these areas, Sami occupy in a minority position vis-à-vis the majority population.  </p>
<p><em type="bold">9.2 Characteristics of those who Experience Discrimination </em></p>
<p>In  our  sample,  approximately  one  in  five  (21.5%)  have  experienced  discrimination. Approximately a third of those who have experienced discrimination, say the discrimination occurred the last two years. Age, ethnicity, education, income and residence were all factors tied  to  discrimination.  Samis,  people  between  the  age  of  30  and  49,  with  13-16  years  of education,  a  household  income  between  301,000  and  600,000  NOK  and/or  living  in  Sami minority areas reported they highest number of incidents (figure 9.3).</p>
<p><em type="bold">Figur 9.3 Characteristics of those who Reported Discrimination</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">9.2.1 Samis Experience Most Discrimination </em></p>
<p>Half of Samis (50%) with a strong Sami connection reported having been discriminated against, 34.3% reported that the offence has happened before and 16.5% said that the event happened in the last two years. In addition, self-reported Samis (32.8% in total, 24.5% before and 8.4% in the last two years) reported a high degree of discrimination. In comparison, 14.3% of nonSamis reported discrimination, 9.9% before and 4.4% in the last two years (in the period 20102012).  Samis  with  Sami  family  background  reported  the  highest  rate  of  discrimination  that occurred earlier, but did not have the same number as non-Samis for violations in the last two years (table 9.2). This shows that Samis with a strong Sami connection report approximately four times as much discrimination as ethnic Norwegians (table 9.2).</p>
<p>Sami men and women with strong Sami ties report a high degree of discrimination in both Sami majority and Sami minority areas. Reports are a somewhat higher in Sami minority areas, but only by a significant amount for Sami women with strong Sami ties. The majority population (non-Samis) report higher rates of discrimination in Sami majority areas than outside of these areas (table 7.3).</p>
<p><em type="bold">9.2.2 Types of Discrimination </em></p>
<p>The most common form of discrimination reported by both Sami men and women with strong Sami  ties  (men:  33.3%,  women:  31.9%)  and  those  who  self-reported  Sami  identity  (men: 15.0%, women: 17.0%), was ethnic discrimination, followed by discrimination based on gender and  place  of  residence.  Women  reported  a  significantly  higher  rate  of  gender  based discrimination than men, and Sami men and women (with strong Sami ties) reported more than non-Samis  (Sami  men:  6.7%;  Sami  women:  11.9%  versus  Norwegian  men:  1,2%  and Norwegian  women:  2.9%).  Samis  also  reported  more  discrimination  on  the  grounds  of geographical  affiliation  than  non-Samis.  Sami  men  and  women  reported  more  age  related discrimination  than  the  majority  Norwegians.  Sami  men  reported  somewhat  higher  rates  of discrimination  on  the  basis  of  learning  difficulties  than  non-Samis.  Sami  women  reported slightly higher rates of discrimination based on illness than non-Samis (1.6-2.8% versus 1.2%) (See figures 9.4 and 9.5).</p>
<p>There was no meaningful difference in reporting  of discrimination due to religion, disability and sexual orientation. In the Sami population, approximately one percent were discriminated against because of sexual orientation, while the number for religion and disability was close to two percent among Samis.</p>
<p>Another  reason  for  discrimination  was  nationality.  The  figures  show  no  difference  between Samis and non-Samis.</p>
<p>Samis reported also a significantly higher rate of other types of discrimination than non-Samis. These  were  not  collected  in  the  ten  categories  mentioned  above  (figures  9.4  and  7.5). Participants  has  the  opportunity  to  specify  other  types  of  discrimination.  Many  reported discrimination connected to work, their Sami identity (because they didn’t speak Sami, were not good enough Samis in others’ eyes, or for other questions related to their Sami provenance), and other pointed out that it was because of their homosexuality.</p>
<p>In total, 66% reported having experienced one form of discrimination, 24% stated that they had experienced two types of discrimination and 7% said that they had experienced three types of discrimination. There was no ethnic difference between Samis and non-Samis with respect to how many types of discrimination they had experienced.</p>
<p><em type="italic">9.2.2.1 Comments </em></p>
<p>Through the ratification of the UN’s Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination (August 6, 1970), Norway has pledged to prohibit discrimination based on race, skin  colour,  heritage  or  national  and  ethnic  origin.  The  convention  was  incorporated  into Norwegian law through the Anti-Discrimination Act (law June 3, 2005 no. 33) (Nystuen, 1991). The  Anti-Discrimination  Act  prohibits  direct  and  indirect  discrimination  based  on  ethnicity, nationality, heritage, skin colour, language, religion or philosophy of life. The Act’s purpose is to promote equality, ensure equal opportunity and rights and prevent discrimination. The act is applicable  to  all  sectors  of  society,  with  the  exception  of  family  life  and  other  personal relationships (Lovdata, 2013).</p>
<p>Many Samis experience ethnic discrimination in Norway and many experience this in typically Norwegian-dominated  areas  (table  9.3).  This  is  in  line  with  earlier  research  about  personal experiences  with  discrimination  of  Samis  in  Norway  (Ketil  Lenert  Hansen,  2011).  Ethnic discrimination is the most common form of discrimination Samis experience. Figures show that approximately  one  in  three  Samis  with  strong  ties  to  the  community  has  experienced discrimination  because  of  his/her  Sami  origin,  compared  to  under  three  percent  of  majority Norwegians. This shows that Samis experience ten times more ethnic discrimination than nonSamis. Our data from 2003/2004 agrees with these numbers, which indicates that Samis still experience a high degree of ethnic discrimination in Norwegian society today.</p>
<p>Gender  discrimination  has  been  highly  prioritized  in  Norway  with  the  implementation  of legislation  in  1978.  Nonetheless,  gender  based  discrimination  is  the  second  most  commonly reported form of discrimination reported by Sami men and women. There is no study in Norway about  gender  discrimination  in  the  general  population  (Skjeie,  2012).  We  know  little  about gender  discrimination  in  the  Sami  population.  Sami  women  report  the  highest  incidence  of gender based discrimination. We can imagine that the fight for equality in Sami society has had to yield to the fight for recognition as an indigenous population, and that the question of equality has  not  been  prioritized  until  the  beginning  of  this  century  (Josefsen,  2004).  We  need  more information  about  why  Samis  (especially  Sami  women)  report  higher  rates  of  gender-based discrimination than the majority population.</p>
<p>Many Samis also say that they feel discriminated against because of their  place of residence. This  can  be  the  result  of  geographical  or  institutional  variations  which  make  the  situation different  for  all  Samis.  For  example,  Josefsen  (2006)  points  out  that  government  authorities have  geographically  differentiated  which  rights  particular  Samis  have  (Josefsen,  2006).  Our data supports this and shows that Samis who live in typically Sami minority areas report higher degree of discrimination than those who live in areas defined as Sami areas, and have strong protection of Sami institutions, language, values and culture (K. L. Hansen, 2012).</p>
<p>Samis also reported higher levels of age discrimination than majority Norwegians (3.4% versus 1.3%). The difference was not very big, but nonetheless significant statistically. In Norway, the debate  on  age  discrimination  has  been  associated  with  work.  Protection  against  age discrimination applies only to work but there is a debate on whether age discrimination should apply to all sectors of society.</p>
<p>When it comes to discrimination based on sexual orientation, 0.7-1.2% of the Sami population have experienced this, versus 0.4% of the majority population. The difference between Samis and non-Samis  is  not  statistically significant.  However, in  the open-ended questions,  quite a few Samis answered that they have experienced discrimination based on their homosexuality. Recently, there has been a spotlight on taboos in Sami society, and homosexuality has been one of these themes. In the debate, many claimed that it is more difficult to be a homosexual Sami than a homosexual Norwegian because of the double stigma that comes from being a minority and a homosexual. (NRK Sápmi, 2016). Homosexuality has been extremely taboo and shameful in the traditional Sami society (NRK Sápmi, 2013).</p>
<p><em type="bold">9.2.3 Where does Discrimination Happen?  </em></p>
<p>Samis experience discrimination in many arenas. The most common arenas are school, work and  local  community.  Around  one  in  five  Samis  with  strong  Sami  ties  has  experienced discrimination at school or in connection with education, compared with around 4% of nonSamis.  Samis  also  report  more  discrimination  at  work  and  in  the  local  community  than Norwegians do. Further, many Samis report incidents in public, on the internet and in stores or restaurants.  More  Sami  men  than  women  with  strong  ties  report  incidents  in  stores  and restaurants (9.3% versus 5.2%). Digital discrimination was also reported far more frequently among Samis with strong Sami ties than non-Samis. Samis experienced more discrimination in a  family  setting,  volunteer  work  and  while  receiving  medical  treatmen  than  non-Samis. However, it must be pointed out that there were few who answered that they had experienced discrimination in these last three areas. Few reported incidents of discrimination while seeking work, buying a home, in the rental market or applying for a loan (less than 3%) (both among Samis and non-Samis). One can therefore say that discrimination in these areas is a minimal problem  in  Norway. However, Samis  experienced far more frequent  discrimination on other areas  than the 12 mentioned.  There is  no big difference between men and women  regarding where discrimination happens (figures 9.6 and 9.7).</p>
<p><em type="italic">9.2.3.1 Comments </em></p>
<p>NOU  2015:  2  –  <em type="italic">Å  høre  til  –  Virkemidler  for  et  trygt  psykososialt  skolemiljø</em>  (Belonging  - Measures for a safe psychosocial school environment), presents data from <em type="italic">Elevundersøkelsen 2014/2015</em> (Student Survey 2014/2015) and <em type="italic">Folkehelseinstituttet </em>(The Norwegian Institute of Public Health) that shows the portion of students who are insulted and bullied in Sami areas is higher than in the rest of the country (Djupedal, 2015). The fact that our survey show that school is the social arena where most Samis experience discrimination supprts these recent findings. This raises a serious question about whether the requirements of paragraph 9a of Education Act 9a  (Lovdata,  2015)  of  a  good  psychosocial  environment  at  school,  free  of  bullying  is  being fulfilled in Norway for Sami children and youth. Even though we work hard to prevent bullying at  schools  in  Norway,  with  several  anti-bullying  campaigns  (Olweus,  2009;  Roland,  2014) going on over the last three decades, none have focused on the prevention against indigenous peoples and minorities (Minton, 2014). These anti-bullying programs have not been adapted to Sami  culture  and  identity.  Cultural  sensitivity  is  an  important  element  which  should  be prioritized in future anti-bullying campaigns and interventions against discrimination at school.  </p>
<p>The workplace was the most common arena where non-Samis experienced discrimination and the second most common arena for Samis (after the educational sector). In total, 7.5% of the sample experienced discrimination or insults at work – 11.5% of the Sami population (all three Sami groups as a whole) and 5.6% of the non-Sami population (regardless of gender). Earlier studies  in  Norway  have  shown  that  the  incidence  of  bullying  at  work  was  around  2-14% (Nielsen et al., 2009). Our numbers lie within this span and show that discrimination at work is an  even  greater  problem  for  Samis  than  non-Samis.  Employers  should  work  actively, purposefully  and  systematically  to  promote  equality  and  prevent  discrimination  within  their establishments.</p>
<p>Samis  experience  further  discrimination  in  the  local  community,  in  public  and  at  stores  or restaurants, far more frequently than non-Samis. These findings suggest that Samis face more prejudice, discriminatory remarks and insults in the public sphere than majority Norwegians. This  can  again  limit  their  opportunities  of  democratic  participation  in  the  welfare  society  in terms of equal access to social and public services and goods.</p>
<p><em type="bold">9.2.4 Discrimination and Social Media </em></p>
<p>Digital bullying has increased in Norway between 2000 and 2010 (Roland, 2014). A 2008 study conducted  by  Læringsmiljøsenteret  (The  Centre  for  Learning  Environment)  in  Stavanger concludes that traditional bullying affects approximately twice the number of people as digital bullying  (Auestad,  2011).  International  studies  have  found  a  weak  tendency  for  girls  to  be exposed to digital bullying more frequently than boys (Parker-Jenkins, 2011). This study used the term discrimination ‘on the internet’ for digital bullying. Samis self-report a significantly higher  number  of  incidents  of  digital  discrimination  than  non-Samis.  Younger  Sami respondents (aged 18-29) frequently reported experiencing digital bullying. More than one in five Sami youth aged 18-29 with strong Sami ties reported experiencing discrimination on the internet. Among non-Samis, we found no gender differences, but among Samis we found that digital discrimination was reported more frequently by women than men, regardless of age (data not shown in tables).</p>
<p>We know little about digital attacks or hate speech experienced by Samis in Norway, as these have not yet been researched or studied in a qualitative approach. We know from media (TV, radio, newspaper and internet), that many Samis experience offensive comments, hate speech and prejudice, as well as stereotypical portrayals of Sami culture and identity in comment fields on the internet and on various websites (Ketil Lenert Hansen, 2012).</p>
<p><em type="bold">9.2.5 Who Discriminates?  </em></p>
<p>Samis  with  strong  Sami  ties  and  self-reported  Samis  have  experienced  much  more discrimination  from  fellow  students,  teachers  and  other  employees  at  school,  other  ethnic groups (majority population), strangers and other Samis than majority Norwegians. In addition, many Samis report offences from public servants and work colleagues. Non-Samis report most discrimination by work colleagues, fellow students and public servants (see figure 9.8 and 9.9).</p>
<p><em type="italic">9.2.5.1 Comments </em></p>
<p>Since many in the survey report discrimination at school, it is not surprising that fellow students were  the  most  common  bullies  reported.  More  surprising  was  that  so  many  Samis  reported offensive comments by teachers or other employees at school.</p>
<p>Being different is a call to discrimination and bullying and as a minority, Samis are vulnerable (Høgmo, 1998). Many Samis experience discrimination by majority Norwegians and strangers. These offences happen in various arenas of society. After fellow students, the most common bullies that Samis face are public servants and colleagues.</p>
<p>Many  Samis  experience  discrimination  by  other  Samis.  This  must  be  seen  in  connection  to Norwegianization  and  the  resulting  shame  associated  with  being  Sami.  Shame  over  Sami culture  is  maybe  one  of  the  most  difficult  and  important  barriers  to  revitalization  and decolonisation  of  individuals,  families  and  local  communities  (Nergård,  2011).  Many  Samis have lived through the assimilation of their identity and language over the last three generations (Høgmo,  1986)  and  this  has  led  to  a  denial  and  suppression  of  Sami  identity  and  culture (Høgmo,  2011).  Høgmo  has  pointed  out  that  the  strongest  Sami  discrimination  occurs  in Norwegianized  Sami-Norwegian  communities,  and  that  people  with  Sami  backgrounds  are often the ones carrying out the discrimination. He points out that this is a reaction to the attitude in the majority society: derogatory comments about Samis take attention away from one’s own Sami  background  (Høgmo,  2005).  These  complex  social  and  psychological  factors  can  help explain why so many Samis in this study experience offences from their own Sami group.</p>
<p><em type="bold">9.2.6 Resilience against Discrimination </em></p>
<p>Research shows that self-reported experience of discrimination is associated with mental and physical health problems (K. L. Hansen, 2015; K. L. Hansen &amp; Sørlie,  2012). A fifth of the sample reported that discrimination affected them a lot (table 9.10) and we know from earlier studies that this group is potentially exposed to health problems (Paradies et al., 2015).</p>
<p>We also know that those who did something to end the discrimination emerge with better health than  those  who  do  not.  In  our  sample,  38%  said  that  they  did  something  to  stop  the discrimination.  One  can  suppose  that  this  group  is  most  resilient  to  the  negative  health consequences that discrimination can inflict (figure 9.11).</p>
<p><em type="bold">9.2.7 Few Samis Report Discrimination to the Equality and  </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Anti-Discrimination Ombudsman </em>Even though many Samis experience discrimination, few have contacted the The Equality and Anti-Discrimination  Ombudsman  (LDO-  <em type="italic">Likestillings-  og  diskrimineringsombudet</em>).  In  our sample, only 1.8% (45 people) who reported having experienced discrimination  had contacted LDO. There can be many reasons that Samis do not contact LDO for help. One of these can be tied to Sami norms and traditions where one should appear strong and not ask for help outside of the family when one is faced with hardship (Bongo, 2012; Kuokkanen, 2015). Cultural and linguistic barriers may also be reasons for Samis not to seek help regarding personal experiences with discrimination.  </p>
<p><em type="bold">9.2.8 Multiple Discrimination </em></p>
<p>Samis experience discrimination in several arenas or settings much more frequently than the majority Norwegian population. This means that Samis more often than non-Samis report that discrimination occurs in more areas of society at the same time, for example in an educational context and/or work environment, local community, public sector, in stores/restaurants and/or on  the  internet.  The  fact  that  Samis  experience  discrimination  (most  often  because  of  their ethnic  background)  in  several  areas  of  society  at  the  same  time,  and  from  both  known  and unknown  people,  can  be  understood  in  relation  to  the  concept  of  cumulative  discrimination. This  term  refers  to  discrimination  that  accumulates  across  spheres  or  arenas.  Cumulative discrimination  in  one  part  of  society  can  contribute  to  reduced  opportunities  in  other  areas (Arnfinn &amp; Hilde, 2016). For example, discrimination at school can affect results at school and in the long run, opportunities in the labour market. These processes are seldom illuminated by research because they often focus on single arenas such as school or work and therefore miss connections between them.</p>
<p><em type="bold">9.3 Challenges and Recommendations </em></p>
<p>Many Samis experience various forms of discrimination in Norwegian society. We know that the  most  common  form  of  discrimination  is  ethnic  discrimination  and  that  they  face  these offences  in  various  arenas  of  society:  in  educational  contexts,  work,  in  contact  with  public services, in stores, restaurants and increasingly in social media, which in the last three years has developed into a new arena for discrimination of Samis.</p>
<p>Discrimination against Samis is a social problem. It has been documented through research over the last ten years (Ketil Lenert Hansen, 2011). Nevertheless, there is little systematic research exploring  equality  and  the  discrimination  challenges  that  Samis  experience  in  Norway,  for example at school, work, local community and in social media. There are many more reports about  immigrants  (Midtbøen,  2015).  Norwegian  authorities  should  establish  a  system  to monitor the extent of discrimination the Norwegian indigenous  population  encounters in  the different social arenas, especially at school, work and local community. In this chapter, we have looked  at  some  of  the  challenges  of  equality  and  discrimination  that  Samis  encounter  in Norwegian society. There are still large gaps in knowledge about discrimination and bullying of  Samis  which  future  research  should  shed  light  on,  especially  on  areas  that  concern  Sami children and youth.</p>
</body></document>