<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title/>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <wordcount>154</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/>
    <multilingual>
      <language xml:lang="swe"/>
      <language xml:lang="eng"/>
    </multilingual>
    <origFileName>http://www.lansstyrelsen.se/dalarna/En/miljo-och-klimat/halsoskydd/Pages/default.aspx</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="miljo-och-klimat-halsoskydd.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="miljo-och-klimat-halsoskydd.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>Environmental health - Länsstyrelsen i Dalarna</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="swe"></p>
    <p type="title">Environmental health</p>
    <p><em type="italic">The County Administrative Board's initiative for health protection is to detect, prevent and eliminate health protection hazards, both indoors and outdoors, to prevent people from becoming sick. </em></p>
    <p>Health protection issues are dealt with in, inter alia, appeal cases, planning applications, inspection and certification of environmentally hazardous activities and in environmental objective measures. As a part of our assessments, we consider aspects including noise, vibration and air shock waves, radiation, odour, legionella risks and radon concentrations.</p>
    <p>The County Administrative Board's commission is to coordinate, monitor and evaluate the municipality's regulatory activities in the field of environmental health and to provide advice on these activities. The work also involves cooperating with municipalities and other bodies or authorities with respect to various projects and training as well as monitoring and measuring the state of air, water and soil. Municipal health decisions can be appealed to the County Administrative Board.</p>
  </body>
</document>
