<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>198</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/><multilingual><language xml:lang="swe"/><language xml:lang="eng"/></multilingual><origFileName>http://www.lansstyrelsen.se/dalarna/En/om-lansstyrelsen/vart-uppdrag/Pages/default.aspx</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="om-lansstyrelsen-vart-uppdrag.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="om-lansstyrelsen-vart-uppdrag.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>Our commission - Länsstyrelsen i Dalarna</p>
<list><p type="listitem"></p>
<p type="listitem"></p>
<p type="listitem"></p>
<p type="listitem"></p>
<p type="listitem"></p>
<p type="listitem"></p>
<p type="listitem"></p>
<p type="listitem"></p>
</list><p></p>
<p type="title">Our commission</p>
<p><em type="bold">The commission of the County Administrative Board is to work for development where the environment, economic growth and good living conditions go hand-in-hand. The goal is a clean living environment, a stable labour market and a good life for the residents. In short, we are working towards sustainable development in the county. </em></p>
<p>The County Administrative Board is responsible for ensuring that decisions from parliament and the Government are implemented in the county and we coordinate government activities. With regard to the county's development, we shall safeguard and work for the interests of both individuals and society.</p>
<p>We are a knowledge based organization which works with many different cross-sectoral issues. Our areas of expertise span diverse social issues, from rural development and biodiversity to integration and the protection of cultural environments.</p>
<p>In accordance with the instructions of the County Administrative Board (SFS 2007:825), our work includes:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">food inspections, animal welfare and general veterinary issues</p>
<p type="listitem">regional growth</p>
<p type="listitem">infrastructure planning</p>
<p type="listitem">sustainable community planning and housing</p>
<p type="listitem">energy and climate</p>
<p type="listitem">cultural environment</p>
<p type="listitem">protection against disaster and emergency preparedness and civil defence</p>
<p type="listitem">nature conservation and environmental and public health</p>
<p type="listitem">agricultural and rural areas</p>
<p type="listitem">fishing equality</p>
<p type="listitem">integration</p>
</list></body></document>
