<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>156</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/><multilingual><language xml:lang="swe"/><language xml:lang="eng"/></multilingual><origFileName>http://www.lansstyrelsen.se/dalarna/En/samhallsplanering-och-kulturmiljo/byggnadsvard/Pages/default.aspx</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="samhallsplanering-och-kulturmiljo-byggnadsvard.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="samhallsplanering-och-kulturmiljo-byggnadsvard.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>Building conservation - Länsstyrelsen i Dalarna</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="swe"></p>
</list><p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Building conservation</p>
<p><em type="bold">Building conservation are a part of the County Administrative Board's long-term efforts to preserve the county's cultural environment. The County Administrative Board handles building conservation grants and subsidies to renovate surplus buildings on farmland. </em></p>
<p type="title">Building preservation</p>
<p>In order for the building to retain its heritage value, it is important that preservation, maintenance and renovation measures are based on the conditions of the individual house. It is also important to use historically accurate materials and methods to make the most of the building's character and appearance while preserving the traditional crafts.</p>
<p>Individuals, municipalities, foundations and companies can apply to the County Administrative Board for a government grant to preserve historically important buildings, what is known as a building preservation grant. Restoration which becomes more expensive than normal may be partially funded through the grant, we can provide 50-90 per cent of the cost that is culturally and historically justified.</p>
</body></document>
