<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Morfa</title><genre code="facta"/><author><person firstname="Lene" lastname="Antonsen" sex="f" born="1962" nationality="NO"/></author><wordcount>246</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Børre Gaup" email="borre.gaup@uit.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://oahpa.no/sme/useoahpa/morfa.eng.html</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="morfa.fin.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="morfa.nob.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="morfa.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title" xml:lang="isl">Morfa</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Options</p>
<p type="listitem">Parts of speech and inflection <list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="est">Links</p>
</list></p>
</list><p>The user may practice word inflection in a systematic way - either with singleton words (Morfa-S) or words in sentences, in order to learn the context in which to use the wordforms (Morfa-C).</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Options</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Parts of speech, see details further down.</p>
<p type="listitem">Stem type (Morfa-S): bisyllabic, trisyllabic or contracted stems, or all of them.</p>
<p type="listitem">Vocabulary according to textbook.</p>
<p type="listitem">The student can get the Norwegian translation by clicking the word she/he does not understand (Morfa-S).</p>
<p type="listitem">Help (Morfa-S): When the student makes mistakes, she/he can be instructed about correct inflection.</p>
</list><p type="title">Parts of speech and inflection</p>
<p>The user may choose what part of speech to work with; nouns, adjectives, verbs or numerals.</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Nouns: nominative plural and other cases. In the other cases, the student will be given base forms in both singular and plural.</p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Verbs: </em>present and past indicative, conditional, potential and imperative </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Adjectives: </em>as attribute or predicative with comparision. Morfa-S has the same inflection categories in different cases. </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Pronouns: </em>personal, deictic, relative, reflexive and reciprocal pronouns, in all cases. </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Numerals: </em>inflected in different cases, also as attribute to nouns. Collective numerals and ordinal numerals in different cases. Morfa S - in level 1 there are numerals up to 10, both in singular and plural. In level 2 there are also bigger numerals. In Morfa C there are numerals up to 10, both singular and plural. </p>
</list><p type="title" xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<p>Morfa-s single words</p>
<p>Morfa-c sentences</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Last changed: $Id: morphdrill.eng.xml,v 1.6 2008/05/05 lene Exp $</p>
</body></document>
