<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title/>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <translator>
      <unknown/>
    </translator>
    <translated_from xml:lang="fin"/>
    <wordcount>2253</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index.php?option=com_docman&amp;task=doc_download&amp;gid=1260&amp;Itemid=10</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="climat_suomi.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="climat_pohjoiss.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="climat_inarinsaame.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="ilmastomuutosta27.pdf"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 125457 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>Climate policy strategy of the Saami Parliamentary Council</p>
    <p>Adopted by the Saami Parliamentary Council on 14th April 2010</p>
    <p>The Saami Parliamentary Council (SPC) praises the UN’s Human Rights Council for its decision and its action  to underscore the connection between climate change and universal human rights and for the consideration given to the vulnerable situation of the indigenous peoples in this context. SPC considers that the initiation of various activities in connection with climate change impacts in many ways on the human  rights  of  indigenous  peoples.  The  voice  of  indigenous  peoples  needs  to  be  clearly  heard  in connection of global climate negotiations.</p>
    <p>SPC  sees  climate  change  in  a  wider  context:  the  growing  environmental  burden  and  increased exploitation  of  natural  resources  make  it  more  difficult  to  act  in  a  flexible  way  to  adapt  the  Saami livelihood and way of life to a changing climate. SPC considers that the most important way for Saami society  to  adapt  to  a  changing  climate  is  by  reducing  vulnerability  while  increasing  the  resilience  of people, animals and nature in Sápmi.</p>
    <p>A global challenge such as climate change can only be met through cooperation and by utilising the best available knowledge – which is why Saami traditional knowledge is extremely important in solving this challenge.</p>
    <p>The  Saami  language  and  its  classification  system  carries  on  Saami  culture  and  traditions  from  one generation to the next. In formulating a climate change contingency plan and systemisation of resources, one must take into consideration the status of the Saami language and secure its survival. The survival of  the  Saami  language  and  the  knowledge  it  embodies  requires  the  retained  vitality  of  Saami livelihoods.</p>
    <p>The  Saami  Parliaments  must  be  able  to  participate  equally  in  the  decision-making  process  regarding climate change at national and international level. The Saami parliaments are to be given broader rights to  decide  on  administration  and  governance  in  their  own  areas.  The  reason  is  that  this  gives  the  best conditions for adapting to climate change with Saami culture as a base.</p>
    <p>SPC considers that the states of Sweden and Finland must ratify ILO Convention 169 and that the states must  implement  the  UN  declaration  on  indigenous  peoples  as  an  integral  part  of  their  national legislation. SPC demands that the Nordic Saami Convention be ratified without delay according to the proposal  done  by  the  expert  group.  The  convention  would  enable  Saami  culture  to  develop  in  three states in a single Saami context. This would also facilitate adaptation to climate change and ensure the human rights of the Saami people.</p>
    <p>Resolution  7/28,  28  March  2008,  Resolution  10/4,  and  Report  of  the  Office  of  the  United  Nations  High</p>
    <p>Commissioner  for  Human  Rights  on  the  relationship  between  climate  change  and  human  rights (A/HRC/10/61).  Resolution  10/4,  para  7  and  8  explicitly  mention  indigenous  peoples  among  the  most vulnerable groups who will feel the most acute affects of climate change: “<em type="italic">Recognising</em> that these implications will affect individuals and communities around the world, the effects of climate change will be felt most acutely by those segments of the population who are already in vulnerable situations  owing  to  factors  such  as  geography,  poverty,  gender,  age,  indigenous  or  minority  status  and disability,”  C169 The Indigenous and Tribal Peoples Convention, 1989 (International Labour Organisation ILO)  Nordisk samekonvensjon. Utkast fra finsk-norsk-svensk-samisk ekspertgruppe. 2005. </p>
    <p>SPRC  demands  that  in  the  next  climate  conference  COP  16  on The  United  Nations  Framework</p>
    <p>Convention  on  Climate  Change in  Mexico  December  2010 the  parties shall  agree  on  emission</p>
    <p>reductions  that  are  legally  binding  and  that  parties  shall  agree  to  a  system  of  sanctions  for  breaches against  the  reduction  requirements.  SPC  demands  that  the  rise  of  the  global  average  temperature  be limited to 1.5 degrees Celsius. Greater increase in the average temperature would bring consequences that  are  impossible  to  predict  and  which  would  probably  jeopardize  the  living  possibilities  of  Arctic Indigenous peoples in the Arctic. States not meeting the emission conditions should pay heavy sanctions annually.  The  funds  levied  would  be  used  to  finance  in  developing  countries  energy  production  that does not give rise to emissions. An international body must be created under the auspices of the UN to enforce the agreement. In connection with this, a body for indigenous peoples is to be set up. This body shall scrutinise compliance with the agreement and the way in which indigenous people are affected by developments.</p>
    <p>SPC demands that emission levels be significantly reduced. For a reduction in emission levels under the Kyoto Protocol, the base year has been set at 1990. SPC considers that if the emissions of a single year are used as a benchmark, the result is uneven, permitting a situation where certain states in practice are not  required  to  reduce  their  emissions  at  all.  SPC  demands  that  states  shall  reduce  their  amount  of emitted greenhouse gases by 40 per cent on average up to the year 2020 and by 90 per cent up to the year 2050.</p>
    <p>SPC  demands  that  developing  renewable  energy  forms  shall  cut  the  growth  in  emissions  and  new technology shall be made available to the population in an economically viable way. Improving energy efficiency  in  construction  must  be  developed  with  the  help  of  planning  permission  and  aids.  Climate legislation should be compiled at national level. Through this, emission levels are to be controlled and activities  funded  that  prevent  climate  change  and  guarantee  the  rights  of  indigenous  peoples  in  the context of climate change.</p>
    <p>SPC considers that the aim in international politics dealing with indigenous peoples must be to mitigate the effects of climate change on indigenous peoples and create opportunities for indigenous peoples to secure  influence  in  decision-making  connected  to  climate  change.  Actions  carried  out  to  mitigate climate  change  must  not  be  at  the  expense  of  indigenous  peoples’  wellbeing  and  their  living possibilities.</p>
    <p>SPC  especially  supports  increased  use  of  solar  energy.  The  possible  growth  of  wind  power  in traditionally Saami settlement areas is to take place in consultation with the Saami parliament involved, as well as in consultation with the representatives of traditional livelihoods that are affected especially with  reindeer  herding  cooperatives.  Wind  power  must  not  be  allowed  to  impact  traditional  Saami livelihoods  negatively  even  remotely,  such  as  Saami  reindeer  herding.  The  increase  of  renewable energy forms demands increased use of bio-energy. In certain areas, bio-energy production threatens the living conditions of indigenous peoples. All bio-energy cultivation must be done sustainably and with</p>
    <p>the respect of the rights of indigenous people. SPC demands that increased use of bio-energy must not</p>
    <p>increase  the  level  of  particle  emissions  and  demands  that  particle  emissions  shall  be  cut  through effective  filtration  methods.  The  increase  of  hydro-electric  power  must  not  be  allowed  to  threaten environmental values or influence negatively even remotely Saami culture. SPC wishes also to reiterate that peat isn’t renewable energy source.</p>
    <p>SPC is opposed to increasing nuclear power. The memory of Chernobyl’s nuclear accident in 1986 lives on  among  the  memories  of  the  Saami,  and  its  consequences  still  affect  Saami  society  and  traditional Saami livelihoods. It is not a clean energy source. It leads to uranium emissions, both during extraction and  mining  and  during  waste  storage.  In  the  Nordic  countries  and neighbouring  areas  in  Russia  ,  the</p>
    <p>Kyoto Protocol, 1997  Saami reindeer herding, Sami agriculture, gathering, hunting and other forest based livelihoods.</p>
    <p>acquisition  and  extraction  of  uranium  and  accidents  in  nuclear  plants  can  destroy  traditional  Saami livelihoods.</p>
    <p>In the new Framework Convention on Climate Change, parties must agree on reducing small particle emission substantially. An international monitoring body shall be set up to monitor the emissions. The states  have  to  reduce  small  particle  emissions  in  industries,  traffic  and  households  by  legislation  and energy funding.  The small particle emissions aren’t regulated specially, the limits apply only to total emissions.  A  financing  system  should  be  set  up  for  the  households  and  industries  of  the  developing countries  that  could  provide  low-cost  filtering  system  to  reduce  these  emissions.  This  would  be economical and efficient way to reduce particle emissions.</p>
    <p>The residue particles  of incomplete combustion, such as black carbon and soot plays a greater role than expected  in  global  warming.  The  reduction  of  these  emissions  gives  favourable  and  fast  results.  The particle  emissions  have  negative  effects  on  health.  At  global  level,  they  give  rise  to  early  death.  The particles accelerate climate change to Arctic areas and reductions of these emissions are of the utmost importance  to  mitigating  climate  change.  The  greater  part  of  particle  emissions  spread  from  Asia  to Arctic  areas  with  air  currents.  When  they  fall  on  snow  or  ice,  they  make  the  surface  darker.  A  dark surface absorbs the sun’s radiation more effectively and in this way causes the ice and snow to melt at an increasing rate. The process also accelerates the warming of the climate in the Arctic.</p>
    <p>SPC  appeals  that  the  efforts  to  make  snowmobile  and  ATV’s    more  energy-efficient  will  be  started quickly. These machines are essential in modern Saami livelihoods, but they need to be developed to reduce  their  emissions.  ATV’s  need  to  be  developed  into  safer  vehicles  with  a  smaller  footprint  in nature. This would also support the biological diversity. SPC proposes that development work should begin immediately, in which state research institutions, industry and representatives of traditional Saami livelihoods are represented.</p>
    <p>SPC  considers  that  in  preventing  climate  change  one  must  take  into  account  the  UN  Convention  on Biological Diversity Article 8 (j) as well as traditional knowledge, innovations and practices and the possibilities of the Saami to influence in international bodies in accordance with this article. SPC wishes to  draw  attention  to  Article  10  (c)  as  well,  which  states  that  the  parties shall  protect  and  encourage</p>
    <p>customary  use  of  biological  resources  in  accordance  with  traditional  cultural  practices  that  are compatible  with  conservation  or  sustainable  use  requirements. SPC  considers  that  the  article  requires</p>
    <p>states to respect traditional Saami ways to use nature.</p>
    <p>SPC is concerned that states, as of 2010, still have not reached the target of stopping the reduction of biological  diversity.  SPC  urges  the  states  to  protect  and  secure  nature’s  diversity.  This  applies</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Se  pres.:  Co-Chair’s  Summary:  Melting  Ice:  Regional  Dramas,  Global  Wake-Up  Call  Tromsø,  28  April</p>
    <p>  United Nation’s Convention on Biological Diversity, 1992.   Article  8(j):  <em type="italic">Subject  to  national  legislation,  respect,  preserve  and  maintain  knowledge,  innovations  and </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">practices of indigenous and local communities embodying traditional lifestyles relevant for the conservation and  sustainable  use  of  biological  diversity  and  promote  their  wider  application  with  the  approval  and involvement of the holders of such knowledge, innovations and practices and encourage the equitable sharing of the benefits arising from the utilisation of such knowledge innovations and practices.</em>  Traditional knowledge in other languages: </p>
    <p> Finnish: perinteinen tieto  Swedish: traditionell kunskap   Norwegian: tradisjonell kunnskap  Article 10(c) <em type="italic">Protect and encourage customary use of biological resources in accordance with traditional </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">cultural practices that are compatible with conservation or sustainable use requirements;</em>  The sub-meeting on the Convention on Biological Diversity, COP6, in 2002 resolved that the parties to the </p>
    <p>agreement undertake to stop the decline in natural diversity by the year 2010.</p>
    <p>specially during 2010, which is Biological Diversity Year.  SPC sees it is of the greatest importance to research traditional knowledge and the influences of climate change to traditional knowledge. It’s also highly  important  to  take  into  account  traditional  knowledge  and  climate  change  in  decision  –making processes and in post 2010 biodiversity targets.</p>
    <p>SPC  proposes  that  at  the  COP10  meeting  in  Nagoya  on  18-29  October  2010  should    be  agreed  on  a decision that in the multi-year work-programme on Article 8 (j) should  be included a new task: climate change and traditional knowledge. SPC  requests countries to advance the fulfilment of this task.</p>
    <p>In  connection  with  the  UN’s  Framework  Convention  on  Climate  Change,  an  official  indigenous peoples’ body should be established. Its task will be to administrate and follow the decisions made in the climate change process and which affect indigenous peoples. This body shall operate in cooperation with the UN Permanent Forum for Indigenous Peoples and the work group for Biodiversity Convention, WG8J.  The  basis  for  this  body’s  work  shall  be  the  UN  Declaration  on  the  Rights  of  Indigenous Peoples’  (indigenous  peoples’  declaration).  The  body  shall  be  guaranteed  adequate  operational  and expert resources. The body should operate in cooperation with the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change  and  with  the  Arctic  Council.  The  body  shall  be  represented  by  an  adequate  number  of representatives  from  representative  organisations  and  organisations  representing  indigenous  peoples, taking into account geographical cover.</p>
    <p>The states shall contribute to the Saami parliaments annually receiving stipulated funding for adaptation to  climate  change,  for  research  into  this  and  for  developing  their  own  policies  on  climate  change.  In each Saami parliament, there shall be an officer to administrate environmental and climate issues and a committee of specialists to deal with them. The states should contribute permanent financing to these operations.</p>
    <p>SPC considers that research on climate change should be increased and that in this research, studies of the  effects  of  climate  change  should  be  intensified  to  minimise  its  effects  in  the  habitats  of  the indigenous peoples in the Arctic. Research and its financing should be coordinated in consultation with the state, the Arctic Council and the indigenous people concerned.</p>
    <p>SPC urges the Saami parliaments of Norway, Finland and Sweden in their operations to work towards sustainable  development  that  leads  to  more  effective  energy  use,  and  work  for  a  reduction  in  the emissions  that  cause  climate  change.  SPC  shall  also  work  to  increase  the  use  of  renewable  energy sources. SPC commits on preparing a climate policy programme.</p>
    <p>Ad Hoc Working Group on Article 8(j) and related provisions  United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples, 2007.  Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC)</p>
  </body>
</document>
