<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>JUO Master in Sámi Journalism from an Indigenous Perspective | Sámi University of Applied Sciences</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>861</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://samas.no/en/studier/juo-master-sami-journalism-indigenous-perspective</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="juo-master-sami-journalism-indigenous-perspective-sami-journalistihka-mastergrada-algoalbmot.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="isl">MA - Program</p>
<p type="title">JUO Master in Sámi Journalism from an Indigenous Perspective</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Photo/govven: Sergey Gavrilov</p>
<p><em type="italic">Language of instruction </em>: English <em type="italic">Study place </em>: Guovdageaidnu/Kautokeino, Norway </p>
<list><p type="listitem">Introduction week: January 16-20, 2017</p>
<p type="listitem">Teaching week 1: January 23-27, 2017</p>
<p type="listitem">Teaching week 2: February 20-24, 2017</p>
<p type="listitem">Teaching week 3: March 20-24, 2017</p>
<p type="listitem">Teaching week 4: April 24-28, 2017</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">Application deadline for <em type="italic">international students </em>21 october 2016 </p>
<p type="listitem">Application deadline for <em type="italic">local students </em>21 october 2016 </p>
</list><p>Are you already a journalist working within indigenous media? Or are you interested in working with indigenous issues? Then this Programme might be a for You! A unique programme bringing together students from all over the world to the magic world of Sápmi, above the Arctic circle – an experience of a lifetime! As the first of its kind, the Sámi University College in Guovdageaisnu/Kautokeino, Norwegian Sámiland, offers a Master´s degree in Indigenous Journalism. We offer high quality education from an indigenous perspective, lectures by world leading experts and exciting international networks.</p>
<list><p type="listitem"><span>Duration: 1 ½ years (for a 90 ECTS Master’s) or 2 years (for a 120 ECTS Master’s, which gives access to further study). </span></p>
<p type="listitem"><span>A Master’s Programme approved by the Norwegian Agency for Quality Assurance in Education. </span></p>
<p type="listitem"><span>The programme has NO TUITION FEES. </span></p>
</list><p type="title">Description of Programme</p>
<p>Indigenous journalism is a developing field in communication practice, with an increasing need for professionals and experts. Sámi University College offers one of the few existing Bachelor programmes in journalism from an indigenous perspective. This international Master’s Programme in Indigenous Journalism started in 2015 as a unique programme in the field of media and journalism in the world. Simultaneously, this programme offers a continuation to the existing Bachelor’s programme at the Sámi University College.</p>
<p>The Master’s Degree Programme in Indigenous Journalism provides rigorous academic training for further study and deep insight into the world of journalism, while simultaneously examining the world of journalism from an indigenous perspective. An important aspect of the programme is to enable the students to reflect upon what it means to be an indigenous journalist, and what, if any, bearings this perspective has on journalistic practice. The programme offers theoretical and research based knowledge of journalism, and of the methods and skills that are required for working as journalists in advanced positions.</p>
<p>Considering the growing field of indigenous media, this is necessary in order to develop the field of indigenous journalism. As of today, there is a great lack of academically trained professionals who can function as teachers or researchers in this field. The growing field of indigenous media also calls for a growing need for policy makers and professionals with an indigenous perspective. This programme meets the demand for the provision of advanced professional development for journalists, Sámi and indigenous journalists in particular.</p>
<p>Simultaneously the programme provides a context for an international exchange of experience, values and professional priorities of journalists in indigenous communities worldwide. It intends to attract students from Sámi and other indigenous communities, and students with a specific interest in indigenous media and journalism, with the aim of providing indigenous and other communities with media professionals, academics and policy makers in the field of media in an indigenous and multicultural context.</p>
<p>Check our Facebook</p>
<p xml:lang="smn"><em type="italic">Indigenous Journalism </em></p>
<p>The programme is built on the two main subject blocks of journalism and media studies, with a special focus on Indigenous media and journalism within an indigenous context. Within these main blocks, the core areas of focus are the following:</p>
<list><p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Theory and methods in journalism research </em></p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">The relations between sources, journalists and society </em></p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Theory and practice of media ethics and law </em></p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Media and global indigenous politics </em></p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">The role of indigenous journalism and the media in diverse societies </em></p>
</list><p type="title">Programme content</p>
<p><em type="italic">Year 1: semesters 1 and 2 </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">The first semester offers basic knowledge in fundamental concepts of indigenous journalism and journalism ethics.</p>
<p type="listitem">The second semester offers advanced knowledge in journalism and journalism research. It teaches theory and methods, knowledge and skills for writing the master’s thesis.</p>
</list><p><em type="italic">Year 2: semesters 3 and 4 </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">The second year focuses on examination of theoretical and methodological skills, and supports the writing of the Master’s Thesis with seminars, and optional courses where possible and appropriate.</p>
<p type="listitem">Students are expected to choose between a more theoretical (60 credits) or more practically oriented (30 credits) Master’s Thesis. The former qualifies for doctoral studies.</p>
</list><p>The students who opt for a 30 credit thesis will attain a 90 credit Master’s Degree. Students who choose a Master’s Thesis of 60 credits will have the option to continue with research studies after completing their Master’s Degree of 120 credits.</p>
<p type="title">How to apply?</p>
<p>Just follow theese steps and we walk you through:</p>
<p><em type="italic">Guidelines on how to apply </em>. </p>
<p>And please remember following:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Application through Søknadsweb ,TOGETHER WITH the following attachments:</p>
<p type="listitem">​Documentation of Bachelor's Degree or equivalent (see entrance requirements)</p>
<p type="listitem">Documentation of your minimum 2 years of work experience (see entrance requirements)</p>
<p type="listitem">Letter of motivation (no longer than one page of A4)</p>
<p type="listitem">Documentation of English skills if relevant</p>
</list><p type="title">For more information on the programme and Kautokeino contact:</p>
<p>The coordinator will answer your questions about the course. Please, send an email to the coordinator Ellen Marianne Siri at:</p>
<p>indigenous_journalism@samiskhs.no</p>
<p type="title">We are looking forward to hearing from you!</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
</body></document>
