<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="science"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>10964</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="2_samegiella_vuoddoskuvllas.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p><em type="bold">7 Sami Language in Primary and </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Secondary Education </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">Torkel Rasmussen, </em>Associate Professor, Sami University College, Kautokeino <em type="bold"></em></p>
<p>Summary</p>
<p><em type="italic">Since the 2005/06 school year, fewer and fewer students are taking Sami as a Second Language at the primary and lower secondary level. The article shows that the decrease appears to have stopped and that the number of students has stabilised, albeit at a lower level than before. The decline in student numbers for South Sami as a second language, however, is still worrisome. There is also a decline in the number of students learning Sami as a first language. Special attention is focused on the differences between the number of students who learn Sami as a mother tongue and the number of students who have Sami as the language of instruction. More and more students at the primary and lower secondary level are choosing to take Sami as a first language without having any other subject taught in Sami. </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">The availability of instructional material to teach subjects other than Sami language in Sami has improved over the las four years. Nevertheless, the situation is still critical for Lule and South Sami where students still lack teaching material in most of the subjects at the primary and lower secondary level. </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">A review of the Office of the County Governor’s inspection reports on Sami education shows that all of the inspections in Nordland and Oslo/Akershus found breaches of the law. In Finnmark, the reports are uniformly positive. A review of Sami education in other counties has not been undertaken. </em><em type="bold">7.1 Sami Language at School </em></p>
<p>This article focuses on Sami language education in Norway at the primary and secondary level over the last five years, from the 2010/11 to 2014/15 school years. In addition, a longer retrospect is used to show developing trends.</p>
<p>The Education Act and the National Curriculum for Knowledge Promotion in Primary and Secondary Education and Training regulate the use of Sami language in education. For this reason, 2.2 gives a short review of the main sections on Sami language in the law and curriculum.</p>
<p>Three Sami languages are taught and used for instruction at the primary and lower secondary level: North, Lule and South Sami. These languages can also be learned and used at the upper secondary level. Section 3 of this article gives a unified account of the total number of students who have instruction in one of the Sami languages at the primary and lower secondary level. Section 4 presents figures for instruction in Sami at the upper secondary level, while section 5 considers the situation of teaching material for instruction of Sami and the various alternatives for Sami as a second language.</p>
<p>The Office of the County Governor conducts inspections of instruction <em type="italic">of </em>and <em type="italic">in </em>Sami at the primary, lower secondary and upper secondary levels. Section 6 will focus on the inspections conducted over the last four years. <em type="bold">7.2 Legislation and Curriculums 7.2.1 Legislation for Primary and Lower Secondary School </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Education </em></p>
<p>In the Education Act, §6-2 Sami Education at Primary and Lower Secondary School establishes the right of students in Sami districts to be educated in Sami. Outside of Sami districts, students have the same rights as long as the parents of at least ten students demand it. Once instruction has started, it cannot be halted as long as there are at least six students left in the group.</p>
<p>According to the Education Act §6-1, a Sami district is defined as an administrative area for Sami language ( <em type="italic">Forvaltningsområdet for samisk språk1) </em>and other municipalities or parts of municipalities that the government has decided to call a Sami district. No areas outside of administrative areas for Sami language have been classified as Sami districts. Since the provisions set out in the Education Act, as of today, only apply to administrative areas for Sami language, the term <em type="italic">Sami administrative area </em>will be used in the rest of the article. </p>
<p>Municipalities within Sami language administrative areas can decide that all students in primary and lower secondary schools will receive instruction of Sami. Three municipalities have made such a resolution, which remains in force today: Nesseby, Karasjok and Kautokeino. In these municipalities, a variety of Sami is an obligatory subject for students at primary and lower secondary schools.</p>
<p>Outside Sami administrative areas, Sami students in primary and secondary school have the right to an education in Sami (Education Act §6-2, paragraph 5). This means that Sami children have an individual right to instruction of a Sami language, but not the right to have Sami as the language of instruction. According to the law’s §6-1, a Sami is defined as a ‘person who can be enrolled in the electoral register, and the child of one who can be enrolled’. The law also sets out that ‘the department can demand alternative forms for such instruction when the teaching personnel at the school cannot offer the instruction’. This has allowed for the use of distance learning in Sami education where the teacher and student are not physically located in the same classroom, but communicate with the help of computers. <em type="bold"></em>1 Sami administrative areas consist of the municipalities of Nesseby, Tana, Karasjok, Porsanger, Kautokeino, Kåfjord, Lavangen, Tysfjord, Røyvik and Snåsa. <em type="bold">7.2.2 Legislation for Upper Secondary Education </em></p>
<p>The Education Act §6-3 establishes that Samis in high school have the right to instruction of Sami. This right is applicable to the whole country and does not disappear even if the school is not able to find a teacher to teach the subject. In the same way as for Sami education at the primary and lower secondary level, ‘the department can set out regulations on alternative forms of instruction when instruction cannot be offered by the teaching personnel at the school’. High schools have therefore an obligation to arrange instruction of Sami through, for example, distance learning.</p>
<p>High school students do not have the right to instruction in Sami. However, the Ministry of Education and Research can order individual schools to offer instruction of or in Sami in particular subjects within certain programs or groups. Most high schools are owned by county authorities and §6-3 of the Education Act gives county authorities the ability to offer instruction in Sami. Additionally, there are two national Sami high schools in Karasjok and Kautokeino. <em type="bold">7.2.3 Curriculums </em></p>
<p>Public school instruction follows either <em type="italic">The Curriculum for Knowledge Promotion in Primary and Secondary Education and Training </em>(LK06) <em type="italic"></em>or <em type="italic">The Sami Curriculum for Knowledge Promotion in Primary and Secondary Education and Training </em>(LK06-S). All public primary and lower secondary schools in Sami language administrative areas follow LK06-S. The curriculum has developed three alternative Sami language educational plans at the primary and lower secondary school level (Udir 2013-1: 2013-2): <em type="italic">Sami as a First Language </em>, <em type="italic">Sami as a Second Language 2 </em>and <em type="italic">Sami as a Second Language 3 </em>. Most students who have <em type="italic">Sami as a First Language </em>at this level also have Sami as the language of instruction in other subjects. At the high school level, a fourth alternative is available: <em type="italic">Sami as a Second Language 4. </em>This alternative is designed for students who have not had instruction of Sami at the primary and lower secondary school level. In the curriculum, the goal of <em type="italic">Sami as a First Language </em>is expressed as follows: </p>
<p><em type="italic">Sami as a First Language shall develop a student’s language skills based on their abilities and (pre)conditions. Oral proficiency as well as competence in reading and writing are goals in themselves and form the necessary basis for learning and comprehension in all subjects in all grades. The subject should motivate the desire to read and write, and contribute to the development of good learning strategies. (Udir 2013-1). </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Sami as a Second Language </em>is meant for students who do not have Sami as a mother tongue and have not learned Sami before starting school. <em type="italic">Sami as a Second Language 2 </em>has a more ambitious goal than <em type="italic">Sami as a Second Language 3 </em>, but both have the same number of class hours. According to the curriculum, <em type="italic">Sami as a Second Language 2 </em>is: <em type="italic">…the alternative that gives the best foreign language skills at the end of schooling, and choosing this alternative at primary and lower secondary school will contribute to laying the groundwork for a student’s functional bilingualism. (Udir 2013-2) </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Sami as a Second Language 3 </em>is intended for beginner students who do not know any Sami when they start instruction. These students will benefit from having more class hours to learn the language. Students who start with Sami late in primary school or not until lower secondary school also follow this alternative. Bilingualism is not necessarily the goal. <em type="italic">Sami as a Second </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Language 4 </em>is meant for high school students who have never had instruction of Sami. This is the first year this course has been taught. (Udir 2013-2; 2015-1) <em type="bold">7.3 Sami Language at Primary and Lower Secondary </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">School </em></p>
<p>Data for this chapter comes from the primary and lower secondary school information system on the internet ( <em type="italic">Grunnskolens informasjonssystem </em>- GSI 2014), as well as the Norwegian Directorate for Education and Training (Udir 2015-1). In addition, some of the figures come from earlier editions of <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller </em>(Todal 2011; 2012). <em type="bold">7.3.1 Total Number of Students Learning Sami </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.1 Total Number of Students Learning Sami 2005/06 2010/11 2011/12 2012/13 2013/14 2014/15 </em></p>
<p>In total 3055 2245 2153 2126 2126 2116</p>
<p>North Sami 2844 2058 1987 1933 1947 1943</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Lule Sami 88 96 72 98 93 99</p>
<p>South Sami 123 91 94 95 86 74</p>
<p>Table 7.1 shows that the number of students learning Sami has decreased by 10 from last year. The number of students who have received instruction of Lule Sami has increased by six or 6.5%. For South Sami, there has been a decrease of 12 students or 14%. There is a considerable decrease in the total number of students who receive instruction of Sami after the 2005/06 school year, which was the last year in which the old curriculum was used. As this has been thoroughly discussed by Todal (2011; 2012), we will focus on developments over the last five years. Since the 2010/11 school year, there has been a decrease of 129 students or 5.7%. Considering that the total number of students in primary and lower secondary school level in Northern Norway has also gone down by 5.3%, it is possible to say that the situation for Sami education has stabilised (GSI 2014), but at a lower level than before. The data also shows that the decline concerns North Sami and South Sami, while instruction of Lule Sami has increased by three students or 3.1% in the five year period. The decline in instruction of South Sami is 17 students or 18.7%. This is characterised as a considerable decrease. <em type="bold">7.3.2 Total Number of Students with Sami as the Language of </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fra"><em type="bold">Instruction </em></p>
<p>Data in the table below shows the total number of students receiving their education at the primary and lower secondary level in South, Lule or North Sami. Data for individual Sami languages is not available.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.2 Total Number of Students in Primary and Lower Secondary </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">School with Sami as the Language of Instruction 2005/06 2010/11 2011/12 2012/13 2013/14 2014/15 </em></p>
<p>In total 977 893 855 873 822 812</p>
<p>Table 7.2 shows that 812 students at the primary and lower secondary school level had Sami as the language of instruction in the 2014/15 school year. This is decrease of 10 students or 1.2% from the previous year. Over the last five years, the total number of students has gone down from 893 to 812. This is a decrease of 81 students or 9.1%. The decrease from the 2005/06 school year to now was of 165 students or 16.9%. In the 2003/04 school year, there were 1057 primary and lower secondary school students in Norway receiving their education in Sami. This was the highest number ever. There has been a decrease of 245 students or 23.2% from the 2003/04 school year to 2014/15. This is characterised as a marked decrease. Some of this decrease can be attributed to falling birth rates in some central Sami areas. The data clearly shows that fewer children are now receiving their education in Sami than at the beginning of the 2000s. This situation is unfavourable to the development of the Sami language and should be examined more closely. <em type="bold">7.3.3 Total Number of Students taking Sami as a First Language </em></p>
<p>At the primary and lower secondary level in Norway, instruction is available in South, Lule and North Sami.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.3 Total Number of Primary and Lower Secondary School Students taking Sami as a First Language 2005/06 2010/11 2011/12 2012/13 2013/14 2014/15 </em></p>
<p>In total 998 971 940 930 916 915</p>
<p>North Sami 953 923 895 879 877 878</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Lule Sami 29 29 25 30 19 22</p>
<p>South Sami 16 19 20 21 20 15</p>
<p>Table 7.3 shows that 915 students are taking Sami as a First Language at the primary and lower secondary level. This is a decrease of 1 student or 1.1% from the previous year. Of these students, 878 receive instruction in North Sami as a First Language, 22 students have Lule Sami as a First Language and 15 have South Sami as a First Language.</p>
<p>The number of students for North Sami as a First Language has gone down from both the 2005/06 and the 2010/11 school years. There was a decrease of 83 students or 8.3% from 2005/06 and of 66 students or 6.8% from 2010/11. The number of students taking Lule Sami as a First Language has been a little bit under 30 for the period in question but fell to 19 last year, and then increased to 22 this year. The number of students with South Sami as a First Language was at around 20, but sank to 15 this year. This is a decrease of 25%. <em type="bold">7.3.4 Sami as the Language of Instruction and Sami as a First </em></p>
<p xml:lang="isl"><em type="bold">Language </em></p>
<p>Most of the students taking Sami as a First Language also have Sami as the language of instruction. However, there is not a complete match between the number of students who take Sami as a First Language and those who have Sami as the language of instruction.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.4 Total Number of Primary and Lower Secondary Students with </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Sami as a First Language and Sami as the Language of Instruction 2005/06 2010/11 2011/12 2012/13 2013/14 2014/15 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Sami as a first language 998 971 940 930 916 915</p>
<p>Sami as lang. of instruction 977 893 855 873 822 812</p>
<p xml:lang="tur">Difference 21 78 85 57 94 103</p>
<p>Table 7.4 shows that in the 2014/15 school year, there were 103 students who took Sami as a First Language without having Sami as the language of instruction. This difference has increased from 21 in the 2005/06 school year. This number has varied over the last five years but has always been markedly higher than for the 2005/06 school year.</p>
<p>The reason for the discrepancy between the number of students studying Sami as a Frist Language and the number of students receiving instruction in Sami is uncertain. It may be because instruction in Sami is not available in the students’ home municipality or nearest school. It may also be that parents have decided not to have Sami as the language of instruction, even if it is available. This topic should be examined more closely. <em type="bold">7.3.5 Number of Students taking Sami as a Second Language </em></p>
<p>It is possible to learn South, Lule and North Sami as a second language at the primary and lower secondary school level in Norway.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.5 Number of Primary and Lower Secondary Students taking Sami as a Second Language 2005/06 2010/11 2011/12 2012/13 2013/14 2014/15 </em></p>
<p>In total 2057 1274 1213 1196 1210 1201</p>
<p>North Sami 1891 1135 1092 1054 1070 1065</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Lule Sami 59 67 47 68 74 77</p>
<p>South Sami 107 72 74 74 66 59</p>
<p>Table 7.5 shows a marked decrease from 2005/06 to now in the number of students who are learning Sami as a second language at the primary and lower secondary school level. The reasons for this decrease are discussed in <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller 4 </em>and <em type="italic">5 </em>(Todal 2011; 2012: 110-11). Todal points to the new curriculums that came after the Knowledge Promotion Reform and examines whether the reform could have influenced parents’ decisions about choice of language at school. Table 7.5 also illustrates that the number of children who learn Sami as a second language at primary and lower secondary school has been relatively stable over the last four years. There was only a slight decrease of nine students or 0.7% from last year and this may indicate that the decline in numbers has ceased. <em type="bold">7.3.6 The Distribution of Students taking Sami as a Second </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Language 2 and Second Language 3 </em></p>
<p>As mentioned earlier, it is possible to choose between two varieties of Sami as a second language at the primary and lower secondary level. Sami as a Second Language 2 has higher competence aims than Sami as a Second Language 3. One can therefore assume that students taking Sami as a Second Language 2 will become more proficient in the language than students taking Sami as a Second Language 3. It is thus interesting to look at the distribution of students in these two subjects.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.6 Number of Primary and Lower Secondary Students taking </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Sami as a Second Language 2 and 3 2010/11 2011/12 2012/13 2013/14 2014/15 </em></p>
<p>Second Language in Total 1285 1213 1196 1210 1201</p>
<p>Second Language 2 645 598 567 617 717</p>
<p>Second Language 3 640 615 629 593 484</p>
<p>Table 7.6 shows that over the last three years, more students who chose to take Sami as a Second Language have chosen Sami as a Second Language 2 over Sami as a Second Language 3. In the 2010/11 school year, the number of students enrolled in the two subjects were almost identical. In the 2014/15 school year, 59.7% have chosen Sami as a Second Language 2 while 40.3% have chosen Sami as a Second Language 3. This is a positive development as more students are learning the language at a level with the aim of giving them a higher degree of competency. <em type="bold">7.3.7 Number of Students in Sami Administrative Areas </em></p>
<p>In <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller 5 </em>, Professor Jon Todal offers a number of figures concerning students in Sami Administrative Areas for the 2011/12 school year. Below, Todal’s figures are compared with figures for the 2014/15 school year to show developments over the last three years. The figures are for the total number of students who are taking Sami either as a first or second language. We look at the numbers in these areas in particular because it allows us to study what portion of the total student population is learning Sami. Since each and every student in these areas can choose to have instruction in Sami, we know the total number of students who can choose to have Sami. Outside of these areas, the right to instruction in Sami is tied to certain criteria, and we do not know how many fulfil these criteria (Todal 2012: 111-12). </p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.7 Change in the Number of Students for Sami Administrative Areas from the 2011/12 to the 2014/15 School Year </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Number of Students in the Municipality 2011/12 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Number of Students in the Municipality 2014/15 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Change in the </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Number of Students from 2011/12 to 2014/15 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Change in the </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Number of </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Students from 2011/12 to 2014/15 </em></p>
<p>In total 2310 2268 -42 -1,8</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Porsanger 460 412 -48 -10,4</p>
<p xml:lang="olo">Karasjok 366 327 -39 -10,7</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Kautokeino 338 359 21 6,2</p>
<p xml:lang="kmr">Tana 307 276 -31 -10,1</p>
<p xml:lang="sma">Snåsa 250 210 -40 -16,0</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Tysfjord 203 211 8 3,9</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Kåfjord 192 219 27 14,1</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Lavangen 119 118 -1 -0,8</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Nesseby 75 78 3 4,0</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Røyrvik (55) 58 3 5,5</p>
<p>Table 7.7 shows that the number of students in Sami Administrative Areas decreased by 42 students from 2011/12 to 2014/15. This is a decline of 1.8%. On January 1, 2013, however, an additional municipality, Røyrvik in North Trønderlag, was designated as a Sami Administrative Area. The true decline in student numbers is therefore 100 students or 4.3%.</p>
<p>The table shows significant differences in the development of student numbers in the different municipalities. Kåfjord and Kautokeino have had the greatest increase with 27 and 21 students respectively, or 14.1 and 6.2 percent. The most substantial decline of 16 percent has occurred in Snåsa. It is also worthwhile to note the decline in student numbers of 10 percent in Karasjok, Porsanger and Tana. These municipalities have a relatively high number of students who receive instruction of Sami.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.8 Comparison of the Number of Students in Sami Administrative </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Areas with and without instruction of Sami as a First or Second Language </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Students in all </em></p>
<p xml:lang="sms"><em type="bold">Sami </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Administrative </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Areas </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Students without Sami </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fra"><em type="bold">Instruction </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Students with </em></p>
<p xml:lang="sms"><em type="bold">Sami </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fra"><em type="bold">Instruction </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Students with Sami as a First </em></p>
<p xml:lang="isl"><em type="bold">Language </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Students with Sami as a Second </em></p>
<p xml:lang="isl"><em type="bold">Language </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Students 2011/12 2310 1092 1218 783 435</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Students 2014/15 2268 1088 1180 741* 439*</p>
<p>Change 2011/12 to 2014/15 -42 - 4 - 38 - 42 + 4 *The exact numbers are a bit higher because figures from two municipalities are so low that the Norwegian Directorate for Education and Training has not released them.</p>
<p>Table 7.8 shows that 1,218 students in Sami Administrative Areas had instruction of Sami in the 2011/12 school year. They constituted 57% of all the students in Norway who receive Sami instruction. This year, 1180 students in Sami Administrative Areas receive instruction of Sami. This works out to 55.8% of all the students in Norway learning Sami, showing a decrease of 1.2 percentage points.</p>
<p>The number of students in Sami Administrative Areas learning Sami as a first language went down by 42 or 5.4%. The number of students learning Sami as a second language went up by four. This is an increase of 0.9%.</p>
<p>In 2011/12, 53% of students in Sami Administrative Areas <em type="bold"></em>received instruction of Sami at the primary and lower secondary school. This year, 52% of students took Sami, the overwhelming majority of which took Sami as a first language. The trend this year is the same as for 2011/12. Roughly every third student in Sami Administrative Areas is taking Sami as a first language. </p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.9 Students per Municipality for the 2011/12 and 2014/15 school year, Students with Sami Instruction, and changes in the same period </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Students in the </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Municipalities 2011/12 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Students with </em></p>
<p xml:lang="sms"><em type="bold">Sami </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fra"><em type="bold">Instruction 2011/12 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Students in the </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Municipalities 2014/15 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Students with </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Sami Instruction 2014/15 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Change from 2011/12 to 2014/15 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Porsanger 460 123 412 119 -4</p>
<p xml:lang="olo">Karasjok 366 366 327 327 -39</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Kautokeino 338 338 359 359 21</p>
<p xml:lang="kmr">Tana 307 155 276 137 -18</p>
<p xml:lang="sma">Snåsa 250 29 210 11 -18</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Tysfjord 203 49 211 73 24</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Kåfjord 192 73 219 85 12</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Lavangen 119 12 118 .</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Nesseby 75 . 78 .</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Røyrvik 55 58 .</p>
<p>Table 7.9 shows trends for students receiving instruction of Sami in various municipalities in Sami Administrative Areas. The 2011/12 numbers for Røyrvik are not known. Sami is an obligatory subject for all students in Karasjok, Kautokeino and Nesseby so changes in these municipalities naturally correspond to changes in the number of students. Tysfjord and Kåfjord have shown a marked increase in the number of students learning Sami, with 49 and 16.4 percent respectively.</p>
<p>Snåsa has experienced a significant decrease of 18 students or 62%. This is due in part to the fact that several of the students who received instruction through distance learning from Åarjelsaemiej School in Snåsa are now receiving instruction of Sami from a local teacher at their home school. Additionally, distance-learning students are now registered as students at their home school and not as students at Snåsa. In the past, these students were registered at the school that offered distance learning (Nilsson Valkeapää 2015). Tana has had a decrease of 18 students who receive instruction of Sami. This is a decline of 11.6%. Both Snåsa and Tana have experienced a large decrease in the number of students at the primary and lower secondary level but conclusions cannot be drawn between these two situations.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.10 Distribution of Students with Sami Instruction for the 2011/12 and 2014/15 School Years, in Percent </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Students with instruction of Sami as % of all students </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Students with Sami as a first language as % of all students </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Students with Sami as a second language as % of all students </em>2011/2012 2014/15 2011/2012 2014/15 2011/2012 2014/15 </p>
<p>Total 53 52,2 34 32,9 19 19,4</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Porsanger 26 28,9 7 5,1 19 23,8</p>
<p xml:lang="olo">Karasjok 100 100,0 76 76,1 24 23,9</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Kautokeino 100 100,0 93 90,5 7 9,5</p>
<p xml:lang="kmr">Tana 51 49,6 31 31,5 20 18,1</p>
<p xml:lang="sma">Snåsa 12 5,2 . . . .</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Tysfjord 24 34,6 10 10,4 14 24,2</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Kåfjord 39 38,8 5 5,9 34 32,9</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Lavangen 10 . . . . .</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Nesseby . 94,9 23 30,8 . 64,1</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Røyrvik . 0 0 .</p>
<p>Table 7.10 shows that over the last four years, most of the municipalities have experienced only small changes in the number of students learning Sami. Nevertheless, Tysfjord has had a clear increase. In 2011/12, 24% of the students received instruction of Sami. This year, the portion is 34.6%. The increase is due to more students taking Sami as a second language, the portion of which has increased from 14% to 24.2%. In Nesseby, the increase has been from 23% to 30.8%. Snåsa has had a decrease in the number of students learning Sami, from 12% to 5.2%. <em type="bold">7.4 Sami Language at the Upper Secondary Level </em></p>
<p>Sami students at the upper secondary level have the right to learn Sami. When talking about Sami education at this level, it is not possible to refer to the same geographical divisions as for the primary and lower secondary school level. This is because many municipalities do not have upper secondary schools so students attend high school outside the home communities.</p>
<p>Figures for the 2010/11 and 2011/12 school years come from <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller 5 </em>(Todal 2012: 114-16). Figures for the 2012/13 and 2014/15 school years come from the Norwegian Directorate for Education and Training (Udir 2015-1) as well as from the Directorate’s overview over subjects chosen by high school students (Udir 2013-3; 2014; 2015-2). </p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.11 Number of Upper Secondary Students Learning Sami 2010/11 2011/12 2012/13 2013/14 2014/15 </em></p>
<p>Whole country 433 473 416 452 449</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Finnmark 341 384 332 356 357</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Troms 49 54 53 42 48</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Nordland 27 16 18 37 24</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Nord-Trøndelag 9 7 . 8 11</p>
<p>Rest of the country 7 12 13* 9 9 *</p>
<p>The figures for Nord-Trøndelag are included in the figures for the rest of the country.</p>
<p>Table 7.11 shows that the number of students learning Sami varies from year to year but no clear trend emerges. At the same time, we do not see the decrease in the number of students learning Sami that we see at the primary and lower secondary level. On the contrary, the number of students has increased by 16 or 3.7% over the five-year period. The table also shows that the vast majority of high school students learning Sami, 79.5%, attend school in Finnmark.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.12 Distribution of Upper Secondary Students Learning Sami as a </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">First and/or Second Language 2010/2011 2011/12 2012/13 2013/14 2014/15 </em></p>
<p>Total 433 473 416 452 449</p>
<p>First Language 248 267 236 243 205</p>
<p>Second Language 185 206 180 209 244</p>
<p>Table 7.12 shows that there has been a shift from last year to this. The number of students learning Sami as a First Language has gone down by 38 or 15.6%. At the same time, the number of students learning Sami as a Second Language has increased by 35 or 16.7%. There was a tendency before 2014/15 of more high school students taking Sami as a first language than as a second. It is without a doubt encouraging if more students who have had Sami as a Second Language at the primary and lower secondary level decide to continue their studies at the high school level. It is equally positive if students who have not had instruction in Sami before choose to start at high school. On the other hand, this is a negative tendency if students are choosing Sami as a Second Language even if they have had Sami as a First Language earlier in their education (NRK 2015). This is something that should be investigated further. <em type="bold">7.4.1 Sami as a First Language at the Upper Secondary Level </em></p>
<p>The number of high school students taking Sami over the last five years is shown below, by county.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.13 Number of Students Learning Sami as a First Language at the </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Upper Secondary Level 2010/2011 2011/12 2012/13 2013/14 2014/15 </em></p>
<p>Whole Country 248 267 236 243 205</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Finnmark 216 249 212 199 187</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Troms 12 11 18 21 18</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Nordland 18 . . 18 .</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Nord-Trøndelag . . . . .</p>
<p>Rest of the Country . 7 6 . 8</p>
<p>Table 7.13 shows that the number of high school students receiving instruction in Sami as a First Language had been relatively stable the first four year of the last five. The number goes down by 38 students or 15.6% in the last year. This is characterised as a significant decrease. It is worth noting that there were 18 students learning Sami as a First Language in Nordland in 2010/11 and 2013/14, while in the other years the number was five or less.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.14 Number of Upper Secondary Students Learning Sami as a First </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Language, Divided into those Learning North Sami and those Learning Lule or South Sami 2010/2011 2011/12 2012/13 2013/14 2014/15 </em></p>
<p>Whole Country 248 267 236 243 205</p>
<p>North Sami * * 229 226 195</p>
<p>Lule Sami/ South Sami * * 7 17 10 *</p>
<p>Figures for 2010/11 and 2011/12 are not available.</p>
<p>Table 7.14 shows that the vast majority of students learning Sami as a First Language have chosen North Sami. In the 2014/15 school year, 195 students or 95% of high school students were taking North Sami as a First Language. The number of students learning Lule or South Sami varies from seven to 17 or 3-7% over the last three years. Separate figures for the number of students taking North and Lule or South Sami are not available for the 2010/11 and 2011/12 school years. <em type="bold">7.4.2 Sami as a Second Language at the Upper Secondary Level </em></p>
<p>Instruction of Sami as a Second Language at the high school level is shown here by county, for the last five years.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.15 Number of Students taking Sami as a Second Language in each </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">County 2010/2011 2011/12 2012/13 2013/14 2014/15 </em></p>
<p>Whole country 185 206 180 209 244</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Finnmark 125 135 120 157 178</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Troms 37 43 35 24 36</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Nordland 9 16 . 16 .</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Nord-Trøndelag 9 7 . . .</p>
<p>Rest of the Country 5 5 25 12 30</p>
<p>When the number of students in a county is not shown, it is combined with the number of students in the counties further south. The figures for the rest of the country, therefore, include the students from Nordland and Trøndelag not shown separately.</p>
<p>Table 7.15 shows a clear increase in the number of students taking Sami as a Second Language at the high school level. Last year, the increase was by 35 students or 16.7%. The increase in Finnmark was by 23 students or 14.6%.</p>
<p>Despite this increase, the numbers indicate that a good number of students who have taken Sami as a Second Language at the primary and lower secondary level have not continued to do so at the high school level. Most students attend three years of high school after finishing their lower secondary education. On average, there are 120 students per grade level learning Sami as a Second Language at the lower secondary level. At the high school level, however, there are on average only 81.3 students per grade level. This is a significant difference.</p>
<p>Moreover, roughly a third of students learning Sami as a Second Language at the high school level take Sami as a Second Language 4, which is a class for beginner students who do not know any Sami from before. This means that there is a high dropout rate in the subject between lower and upper secondary school. This situation should be studied further.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.16 Number of Students with Sami as a Second Language, shown by language 2010/2011 2011/12 2012/13 2013/14 2014/15 </em></p>
<p>Whole Country 185 206 180 209 244</p>
<p>North Sami * * 155 184 217</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Lule Sami * * 9 10 12</p>
<p>South Sami * * 16 15 15 *</p>
<p>Figures for 2010/11 and 2011/12 are not available.</p>
<p>Table 7.16 shows that the large majority of students learning Sami as a Second Language have chosen North Sami. There were 244 students or 89% taking the class in the 2014/15 school year. The number of students learning Lule Sami as a Second Language is 12 or 5%, while the number for South Sami as a Second Language is 15 or 6%.</p>
<p>The increasing number of students applies especially for North Sami, which went from 155 to 217 students, a rise of 40%. Lule Sami has also experienced a slight increase while the numbers for South Sami have been quite stable. Separate figures for each of the languages are not available for the 2010/11 and 2011/12 school year.</p>
<p>The increase over the last year in the number of students learning Sami as a Second Language is possibly attributable to the introduction of the new class <em type="italic">Sami as a Second Language 4 </em>. This class is for students with no prior experience with Sami. As no students chose the class in 2013/14, this course was first taught in the fall of 2014. This year, 100 students are taking Sami as a Second Language 2, while 74 are taking Sami as a Second Language 3 and an additional 74, Sami as a Second Language 4. In the previous school year, there were about the same number of students taking Sami as a Second Language 2 as there was taking Sami as a Second Language 3 (Udir 2014: 27; 2015-1: 27; 2015-2: 27). <em type="bold">7.4.3 Sami as the Language of Instruction </em></p>
<p>As mentioned in section 7.2.2, § 6-3 of the Education Act allows the ministry to instruct individual schools to offer Sami as the language of instruction at the upper secondary level. Counties, under their own initiative, can also offer Sami as the language of instruction in their schools. Despite this option, no county schools currently use Sami as the language of instruction. While two national Sami upper secondary schools offer part of the study programs in Sami, it has not been possible to get an overview of exactly how much of the schooling is carried out in the language. In its annual report to the Norwegian Directorate for Education and Training, the Sami Upper Secondary School in Karasjok writes that, at a minimum, the school wants to offer identity-forming core subjects in Sami. Teaching in Sami means that all instruction and guidance of students is carried out in Sami and that students can write exercises and tests in Sami. In the 2013/14 and 2014/15 school years, Sami was used 50 class hours (of 45 minutes) per week. The rest of the class hours were conducted in Norwegian or Norwegian/Sami. All instruction in media and communication, which requires Sami as a First Language, is carried out in Sami. In the General Studies Program, Sami was used to teach Social Studies, Natural Sciences and History in 2013/14 and Natural Sciences, History and Religion in 2014/15 (Sami videregående skole i Karasjok 2014). <em type="bold">7.5 Situation of Instructional Material </em></p>
<p>This chapter looks at the situation of instructional material for the teaching of North, Lule and South Sami as well as for that of Sami as a Second Language. Teaching aids are important tools in ensuring that students develop basic skills and attain the competence goals relevant to their study program. In 2010 and 2014, The Sami Parliament compiled information about the state of instructional material and teaching aids for Sami. This information is used here to describe the situation and developments over the last few years (Sametinget et al. 2010: 19-24; Sametinget 2015). The Sami Parliament’s overview is divided by language and explains the situation for each subject and grade level using the following categories: 1. Needs as outlined in the curriculum for <em type="italic">Kunnskapsløftet samisk </em>(Knowledge Promotion </p>
<p>Reform Sami) are covered - textbooks and digital resources are available, the majority of competence objectives are covered 2. Part of the required qualifications as outlined in the <em type="italic">Kunnskapsløftet samisk </em>are covered – textbooks/booklets/digital resources are available 3. Textbooks are available covering almost all of the previous curriculum 4. Very little coverage of competence aims or no teaching aids at all <em type="bold">7.5.1 Instruction in North Sami </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.17 The State of Teaching Aids for North Sami at the Primary and </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Lower Secondary Level in 2010 and 2014 – Coverage by Subject and Grade </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Covered </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Partly </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Covered </em></p>
<p xml:lang="smn"><em type="bold">Almost </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Covered (old curriculum) </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Very </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">Little/Almost </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">No coverage </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Total: </em></p>
<p>Primary 2010 13 26 31 21 91</p>
<p>Primary 2014 36 22 7 26 91</p>
<p>Lower Secondary 2010 3 13 11 15 42</p>
<p>Lower Secondary 2014 21 3 9 9 42</p>
<p>Table 7.17 shows a significant shortage of teaching material in 2010. Of 91 investigated subjects/grades at the primary level, there was very little or no material for 21 subjects/grades. Thirty-one subjects/grades were covered according to the requirements of the previous curriculum. Thirteen subjects/grades were covered and 26 were partially covered. There has been a positive development from 2010 to 2014 at both the primary and lower secondary level. However, teaching aids are still needed for 26 subjects/grades at the primary school level and for 15 of 42 subjects/grades at the lower secondary level. In 2014, subjects that needed teaching aids at the primary level were English for grades 5-7, Norwegian for Sami 1, Geography 1-4, History 1-4, Gym 1-7 and Math and Health 5-7. Subjects still requiring teaching aids at the lower secondary level are Norwegian for Sami 1, English and Gym. <em type="bold">7.5.2 Instruction in Lule Sami </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.18 The State of Teaching Aids for Lule Sami at the Primary and </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Lower Secondary Level in 2010 and 2014 – Coverage by Subject and Grade </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Covered </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Partly </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Covered </em></p>
<p xml:lang="smn"><em type="bold">Almost </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Covered (old curriculum) </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Very </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">Little/Almost </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">No coverage </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Total: </em></p>
<p>Primary 2010 4 41 3 43 91</p>
<p>Primary 2014 21 9 6 55 91</p>
<p>Lower Secondary 2010 0 3 5 34 42</p>
<p>Lower Secondary 2014 3 3 0 36 42</p>
<p>Table 7.18 shows a significant shortage of teaching material for Lule Sami in both 2010 and 2014. Of the 91 subjects/grades investigated at the primary level in 2010, very little or no material existed for 43 of them. In the same period, three subjects/grades were almost covered by material for the previous curriculum, four subjects/grades were covered and 41 were partly covered. At the primary level, we see a positive development from 2010 to 2014, where 21 subjects/grades are covered while 9 are partly covered. But now, 55 subjects/grades have very little to no teaching material. At the lower secondary level, there were no teaching aids for 36 of 42 subjects/grades in 2014. <em type="bold">7.5.3 Instruction in South Sami </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.19 The State of Teaching Aids for South Sami at the Primary and </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Lower Secondary Level in 2010 and 2014 – Coverage by Subject and Grade </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Covered </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Partly </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Covered </em></p>
<p xml:lang="smn"><em type="bold">Almost </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Covered (old curriculum) </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Very </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">Little/Almost </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">No coverage </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Total: </em></p>
<p>Primary 2010 4 23 3 61 91</p>
<p>Primary 2014 24 4 0 63 91</p>
<p>Lower Secondary 2010 0 0 0 42 42</p>
<p>Lower Secondary 2014 0 3 0 39 42</p>
<p>Table 7.19 shows a significant shortage of teaching aids for South Sami in both 2010 and 2014. Of the 91 subjects/grades investigated at the primary level in 2010, there was very little or no material for 61 of them. Four grades/subjects were covered and 23 partially so. There were no teaching aids at the lower secondary level. There has been a positive development at the primary level from 2010 to 2014. Twenty-four subjects/grades are covered and four are partially covered. Teaching materials are still needed for 63 subjects/grades. At the lower secondary level, 39 of 42 subjects/grades need teaching aids. <em type="bold">7.5.4 Instruction of Sami as a Second Language </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.20 Teaching Aids for Sami as a Second Language at the Primary and Lower Secondary Level in 2010 and 2014 – Number of Grade Levels Covered </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Covered </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Partly </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Covered </em></p>
<p xml:lang="smn"><em type="bold">Almost </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Covered (old curriculum) </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Very </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">Little/Almost </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">No coverage </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Total: </em></p>
<p>North Sami 2010 0 0 8 2 10</p>
<p>North Sami 2014 7 3 0 0 10</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Lule Sami 2010 0 6 0 4 10</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Lule Sami 2014 10 0 0 0 10</p>
<p>South Sami 2010 2 0 8 0 10</p>
<p>South Sami 2014 10 0 0 0 10</p>
<p>Table 7.20 shows that after the 2010 curriculum reform, there was a significant shortage of teaching material for North, Lule and South Sami as a Second Language. In eight grade levels, North and South Sami was taught with material developed for an older curriculum. Additionally, there was very little to no teaching aids available for two grade levels. Six grade levels of Lule Sami as a Second Language 2 were are partially covered. Four grade levels had very little or no teaching material available.</p>
<p>In 2014, the situation was very much improved. Teaching material is available for all 10 grades of Lule and South Sami as a Second Language 2. For North Sami, grades 1-7 are covered. In grades 8-10, newly developed or newly reprinted or revised editions of textbooks <em type="bold">, </em>booklets and digital material cover parts of the competence aims. In addition, there are textbooks which cover almost all of the requirements of the earlier curriculums. </p>
<p>The Sami Parliament’s matrix shows that teaching material for Sami as a Second Language 3 is almost covered at the primary and secondary school level. The exceptions are Lule Sami as a Second Language 3, grade 10 and South Sami as a Second Language 3, grades 8-10. Competence aims in these subjects are partially covered by newly developed material or newly reprinted or revised editions of textbooks, booklets or digital material. <em type="bold">7.5.5 The Sami Parliament’s View </em>This overview shows that there is a significant gap between the Sami Parliament’s fundamental view on Sami language teaching aids and reality. The Sami Parliament’s position (2014-1: 5) is that Sami students have the same rights to teaching aids in their native language as other students in the Norwegian school system. This right is not being fulfilled, as there is a shortage of Sami language material in many subjects. </p>
<p>In its analysis of the Education Act in June 2014, the Sami Parliament pointed out that Sami students’ right to teaching material in their language of instruction is not ensured by law in accordance with the pertinent regulations. The Education Act protects by law the right to have teaching material in both of the written forms of Norwegian. Moreover, the regulations of the law further clarify and strengthen this right. For this reason, the Sami Parliament has requested a revision of both the Education and Private Education Acts to strengthen Sami students’ rights to instruction in and of Sami on the basis of cultural values, including special rights to Sami teaching aids for all subjects throughout primary and lower secondary school (Sametinget 2014-1: 5; 2014-2: 120.) <em type="bold">7.6 Inspection of Sami Education </em></p>
<p>Sami students’ educational rights have been a prioritized area of inspection at all school levels since 2009. The Ministry of Education and Research assigned the Norwegian Directorate for Education and Training the task of: ‘inspecting, with follow-up carried out by the counties and municipalities, Sami students’ rights in accordance with the Education Act, also including access to teaching aid’ (Kunnskapsdepartementet 2009: 31).</p>
<p>In practice, the Offices of the County Governor are responsible for conducting inspections of Sami education in their respective counties.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7.21 County Governor’s Inspection of Sami Education from 2012 to 2015 2012 2013 2014 2015 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Oslo and Akershus 5 0 0 0</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sør-Trøndelag 0 0 0 1</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Nordland 0 4 0 0</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Finnmark 0 2 1 1</p>
<p>Total 5 6 1 2</p>
<p>Table 7.21 shows that the County Governor’s Office conducted 14 inspections of Sami education from 2012 to June, 2015. These inspections were held in Oslo and Akershus, Sør-Trøndelag, Nordland and Finnmark. Thirteen inspections were of primary and lower secondary schools and one was of an upper secondary school.</p>
<p>Information was requested from day cares and educational institutions in Oslo and Akershus, as well as in the five northernmost counties. Inspection reports for the northern counties are public and accessible on the County Governor’s website. Inspection reports from Oslo and Akershus were sent from the Office of the County Governor in Oslo/Akershus. The County Governor in Sør-Trøndelag conducted an inspection of Sami education in the municipality of Namdalseid. The report, dated June 9, 2015, was not yet public at the time of writing. <em type="bold">7.6.1 Content of the Inspections </em></p>
<p>The primary goal of the inspections is to ensure that Sami students receive the education they have a right to under the Education Act. Sami students should have the opportunity to attain proficiency in Sami. The inspections verify that local governments act in accordance to the law and perhaps contribute so that the situation in the community conforms to the requirements of the legislation. The requirements that are checked during the inspection are chosen based on which provisions are most central for Sami students to receive instruction of and in Sami. Choice of provisions to be checked in the inspection were based on experience gained in the pilot inspection conducted in Nordland in the autumn of 2009 (Fylkesmannen i Oslo og Akershus 2012-3: 3).</p>
<p>Inspection reports contain a chapter explaining what is being investigated. Below is a summary of the main points from an inspection of the municipality of Rana in Nordland. This gives an idea of what was examined in all the municipalities (Fylkesmannen i Nordland 2014-1). In addition, the inspection report from Kautokeino is used (Fylkesmannen i Finnmark 2015) to show what has been examined in a Sami Administrative Area. Four particular areas have been examined in the inspections. <em type="bold">1. Tenable System – Education Act §13-10 paragraph 2 </em></p>
<p>According to the Education Act §13-10 paragraph two, a municipality has the primary responsibility to ensure that the administration at each and every school complies with the demands and obligations of the law as well as offers the services and activities prescribed by it. To comply with the demands of a tenable <em type="bold"></em>system, the school owner must be able to document that routines are in place to:  ensure that all in the organization with tasks connected to Sami students’ rights have adequate knowledge about the content and demands in the relevant provisions of the law  ensure that the municipality receives adequate information about what is happening in the field of Sami education  assess the provided information in relation to the demands of the law  to put in place necessary measures if it is discovered that what is being done does not conform to the law <em type="bold">2. Sami Education at Primary and Lower Secondary School – Education Act §6-2 </em></p>
<p>Inspections were conducted in four municipalities in the county of Nordland. These municipalities are not Sami Administrative Areas and so are not considered as Sami districts pursuant to the Education Act. This means that the County Governor’s assessments were limited to the statutory provisions of the Education Act §6-2 which concerns rights outside of Sami districts. At the primary and lower secondary level, these students have the right to instruction of Sami. This means that these municipalities have to provide Sami language classes regardless of group size.</p>
<p>The school owner must have a system that ensures that instruction of Sami conforms to the Sami Curriculum for Knowledge Promotion in Primary and Secondary Education and Training (LK06– S), cf. Education Act §6-4 and regulations of the Education Act §§1-1 and 1-11. Sami education must follow the allotted subjects and class hours at all times, cf. Education Act §2-2. Subjects and class hours are obligatory parts of the curriculum and cannot be deviated from, cf. Education Act §§ 2-1 and 2-3.</p>
<p>The County Governor in Finnmark has held two inspections of Sami education in municipalities that lie within Sami Administrative Areas and therefore considered as Sami districts, Kautokeino and Porsanger (Fylkesmannen i Finnmark 2014; 2015). In these municipalities, according to the Education Act §6-2, students at the primary and lower secondary level have the right to instruction of and in Sami. Moreover, the municipality of Kautokeino has decided to exercise its authority to include instruction of Sami as an obligatory part of the curriculum at this level. <em type="bold">3. Necessary Equipment, Inventory and Teaching Aids – Education Act §9-3 </em></p>
<p>According to the Education Act §9-3, the school owner must ensure that schools have access to necessary equipment, inventory and teaching aids. Further, it states that teaching aids shall be suitable for use in instruction. In connection to Sami education, this entails, among other things, the obligation to have teaching aids in line with the relevant curriculums and equipment that enables instruction or distance education. <em type="bold">4. Alternative Models of Sami Education – Education Act Regulations §7-1 </em></p>
<p>In the case of a school not having suitable teaching personnel, a student with the right to education in Sami is required to receive this education in an alternative form. These alternatives could include distance education, intensive courses and language camps. If distance education is used, the school owner is responsible to ensure that instruction conforms to the regulations. Each student’s rights are to be protected and routines to assist with distance learning, such as proving proper technical support, must be in place. <em type="bold">7.6.2 Inspections in Oslo and Akershus </em></p>
<p>The County Governor in Oslo and Akershus conducted five inspections of Sami education in 2012. Inspections were carried out in the municipalities of Oppegård, Oslo, Rælingen, Skedsmo and Ås (Fylkesmannen i Oslo og Akershus 2012-1; 2012-2; 2012-3; 2012-4; 2012-5). All five inspections resulted in an order of rectification. The inspection reports are summarized in a memorandum from the Norwegian Directorate for Education and Training to the Ministry of Education and Research (Udir 2013-4: 19-20). Most infractions concerned the requirement to develop written protocols to ensure that:  the municipality receives adequate information about what is happening in the field of</p>
<p>Sami education <em type="bold"></em> protocols are in place to ensure that information is assessed in accordance to the requirements of the law  necessary measures are in place if it is discovered that what is being done does not conform to the law <em type="bold"></em> authority delegated to the principal is included in the delegation manual  the municipality’s system to ensure that students with the right to instruction of Sami receive the required classroom hours, that the municipality ensures that students/parents or guardians are able to choose between Sami as a first or second language  the municipality must ensure that schools using Skype/internet for distance education have stable technical solutions. </p>
<p>Several violations regarding the performance of audits were also uncovered. These concerned:  the requirement to have protocols to ensure that all who have tasks connected to Sami students’ rights have adequate knowledge about the content and demands in the relevant provisions of the law (dissemination of information to relevant personnel) <em type="bold"></em> the requirement to document parents’ consent for exemption from other subjects for students at primary school  the requirement of the municipality to ensure that students who have the right to instruction of and in Sami can choose between North, South and Lule Sami. </p>
<p>Since only one County Governor conducted an inspection in 2012, the Norwegian Directorate for Education and Training draws no general conclusions about Sami education from the inspections in Oslo and Akershus. In conclusion, the Directorate writes that: ‘from the instructions given, it has emerged that school owners should, to a greater degree, ensure that adequate equipment and teaching material is available to students who have the right to Sami education’ (Udir 2013: 25). <em type="bold">7.6.3 Inspections in Nordland </em></p>
<p>Four inspections of Sami education have been conducted in the county of Nordland. All started in 2013 and ended in 2014. Inspections were carried out in Rana, Narvik, Evenes and Saltdal (Fylkesmannen i Nordland 2014-1; 2014-2; 2014-3; 2014-4).</p>
<p><em type="italic">Results of the Inspections in Nordland </em></p>
<p>The County Governor in Nordland uncovered infractions in all of the four municipalities involved in the inspections. The fewest infractions occurred in Evenes, which had not ensured Sami students’ right to the obligatory subjects and class hours as well as minimum yearly school hours.</p>
<p>The other municipalities did not have an adequate system to uncover, assess and follow up on whether the requirements of the Education Act were being met. Additionally, the municipality of Narvik did not ensure Sami students’ rights concerning obligatory subjects and class hours as well as minimum yearly school hours <em type="bold">. </em>Finally, there was no written agreement with the organization providing distance education clarifying who was responsible to cover the curriculum, assessment, teacher competence, organization of study and reporting to the school owner. </p>
<p>The municipality of Saltdal did not comply with the Education Act §6-2 with regard to the right to choose between North, Lule or South Sami and the right to instruction of Sami was not honoured to the extent prescribe by law.</p>
<p>The municipalities were given a deadline to rectify a number of shortcomings and deficiencies. The requirement was to establish and implement a tenable, written system suitable to assess whether requirements of the Education Act were being fulfilled, and in this regard, make sure that:  the requirement to have protocols to ensure that all who have tasks connected to Sami students’ rights have adequate knowledge about the content and demands in the relevant provisions of the law (dissemination of information to relevant personnel) <em type="bold"></em> the municipality receives adequate information about what is happening in the field of </p>
<p>Sami education  protocols are in place to make sure the exchange of information is assessed according to the requirements of the law  necessary protocols are in place if it is discovered that what is being done does not conform to the law.</p>
<p>The municipalities must also ensure that the right to Sami education at the primary and lower secondary level is honoured, and in this regard, make sure to establish protocols:  to ensure that yearly directives about subject and class hour distribution are disseminated and followed  to ensure that Sami students receive the required number of class hours as well as draw up and implement routines to verify that this is being done  to ensure that the content of the courses conforms to the curriculum at all times  to ensure guardians’ and/or students’ right to choose between North, Lule or South Sami</p>
<p>In addition, the municipalities must ensure that the right to alternative education in Sami is protected, and in this regard, see to it that routines are established to ensure parental input when alternative education is going to be used. <em type="bold">7.6.4 Inspections in Finnmark </em></p>
<p>Five inspections of Sami education have been conducted in the county of Finnmark: primary and lower secondary schools in Alta, Alta Upper Secondary School, Lakselv School in the municipality of Porsanger and Kautokeino Primary and Lower Secondary Schools (Fylkesmannen i Finnmark 2013-1; 2013-2; 2014; 2015). The inspections in Finnmark follow the same template as those further south but stand out in that no breaches of the law were found.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Lower Secondary Schools in the Municipality of Alta </em></p>
<p>The County Governor’s evaluation of the lower secondary schools in Alta was completely positive. The report concludes by saying that ‘the municipality of Alta has a tenable system to assess and follow up on whether the Education Act’s requirements for Sami education are being attended to’. No infractions were uncovered and no instructions were given.</p>
<p>The County Governor concludes that the municipality of Alta’s system of quality assessment consists of good routines with regard to structure and process. Structural quality is characterised by motivated and qualified teachers with competence in Sami. The municipality has local instruction at the schools. This applies to lower secondary students in Alta who would like to learn Sami. The municipality further states that they have received requests for alternative education and that they have offered multimedia distance learning. The County Governor observes that the municipality has a system to accommodate alternative education models and that they have different solutions to make sure individual students receive alternative education.</p>
<p>Other aspects that have led to the positive assessment are that the municipality has information protocols to inform guardians/students about the right to Sami education. The municipality distributes a letter to parents and guardians at the beginning of each school year. In addition, the Alta municipal council has decided to offer education of and in Sami to students at Komsa School. A third example is the establishment of a municipality-wide Sami teachers’ network. Teachers meet during the regular workday and have marked off time to conduct regular monthly meetings. The network has developed a plan for the schools to use in Sami education. According to the County Governor’s inspection report, the school owner has allocated time and resources to impressive and important work.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="italic">Lakselv School – The Municipality of Porsanger </em></p>
<p>The County Governor has conducted an inspection of Sami education at Lakselv School in the municipality of Porsanger. The municipality lies in a Sami Administrative Area and is considered to be a Sami district in accordance with the Education Act. Lower secondary schools in the municipality are therefore bound to offer education of and in Sami (Education Act §6-2).</p>
<p>The assessments in the inspection report are based on the minimum requirements for municipalities with students in a Sami district. 1. The Sami curriculum must be followed. 2. Subject and class hours distribution <em type="bold"></em>are binding. 3. The school offers Sami as a first or second language. </p>
<p>The assessments in the inspection report are all positive <em type="bold">. ‘ </em>Documentation shows that education is offered of and/or in Sami at all grade levels and the school has protocols for transition between primary and lower secondary school that ensure students’ right to language choice and alternative.” The County Governor means that Lakselv school offers Sami as a first or second language to students at school. In its documentation, the school has shown examples of halfyear plans and year plans where competence aims from the Sami curriculum guide and form the basis for the content of the course. Submitted documentation shows that the school uses approved textbooks and/or other teaching aids pursuant to LK06-S. Students receive an education of and/or in Sami in accordance with the Sami curriculum and are assessed against competence aims in the various subjects. Students are divided into separate Sami classes at the primary and lower secondary levels and follow the applicable subject and class hour distribution. </p>
<p>Documentation shows that teachers at Lakselv School have the required relevant and approved competence. The Country Governor contends that the municipality of Porsanger ensures that the requirements of the law are met. The school has approved teaching material and aids and fulfils §9-3 of the Education Act regarding ‘equipment’ which states: ‘Schools shall have access to necessary equipment, inventory and teaching aids’.</p>
<p>The County Governor refers to § 13-10 of the Education Act about systems. The municipality of Porsanger shall have a system to assess whether the requirements and regulations of the law are being fulfilled. The system shall uncover, assess and implement necessary measures. System requirements involve the obligation of routines for communication and cooperation between the school owner and schools in the organization. Routines refer to what is to be done, who should do it, how it should be done and when. In light of documentation from the municipality, the County Governor is of the opinion that the municipality of Porsanger has a tenable system, robust enough to uncover breaches of the law.</p>
<p>The County Governor concludes that the municipality of Porsanger and Lakselv School have demonstrated that they arrange for students to receive Sami education and that no violations of the law have been uncovered.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno"><em type="italic">Kautokeino Primary School and Kautokeino Lower Secondary School </em></p>
<p>The County Governor conducted and inspection of Sami education at Kautokeino Primary School and Kautokeino Lower Secondary School in the municipality of Kautokeino in 2015. The municipality lies in a Sami Administrative Area and is considered to be a Sami district pursuant to the Education Act. Primary and lower secondary schools in the municipality are therefore required to offer education both of and in Sami (Education Act §6-2). Assessments in the inspection report are uniformly positive. Documentation shows that instruction is offered both of and in Sami, as well as both of and in Norwegian at all grade levels in primary and lower secondary school. The schools have routines in place regarding the transition from primary to lower secondary school to ensure that students’ rights to language choice and alternatives are fulfilled. In their documentation, the schools have shown half-year and full-year plans where competence aims from the Sami curriculum guide and form the basis for the content of the courses. This is the situation for Sami as a First and Second Language. Both schools have submitted documentation for local curriculums for Sami as a First Language.</p>
<p>Submitted documentation shows that the schools use approved textbooks and/or other teaching aids pursuant to LK06-S. Students receive an education of and/or in Sami in accordance with the Sami curriculum and are assessed against competence aims in the various subjects. Therefore, the County Governor concludes that students follow the Sami curriculum at schools in the municipality of Kautokeino, and that there is sufficient documentation that shows the schools are following the applicable subject and class hour distribution.</p>
<p>Documentation shows that teachers at Kautokeino Primary School and Kautokeino Lower Secondary School have the required competence and, in light of this, the Country Governor considers the municipality of Kautokeino as ensuring that the requirements of the law are met. The school has access to approved teaching material and aids.</p>
<p>The County Governor also assesses the fulfilment of Education Act §13-10. This section requires systems to be in place regarding routines for communication and cooperation between the school owner and the schools within the organization. Routines refer to what is to be done, who should do it, how it should be done and when. Based on the documentation submitted by the municipality, the County Governor is of the opinion that the municipality of Kautokeino has a tenable system robust enough to uncover breaches of the law.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="italic">Alta Upper Secondary School </em></p>
<p>In the period 2012 to June 2015, there has been one inspection of Sami education at the upper secondary level in Norway. This was conducted at Alta Upper Secondary School, which is owned by the county of Finnmark. The inspection was conducted via a check on documentation and interviews with key figures and students.</p>
<p>The legal basis for the inspection is distinguished from the other inspections because it focused on §6-3 of the Education Act which states that Sami students at the upper secondary level have the right to instruction of Sami. The Ministry can instruct the provision of alternative forms for this education when instruction cannot be offered by the teaching staff at the school.</p>
<p>The County Governor concluded that Alta Upper Secondary School fulfils this section of the act and has good routines to implement instruction of Sami. <em type="bold">7.7 Challenges and Recommendations </em></p>
<p>This article has shown that there are a number of challenges confronting Sami education at the primary, lower secondary and upper secondary level. The number of students learning Sami as a First Language is decreasing at all levels of both primary and secondary education. This decrease has been occurring for such an extended period at the primary and lower secondary level that it can be called a trend. It is too early to draw any conclusions about the upper secondary level.</p>
<p>Students taking Sami as a First Language at the primary and lower secondary level usually have Sami as the language of instruction in other subjects as well. The number of students taking Sami as a First Language without having Sami as the language of instruction in other subjects has however increased. At this time, it is not possible to explain the increase; further study is necessary.</p>
<p>The number of students learning Sami as a Second Language appears to have stabilised at a lower level than before. Increasing this student number should be a goal to help strengthen the revitalisation of Sami languages.</p>
<p>At the upper secondary level, the number of students learning Sami as a Second Language has increased. This is a positive development. Further study should be conducted to find out whether students who have had Sami as a Second Language at the primary and lower secondary level are choosing to cease their studies of the subject. This appears to be the situation and possible reasons for this should be studied further.</p>
<p>The situation for Sami education may be related to two other circumstances matters mentioned in this chapter: the situation of teaching aids for instruction of and in Sami and the County Governor’s inspection of Sami education. Even though the situation for teaching aids at the primary and lower secondary level has improved over the last four years, there is still a great shortage in some cases. Inspections in Oslo and Akershus and in Nordland showed breaches of the law and that Sami students’ rights to an education in Sami was not being honoured. Inspections in Finnmark showed that the three inspected municipalities and the one upper secondary school performed their responsibilities in a satisfactory manner. An interesting finding was that no inspections were conducted in other counties over the last four years.</p>
</body></document>
