<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The Sami Parliament´s mineral guide</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2010</year><wordcount>5462</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://samediggi.no/content/download/559/4960/version/1/file/The+Sami+Parliament%E2%80%99s+mineral+guide+%282010%29.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="sametingets_mineralveileder_2010_.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="sa_medikki_minera_lapla_naveahkki_2010_.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>The Sami Parliament’s mineral guide for exploration work and operations relating to mineral resources</p>
<p>THE SAMI PARLIAMENT’S MINERAL GUIDE 3</p>
<p>In June 2010, the Sami Parliament agreed on a mineralguide for how the Sami Parliament and mineralscompanies can relate to each other in connection withmineral operations in Sami areas. This mineral guideaims for agreements to be entered into between the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament and companies regarding exploration workand plans to apply for operating licences.</p>
<p>The Sami Parliament’s goal is for business operationsrelating to mineral resources in traditional Sami areas tobenefit and directly strengthen and develop Sami cultureand local communities. Such operations must also takeplace in co-existence with, and not displace, traditional</p>
<p>Sami industries and traditional Sami culture-based harvesting. The Minerals Act, which the Norwegianparliament (Storting) passed on 10 June 2009, does notsafeguard these considerations and did not safeguardthe obligations that the State has to the Sami as anindigenous people in accordance with human rights.</p>
<p>Therefore the Sami Parliament could not give its consentto the Act. In order for the Sami Parliament to nonethelesshave an opportunity to give its approval to mineral ope-rations in Sami areas, the Sami Parliament has issued itsown guide, which will form the basis for compliance withthe Sami rights pursuant to international law concerningindigenous peoples and minorities.</p>
<p>With the mineral guide, the Sami Parliament is makingconditions suitable for an overall consideration of allaffected Sami interests in the case of mineral operations.</p>
<p>This applies to the need which traditional Sami industriesand users of uncultivated land have to secure their landbasis and Sami society’s need for jobs and value creationbased on a new utilisation of the resources.</p>
<p>In that the Minerals Act does not establish thepredictability in relation to Sami rights and interests thata capital-intensive mineral industry requires, the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament’s mineral guide will be an importantcontribution to achieve this. The mineral guide clarifiesthe Sami Parliament’s role in exploration, extraction andoperations relating to minerals throughout the traditional</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sami area.</p>
<p>Yours faithfully</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Egil Olli</p>
<p><em type="bold">President of the Sami Parliament </em></p>
<p>The Sami Parliament’s mineral guide for exploration work and operations relating to mineral resources4</p>
<p>THE SAMI PARLIAMENT’S MINERAL GUIDE</p>
<p>Mineral guide for exploration work and operations relating to mineral resources1</p>
<p>Objective1.1 This guide is intended to make conditions suitable for Sami culture, business and sociallife to be emphasised and safeguarded in plans relating to the use of mineral resources. 1.2 The guide states the Sami Parliament’s expectations regarding companies and formsof cooperation with companies that want to establish agreement with the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament on actual exploration work, pilot extraction and plans to apply for an ope-rating licence for mineral resources. 1.3 The guide is intended to ensure compliance with the rights which the Sami have inaccordance with international law regarding indigenous peoples and minorities.2 Scope2.1 The guide is to be used in the case of actual exploration work, pilot extractions andplans to apply for an operating licence for metals. 2.2 The guide is to be used for industrial minerals, building raw materials and natural stonein traditional Sami areas where Sami land rights are not recognised and where Statskog</p>
<p>SF currently administers the ground. 2.3 The guide applies to the traditional Sami areas which are covered by Finnmark, Troms,</p>
<p>Nordland and Nord-Trøndelag as well as the municipalities of Osen, Roan, Åfjord,</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Bjugn, Rissa, Selbu, Meldal, Rennebu, Oppdal, Midtre Gauldal, Tydal, Holtålen and</p>
<p>Røros in the county of Sør-Trøndelag, Engerdal and Rendalen, Os, Tolga, Tynset and</p>
<p>Folldal municipalities in the county of Hedmark and Surnadal, Rindal and Sunndalmunicipalities in the county of Møre and Romsdal.3 Information on and assessments of Sami interests3.1 A party that is granted an exploration permit pursuant to section 13 of the Norwegian</p>
<p>Minerals Act shall prepare a report containing information on and assessments of the</p>
<p>Sami interests that may be directly affected by actual exploration work and any pilotextraction pursuant to sections 19 and 20 of the Minerals Act.</p>
<p>THE SAMI PARLIAMENT’S MINERAL GUIDE 53.2 A party that is granted an extraction permit pursuant to sections 29 and 30 of the</p>
<p>Minerals Act shall prepare an impact analysis in accordance with chapters 4 and 14 ofthe Norwegian Planning and Building Act and the Sami Parliament’s planning guidebefore submitting an application for an operating licence in accordance with section43 of the Minerals Act. 3.3 When Statskog SF is considering entering into agreements regarding exploration forindustrial minerals, building raw materials and natural stone, it should ensure that areport is prepared containing information on and assessments of the Sami intereststhat may be affected by exploration work, and if relevant by pilot extraction and ope-rations. 3.4 The report and impact analysis that have been prepared are to form the basis fornegotiations on the actual exploration work and operations respectively, cf item 4 ofthis guide. 4 Negotiations4.1 Parties wishing to carry out actual exploration work and pilot extraction and partieswishing to apply for an operating licence pursuant to sections 13, 20 and 43 of the</p>
<p>Minerals Act are to contact the Sami Parliament to agree on the holding of negotiationsregarding this. 4.2 Separate negotiations are to be held for actual exploration work, for plans to apply foran extraction permit and for plans to apply for an operating licence. In the case ofplans to apply for an extraction permit, a common document shall be prepared statingthat negotiations are to be held prior to any application for an operating licence. 4.3 Separate consultations are to be held with Statskog SF if Statskog SF is consideringentering into agreements with a company regarding exploration for, the pilot extractionof or operations relating to industrial minerals, building raw materials or natural stone. 4.4 The Sami Parliament may clarify participation in such negotiations with directly affected</p>
<p>Sami interests. Following prior informed consent, the Sami Parliament may safeguarddirectly affected Sami interests in these negotiations. 4.5 A party that wishes to carry out work in accordance with item 4.1 of the guide may beasked to cover the actual costs of holding the negotiations. 5 Agreements, record and contents5.1 An agreement regarding actual exploration work and agreement regarding pilotextraction may cover the scope, exploration period, activity dates, access, storage ofequipment, etc, and measures to prevent harm or inconvenience to existing andtraditional usage. 5.2 An agreement to apply for an operating licence may cover the extraction area, anextraction plan, plan of operations and the termination of the agreement if operationsdo not start within a certain period or are suspended for a lengthy period. The agree-ment may include measures to prevent harm or inconvenience to existing andtraditional usage. 5.3 A record of the consultations with Statskog SF shall be prepared, stating whether theparties have reached agreement and if so what they have agreed shall be included inthe option and operations agreements with the company. 5.4 Conditions regarding compensation to benefit Sami culture, business and social life in6</p>
<p>THE SAMI PARLIAMENT’S MINERAL GUIDE the form of jobs, the strengthening of the Sami language, the development of expertiseand capacity, etc, are to be considered. 5.5 Conditions regarding and schemes for a financial payment that comprises part of theutility value of exploration work and operations are to be considered. 5.6 A condition that the agreement is to be reviewed after a certain period of time may bestipulated. The agreement is to be reviewed before the licence is revised in accordancewith section 43 of the Minerals Act. 5.7 If no agreement on the planned work and applications is entered into, a negotiationrecord is to be prepared and approved by the parties.</p>
<p>THE SAMI PARLIAMENT’S MINERAL GUIDE 7</p>
<p>Comments on the mineral guide</p>
<p>Re. Item 1 Objective1.1 This guide is intended to make conditions suitable for Sami culture, business and sociallife to be emphasised and safeguarded in plans relating to the use of mineral resources. 1.2 The guide states the Sami Parliament’s expectations regarding companies and formsof cooperation with companies that want to establish agreement with the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament on actual exploration work, pilot extraction and plans to apply for an ope-rating licence for mineral resources. 1.3 The guide is intended to ensure compliance with the rights which the Sami have inaccordance with international laws regarding indigenous peoples and minorities.</p>
<p>Item 1 states the mineral guide’s objective. Item 1.1 is based on sections 1 and 2 of the</p>
<p>Minerals Act. Section 1 of the Minerals Act states that the Act shall promote and ensurethe socially responsible administration and use of mineral resources in accordance withthe principle of sustainable development. Section 2 of the Minerals Act stipulates thatthe administration and use of mineral resources shall take account of value creation,the natural foundation of Sami Culture, the environment and subsequent use. Item 1.1makes it clear that the objective of this guide is specifically to safeguard the interestsof Sami culture, business development and social life.</p>
<p>Item 1.2 is an amendment compared to §1, third sub-paragraph of the discussion paper.</p>
<p>Item 1.2 emphasises that this is the Sami Parliament’s guide relating to the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament’s expectations regarding companies that want to carry out exploration workor operations related to mineral resources in Sami areas. The focus is on plans that areof direct importance to physical encroachments on nature. The guide does not, there-fore, have a direct focus on applications for an extraction permit, as was the case inthe discussion paper. An extraction permit can more precisely be said to be a priorityright to possible extraction work and not a right to actual extraction. This is furthermade clear by the fact that the guide states how a collaboration with companies mustbe carried out if companies want to reach agreement with the Sami Parliament onactual exploration work and plans to apply for an operating licence. From item 1.2, itfollows that the Sami Parliament is not authorised to order companies to either coope-8</p>
<p>THE SAMI PARLIAMENT’S MINERAL GUIDE rate or agree with the Sami Parliament on their activities in traditional Sami areas. Item1.2 also shows that this guide does not mean that the Minerals Act and other Acts donot have to be complied with. The procedural rules and permits that follow from Actsand the prevailing law must naturally be complied with.</p>
<p>Item 1.3 stipulates that the guide is intended to ensure that mineral operations in Samiareas comply with international law rules on indigenous peoples and minorities. Sincethe Minerals Act is not in accordance with international law, this guide is a way ofstrengthening the foundation for the practical implementation of international lawregulations in the case of plans for mineral activities. Especially relevant internationallaw provisions are the UN International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, articles1 and 27, the ILO Convention, articles 6, 7 and 15, and the Declaration on the Rightsof Indigenous Peoples, articles 3, 19 and 32. Even if companies comply with</p>
<p>Norwegian law, this does not relieve them from their independent duty to find outabout and comply with the indigenous peoples’ rights when they want to operate in</p>
<p>Sami areas. If companies choose not to have direct contact with the Sami Parliamentor to agree with the Sami Parliament before starting their operations, they do so subjectto the financial, ethical and political risks that this entails.</p>
<p>Re Item 2 Scope2.1 The guide is to be used in the case of actual exploration work, pilot extractions andplans to apply for an operating licence for metals. 2.2 The guide is to be used for industrial minerals, building raw materials and natural stonein traditional Sami areas where Sami land rights are not recognised and where Statskog</p>
<p>SF currently administers the ground. 2.3 The guide applies to the traditional Sami areas which are covered by Finnmark, Troms,</p>
<p>Nordland and Nord-Trøndelag as well as the municipalities of Osen, Roan, Åfjord,</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Bjugn, Rissa, Selbu, Meldal, Rennebu, Oppdal, Midtre Gauldal, Tydal, Holtålen and</p>
<p>Røros in the county of Sør-Trøndelag, Engerdal and Rendalen, Os, Tolga, Tynset and</p>
<p>Folldal municipalities in the county of Hedmark and Surnadal, Rindal and Sunndalmunicipalities in the county of Møre and Romsdal.</p>
<p>Item 2.1 stipulates that the substantive scope of the mineral guide is that which isdefined as minerals owned by the State in section 7 of the Minerals Act. The Sami</p>
<p>Parliament has in principle stated that the resources above and below the ground in</p>
<p>Sami areas also belong to the Sami people. However, the Sami Parliament has not op-posed the use of a legal system that differentiates between metals with a specific weightof 5 grams/cm3 or more, which the State exercises the right of ownership to, andother minerals which the landowner has the right of ownership to and which are oftendivided into the main categories of industrial minerals, building raw materials andnatural stone. The discussion paper used the concept of minerals that the State claimsit has the right of ownership to. It is regarded as briefer and more expedient to use theconcept of metals versus industrial minerals, building raw materials and natural stone.</p>
<p>Item 2.1 stipulates that the mineral guide is to be used in the case of actual explorationwork. This means that the guide is not applicable to applications for an explorationpermit, but becomes relevant when this exploration permit entails physical activity oractivity that might disturb or prevent existing or traditional business. The mineral guideis also to be used prior to applications when a permit will directly lead to a physical</p>
<p>THE SAMI PARLIAMENT’S MINERAL GUIDE 9encroachment on nature, as will be the case for a permit to carry out actual explorationwork (section 13 of the Minerals Act, cf section 17), an extraction permit (cf section20 of the Minerals Act) and an operating licence (section 43 of the Minerals Act). Thisis new compared to the discussion paper, which placed great emphasis on applicationsfor an extraction permit pursuant to section 29 of the Minerals Act.</p>
<p>Item 2.2 is new compared to the discussion paper. Sami land rights are not recognisedoutside Finnmark. This will first take place as a result of further work on the proposalsof the Sami Law Committee II. The Sami Parliament is aware that, as the land ad-ministrator, Statskog SF enters into agreements with minerals companies regardingexploration for and the extraction of/operations relating to industrial minerals, buildingraw materials and natural stone (minerals owned by a landowner). These agreementsmay be of direct importance to the Sami people. As a state-owned enterprise, Statskog</p>
<p>SF is obliged pursuant to the consultation agreement between the government and</p>
<p>Sami Parliament to hold consultations regarding such agreements. So it is reasonableto allow this guide to also cover the interaction with Statskog SF, which administersminerals in areas where Sami land rights are not yet recognised. The more specificguidance items will show which of them are to be used in relation to Statskog SF.</p>
<p>Item 2.3 defines what is to be understood as the traditional Sami area. The geographicalarea is the same as that covered by issues linked to the substantive cultural basis in‘Procedures for consultations between state authorities and the Sami Parliament’. Inaddition, it is the same area as is defined in the comments on section 5-4, third sub-section of the Planning and Building Act regarding the Sami Parliament’s authority toobject. Within the traditional Sami area, not all mineral operations will necessary be ofimportance to Sami culture. However, this must be assessed for each area.</p>
<p>Re Item 3 Information on and assessments of Sami interests3.1 A party that is granted an exploration permit pursuant to section 13 of the Minerals</p>
<p>Act shall prepare a report containing information on and assessments of Sami intereststhat may be directly affected by actual exploration work and any pilot extractionpursuant to sections 19 and 20 of the Minerals Act. 3.2 A party that is granted an extraction permit pursuant to sections 29 and 30 of the</p>
<p>Minerals Act shall prepare an impact analysis in accordance with chapters 4 and 14 ofthe Norwegian Planning and Building Act and the Sami Parliament’s planning guidebefore submitting an application for an operating licence in accordance with section43 of the Minerals Act.3.3 When Statskog SF is considering entering into agreements regarding exploration forindustrial minerals, building raw materials and natural stone, it should ensure that areport is prepared containing information on and assessments of the Sami intereststhat may be affected by exploration work, and if relevant by pilot extraction and ope-rations. 3.4 The report and impact analysis that have been prepared are to form the basis fornegotiations on the actual exploration work and operations respectively, cf item 4 ofthis guide.</p>
<p>Item 3.1 precisely defines and clarifies the provision resulting from section 17, secondsubsection of the Minerals Act, but with the difference that it applies to the entire10</p>
<p>THE SAMI PARLIAMENT’S MINERAL GUIDE traditional Sami area and is not just restricted to Finnmark. A report containing infor-mation on and assessments of the Sami interests that may be affected must be preparedby the party carrying out the exploration work and/or the applicant for an extractionpermit and operating licence. The scope of the report is not equivalent to that of animpact analysis pursuant to the Planning and Building Act’s provisions. However, themore thorough and concrete the report is the better basis it will provide for negotiationspursuant to item 4 of the mineral guide. What Sami interests are and the considerationsthat such a report must seek information on and assess are specified in the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament’s planning guide to ensure the natural foundation of Sami culture, businessand social life.</p>
<p>Item 3.2 is new compared to the discussion paper. This states that impact analyses inaccordance with the Planning and Building Act’s provisions and regulations are to formthe basis for negotiations on the operations and use of land. That for which an impactanalysis is to be prepared, the issues to be covered and the way in which the impactanalyses are to be conducted follow from the regulation regarding an impact analysisand the Sami Parliament’s planning guide to ensure the natural foundation of Samiculture, business and social life in the case of planning in accordance with the Planningand Building Act’s planning part. In Finnmark, the Sami Parliament’s guidelines forassessing Sami interests in the case of a change in the use of meahcci/uncultivatedland stated in section 4 of the Finnmark Act shall also apply. The contents of theguidelines stipulated in section 4 of the Finnmark Act and the Sami Parliament’s plan-ning guide are coordinated. The change compared to the discussion paper - that theimpact analysis is to form the basis for negotiations on operations – is a result of therebeing no negotiations prior to the application for an extraction permit since theextraction permit does not directly lead to any physical encroachment on nature.</p>
<p>Item 3.3 is new compared to the discussion paper. This item states an expectation that</p>
<p>Statskog SF will ensure there is a basis consisting of information on and assessmentsof Sami interests when it is considering entering into agreements regarding explorationwork, pilot extraction and operations relating to minerals that it administers. In that</p>
<p>Statskog SF is obliged to hold consultations regarding such agreements, it is assumedto also prepare an assessment basis for real consultations/negotiations with the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament. Both section 110a of the Norwegian Constitution and sections 2 and 3 ofthe Human Rights Act also state that the Sami culture’s interests are to be assessed andplaced emphasis on in any decisions or measures that may affect the Sami.</p>
<p>Item 3.4 clarifies that reports containing information on and assessments of Sami in-terests and impact analyses pursuant to the Planning and Building Act’s provisions willbe the key basic documents for reaching agreement on mineral activities.</p>
<p>Re Item 4 Negotiations4.1 Parties wishing to carry out actual exploration work and pilot extraction and partieswishing to apply for an operating licence pursuant to sections 13, 20 and 43 of the</p>
<p>Minerals Act are to contact the Sami Parliament to agree on the holding of negotiationsregarding this. 4.2 Separate negotiations are to be held for actual exploration work, for plans to apply foran extraction permit and for plans to apply for an operating licence. In the case of</p>
<p>THE SAMI PARLIAMENT’S MINERAL GUIDE 11plans to apply for an extraction permit, a common document shall be prepared statingthat negotiations are to be held prior to any application for an operating licence. 4.3 Separate consultations are to be held with Statskog SF if it is considering entering intoagreements with a company regarding exploration for, the pilot extraction of or ope-rations relating to industrial minerals, building raw materials or natural stone. 4.4 The Sami Parliament may clarify participation in such negotiations with directly affected</p>
<p>Sami interests. Following prior informed consent, the Sami Parliament may safeguarddirectly affected Sami interests in these negotiations. 4.5 A party that wishes to carry out work in accordance with item 4.1 of the guide may beasked to cover the actual costs of holding the negotiations.</p>
<p>Item 4.1 stipulates that parties wishing to carry out actual exploration work and pilotextraction and parties wishing to apply for an operating licence are to contact the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament to agree on the holding of negotiations on the desired activity. The Sami</p>
<p>Parliament’s opposite party in the negotiations is the company that will carry out theactual exploration work and pilot extraction and the company that is planning to applyfor an operating licence. If a company takes over another company’s exploration permitor operating licence, it is assumed that new negotiations must be held. These maynaturally be based on agreements with the previous holder of the exploration permitor operating licence. It is assumed that work can only be carried out and applicationscan only be submitted after an agreement has been entered into between the parties,cf item 5.1. Directly affected Sami interests may also take part in the negotiations.</p>
<p>Directly affected Sami interests are understood to be a group or gathering of users,such as a siida, regional society or district. Individuals are not included in this category.</p>
<p>The second point in item 4.1 is new compared to the discussion paper. This point is aresult of negotiations being moved from the extraction permit stage to the operatinglicence stage. To the Sami Parliament, it is nonetheless of importance that it is clear toboth parties even at the stage when an application is being made for an extractionpermit that negotiations are to be held regarding an operating licence. If this were notthe case, the Sami Parliament would have relinquished its opportunity pursuant tosection 30 of the Minerals Act to oppose the award of an extraction permit.</p>
<p>Item 4.2 clarifies that separate negotiations are to be held and agreements entered intoregarding actual exploration work, pilot extraction and plans to apply for an operatinglicence. This complies with the Minerals Act’s structure and priority system. Existingand traditional industries will have differing levels of activity and efficiency when itcomes to actual exploration work, pilot extraction and operations. In addition, in mostcases it will be such that actual exploration work does not lead to plans to apply for anoperating licence and, if operations become relevant, the exploration work that hasbeen carried out naturally sets the terms for how these are to be carried out. It is alsooften the case that it is not the same company that is responsible for the actualexploration work and for the later operations. All this makes it most expedient to haveseparate negotiations on the various activities.</p>
<p>Item 4.3 is new compared to the discussion paper. This item makes clear Statskog SF’sduty to hold consultations pursuant to the agreement between the Government andthe Sami Parliament regarding ‘Procedures for consultations between state authoritiesand the Sami Parliament’. According to this item, there are thus no direct negotiationswith the company that wants to explore for or have operations relating to minerals ad-ministered by Statskog SF. The negotiations here are with the state-owned enterprise12</p>
<p>THE SAMI PARLIAMENT’S MINERAL GUIDE that administers rights that are not recognised as belonging to the Sami. Item 4.3 usesthe concept of consultation. This is because the item directly relates to the consultationagreement. This does not mean that it is not just as crucial to the Sami Parliament toreach agreement with Statskog SF as it is to reach agreement with companies that wantto have metals operations.</p>
<p>Item 4.4 is slightly different to §4, third paragraph of the discussion paper. While thediscussion paper intended the Sami Parliament to be responsible for clarifying whetherother parties are to participate in the negotiations, it is now stated that the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament may clarify this. It will thus to a larger extent be up to the companies and</p>
<p>Statskog SF whether they want the Sami Parliament to contribute to such a coordinationor whether they wish to do this themselves, and if relevant whether they want tonegotiate separately with the Sami Parliament and directly affected Sami interests. Thereis nonetheless reason to warn against processes that may lead to a <span type="quote" xml:lang="ita">“divide and conquer”</span>situation between the negotiating parties. In some circumstances, it may be desirableand expedient for the Sami Parliament, as the Sami elected body, to also safeguarddirectly affected Sami interests and local communities in the negotiations. If this is totake place, the group or gathering of users must have given their informed consent tothe Sami Parliament safeguarding their interests.</p>
<p>Item 4.5 is also slightly different to §4, fourth paragraph of the discussion paper. Whilethe discussion paper stated that the Sami Parliament was to be able to impose a fine toensure that negotiations were held, the guide now states that those that wish to conductactual exploration work and plan to apply for pilot extraction, an extraction permit oran operating licence for metals are urged to cover the direct costs of holdingnegotiations. It is assumed that the companies will benefit considerably fromnegotiations being held in a confidence-creating and efficient manner, which oftenmeans there is a need for capacity for this. The coverage of such costs will primarilybe of interest to directly affected Sami interests and to a lesser extent to the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament. It is considered to be important that there is openness regarding and publicaccess to the way in which such costs are covered.</p>
<p>Re Item 5 Agreements and records 5.1 An agreement regarding actual exploration work and agreement regarding pilotextraction may cover the scope, exploration period, activity dates, access, storage ofequipment, etc, and measures to prevent harm or inconvenience to existing andtraditional usage. 5.2 An agreement to apply for an operating licence may cover the extraction area, anextraction plan, plan of operations and the termination of the agreement if operationsdo not start within a certain period or are suspended for a lengthy period. The agree-ment may include measures to prevent harm or inconvenience to existing andtraditional usage. 5.3 A record of the consultations with Statskog SF shall be prepared, stating whether theparties have reached agreement and if so what they have agreed is to be included inthe option and operations agreements with the company. 5.4 Conditions regarding compensation to benefit Sami culture, business and social life inthe form of jobs, the strengthening of the Sami language, the development of expertiseand capacity, etc, are to be considered.</p>
<p>THE SAMI PARLIAMENT’S MINERAL GUIDE 135.5 Conditions regarding and schemes for financial remuneration that comprises part ofthe utility value of exploration work and operations are to be considered. 5.6 A condition that the agreement is to be reviewed after a certain period of time may bestipulated. The agreement is to be reviewed before the licence is revised in accordancewith section 43 of the Minerals Act. 5.7 If no agreement on the planned work and applications is entered into, a negotiationrecord is to be prepared and approved by the parties.</p>
<p>Item 5.1 deals with what agreements on actual exploration work and the pilot extractionof metals may cover. In addition to agreements on how activities may be carried out,such agreements may also cover measures which prevent or remedy harm orinconvenience to existing and traditional use of the area.</p>
<p>Item 5.2 deals with what operating licence agreements cover as regards the size of thearea, plan of operations and termination of the agreement if operations are not startedup. This item of the guide states that an agreement regarding an application for anoperating licence is to be arrived at before an application is sent to the Directorate of</p>
<p>Mining and before comments are invited on the proposed land-use plan. This is becausethe processing of the operating licence application is usually coordinated with the planclarification pursuant to the Planning and Building Act and any agreements with thelandowner and those holding rights of use.</p>
<p>Item 5.3 is new compared to the discussion paper. This precisely defines Statskog SF’sduty to consult that follows from the ‘Procedures for consultations between stateauthorities and the Sami Parliament’. This stipulates that the parties are to try to reachconsensus that is not to be set out in the form of an agreement but instead in the formof a record. To the extent that no agreement is reached, this must also be recorded.</p>
<p>Contact here is not with the company directly but with the state-owned enterprise thatadministers the minerals. If the agreement reached by the Sami Parliament and Statskog</p>
<p>SF cannot be achieved in Statskog SF’s negotiations with the company, Statskog SF isexpected to return to the Sami Parliament for renewed consultations. Another pos-sibility is for Statskog SF and the Sami Parliament to hold consultations to reach agree-ment on some overarching principles which must form the basis for Statskog SF’sadministration of industrial minerals, building raw materials and natural stone.</p>
<p>Item 5.4 deals with conditions of a compensatory nature when measures may lead toharm or inconvenience to or the repression of Sami culture. This item corresponds tothe provision in §7, third sub-paragraph, cf §4, second sub-paragraph, of the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament’s guidelines for changes in the use of uncultivated land in Finnmark, cfsection 4 of the Finnmark Act. The great importance of mineral operations to societymust be compared with the responsibility one has to safeguard Sami culture. Planswhich make it impossible or significantly more difficult to maintain Sami culture in thearea are under no circumstances permitted according to international law. Accordingto international law, a measure that entails villages and local communities being movedalso cannot be implemented without the express prior informed consent of thoseaffected and the Sami Parliament. In cases where it may be disputed or unclear whetherplans or measures will lead to the exercise of Sami culture in the area being impossible,or where it is clear that the negative consequences for Sami culture are considerable,measures of a compensatory nature may be conditions which allow consent to be givento the plan. The scope of such conditions will be linked to the scope of the measureand its effects on Sami culture, business development and social life. The opportunity</p>
<p>Item 5.5 must be considered in connection with item 5.4 of the mineral guide.</p>
<p>Conditions concerning a financial payment that comprises part of the utility value inthe case of extraction and operations must always be considered. The size of such apayment will depend on the scope of the activities and the effects that such activitieshave on Sami culture and communities, especially those that are directly affected. Thepayment will also depend on which other measures of a compensatory nature theparties can agree on pursuant to item 5.4 of the guide. Item 5.5 also means that theparties may agree on financial payment schemes. This means a large degree of flexibilityregarding how a financial payment is to be determined, utilised and organised. This initself may be a negotiation issue. Schemes which entail the establishment of new enter-prises or institutions must be approved by the Sami Parliament in plenum. Under anycircumstances, it is to be assumed that such schemes comply with legal frameworksand that there is transparency with regard to what they entail. Those who are directlyaffected by mineral operations, who exercise forms of collective use of the area inwhich a new enterprise is to be established and who in some other way are significantlyaffected by the activities from a business, environmental, cultural or social point ofview, such as siida, regional associations and suchlike, will be those that such a paymentis primarily to benefit.</p>
<p>Item 5.6 makes it clear that further conditions regarding a review of the agreementmay be stated in the agreement. This has been included so that the agreement may takeinto account any conditions which the Directorate of Mining includes in its operatinglicences in accordance with section 43. Pursuant to this provision, the Directorate of</p>
<p>Mining may stipulate a time limit for the operating licence or a requirement that it is tobe reviewed after a certain time. The Directorate of Mining may also require a reviewof the licence every 10 years irrespective of that stated in the licensing conditions. Theopportunity to review agreements is also based on the need to change plans of ope-rations as a result of clear changes to the assumptions on which the extraction andoperations are based.</p>
<p>Item 5.7 makes it clear that if negotiations do not result in the entry into of an agree-ment to carry out further activities linked to the mineral resources, then a negotiationrecord is to be prepared and approved by the parties. This is so that the negotiationprocess is documented, can be subsequently accessed by the public and is available ifnew initiatives relating to the same deposits in the same area should later arise.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">SAMETINGETS PLANVEILEDER</p>
</body></document>
