<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The Sami Parliament´s mineral guide</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2010</year><wordcount>5726</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://samediggi.no/content/download/559/4960/version/1/file/The+Sami+Parliament%E2%80%99s+mineral+guide+%282010%29.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="sametingets_mineralveileder_2010_.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="sa_medikki_minera_lapla_naveahkki_2010_.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p>The Sami Parliament’s mineral guide</p>
<p>for exploration work and operations</p>
<p>relating to mineral resources The Sami Parliament’s mineral guide for exploration work and operations relating to mineral resources</p>
<p>In June 2010, the Sami Parliament agreed on a mineral</p>
<p>guide  for  how  the  Sami  Parliament  and  minerals</p>
<p>companies can relate to each other in connection with</p>
<p>mineral  operations  in  Sami  areas.    This  mineral  guide</p>
<p>aims for agreements to be entered into between the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament  and  companies  regarding  exploration  work</p>
<p>and plans to apply for operating licences.</p>
<p>The  Sami  Parliament’s  goal  is  for  business  operations</p>
<p>relating to mineral resources in traditional Sami areas to</p>
<p>benefit and directly strengthen and develop Sami culture</p>
<p>and local communities. Such operations must also take</p>
<p>place in co-existence with, and not displace, traditional</p>
<p>Sami  industries  and  traditional  Sami  culture-based</p>
<p>harvesting.  The  Minerals  Act,  which  the  Norwegian</p>
<p>parliament (Storting) passed on 10 June 2009, does not</p>
<p>safeguard these considerations and did not safeguard</p>
<p>the  obligations  that  the  State  has  to  the  Sami  as  an</p>
<p>indigenous  people  in  accordance  with  human  rights.</p>
<p>Therefore the Sami Parliament could not give its consent</p>
<p>to the Act. In order for the Sami Parliament to nonetheless</p>
<p>have an opportunity to give its approval to mineral ope</p>
<p>rations in Sami areas, the Sami Parliament has issued its</p>
<p>own guide, which will form the basis for compliance with</p>
<p>the Sami rights pursuant to international law concerning</p>
<p>indigenous peoples and minorities.  With the mineral guide, the Sami Parliament is making</p>
<p>conditions  suitable  for  an  overall  consideration  of  all</p>
<p>affected Sami interests in the case of mineral operations.</p>
<p>This applies to the need which traditional Sami industries</p>
<p>and users of uncultivated land have to secure their land</p>
<p>basis and Sami society’s need for jobs and value creation</p>
<p>based on a new utilisation of the resources.</p>
<p>In  that  the  Minerals  Act  does  not  establish  the</p>
<p>predictability in relation to Sami rights and interests that</p>
<p>a  capital-intensive  mineral  industry  requires,  the  Sami</p>
<p>Parliament’s  mineral  guide  will  be  an  important</p>
<p>contribution to achieve this. The mineral guide clarifies</p>
<p>the Sami Parliament’s role in exploration, extraction and</p>
<p>operations relating to minerals throughout the traditional</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sami area.</p>
<p>Yours faithfully</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Egil Olli</p>
<p><em type="bold">President of the Sami Parliament</em> </p>
<p>Mineral guide for exploration work and operations relating to mineral resources</p>
<p>Objective</p>
<p>1.1  This guide is intended to make conditions suitable for Sami culture, business and social</p>
<p>life to be emphasised and safeguarded in plans relating to the use of  mineral resources.</p>
<p>1.2  The guide states the Sami Parliament’s expectations regarding companies and forms</p>
<p>of   cooperation  with  companies  that  want  to  establish  agreement  with  the  Sami</p>
<p>Parliament on actual exploration work, pilot extraction and plans to apply for an ope</p>
<p>rating licence for mineral resources.</p>
<p>1.3  The guide is intended to ensure compliance with the rights which the Sami have in</p>
<p>accordance with international law regarding indigenous peoples and minorities.</p>
<p>2  Scope</p>
<p>2.1  The guide is to be used in the case of  actual exploration work, pilot extractions and</p>
<p>plans to apply for an operating licence for metals.</p>
<p>2.2  The guide is to be used for industrial minerals, building raw materials and natural stone</p>
<p>in traditional Sami areas where Sami land rights are not recognised and where Statskog</p>
<p>SF currently administers the ground.</p>
<p>2.3  The guide applies to the traditional Sami areas which are covered by Finnmark, Troms,</p>
<p>Nordland and Nord-Trøndelag as well as the municipalities of  Osen, Roan, Åfjord,</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Bjugn, Rissa, Selbu, Meldal, Rennebu, Oppdal, Midtre Gauldal, Tydal, Holtålen and</p>
<p>Røros in the county of  Sør-Trøndelag, Engerdal and Rendalen, Os, Tolga, Tynset and</p>
<p>Folldal municipalities in the county of  Hedmark and Surnadal, Rindal and Sunndal</p>
<p>municipalities in the county of  Møre and Romsdal.</p>
<p>3  Information on and assessments of Sami interests</p>
<p>3.1  A party that is granted an exploration permit pursuant to section 13 of  the Norwegian</p>
<p>Minerals Act shall prepare a report containing information on and assessments of  the</p>
<p>Sami interests that may be directly affected by actual exploration work and any pilot</p>
<p>extraction pursuant to sections 19 and 20 of  the Minerals Act.</p>
<p>3.2  A party that is granted an extraction permit pursuant to sections 29 and 30 of  the</p>
<p>Minerals Act shall prepare an impact analysis in accordance with chapters 4 and 14 of</p>
<p>the Norwegian Planning and Building Act and the Sami Parliament’s planning guide</p>
<p>before submitting an application for an operating licence in accordance with section</p>
<p>43 of  the Minerals Act.</p>
<p>3.3  When Statskog SF is considering entering into agreements regarding exploration for</p>
<p>industrial minerals, building raw materials and natural stone, it should ensure that a</p>
<p>report is prepared containing information on and assessments of  the Sami interests</p>
<p>that may be affected by exploration work, and if  relevant by pilot extraction and ope</p>
<p>rations.</p>
<p>3.4  The report and impact analysis that have been prepared are to form the basis for</p>
<p>negotiations on the actual exploration work and operations respectively, cf  item 4 of</p>
<p>this guide.</p>
<p>4  Negotiations</p>
<p>4.1  Parties wishing to carry out actual exploration work and pilot extraction and parties</p>
<p>wishing to apply for an operating licence pursuant to sections 13, 20 and 43 of  the</p>
<p>Minerals Act are to contact the Sami Parliament to agree on the holding of  negotiations</p>
<p>regarding this.</p>
<p>4.2  Separate negotiations are to be held for actual exploration work, for plans to apply for</p>
<p>an extraction permit and for plans to apply for an operating licence. In the case of</p>
<p>plans to apply for an extraction permit, a common document shall be prepared stating</p>
<p>that negotiations are to be held prior to any application for an operating licence.</p>
<p>4.3  Separate consultations are to be held with Statskog SF if  Statskog SF is considering</p>
<p>entering into agreements with a company regarding exploration for, the pilot extraction</p>
<p>of  or operations relating to industrial minerals, building raw materials or natural stone.</p>
<p>4.4  The Sami Parliament may clarify participation in such negotiations with directly affected</p>
<p>Sami interests. Following prior informed consent, the Sami Parliament may safeguard</p>
<p>directly affected Sami interests in these negotiations.</p>
<p>4.5  A party that wishes to carry out work in accordance with item 4.1 of  the guide may be</p>
<p>asked to cover the actual costs of  holding the negotiations.</p>
<p>5  Agreements, record and contents</p>
<p>5.1  An  agreement  regarding  actual  exploration  work  and  agreement  regarding  pilot</p>
<p>extraction may cover the scope, exploration period, activity dates, access, storage of</p>
<p>equipment,  etc,  and  measures  to  prevent  harm  or  inconvenience  to  existing  and</p>
<p>traditional usage.</p>
<p>5.2  An agreement to apply for an operating licence may cover the extraction area, an</p>
<p>extraction plan, plan of  operations and the termination of  the agreement if  operations</p>
<p>do not start within a certain period or are suspended for a lengthy period. The agree</p>
<p>ment  may  include  measures  to  prevent  harm  or  inconvenience  to  existing  and</p>
<p>traditional usage.</p>
<p>5.3  A record of  the consultations with Statskog SF shall be prepared, stating whether the</p>
<p>parties have reached agreement and if  so what they have agreed shall be included in</p>
<p>the option and operations agreements with the company.</p>
<p>5.4  Conditions regarding compensation to benefit Sami culture, business and social life in the form of  jobs, the strengthening of  the Sami language, the development of  expertise</p>
<p>and capacity, etc, are to be considered.</p>
<p>5.5  Conditions regarding and schemes for a financial payment that comprises part of  the</p>
<p>utility value of  exploration work and operations are to be considered.</p>
<p>5.6  A condition that the agreement is to be reviewed after a certain period of  time may be</p>
<p>stipulated. The agreement is to be reviewed before the licence is revised in accordance</p>
<p>with section 43 of  the Minerals Act.</p>
<p>5.7  If  no agreement on the planned work and applications is entered into, a negotiation</p>
<p>record is to be prepared and approved by the parties.</p>
<p>Comments on the mineral guide</p>
<p>Re. Item 1 Objective</p>
<p>1.1  This guide is intended to make conditions suitable for Sami culture, business and social</p>
<p>life to be emphasised and safeguarded in plans relating to the use of  mineral resources.</p>
<p>1.2  The guide states the Sami Parliament’s expectations regarding companies and forms</p>
<p>of   cooperation  with  companies  that  want  to  establish  agreement  with  the  Sami</p>
<p>Parliament on actual exploration work, pilot extraction and plans to apply for an ope</p>
<p>rating licence for mineral resources.</p>
<p>1.3  The guide is intended to ensure compliance with the rights which the Sami have in</p>
<p>accordance with international laws regarding indigenous peoples and minorities.</p>
<p>Item 1 states the mineral guide’s objective. Item 1.1 is based on sections 1 and 2 of  the</p>
<p>Minerals Act. Section 1 of  the Minerals Act states that the Act shall promote and ensure</p>
<p>the socially responsible administration and use of  mineral resources in accordance with</p>
<p>the principle of  sustainable development. Section 2 of  the Minerals Act stipulates that</p>
<p>the administration and use of  mineral resources shall take account of  value creation,</p>
<p>the natural foundation of  Sami Culture, the environment and subsequent use. Item 1.1</p>
<p>makes it clear that the objective of  this guide is specifically to safeguard the interests</p>
<p>of  Sami culture, business development and social life.</p>
<p>Item 1.2 is an amendment compared to §1, third sub-paragraph of  the discussion paper.</p>
<p>Item  1.2  emphasises  that  this  is  the  Sami  Parliament’s  guide  relating  to  the  Sami</p>
<p>Parliament’s expectations regarding companies that want to carry out exploration work</p>
<p>or operations related to mineral resources in Sami areas. The focus is on plans that are</p>
<p>of  direct importance to physical encroachments on nature. The guide does not, there</p>
<p>fore, have a direct focus on applications for an extraction permit, as was the case in</p>
<p>the discussion paper. An extraction permit can more precisely be said to be a priority</p>
<p>right to possible extraction work and not a right to actual extraction. This is further</p>
<p>made clear by the fact that the guide states how a collaboration with companies must</p>
<p>be carried out if  companies want to reach agreement with the Sami Parliament on</p>
<p>actual exploration work and plans to apply for an operating licence. From item 1.2, it</p>
<p>follows that the Sami Parliament is not authorised to order companies to either cooperate or agree with the Sami Parliament on their activities in traditional Sami areas. Item</p>
<p>1.2 also shows that this guide does not mean that the Minerals Act and other Acts do</p>
<p>not have to be complied with. The procedural rules and permits that follow from Acts</p>
<p>and the prevailing law must naturally be complied with.</p>
<p>Item 1.3 stipulates that the guide is intended to ensure that mineral operations in Sami</p>
<p>areas comply with international law rules on indigenous peoples and minorities. Since</p>
<p>the Minerals Act is not in accordance with international law, this guide is a way of</p>
<p>strengthening the foundation for the practical implementation of  international law</p>
<p>regulations in the case of  plans for mineral activities. Especially relevant international</p>
<p>law provisions are the UN International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, articles</p>
<p>1 and 27, the ILO Convention, articles 6, 7 and 15, and the Declaration on the Rights</p>
<p>of   Indigenous  Peoples,  articles  3,  19  and  32.  Even  if   companies  comply  with</p>
<p>Norwegian law, this does not relieve them from their independent duty to find out</p>
<p>about and comply with the indigenous peoples’ rights when they want to operate in</p>
<p>Sami areas. If  companies choose not to have direct contact with the Sami Parliament</p>
<p>or to agree with the Sami Parliament before starting their operations, they do so subject</p>
<p>to the financial, ethical and political risks that this entails.</p>
<p>Re Item 2 Scope</p>
<p>2.1  The guide is to be used in the case of  actual exploration work, pilot extractions and</p>
<p>plans to apply for an operating licence for metals.</p>
<p>2.2  The guide is to be used for industrial minerals, building raw materials and natural stone</p>
<p>in traditional Sami areas where Sami land rights are not recognised and where Statskog</p>
<p>SF currently administers the ground.</p>
<p>2.3  The guide applies to the traditional Sami areas which are covered by Finnmark, Troms,</p>
<p>Nordland and Nord-Trøndelag as well as the municipalities of  Osen, Roan, Åfjord,</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Bjugn, Rissa, Selbu, Meldal, Rennebu, Oppdal, Midtre Gauldal, Tydal, Holtålen and</p>
<p>Røros in the county of  Sør-Trøndelag, Engerdal and Rendalen, Os, Tolga, Tynset and</p>
<p>Folldal municipalities in the county of  Hedmark and Surnadal, Rindal and Sunndal</p>
<p>municipalities in the county of  Møre and Romsdal.</p>
<p>Item 2.1 stipulates that the substantive scope of  the mineral guide is that which is</p>
<p>defined as minerals owned by the State in section 7 of  the Minerals Act. The Sami</p>
<p>Parliament has in principle stated that the resources above and below the ground in</p>
<p>Sami areas also belong to the Sami people. However, the Sami Parliament has not op</p>
<p>posed the use of  a legal system that differentiates between metals with a specific weight</p>
<p>of  5 grams/cm3 or more, which the State exercises the right of  ownership to, and</p>
<p>other minerals which the landowner has the right of  ownership to and which are often</p>
<p>divided into the main categories of  industrial minerals, building raw materials and</p>
<p>natural stone. The discussion paper used the concept of  minerals that the State claims</p>
<p>it has the right of  ownership to. It is regarded as briefer and more expedient to use the</p>
<p>concept of  metals versus industrial minerals, building raw materials and natural stone.</p>
<p>Item 2.1 stipulates that the mineral guide is to be used in the case of  actual exploration</p>
<p>work. This means that the guide is not applicable to applications for an exploration</p>
<p>permit, but becomes relevant when this exploration permit entails physical activity or</p>
<p>activity that might disturb or prevent existing or traditional business. The mineral guide</p>
<p>is also to be used prior to applications when a permit will directly lead to a physical encroachment on nature, as will be the case for a permit to carry out actual exploration</p>
<p>work (section 13 of  the Minerals Act, cf  section 17), an extraction permit (cf  section</p>
<p>20 of  the Minerals Act) and an operating licence (section 43 of  the Minerals Act). This</p>
<p>is new compared to the discussion paper, which placed great emphasis on applications</p>
<p>for an extraction permit pursuant to section 29 of  the Minerals Act.</p>
<p>Item 2.2 is new compared to the discussion paper. Sami land rights are not recognised</p>
<p>outside Finnmark. This will first take place as a result of  further work on the proposals</p>
<p>of  the Sami Law Committee II. The Sami Parliament is aware that, as the land ad</p>
<p>ministrator, Statskog SF enters into agreements with minerals companies regarding</p>
<p>exploration for and the extraction of/operations relating to industrial minerals, building</p>
<p>raw materials and natural stone (minerals owned by a landowner). These agreements</p>
<p>may be of  direct importance to the Sami people. As a state-owned enterprise, Statskog</p>
<p>SF is obliged pursuant to the consultation agreement between the government and</p>
<p>Sami Parliament to hold consultations regarding such agreements. So it is reasonable</p>
<p>to allow this guide to also cover the interaction with Statskog SF, which administers</p>
<p>minerals in areas where Sami land rights are not yet recognised. The more specific</p>
<p>guidance items will show which of  them are to be used in relation to Statskog SF.</p>
<p>Item 2.3 defines what is to be understood as the traditional Sami area. The geographical</p>
<p>area is the same as that covered by issues linked to the substantive cultural basis in</p>
<p>‘Procedures for consultations between state authorities and the Sami Parliament’. In</p>
<p>addition, it is the same area as is defined in the comments on section 5-4, third sub</p>
<p>section of  the Planning and Building Act regarding the Sami Parliament’s authority to</p>
<p>object. Within the traditional Sami area, not all mineral operations will necessary be of</p>
<p>importance to Sami culture. However, this must be assessed for each area.</p>
<p>Re Item 3 Information on and assessments of Sami interests</p>
<p>3.1  A party that is granted an exploration permit pursuant to section 13 of  the Minerals</p>
<p>Act shall prepare a report containing information on and assessments of  Sami interests</p>
<p>that  may  be  directly  affected  by  actual  exploration  work  and  any  pilot  extraction</p>
<p>pursuant to sections 19 and 20 of  the Minerals Act.</p>
<p>3.2  A party that is granted an extraction permit pursuant to sections 29 and 30 of  the</p>
<p>Minerals Act shall prepare an impact analysis in accordance with chapters 4 and 14 of</p>
<p>the Norwegian Planning and Building Act and the Sami Parliament’s planning guide</p>
<p>before submitting an application for an operating licence in accordance with section</p>
<p>43 of  the Minerals Act.</p>
<p>3.3  When Statskog SF is considering entering into agreements regarding exploration for</p>
<p>industrial minerals, building raw materials and natural stone, it should ensure that a</p>
<p>report is prepared containing information on and assessments of  the Sami interests</p>
<p>that may be affected by exploration work, and if  relevant by pilot extraction and ope</p>
<p>rations.</p>
<p>3.4  The report and impact analysis that have been prepared are to form the basis for</p>
<p>negotiations on the actual exploration work and operations respectively, cf  item 4 of</p>
<p>this guide.</p>
<p>Item 3.1 precisely defines and clarifies the provision resulting from section 17, second</p>
<p>subsection of  the Minerals Act, but with the difference that it applies to the entire traditional Sami area and is not just restricted to Finnmark. A report containing infor</p>
<p>mation on and assessments of  the Sami interests that may be affected must be prepared</p>
<p>by the party carrying out the exploration work and/or the applicant for an extraction</p>
<p>permit and operating licence. The scope of  the report is not equivalent to that of  an</p>
<p>impact analysis pursuant to the Planning and Building Act’s provisions. However, the</p>
<p>more thorough and concrete the report is the better basis it will provide for negotiations</p>
<p>pursuant to item 4 of  the mineral guide. What Sami interests are and the considerations</p>
<p>that  such  a  report  must  seek  information  on  and  assess  are  specified  in  the  Sami</p>
<p>Parliament’s planning guide to ensure the natural foundation of  Sami culture, business</p>
<p>and social life.</p>
<p>Item 3.2 is new compared to the discussion paper. This states that impact analyses in</p>
<p>accordance with the Planning and Building Act’s provisions and regulations are to form</p>
<p>the basis for negotiations on the operations and use of  land. That for which an impact</p>
<p>analysis is to be prepared, the issues to be covered and the way in which the impact</p>
<p>analyses are to be conducted follow from the regulation regarding an impact analysis</p>
<p>and the Sami Parliament’s planning guide to ensure the natural foundation of  Sami</p>
<p>culture, business and social life in the case of  planning in accordance with the Planning</p>
<p>and Building Act’s planning part. In Finnmark, the Sami Parliament’s guidelines for</p>
<p>assessing Sami interests in the case of  a change in the use of  meahcci/uncultivated</p>
<p>land stated in section 4 of  the Finnmark Act shall also apply. The contents of  the</p>
<p>guidelines stipulated in section 4 of  the Finnmark Act and the Sami Parliament’s plan</p>
<p>ning guide are coordinated. The change compared to the discussion paper - that the</p>
<p>impact analysis is to form the basis for negotiations on operations – is a result of  there</p>
<p>being  no  negotiations  prior  to  the  application  for  an  extraction  permit  since  the</p>
<p>extraction permit does not directly lead to any physical encroachment on nature.</p>
<p>Item 3.3 is new compared to the discussion paper. This item states an expectation that</p>
<p>Statskog SF will ensure there is a basis consisting of  information on and assessments</p>
<p>of  Sami interests when it is considering entering into agreements regarding exploration</p>
<p>work, pilot extraction and operations relating to minerals that it administers. In that</p>
<p>Statskog SF is obliged to hold consultations regarding such agreements, it is assumed</p>
<p>to also prepare an assessment basis for real consultations/negotiations with the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament. Both section 110a of  the Norwegian Constitution and sections 2 and 3 of</p>
<p>the Human Rights Act also state that the Sami culture’s interests are to be assessed and</p>
<p>placed emphasis on in any decisions or measures that may affect the Sami.</p>
<p>Item 3.4 clarifies that reports containing information on and assessments of  Sami in</p>
<p>terests and impact analyses pursuant to the Planning and Building Act’s provisions will</p>
<p>be the key basic documents for reaching agreement on mineral activities.</p>
<p>Re Item 4 Negotiations</p>
<p>4.1  Parties wishing to carry out actual exploration work and pilot extraction and parties</p>
<p>wishing to apply for an operating licence pursuant to sections 13, 20 and 43 of  the</p>
<p>Minerals Act are to contact the Sami Parliament to agree on the holding of  negotiations</p>
<p>regarding this.</p>
<p>4.2  Separate negotiations are to be held for actual exploration work, for plans to apply for</p>
<p>an extraction permit and for plans to apply for an operating licence. In the case of plans to apply for an extraction permit, a common document shall be prepared stating</p>
<p>that negotiations are to be held prior to any application for an operating licence.</p>
<p>4.3  Separate consultations are to be held with Statskog SF if  it is considering entering into</p>
<p>agreements with a company regarding exploration for, the pilot extraction of  or ope</p>
<p>rations relating to industrial minerals, building raw materials or natural stone.</p>
<p>4.4  The Sami Parliament may clarify participation in such negotiations with directly affected</p>
<p>Sami interests. Following prior informed consent, the Sami Parliament may safeguard</p>
<p>directly affected Sami interests in these negotiations.</p>
<p>4.5  A party that wishes to carry out work in accordance with item 4.1 of  the guide may be</p>
<p>asked to cover the actual costs of  holding the negotiations.</p>
<p>Item 4.1 stipulates that parties wishing to carry out actual exploration work and pilot</p>
<p>extraction and parties wishing to apply for an operating licence are to contact the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament to agree on the holding of  negotiations on the desired activity. The Sami</p>
<p>Parliament’s opposite party in the negotiations is the company that will carry out the</p>
<p>actual exploration work and pilot extraction and the company that is planning to apply</p>
<p>for an operating licence. If  a company takes over another company’s exploration permit</p>
<p>or operating licence, it is assumed that new negotiations must be held. These may</p>
<p>naturally be based on agreements with the previous holder of  the exploration permit</p>
<p>or operating licence. It is assumed that work can only be carried out and applications</p>
<p>can only be submitted after an agreement has been entered into between the parties,</p>
<p>cf  item 5.1. Directly affected Sami interests may also take part in the negotiations.</p>
<p>Directly affected Sami interests are understood to be a group or gathering of  users,</p>
<p>such as a siida, regional society or district. Individuals are not included in this category.</p>
<p>The second point in item 4.1 is new compared to the discussion paper. This point is a</p>
<p>result of  negotiations being moved from the extraction permit stage to the operating</p>
<p>licence stage. To the Sami Parliament, it is nonetheless of  importance that it is clear to</p>
<p>both parties even at the stage when an application is being made for an extraction</p>
<p>permit that negotiations are to be held regarding an operating licence. If  this were not</p>
<p>the case, the Sami Parliament would have relinquished its opportunity pursuant to</p>
<p>section 30 of  the Minerals Act to oppose the award of  an extraction permit.</p>
<p>Item 4.2 clarifies that separate negotiations are to be held and agreements entered into</p>
<p>regarding actual exploration work, pilot extraction and plans to apply for an operating</p>
<p>licence. This complies with the Minerals Act’s structure and priority system. Existing</p>
<p>and traditional industries will have differing levels of  activity and efficiency when it</p>
<p>comes to actual exploration work, pilot extraction and operations. In addition, in most</p>
<p>cases it will be such that actual exploration work does not lead to plans to apply for an</p>
<p>operating licence and, if  operations become relevant, the exploration work that has</p>
<p>been carried out naturally sets the terms for how these are to be carried out. It is also</p>
<p>often  the  case  that  it  is  not  the  same  company  that  is  responsible  for  the  actual</p>
<p>exploration work and for the later operations. All this makes it most expedient to have</p>
<p>separate negotiations on the various activities.</p>
<p>Item 4.3 is new compared to the discussion paper. This item makes clear Statskog SF’s</p>
<p>duty to hold consultations pursuant to the agreement between the Government and</p>
<p>the Sami Parliament regarding ‘Procedures for consultations between state authorities</p>
<p>and the Sami Parliament’. According to this item, there are thus no direct negotiations</p>
<p>with the company that wants to explore for or have operations relating to minerals ad</p>
<p>ministered by Statskog SF. The negotiations here are with the state-owned enterprise that administers rights that are not recognised as belonging to the Sami. Item 4.3 uses</p>
<p>the concept of  consultation. This is because the item directly relates to the consultation</p>
<p>agreement. This does not mean that it is not just as crucial to the Sami Parliament to</p>
<p>reach agreement with Statskog SF as it is to reach agreement with companies that want</p>
<p>to have metals operations.</p>
<p>Item 4.4 is slightly different to §4, third paragraph of  the discussion paper. While the</p>
<p>discussion paper intended the Sami Parliament to be responsible for clarifying whether</p>
<p>other  parties  are  to  participate  in  the  negotiations,  it  is  now  stated  that  the  Sami</p>
<p>Parliament may clarify this. It will thus to a larger extent be up to the companies and</p>
<p>Statskog SF whether they want the Sami Parliament to contribute to such a coordination</p>
<p>or whether they wish to do this themselves, and if  relevant whether they want to</p>
<p>negotiate separately with the Sami Parliament and directly affected Sami interests. There</p>
<p>is nonetheless reason to warn against processes that may lead to a <span type="quote">“divide and conquer”</span></p>
<p>situation between the negotiating parties. In some circumstances, it may be desirable</p>
<p>and expedient for the Sami Parliament, as the Sami elected body, to also safeguard</p>
<p>directly affected Sami interests and local communities in the negotiations. If  this is to</p>
<p>take place, the group or gathering of  users must have given their informed consent to</p>
<p>the Sami Parliament safeguarding their interests.</p>
<p>Item 4.5 is also slightly different to §4, fourth paragraph of  the discussion paper. While</p>
<p>the discussion paper stated that the Sami Parliament was to be able to impose a fine to</p>
<p>ensure that negotiations were held, the guide now states that those that wish to conduct</p>
<p>actual exploration work and plan to apply for pilot extraction, an extraction permit or</p>
<p>an  operating  licence  for  metals  are  urged  to  cover  the  direct  costs  of   holding</p>
<p>negotiations.  It  is  assumed  that  the  companies  will  benefit  considerably  from</p>
<p>negotiations being held in a confidence-creating and efficient manner, which often</p>
<p>means there is a need for capacity for this. The coverage of  such costs will primarily</p>
<p>be of  interest to directly affected Sami interests and to a lesser extent to the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament. It is considered to be important that there is openness regarding and public</p>
<p>access to the way in which such costs are covered.</p>
<p>Re Item 5 Agreements and records</p>
<p>5.1  An  agreement  regarding  actual  exploration  work  and  agreement  regarding  pilot</p>
<p>extraction may cover the scope, exploration period, activity dates, access, storage of</p>
<p>equipment,  etc,  and  measures  to  prevent  harm  or  inconvenience  to  existing  and</p>
<p>traditional usage.</p>
<p>5.2  An agreement to apply for an operating licence may cover the extraction area, an</p>
<p>extraction plan, plan of  operations and the termination of  the agreement if  operations</p>
<p>do not start within a certain period or are suspended for a lengthy period. The agree</p>
<p>ment  may  include  measures  to  prevent  harm  or  inconvenience  to  existing  and</p>
<p>traditional usage.</p>
<p>5.3  A record of  the consultations with Statskog SF shall be prepared, stating whether the</p>
<p>parties have reached agreement and if  so what they have agreed is to be included in</p>
<p>the option and operations agreements with the company.</p>
<p>5.4  Conditions regarding compensation to benefit Sami culture, business and social life in</p>
<p>the form of  jobs, the strengthening of  the Sami language, the development of  expertise</p>
<p>and capacity, etc, are to be considered.</p>
<p>5.5  Conditions regarding and schemes for financial remuneration that comprises part of</p>
<p>the utility value of  exploration work and operations are to be considered.</p>
<p>5.6  A condition that the agreement is to be reviewed after a certain period of  time may be</p>
<p>stipulated. The agreement is to be reviewed before the licence is revised in accordance</p>
<p>with section 43 of  the Minerals Act.</p>
<p>5.7  If  no agreement on the planned work and applications is entered into, a negotiation</p>
<p>record is to be prepared and approved by the parties.</p>
<p>Item 5.1 deals with what agreements on actual exploration work and the pilot extraction</p>
<p>of  metals may cover. In addition to agreements on how activities may be carried out,</p>
<p>such  agreements  may  also  cover  measures  which  prevent  or  remedy  harm  or</p>
<p>inconvenience to existing and traditional use of  the area.</p>
<p>Item 5.2 deals with what operating licence agreements cover as regards the size of  the</p>
<p>area, plan of  operations and termination of  the agreement if  operations are not started</p>
<p>up. This item of  the guide states that an agreement regarding an application for an</p>
<p>operating licence is to be arrived at before an application is sent to the Directorate of</p>
<p>Mining and before comments are invited on the proposed land-use plan. This is because</p>
<p>the processing of  the operating licence application is usually coordinated with the plan</p>
<p>clarification pursuant to the Planning and Building Act and any agreements with the</p>
<p>landowner and those holding rights of  use.</p>
<p>Item 5.3 is new compared to the discussion paper. This precisely defines Statskog SF’s</p>
<p>duty to consult that follows from the ‘Procedures for consultations between state</p>
<p>authorities and the Sami Parliament’. This stipulates that the parties are to try to reach</p>
<p>consensus that is not to be set out in the form of  an agreement but instead in the form</p>
<p>of  a record. To the extent that no agreement is reached, this must also be recorded.</p>
<p>Contact here is not with the company directly but with the state-owned enterprise that</p>
<p>administers the minerals. If  the agreement reached by the Sami Parliament and Statskog</p>
<p>SF cannot be achieved in Statskog SF’s negotiations with the company, Statskog SF is</p>
<p>expected to return to the Sami Parliament for renewed consultations. Another pos</p>
<p>sibility is for Statskog SF and the Sami Parliament to hold consultations to reach agree</p>
<p>ment on some overarching principles which must form the basis for Statskog SF’s</p>
<p>administration of  industrial minerals, building raw materials and natural stone.</p>
<p>Item 5.4 deals with conditions of  a compensatory nature when measures may lead to</p>
<p>harm or inconvenience to or the repression of  Sami culture. This item corresponds to</p>
<p>the provision in §7, third sub-paragraph, cf  §4, second sub-paragraph, of  the Sami</p>
<p>Parliament’s guidelines for changes in the use of  uncultivated land in Finnmark, cf</p>
<p>section 4 of  the Finnmark Act. The great importance of  mineral operations to society</p>
<p>must be compared with the responsibility one has to safeguard Sami culture. Plans</p>
<p>which make it impossible or significantly more difficult to maintain Sami culture in the</p>
<p>area are under no circumstances permitted according to international law. According</p>
<p>to international law, a measure that entails villages and local communities being moved</p>
<p>also cannot be implemented without the express prior informed consent of  those</p>
<p>affected and the Sami Parliament. In cases where it may be disputed or unclear whether</p>
<p>plans or measures will lead to the exercise of  Sami culture in the area being impossible,</p>
<p>or where it is clear that the negative consequences for Sami culture are considerable,</p>
<p>measures of  a compensatory nature may be conditions which allow consent to be given</p>
<p>to the plan. The scope of  such conditions will be linked to the scope of  the measure and its effects on Sami culture, business development and social life. The opportunity</p>
<p>Item  5.5  must  be  considered  in  connection  with  item  5.4  of   the  mineral  guide.</p>
<p>Conditions concerning a financial payment that comprises part of  the utility value in</p>
<p>the case of  extraction and operations must always be considered. The size of  such a</p>
<p>payment will depend on the scope of  the activities and the effects that such activities</p>
<p>have on Sami culture and communities, especially those that are directly affected. The</p>
<p>payment will also depend on which other measures of  a compensatory nature the</p>
<p>parties can agree on pursuant to item 5.4 of  the guide. Item 5.5 also means that the</p>
<p>parties may agree on financial payment schemes. This means a large degree of  flexibility</p>
<p>regarding how a financial payment is to be determined, utilised and organised. This in</p>
<p>itself  may be a negotiation issue. Schemes which entail the establishment of  new enter</p>
<p>prises or institutions must be approved by the Sami Parliament in plenum. Under any</p>
<p>circumstances, it is to be assumed that such schemes comply with legal frameworks</p>
<p>and that there is transparency with regard to what they entail. Those who are directly</p>
<p>affected by mineral operations, who exercise forms of  collective use of  the area in</p>
<p>which a new enterprise is to be established and who in some other way are significantly</p>
<p>affected by the activities from a business, environmental, cultural or social point of</p>
<p>view, such as siida, regional associations and suchlike, will be those that such a payment</p>
<p>is primarily to benefit.</p>
<p>Item 5.6 makes it clear that further conditions regarding a review of  the agreement</p>
<p>may be stated in the agreement. This has been included so that the agreement may take</p>
<p>into account any conditions which the Directorate of  Mining includes in its operating</p>
<p>licences in accordance with section 43. Pursuant to this provision, the Directorate of</p>
<p>Mining may stipulate a time limit for the operating licence or a requirement that it is to</p>
<p>be reviewed after a certain time. The Directorate of  Mining may also require a review</p>
<p>of  the licence every 10 years irrespective of  that stated in the licensing conditions. The</p>
<p>opportunity to review agreements is also based on the need to change plans of  ope</p>
<p>rations as a result of  clear changes to the assumptions on which the extraction and</p>
<p>operations are based.</p>
<p>Item 5.7 makes it clear that if  negotiations do not result in the entry into of  an agree</p>
<p>ment to carry out further activities linked to the mineral resources, then a negotiation</p>
<p>record is to be prepared and approved by the parties. This is so that the negotiation</p>
<p>process is documented, can be subsequently accessed by the public and is available if</p>
<p>new initiatives relating to the same deposits in the same area should later arise.</p>
</body></document>