<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title> 
Untitled
</title>
    <genre code="ficti"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <wordcount>270</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <submitter name="Sindre Reino Trosterud" email="sindre.reino.trosterud@gmail.com"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="fkv" location="kafjord_voinko_toivoa.doc"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>-----------</p>
    <p>I'm tired of saying</p>
    <p>That I won't get lost Ever again Who knows,</p>
    <p>maybe I will And everywhere I go There I'll be</p>
    <p>with a rusty old rake</p>
    <p>In a pile of leaves,</p>
    <p>Oh my, truly daunting</p>
    <p>But my blue eyes cannot see That their real hue is probably green I should keep records of these things And I'll know what yesterdays bring</p>
    <p>And I'm not really sure But I'm starting to think That I've been here before Who knows, maybe I have</p>
    <p>And everywhere I went There I was</p>
    <p>with a choir of bees They were all abuzz Oh my,</p>
    <p>how amusing</p>
    <p>But my blue eyes cannot see That their real hue is probably green I should keep records of these things And I'll know what yesterdays bring</p>
    <p>But one time, there was this one time When I swore god, she spoke to me And she told me, oh yes, she told me Of all the wonders that she could bring</p>
    <p>And I said, won't you Won't you fill me up with it? Why don't you fill me up with it? Won't you fill me? Won't you Won't you fill me up with it? Why don't you fill me up with it? Why don't you fill me? Won't you Won't you fill me up with it? Why don't you fill me up with it? Why don't you fill me up? But my blue eyes cannot see That their real hue is probably green I will keep records of these things And I'll know what yesterdays bring</p>
    <p>I am always here with me And I'll know what yesterdays bring</p>
  </body>
</document>
