<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title/>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <translator>
      <unknown/>
    </translator>
    <translated_from xml:lang="fin"/>
    <wordcount>970</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index.php?option=com_docman&amp;task=doc_download&amp;gid=1856&amp;Itemid=10</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="juha_guttorm_sajos_3.4.2012_suomi.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="juha_guttorm_sajos_03042012_koltansaame.pdf"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 125457 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p xml:lang="fin">JUHA GUTTORM  Sajos 03 04 2012_in english</p>
    <p><em type="bold">SPEECH UPON INAUGURATION OF THE SAJOS SÁMI CULTURAL CENTRE 3rd APRIL 2012   </em></p>
    <p>Honourable President of the Republic of Finland, Mrs Haukio, buorit Sámedikkiid politihkalaš jođiheaddjit, dear guests!</p>
    <p>Sometimes,  one's  hopes  and  dreams  come  true.    This  is  particularly  so  if you remain true to your dreams and work  long term  to achieve them.  The decades-long  wish  of  the  Finnish  Sámi  for  a  cultural  centre  of  their  own has  now  been  fulfilled.    Today,  we  can  celebrate  the  inauguration  of  the centre and enjoy the fruits of our labour.</p>
    <p>Although  our  journey  to  this  wonderful  day  has  been  long,  sometimes exhausting,  it  has  been  an  inspiring  and  positive  experience.    To understand the  general picture, we  have to return to 1994. Then,  in  its  Bill for  the establishment of Sámi  cultural autonomy,  the Finnish  government stated  to  Parliament  that  it  "would  be  appropriate  to  provide  the forthcoming  Sámi  Parliament  with  its  own  premises,  like  those  of  the Norwegian  Sámi  Parliament  and  those  proposed  for  the  Swedish  Sámi Parliament.”  In line with this proposal, in 2000 the Sámi Parliament began preparations  for  the  Sajos  Sámi  Cultural  Centre  project.    As  a  result, multifaceted  and  rigorous  master  planning  was  carried  out  between  2000 and  2007.  This  work  was  chiefly  funded  from  EU  project  support  funds approved  by  EU  agencies  engaged  in  Lapland.    A  total  of  almost  one million,  two- hundred-thousand euros were  granted by EU Structural Fund programmes.</p>
    <p>After intensive preparatory work, project investment funding took shape in the spring of 2007, when the Region of Lapland granted five million euros of  EU  funding and the Finnish Government entered the project  in the state budget  for  2008  to  2011.    These  decisions  finally  put  the  project  on  a proper footing.  Senate Properties, a builder of public sector premises, took charge of the project's practical achievement in the autumn of 2007.</p>
    <p>As  project  planning  continued,  challenges  arose  in  reconciling  varying user requirements.  For example, this  hall, the  Dolla Auditorium,  needs to convert  into a  meeting and conference  facility, as well as a teaching room, and a  venue  for  musical, cinema and theatre performances.  Despite this, I think that  we succeeded well  in our planning  work.  Our special thanks  go to the  young designers of  Halo Architects, the winner of  the architectural competition, for their wonderful co-operation.</p>
    <p>The  building's  main  user  will  be  the  Sámi  Parliament,  with  the  Sámi Education  Institute as the second primary  user.  Other  users are  the Sámi Archive  (under  The  National  Archives  Service  of  Finland),  the  Sámi Library  (run  by  the  Municipality  of  Inari),  SámiSoster  (Sámi  Association for Health and Social Issues), Duodji Shop (which sells Sámi  handicrafts), the Anarâškiela servi association  for  the Inari Sámi  language,  the Lapland Regional State Administrative Agency and the Galla restaurant.</p>
    <p>Sajos is primarily intended for use by the Sámi.  It is meant as a symbol of Sámi autonomy and the living and evolving Sámi culture.  As such, its key purpose  is,  firstly, to  nurture traditional Sámi culture and, secondly, to see to  its renewal and development.   Sajos  is the Sámi parliament building, a versatile  activity  centre  and  a  meeting  place  and  forum.    This  is wonderfully  captured  by  the  building's  name  in  the  Inari  Sámi  language, Sajos.  Of old, this  word  refers  to a base or camp where people  met, and even  spent  longer  periods  of  time,  around  a  campfire.    The  name  was suggested by Matti Morottaja, an Inari Sámi.</p>
    <p>In  addition  to  its  main  purpose,  thanks  to  its  state-of-the-art,  high-quality meeting  rooms  and  ultramodern  studio  facilities,  Sajos  offers  excellent options  for  organising  various  meetings,  conferences  and  events  in  a unique environment.  In this way, Sajos will  revive  the area's business  life and reinforce its vitality in other ways.</p>
    <p>Already, on  the basis of a  few  months'  use,  I can confirm  that these aims are being  fulfilled.  Since the beginning of the  year, a range of events and meetings  have been  held  in Sajos.  So  much  interest  has been  raised on a wider  basis  that  it  receives  many  visitors  every  day,  including  from abroad.  In addition, the completion of Sajos has been a huge relief to both the Sámi Parliament and  its  secretariat.  After  many  years of  moving  from place to place, we can at last work in proper premises under the same roof, or even  sharing a  floor and  landing.  Of course, the same  is true of other users of the building.</p>
    <p>Honourable  President  of  the  Republic,  Mrs  Haukio,  dear  guests!    I  am aware that many hopes and demands are pinned on Sajos, among the Sámi and  in  wider circles  within the  region. Only after a  few  years' experience can  we  assess  how  well  the  building  works  in  practice  and  the  extent  to which  the  related  hopes  and  expectations  will  be  met.    However,  I  both hope  and  believe  that,  after  the  busy  running- in  period,  when  we  have properly  settled  into  the  building  and  ordered  our  papers  and  thoughts, those of us working from Sajos will be able to meet these challenges.</p>
    <p>Finally,  on  behalf  of  Sajos'  users  and  myself,  I  would  like  to  give  my warm thanks to the  individual actors and organisations that  influenced and participated  in the creation of Sajos; as well as the  funding bodies, Senate Properties, the Municipality of Inari, architectural and other designers, and supervisors and subcontractors.  My special thanks  go those who worked on  behalf  of  the  main  contractor,  Keski-Suomen  Betonirakenne,  for  their responsible,  service- minded  work.    In  every  case,  cooperation  has  been excellent.  Without you, the Sajos Sámi Cultural Centre would never  have moved off the drawing board.  My heartfelt thanks to you!</p>
    <p>May  Sajos  prove  useful  to  the  Sámi  and  other  citizens  and,  in  particular, may  it  inspire  enthusiasm  and  belief  in  younger  generations  of  Sámi,  in striving for the preservation and renewal of their own culture!</p>
    <p xml:lang="sms">Juha Guttorm,</p>
    <p>Director o f Administration</p>
  </body>
</document>
