<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Parliamentary Sessions Are Open to the Public - 
	Oikeusministeriö - Oikeusministeriö
</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2016</year><wordcount>220</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.oikeusministerio.fi/en/index/publications/esitteet/perustuslaki/eduskunnanistunnotovatjulkisia.html</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="eduskunnanistunnotovatjulkisia.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="riikkabeivviidcoahkkimatleatalmmolaccat.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Constitution</p>
<p type="title">Parliamentary Sessions Are Open to the Public</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">CHAPTER 4</p>
<p>The Parliament takes decisions in plenary sessions chaired by the Speaker or a Deputy Speaker. Only the Representatives may take part in a decision.</p>
<p>The plenary sessions are open to the public. They may be followed from the balcony of the assembly hall and in the media. The records of the parliamentary sessions are also public.</p>
<p>Only Representatives and ministers may speak during the plenary sessions. The Parliamentary Ombudsman and Chancellor of Justice may also speak if matters concerning them are considered.</p>
<p>In the Parliament an issue is raised either as a governmental bill or as a motion submitted by a Representative. At least fifty thousand Finnish citizens entitled to vote have the right to submit an initiative for the enactment of an Act to the Parliament.</p>
<p>Before a decision is taken all bills and motions are prepared by a select committee, i.e. by an internal preparatory body of the Parliament. Its work is not public until it publishes its report or statement. A group of at least twenty Representatives may address an interpellation to the Government. After a discussion about the reply of the Government, the Parliament takes a vote on whether the Government enjoys its confidence.</p>
<p>A Representative may address an oral or written question to a minister.</p>
</body></document>
