<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="fin"/><wordcount>1743</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index.php?option=com_docman&amp;task=doc_download&amp;gid=1325&amp;Itemid=10</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="liite_15_sp_suomi.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="mielddus_15_sprpohjoissaame.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 125457 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="deu">9 September 2010 Docket:</p>
<p><em type="bold">The Saami Parliamentary Council's proposal for the European Union target for biodiversity by 2020 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">1. Introduction </em></p>
<p>The  Saami  are  the  only  indigenous  people  in  the  European  Union,  whose  legal  status  has  been acknowledged in the Accession Treaty of Sweden and Finland. The Saami live in Finland, Sweden, Norway  and  Russia.  The  total  Saami  population  is  estimated  to  be  between  75,000  and  100,000 depending  on  the  method  of  calculation.  The  Saami  people's  Rights  of  Indigenous  People  are  an integral part of European Union's internal and external policies. In Sweden, Norway and Finland, the Saami are represented by the elected Saami Parliament. In Russia, there is no elected body, but the Saami are represented by Saami organisations. The Saami Parliamentary Council (SPC) is a cooperational body for the Saami Parliaments of Finland, Sweden and Norway, established to secure the  legal  position  of  the  Saami  especially  regarding  international  issues.  Russian  Saami organisations participate as spectators.</p>
<p>The  United  Nations  Convention  on  Biological  Diversity  (CBD)  was  opened  for  signature  at  the 1992 United Nations Conference on Environment and Development (UNCED) in Rio de Janeiro. Finland,  Sweden  and  Norway  have  ratified  the  convention.  The  goal  of  the  Convention  on Biological  Diversity  is  to  promote  the  conservation  of  ecosystems,  plant  and  animal  species  and their genetic diversity, the sustainable use of natural resources, and the fair and equitable sharing of benefits arising out of the utilization of genetic resources. The European Union participates in the execution of the Convention on Biological Diversity.</p>
<p>Articles 8 (j), 10 (c) and 15 of the convention refer to the rights of indigenous peoples. Article 8 (j) obliges  the  parties  to  protect  traditional  knowledge,  innovations  and  practices  related  to  the biological  diversity  of  indigenous  peoples. iArticle  10  (c)  obliges  the  parties  to  protect  and encourage  the  customary  use  of  biological  resources  in  accordance  with  traditional  cultural practices compatible with conservation and sustainable requirementsii. Article 15 obliges the parties to encourage the equitable sharing of the benefits arising out of the utilization of genetic resources.iii</p>
<p>The European Commission has communicated options for an EU vision and target for biodiversity beyond  2010  to  the  European  Parliament,  the  Council,  the  European  Economic  and  Social Committee, and the Committee of the Regions. The Saami Parliamentary Council was not invited to participate in the preparation of this communication.</p>
<p><em type="bold">2. The Saami Parliamentary Council's proposal </em></p>
<p>On 20 November 2008, the Commission's Communication on the European Union and the Arctic Region  was  approved.  In  its  Communication,  the  European  Union  commits  to  uninterrupted dialogue with the indigenous peoples of the Arctic Region.</p>
<p>In 2007, the UN General Assembly adopted the Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoplesiv. All EU Member States and Norway voted in favour of the Declaration. The Declaration guarantees indigenous peoples the right to self-determinationv and the right to participate in decision-making in matters  affecting  them.vi  The  Saami  Parliamentary  Council  is  of  the  opinion  that  the  European</p>
<p>Union is to implement the declaration on the rights of indigenous peoples in its internal and external policies,  and  to  ensure  that  the  Saami  can  influence  the  decision-making  processes  regarding  the convention  on  biodiversity  to  the  extent  intended  by  the  declaration  on  the  rights  of  indigenous peoples.  The  SPC  emphasises  Article  31  of  the  Declaration,  in  particular,  which  guarantees  the Saami people the right to their cultural heritage, genetic resources and traditional knowledgevii. The Article complements the obligations laid down by the CBD.</p>
<p>The Saami Parliamentary Council insists that the European Commission enters into uninterrupted dialogue  with  the  Saami  Parliamentary  Council  in  accordance  with  the  Commission's Communication  and  the  Declaration  on  the  Rights  of  Indigenous  Peoples  concerning  the preparation of the EU target for biodiversity. The SPC further insists that the EU negotiates with the Parliamentary Council when EU opinions are being formulated in the meetings of different parties. The Saami Parliamentary Council would like to point out that the EU and EEA Member States as well  as  the  Commission  are  obliged  to  ensure  indigenous  peoples  have  influence  over  decisions concerning themselves.</p>
<p>The Saami Parliamentary Council suggests the following items be considered in the EU target for biodiversity:</p>
<p>o  The  European  Union  will  commit  to  stopping  the  loss  of  biodiversity  and  ecosystem services  in  the  EU  by  2020.  Furthermore,  the  EU  shall  revive  endangered  ecosystems through  its  internal  and  external  policies  by  securing  guidance  and  financing  and  by participating in international decision-making on preserving natural biodiversity. Executing the Convention on Biodiversity will penetrate all EU actions.</p>
<p>o  In its 2010 biodiversity target, the EU shall take into consideration the rights of indigenous peoples  in  accordance  with  the  CBD  and  UN  Declaration  on  the  Rights  of  Indigenous Peoples, and promote these rights in its internal and external policies.</p>
<p>o  The  EU  shall  enter  into  continuous  dialogue  with  the  Saami  Parliamentary  Council regarding  actions  concerning  biodiversity,  secure  the  Saami  the  opportunity  to  have influence over decisions concerning themselves, and advise its Member States to secure the rights of indigenous peoples in their respective actions aimed at preserving biodiversity.</p>
<p>o  The EU establishes a dedicated unit to execute and coordinate the Convention on Biological Diversity  and  nominates  the  coordinators  to  promote  the  execution  of  Article  8  (j)  as  per decisions made in the COP-10.</p>
<p>o  The EU secures sustainable financing of actions aimed at preserving biodiversity. Financing is to secure the implementation of Articles 8 (j), 10 (c) and 15, in particular, and the Saami language  and  traditional  lifestyles  as  carriers  of  traditional  knowledge.  To  preserve biodiversity, the EU financing tools are to take notice of securing and protecting traditional knowledge linked to biological natural resources.</p>
<p>The  Saami  Parliamentary  Council  is  particularly  concerned  about  the  situation  of  the  Saami languages.  The  Saami  language  conveys  traditional  knowledge  from  one  generation  to  the  next. Thus, the vitality of the language is essential for the preservation of traditional Saami knowledge. The Saami Parliamentary Council ascribes the duty to secure the future of the Saami language in part  also  to  the  European  Union  and  suggests  the  issue  be  integrated  into  the  EU  target  for biodiversity. The Saami Parliamentary Council trusts the Commission and EU Member States will take the proposals of the Saami Parliamentary Council into consideration and will secure the rights of indigenous peoples. It is the wish of the Saami Parliamentary Council that following this the EU, its  Member  States  and  the  Saami  Parliamentary  Council  will  engage  in  close  co-operation  to preserve  the  nature's  biodiversity  and  to  promote  the  rights  of  indigenous  peoples.  The  Saami Parliamentary Council expects to receive your reply at your earliest convenience. The Secretariat of the Saami Parliament will be happy to provide additional information.</p>
<p>Inari, 9 September 2010</p>
<p>Klemetti N채kk채l채j채rvi   Rauna Rahko The Saami Parliamentary     The Saami Parliamentary  Council, President   Council, Secretary</p>
<p>Distribution: European Commission Finnish Ministry of the Environment Norwegian Ministry of the Environment Swedish Ministry of the Environment</p>
<p>Appendices: The Saami Parliamentary Council's Climate Policy Strategy</p>
<p>i  8(j) Subject to its national legislation, respect, preserve and maintain knowledge, innovations and practices of</p>
<p>indigenous and local communities embodying traditional lifestyles relevant for the conservation and sustainable use of biological diversity and promote their wider application with the approval and involvement of the holders of such knowledge, innovations and practices and encourage the equitable sharing of the benefits arising from the utilization of such knowledge, innovations and practices; ii  (c) Protect and encourage customary use of biological resources in accordance with traditional cultural</p>
<p>practices that are compatible with conservation or sustainable use requirements. iii  1. Recognizing the sovereign rights of States over their natural resources, the authority to determine access to</p>
<p>genetic resources rests with the national governments and is subject to national legislation. 2. Each Contracting Party shall endeavour to create conditions to facilitate access to genetic resources for environmentally sound uses by other Contracting Parties and not to impose restrictions that run counter to the objectives of this Convention. 3. For the purpose of this Convention, the genetic resources being provided by a Contracting Party, as referred to in this Article and Articles 16 and 19, are only those that are provided by Contracting Parties that are countries of origin of such resources or by the Parties that have acquired the genetic resources in accordance with this Convention. 4. Access, where granted, shall be on mutually agreed terms and subject to the provisions of this Article. 5. Access to genetic resources shall be subject to prior informed consent of the Contracting Party providing such resources, unless otherwise determined by that Party. 6. Each Contracting Party shall endeavour to develop and carry out scientific research based on genetic resources provided by other Contracting Parties with the full participation of, and where possible in, such Contracting Parties. 7. Each Contracting Party shall take legislative, administrative or policy measures, as appropriate, and in accordance with Articles 16 and 19 and, where necessary, through the financial mechanism established by Articles 20 and 21 with the aim of sharing in a fair and equitable way the results of research and development</p>
<p>and the benefits arising from the commercial and other utilization of genetic resources with the Contracting Party providing such resources. Such sharing shall be upon mutually agreed terms. iv  A/RES/61/295 v   Article 3: Indigenous peoples have the right to self-determination. By virtue of that right they freely</p>
<p>determine their political status and freely pursue their economic, social and cultural development. vi  Article 18:</p>
<p>Indigenous peoples have the right to participate in decision-making in matters which would affect their rights, through representatives chosen by themselves in accordance with their own procedures, as well as to maintain and develop their own indigenous decision-making institutions. Article 19: States shall consult and cooperate in good faith with the indigenous peoples concerned through their own representative institutions in order to obtain their free, prior and informed consent before adopting and implementing legislative or administrative measures that may affect them. vii  Article 31:</p>
<p>1. Indigenous peoples have the right to maintain, control, protect and develop their cultural heritage, traditional knowledge and traditional cultural expressions, as well as the manifestations of their sciences, technologies and cultures, including human and genetic resources, seeds, medicines, knowledge of the properties of fauna and flora, oral traditions, literatures, designs, sports and traditional games and visual and performing arts. They also have the right to maintain, control, protect and develop their intellectual property over such cultural heritage, traditional knowledge, and traditional cultural expressions. 2. In conjunction with indigenous peoples, States shall take effective measures to recognize and protect the exercise of these rights.</p>
</body></document>