<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Subject curriculum in Sami as the first language - Sami 1</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>5002</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.udir.no/Upload/larerplaner/Fastsatte_lareplaner_for_Kunnskapsloeftet/english/5/Subject_curriculum_in_sami_as_the_first_language_sami_1.doc</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="laereplan_samisk_foerstespraak.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="laereplan_samisk_foerstespraak.odt"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="laereplan_samisk_foerstespraak.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smj" location="laereplan_samisk_foerstespraak.odt"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p>Sami first-language subject curriculum in Knowledge Promotion – Sami, established by the Sami Parliament 20 April 2006</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">SUBJECT CURRICULUM IN SAMI AS THE FIRST LANGUAGE</p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">SAMI 1 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">The objectives of the subject </em></p>
<p>The Sami are one people even if they live in different countries, and their language unifies the Sami across national borders. The Sami language is an important culture bearer and embeds common values, experiences and knowledge. Sami is an official language in Norway, Sweden and Finland, and it is a goal that the Sami language shall be preserved and developed for coming generations. Sami is also a minority language in Norway, Sweden, Finland and Russia, and the situation and conditions for the Sami language are not the same in the different areas of <em type="italic">Sápmi/Sábme/Saepmie, </em>the name of the Sami areas. In some Sami communities Sami is the majority language, in others it is a minority language. </p>
<p>Sami language education shall contribute to making children and young persons members of Sami culture and social life, where cultural understanding, communication, formal education and identity development are key elements of the teaching. Education that promotes positive attitudes to the Sami language, and which considers the linguistic and cultural diversity the pupils experience, will provide the pupils with multilingual and multicultural competence and linguistic self-confidence that constitutes the basis for active social participation and lifelong learning. Solid Sami language skills provide opportunities when it comes to education and employment.</p>
<p>Together with the Norwegian subject, Sami as a first language shall form the basis for developing the bilingual skills of the pupils, and contribute to giving each and every pupil knowledge, motivation and confidence to preserve, strengthen and develop the language in writing and orally. By preserving central values in Sami culture the subject may also help to show how Sami values can be developed and adapted to new situations in a time of continuous change. Knowledge about other indigenous peoples and cultures may contribute to increasing one's respect and understanding of others and also to a better understanding of one's own culture.</p>
<p>The pupils must be encouraged to experience, create, work creatively on and develop their aesthetic nature through active use of the language. The subject shall develop each pupil's language and text competence, based on the pupil's aptitudes and experiences, and stimulate good learning strategies and the ability to think critically. The subject shall also motivate the development of enjoyment in reading and writing, and good reading and writing habits. Through the encounter with Sami literature and different Sami languages and dialects pupils may develop their understanding of the linguistic and cultural diversity of Sami communities.</p>
<p>If the pupils are to develop their Sami competence optimally, it is important that they use different linguistic arenas. The Sami as a first language subject may also be useful as a tool in other subjects. The subjects Sami and Norwegian have many common elements, and it is thus important that there is close cooperation between them.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Main subject areas </em></p>
<p>The subject has been structured into main subject areas with competence aims. These main subject areas supplement each other and must be considered together.</p>
<p>This subject is a common core subject for all the upper secondary education programmes. Learning in this subject shall therefore be made as relevant as possible for pupils by adapting each subject to its education programme as much as possible.</p>
<p>Sami as a first language has competence aims after the second, fourth, seventh and tenth years in primary and lower secondary school and after the first year (Vg1), second year (Vg2) and third year (Vg3) in the programmes for general studies.</p>
<p>In vocational education programmes the total number of teaching hours in Sami in Vg1and Vg2 will be lower than in Vg1 programmes for general studies. Competence aims marked with an asterisk (*) in Vg1 do not apply to pupils in vocational education programmes.</p>
<p>Overview of main subject areas:</p>
<p><em type="bold">Year of school </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Main subject areas </em></p>
<p xml:lang="vep">1 - 10</p>
<p>First year (Vg1) – Third year (Vg3)</p>
<p>Oral communication</p>
<p>Written communication</p>
<p>Traditional knowledge</p>
<p>Language usage</p>
<p>Oral communication</p>
<p>In the main subject area <em type="italic">oral communication </em>being able to listen and speak are key elements. Speaking Sami means communicating orally in active participation in many and different arenas. This is developed through playing and games, experiences, learning, presentations and interacting with others. When new and various media are taken into use, the linguistic repertoire increases across subjects and topics. This main subject area also includes developing interpretation competence. </p>
<p>Written communication</p>
<p>The main subject area <em type="italic">written communication </em>focuses on reading and writing, on understanding the texts of others and being able to communicate in writing with others. Reading and writing are parallel processes in the individual's learning progress. Language skills and textual understanding are developed through listening, reading and writing, and literature is a natural part of this. This main subject area includes working with different texts, written texts, pictorial texts and sound texts. Experience, critical evaluation, text analysis and creating one's own texts are all part of this main subject area. Literature gives common experiences that can be talked about and studied, while pupils also learn about language and culture. </p>
<p>Traditional knowledge</p>
<p>The main subject area <em type="italic">traditional knowledge </em>focuses on developing the language in connection with traditional use of concepts and terms. Transferring traditional knowledge from one generation to the next is an important part of this. The Sami narrative tradition, <em type="italic">joik </em>(Sami chant), songs and hymns, <em type="italic">diiddat/dijda </em>1 and proverbs are part of traditional knowledge. The main subject area also includes which functions such values as family relationships, <em type="italic">birgejupmi/bierggim/bïerkenidh </em>2 and learning through active participation have had and have, and how these are adapted and developed. </p>
<p>The language in use</p>
<p>The main subject area <em type="italic">the language in use </em>focuses on acquiring knowledge about how language works when people interact. This includes knowledge about the history, form and structure of the Sami languages. Knowledge about the language is developed by using it, and linguistic competence strengthens the understanding of how we learn a language. </p>
<p><em type="bold">Teaching hours </em></p>
<p>Teaching hours are given in 60-minute units.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">PRIMARY SCHOOL</p>
<p>Years 1 to 7: 916 teaching hours</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">LOWER SECONDARY SCHOOL</p>
<p>Years 8 to 10:</p>
<p>Alternative 1: 335 teaching hours, applies to pupils who do not choose a foreign language/in-depth language study</p>
<p>Alternative 2: 278 teaching hours, applies to pupils who choose a foreign language/in-depth language study</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">PROGRAMMES FOR GENERAL STUDIES</p>
<p>Vg1: 103 teaching hours</p>
<p>Vg2: 103 teaching hours</p>
<p>Vg3: 103 teaching hours</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">VOCATIONAL EDUCATION PROGRAMMES</p>
<p>Vg1: 45 teaching hours</p>
<p>Vg2: 45 teaching hours</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">SUPPLEMENTARY STUDIES QUALIFYING FOR HIGHER EDUCATION FOR VOCATIONAL EDUCATION PROGRAMMES:</p>
<p>Vg3: 219 teaching hours</p>
<p><em type="bold">Basic skills </em></p>
<p>Basic skills are integrated in the competence aims where they contribute to the development of competence in the subject, while also being part of this competence. In the subject curriculum for Sami as a first language, the basic skills are understood as follows:</p>
<p><em type="italic">Being able to express oneself orally </em>in Sami as a first language means having the ability to listen and speak and to be able to assess the elements in a complex verbal situation, which is a requirement for communication with others when it comes to social interaction, working life and participation in public life. Speaking and listening are fundamental human activities, which in the subject of Sami as a first language are developed through systematic training in various oral genres and activities. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Being able to express oneself in writing </em><em type="italic"></em>in Sami as a first language is a primary area of the subject from the initial teaching in writing and continuing through the 13 years of teaching this. Language is used more and more in its written form in society, not least through the development of digital communication forms, and the demand for mastering written presentation in various genres has increased. Writing is a way of developing and structuring ideas and thoughts, but it is also a communication form and a method for learning. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Being able to read </em>in Sami as a first language means developing decoding skills and gradually improving understanding of what is read. Encountering texts from different genres and with various levels of difficulty will contribute to developing textual competence and appropriate reading strategies. Understanding what is read depends on cultural reference frameworks, while reading develops communicative skills and cultural understanding. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Having skills in mathematics </em><em type="italic"></em>in Sami as a first language is together with language competence a requirement for concept development, logical reasoning and problem solving. The special Sami measurement units and mathematical methods are also a natural part of this. Moreover, skills in mathematics require understanding of form, system and composition. Thus basic mathematical skills help develop competence in Sami. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Being able to use digital tools </em>in Sami as a first language is necessary to master new text forms and expressions. This opens for new learning arenas and allows new possibilities in the teaching of reading and writing, and for the production, composition and editing of texts. In this context it is vital to develop the ability to critically assess and use sources. Digital tools provide new opportunities to use traditional Sami knowledge and may support and develop communication skills and presentations. </p>
<p><em type="bold">Competence aims in the subject </em></p>
<p>Competence aims after Year 2</p>
<p>Oral communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">play and experiment with rhyme, rules, rhythm, sounds and words</p>
<p type="listitem">express and tell others cohesively about his or her own feelings, experiences and opinions</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">talk about pictures and cartoons and tell others stories with pictures</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">listen, praise and ask questions when others tell stories and read</p>
</list><p>Written communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">recognise language sounds and write small and capital letters</p>
<p type="listitem">talk about what words, sentences, full stops and question marks are</p>
<p type="listitem">split words into syllables</p>
<p type="listitem">use letters and experiment with words when writing longhand and when using a keyboard</p>
<p type="listitem">tell others about the direction principle and discuss ways of writing in other places in the world</p>
<p type="listitem">write poems and present them</p>
<p type="listitem">find fiction and fact books in the library for his or her own reading</p>
</list><p>Traditional knowledge</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">talk about persons and plots in Sami fairytales and stories</p>
<p type="listitem">use terms for close family relations and tell others what <em type="italic">gáibmi/gájmme </em>3 means </p>
<p type="listitem">express him-/herself by dramatising through song, <em type="italic">joik </em>, verse and fairytales </p>
</list><p>The language in use</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">talk about how the local community might be used to learn Sami words and methods of expression</p>
<p type="listitem">recognise some words in his or her own dialect that are similar or different from another dialect.</p>
</list><p>Competence aims after Year 4</p>
<p>Oral communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">use different oral expressions that are appropriate for the situation</p>
<p type="listitem">present texts</p>
<p type="listitem">talk about how language usage may have positive and negative effects</p>
<p type="listitem">listen to, read and present different fiction texts based on his or her own interests and talk about them</p>
</list><p>Written communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">read texts that are appropriate for his or her age with flow, cohesion and understanding of the content</p>
<p type="listitem">set-up texts with title, introduction and conclusion</p>
<p type="listitem">write with flowing and functional handwriting</p>
<p type="listitem">recognise and use some language techniques in his or her own texts</p>
<p type="listitem">compose stories, poems, letters and factual prose</p>
<p type="listitem">find material for his or her own writing and other tasks in the library and on the internet and create, save and retrieve texts using digital tools</p>
</list><p>Traditional knowledge</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">use terms for family relationships</p>
<p type="listitem">talk about names from the animal realm pertaining to Sami industries such as reindeer herding, animal husbandry, fishing and hunting</p>
<p type="listitem">talk about local Sami names of places and their importance and meaning, and compare with Norwegian and other place names if these places also have such names</p>
<p type="listitem">use traditional stories in his or her own work</p>
</list><p>The language in use</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">explain and demonstrate using examples of how words may be derived</p>
<p type="listitem">describe language and language usage, word classes and their functions</p>
<p type="listitem">use the most important spelling rules</p>
<p type="listitem">discuss what multilingualism means</p>
</list><p>Competence aims after Year 7</p>
<p>Oral communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">perform in various linguistic roles through role play and drama, reading out loud, interviews and presentations</p>
<p type="listitem">chair a meeting</p>
<p type="listitem">listen to others, express standpoints and give grounds for them and show respect for others' opinions</p>
<p type="listitem">present material orally with or without aids</p>
<p type="listitem">discuss how language may express and create attitudes to individuals and groups of people</p>
<p type="listitem">use Sami words and terms consciously</p>
<p type="listitem">read long fiction texts, literature for children and young people and factual prose and express understanding and experiences from reading</p>
<p type="listitem">read stories by other indigenous peoples and compare with Sami fairytales and stories</p>
</list><p>Written communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">use various reading strategies in reading different types of texts at varied speeds</p>
<p type="listitem">develop his or her own texts from idea to product, and asses the development of the text based on response</p>
<p type="listitem">present his or her own experiences as a reader of fiction and textbooks and use these experiences as the basis for his or her own written work</p>
<p type="listitem">asses his or her own texts and those of others</p>
<p type="listitem">use sources and reference literature when working with texts</p>
<p type="listitem">write cohesively with personal and functional handwriting</p>
<p type="listitem">use digital word processors in writing processes and production of interactive texts</p>
<p type="listitem">use the library, Sami reference literature, Sami media and digital information channels in a deliberate way</p>
</list><p>Traditional knowledge</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">use words and terms for weather and outdoor conditions, and tell others about days marked on the calendar stick and weather signs</p>
<p type="listitem">collect information from his or her local neighbourhood about <em type="italic">diiddat/dijda </em>and sayings about how these are used on a day-to-day basis </p>
<p type="listitem">use words and terms connected to traditional work tasks and discuss what <em type="italic">birgejupmi/bierggim/bïerkenidh </em>is </p>
</list><p>The language in use</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">explain how word derivations and composite words are made and how to adapt loan words</p>
<p type="listitem">demonstrate how language changes in relation to situation, time and place</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">distinguish between complete sentences and subordinate clauses and use different sentence constructions</p>
<p type="listitem">structure text according to chronological order and theme and create cohesion between sentences and paragraphs</p>
<p type="listitem">explain how the majority languages have influenced and continue to influence the Sami language</p>
<p type="listitem">describe characteristics of his or her own dialect in relation to the written language</p>
<p type="listitem">tell others about the language areas in <em type="italic">Sápmi/Sábme/Saepmie </em>4 </p>
</list><p>Competence aims after Year 10</p>
<p>Oral communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">tell others about different communication forms and how linguistic and cultural variations influence communication</p>
<p type="listitem">discuss how to protect the language</p>
<p type="listitem">chair and keep minutes from meetings and discussions, express his or her own opinions and assess what is factual argumentation</p>
<p type="listitem">discuss, elaborate on and explain multilingualism and multicultural belonging</p>
<p type="listitem">carry out simple lectures, presentations, interpretative readings, role play and dramatisation adapted to different recipients</p>
<p type="listitem">assess his or her own oral presentations and those of others</p>
<p type="listitem">tell others about books and authors based on his or her own interests and argue for book choices</p>
<p type="listitem">read and compare Sami literature and that of other indigenous peoples</p>
<p type="listitem">assess techniques in advertising and entertainment media and reflect upon their influence</p>
</list><p>Written communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">present his or her own reading experiences and reading perceptions based on interpretation and reflection</p>
<p type="listitem">recognise different linguistic techniques and use them in his or her own texts</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">plan and complete a written project from idea to finished product and asses his or her own text and written development using knowledge about language and text</p>
<p type="listitem">express him-/herself precisely with a varied and nuanced vocabulary in various types of text</p>
<p type="listitem">use word processors for filing and systematising his or her own work</p>
<p type="listitem">use texts taken from libraries, the internet and mass media in a critical manner, discuss the texts and acknowledge sources used</p>
<p type="listitem">read and write texts in different genres, including fiction and factual prose</p>
<p type="listitem">elaborate on the main periods of Sami literary history and tell others about authors and classics in Sami literature</p>
<p type="listitem">present the result of in-depth studies of a topic of his or her choice</p>
</list><p>Traditional knowledge</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">compare traditional Sami texts with modern texts</p>
</list><p type="listitem">use words, concepts and terms that relate to nature</p>
<p type="listitem">compare Sami sayings with Norwegian ones</p>
<p>The language in use</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">master spelling and orthography and common text-splitting methods</p>
<p type="listitem">explain word classes, conjugation rules, word derivations and the basic principles of syntax when working with language and texts</p>
<p type="listitem">discuss and elaborate on how to protect the language and its development</p>
<p type="listitem">identify the Sami languages and tell others about the similarities and differences between them and tell others about the Finno-Ugric languages</p>
<p type="listitem">elaborate on rights relating to Sami languages</p>
</list><p><em type="bold">Competence aims after Vg1 – programmes for general studies </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Competence aims after Vg2 – vocational education programmes </em></p>
<p>Oral communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">master various oral roles in group discussions, lectures, dramatisations, presentations and performances as the actor and as a listener</p>
<p type="listitem">explain what things influence communication, including factors that promote and impede communication</p>
<p type="listitem">use specialised knowledge from programme subjects in specialist communication</p>
<p type="listitem">interpret from Norwegian to Sami in day-to-day situations</p>
<p type="listitem">discuss the terms <em type="italic">native language, bilingualism and functional bilingualism </em>based on his or her own language situation and his or her own experiences and assess his or her own language skills in a number of languages and in different language contexts </p>
<p type="listitem">discuss linguistic and aesthetic techniques in literature, TV shows and fairytales and compare them with each other</p>
</list><p>Written communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">read texts and talk with others about what he or she has read</p>
<p type="listitem">master spelling rules when working with his or her own texts</p>
<p type="listitem">master different writer roles in the school's public space and in societal and working life</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">translate his or her own texts from Norwegian into Sami</p>
<p type="listitem">write creative texts in different genres</p>
<p type="listitem">use digital tools to systematise and file texts and for presentation and publication of his or her own work</p>
<p type="listitem">use a wide range of linguistic techniques in his or her own writing of both fiction and factual prose *</p>
<p type="listitem">read and analyze a representative selection of texts, fiction and factual prose, from the period after 1995 *</p>
</list><p>Traditional knowledge</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">elaborate on how stories, sayings, <em type="italic">diiddat </em>and <em type="italic">nárrideapmi </em>(socializing and teasing each other) are used in bringing up children </p>
<p type="listitem">elaborate on different varieties of fairytales and examples of traces of cultural exchange in the fairytales</p>
</list><p>The language in use</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">explain how new words and terms in Sami are developed and about the use and adaptation of loan words</p>
<p type="listitem">use words and expressions connected to traditional and modern working life and propose and assess new terms</p>
<p type="listitem">explain grammatical features of Sami languages and compare with other languages and explain the consequences this has in translation work *</p>
<p type="listitem">identify variations within the Sami languages *</p>
<p type="listitem">use words and expressions connected to traditional and modern working life, propose and assess new terms</p>
</list><p>Competence aims after Vg2 – programmes for general studies</p>
<p>Oral communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">use specialised knowledge from his or her own programme subjects in lectures and discussions on school, society and working life</p>
<p type="listitem">assess and give feedback on his or her own presentations and those of others</p>
<p type="listitem">interpret matters relating to school from Norwegian into Sami</p>
<p type="listitem">analyse, discuss and elaborate on communication methods and strategies in Sami communities before and now</p>
<p type="listitem">compare the texts of Sami and other indigenous peoples and assess the importance of the texts for cultural and identity development</p>
<p type="listitem">talk about the main periods in Sami literary history and compare with Nordic literary history</p>
</list><p>Written communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">read simple texts in the other Sami languages</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">read texts written with older orthography and compare to current orthography</p>
<p type="listitem">analyse texts from different genres to take a stance on the issues raised by the texts and the values they represent</p>
<p type="listitem">select appropriate genres, techniques and language usage when producing text</p>
<p type="listitem">describe and assess his or her own reading and writing strategies</p>
<p type="listitem">read and analyse a representative sample of literature and texts, fiction and factual prose, relating to the period before 1965</p>
</list><p>Traditional knowledge</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">elaborate on the tradition of   <em type="italic">joik  </em> and its status, value and situation before and now   </p>
</list><p type="listitem">compare Sami and Norwegian song and hymn traditions</p>
<p>The language in use</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">elaborate on Sami language history</p>
<p type="listitem">discuss how the status of the language in society has influenced Sami language skills, bilingualism and self-confidence</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">assess the language provision of the Sami Act and the establishment of the Sami Parliament in relation to the language situation and bilingualism</p>
<p type="listitem">discuss and elaborate on how the school, society and working life might support bilingualism</p>
<p type="listitem">use sentence analysis and grammar terminology when describing language</p>
</list><p><em type="bold">Competence aims after Vg3 – programmes for general studies </em></p>
<p>Oral communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">interpret and apply knowledge on interpretation in practical interpretation situations</p>
<p type="listitem">talk about ways of communicating in different cultures</p>
<p type="listitem">compare and assess the fiction texts and factual prose of Sami and other indigenous peoples in a cultural context</p>
</list><p><em type="bold">Written communication </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">carry out and present an in-depth study on a linguistic, literary or other Sami topic of his or her own choice</p>
<p type="listitem">examine ideologies in texts and assess sources and media</p>
<p type="listitem">translate and adapt texts by others from Norwegian into Sami</p>
<p type="listitem">write technical texts in accordance with common norms for this type of text</p>
<p type="listitem">write texts with a clear structure, focus and objective argumentation</p>
<p type="listitem">read and analyse a representative sample of literature and texts, fiction and factual, from the period 1965 to 1995 and discuss how the social and cultural characteristics of the period are reflected in the texts</p>
</list><p>Traditional knowledge</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">elaborate on Sami narrative traditions</p>
<p type="listitem">tell others fairytales by using elements from the Sami narrative traditions</p>
<p type="listitem">compare Sami fairytales with those of other indigenous peoples and fairytales from other cultures</p>
</list><p>The language in use</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">listen to and read texts from the other Sami languages and discuss similarities and dissimilarities</p>
<p type="listitem">compare the main features of Sami language history with the history of the Nordic languages</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">assess the position of the Sami languages in society and compare with the language situation for other indigenous peoples</p>
<p type="listitem">discuss aspects of Sami language policy and cultural development</p>
<p type="listitem">elaborate on the relationship between spoken and written languages</p>
</list><p>Competence aims after the supplementary studies qualifying for higher education – vocational education programmes</p>
<p>Oral communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">use specialised knowledge from his or her own programme subjects in presentations and discussions on school, society and working life</p>
<p type="listitem">assess and give feedback on his or her own presentations and those of others</p>
<p type="listitem">analyse and elaborate on communication methods and strategies in Sami society before and now</p>
<p type="listitem">talk about ways of communicating in different cultures</p>
<p type="listitem">interpret and apply knowledge on interpretation in practical interpretation situations</p>
<p type="listitem">talk about the main periods in Sami literary history and compare with Nordic literary history</p>
<p type="listitem">compare the texts of Sami and other indigenous peoples and assess the importance of the texts for cultural and identity development</p>
<p type="listitem">compare and assess the fictional and factual texts of the Sami and other indigenous peoples in a cultural context</p>
</list><p>Written communication</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">use a wide range of linguistic techniques in his or her own writing of both fiction and factual prose</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">select appropriate genres, aesthetic techniques and language usage when producing text</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">read simple texts in the other Sami languages</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">read texts written with older orthography and compare to current orthography</p>
<p type="listitem">describe and assess his or her own reading and writing strategies</p>
<p type="listitem">carry out and present a selected in-depth study on a linguistic, literary or other Sami topic</p>
<p type="listitem">examine ideologies in texts and assess sources and media</p>
<p type="listitem">translate and adapt texts by others from Norwegian into Sami</p>
<p type="listitem">write technical texts in accordance with common norms for this type of text</p>
<p type="listitem">write texts with a clear structure, focus and objective argumentation</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">read and analyse a representative selection of literature and texts, fiction and factual, from the period before 1965</p>
<p type="listitem">read and analyse a representative selection of literature and texts, fiction and factual, from the period 1965 to 1995 and discuss how the social and cultural characteristics of the period are reflected in the texts</p>
<p type="listitem">read and analyse a representative selection of literature and texts, fiction and factual, from the period after 1995</p>
</list><p>Traditional knowledge</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">elaborate on the tradition of   <em type="italic">joik  </em> and its status, value and situation in today's society   </p>
</list><p type="listitem">compare Sami and Norwegian song and hymn traditions</p>
<p type="listitem">elaborate on Sami narrative traditions</p>
<p type="listitem">tell fairytales by using elements from the Sami narrative traditions</p>
<p type="listitem">compare Sami fairytales with those of other indigenous peoples and fairytales from other cultures</p>
<p>The language in use</p>
<p><em type="italic">The aims for the education are that the pupil shall be able to </em></p>
<list><p type="listitem">explain grammatical features of the Sami languages and compare with other languages and explain the consequences for translation work</p>
<p type="listitem">use sentence analysis and grammar terminology when describing language</p>
<p type="listitem">elaborate on the relationship between spoken and written language</p>
<p type="listitem">identify variations within the Sami languages</p>
<p type="listitem">listen to and read texts from the other Sami languages and discuss similarities and dissimilarities</p>
<p type="listitem">elaborate on the main features of Sami language history and compare its main features with the history of the Nordic languages</p>
<p type="listitem">discuss how the status of the language in society has influenced Sami language skills, bilingualism and self-confidence, and how school, the community and working life may support bilingualism</p>
<p type="listitem">assess the language provision of the Sami Act and the establishment of the Sami Parliament in relation to the language situation and bilingualism</p>
<p type="listitem">discuss aspects of Sami language policy and cultural development</p>
<p type="listitem">compare the Sami language situation with the language situation for other indigenous peoples</p>
</list><p><em type="bold">Subject assessment </em></p>
<p>Provisions for final assessment</p>
<p>Overall achievement grade</p>
<p><em type="bold">Year </em></p>
<p>Provision</p>
<p>Year 10</p>
<p>The pupils shall have two overall achievement grades, one for written Sami 1 and one for oral Sami 1.</p>
<p>Vg1 programmes for general studies</p>
<p>Vg2 vocational education programmes</p>
<p>The pupils shall have two overall achievement grades, one for written Sami 1 and one for oral Sami 1.</p>
<p>Vg2 programmes for general studies</p>
<p>Vg3 programmes for general studies</p>
<p>Supplementary studies qualifying for higher education</p>
<p>The pupils shall have two overall achievement grades, one for written Sami 1 and one for oral Sami 1.</p>
<p>In subjects taught over a number of years only the overall achievement grade from the highest level in the subject taken by the pupil shall be entered on the competence certificate or diploma.</p>
<p>Examinations for pupils</p>
<p><em type="bold">Year </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Provision </em></p>
<p>Year 10</p>
<p>The pupils may be selected for a written examination in Sami 1. The written examination is prepared and graded centrally. The pupils may also be selected for an oral examination in Sami 1. The oral examination is prepared and graded locally.</p>
<p>Vg2 vocational education programmes</p>
<p>The pupils may be selected for a written examination in Sami 1. The written examination is prepared and graded locally. The pupils may also be selected for an oral examination in Sami 1. The oral examination is prepared and graded locally.</p>
<p>Vg3 programmes for general studies</p>
<p>Supplementary studies qualifying for higher education</p>
<p>The pupils shall sit for a written examination in Sami 1. The written examination is prepared and graded centrally. The pupils may also be selected for an oral examination in Sami 1. The oral examination is prepared and graded locally.</p>
<p>Examinations for external candidates</p>
<p><em type="bold">Year </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Provision </em></p>
<p>Year 10</p>
<p>See the provision in force for primary school education for adults.</p>
<p>Vg2 vocational education programmes</p>
<p>External candidates shall sit for written and oral examinations in Sami 1. The written examination is prepared and graded locally. The oral examination is prepared and graded locally.</p>
<p>Vg3 programmes for general studies</p>
<p>Supplementary studies qualifying for higher education</p>
<p>External candidates shall sit for a written examination on the Vg3 level in Sami. The written examination is prepared and graded centrally. The pupils shall take an oral examination in Sami. The oral examination is prepared locally.</p>
<p>The general provisions on assessment have been laid down in the Regulations relating to the Norwegian Education Act.</p>
<p>1  <em type="italic">Diidat/dijda </em> – popular belief (traditions, customs, maxims) about how to handle different situations and phenomena in day-to-day life.  </p>
<p>2  <em type="italic">Birgejupmi/bierggim/bïerkenidh </em> - make do, cope with, master  </p>
<p xml:lang="sme">3  <em type="italic">gáibmi/gájmme </em> – namesake   </p>
<p>4 The term  <em type="italic"><span type="quote" xml:lang="sme">"Sápmi/Sábme/Saepmie"</span> </em> refers to the traditional Sami settlement areas. It can also mean Sami, the Sami population or the Sami language. In the subject curriculum it primarily refers to  <em type="italic"><span type="quote" xml:lang="vep">"Samiland"</span> </em> , the traditional Sami settlement area in four national states.  </p>
<p xml:lang="vep">11</p>
</body></document>
