<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2005</year><wordcount>3995</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://skuvla.info/skolehist/josefsen-e.htm</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="josefsen-n.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 32948 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p>Three generations as a pupil in Alta</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Sámegillii På norsk</p>
<p>Article in the book Sami School History 1 . Davvi Girji 2005.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nno">Ruth, Eva and Irja Marie Josefsen:</p>
<p type="title">Three generations as a pupil in Alta</p>
<p type="title">Told to and translated by Svein Lund</p>
<p><em type="bold">In Alta we have talked with three generations of Samis who each have their different experiences from the Norwegian school. The oldest started school in 1931, the youngest in 2000. </em></p>
<p type="title">1st generation: Ruth Rye Josefsen</p>
<p xml:lang="nno"><em type="bold">Ruth Rye Josefsen, Alta 2003 </em>(Photo: Svein Lund) </p>
<p><em type="bold">Ruth Rye Josefsen is born in 1923. She grew up in Rafsbotn / Reaššvuotna in Alta, where she still lives. Here she has lived most of her life, except for the evacuation period in the end of the 2. World War and some years in Nordland in the 40's and 50's. </em></p>
<p>She is known as a woman able to talk and write in public, with opinions about many issues, and most people in Finnmark have noticed her writings in the newspapers. She is most famous as the leader of <span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">"Folkeaksjonen mot utbygging av Alta-Kautokeino-vassdraget"</span> (Peoples action against the development of water power plant in Alta-Kautokeino river) in 1979-80 and that she was a member of the Norwegian Sami parliament in its first election period (1989-1993). Locally and on Finnmark county level she has been active in different organisations like Norgga Sámiid Riikkasearvi / Norske Samers Riksforbund (Norwegian Samis National Association), Norges kommunistiske parti (Norwegian Communist Party), Nei til EU (No to Noršegian membership in European Union) and Handel og kontor (Trade union of trade and office workers).</p>
<p type="title">Rafsbotn</p>
<p>Rafsbotn is a village about 20 km from Alta. For most people who pass by, it is only a few houses along the road just where one leaves the Alta Fjord to drive up to Sennalandet (in direction towards Hammerfest). But there are also many houses which are not seen from the main road, especially in direction towards Russeluft and upwards Sørelvdalen, where Ruth grew up. Altogether around 500 people live in Rafsbotn and surroundings. Most of them have Sami and/or Kven background. It is difficult to find written materials about Rafsbotn, there is no written village history nor history of families. The people in Rafsbotn fit well to the expression used by Reidar Nielsen in his book about the Coast-Samis in Finnmark: <em type="italic"><span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">"Folk uten fortid"</span> </em>(People without a past). </p>
<p>In 1985 the historician Jens Petter Nielsen was assigned by Alta municipality to write a report on <em type="italic"><span type="quote">"The Sami strain in the population in Alta fjord"</span>. </em>Basing on old censuses he wrote about Rafsbotn: <em type="italic">"Rafsbotn is etnically, most known for a relatively strong Kven strain in the population. The censuses however show that the Sami element, at least in our century, all the time has been stronger than the Kven." </em>In 1930 was as much as 80,2 % of the population in Rafsbotn registrered as Sami, in 1970 this was reduced to 23,3 %, without having been any substancial emigration nor immigration. </p>
<p>Subsistence in Rafsbotn has, as in many other villages in the fjords in Finnmark, been small farms, fishing, hunting and other gatherings from the nature. From the 1920's there were many who worked in the slate mountain in Alta. This was a suitable seasonal work, which easily could be combined with other livelihoods. Ruth's father was one of them who worked in the slate mountain. Later on many have been working with roads and constructions.</p>
<p type="title">From trilingual to monolingual</p>
<p>- When I was a child Sami was the daily language in most homes in Rafsbotn, tells Ruth. - But the language was already in decrease. It was becoming more popular to speak Kven, it gave a higher status than Sami. Both my parents were trilingual, but to the children they spoke only Norwegian. They meant that it would be the best for us, and they cared for that we only spoke Norwegian. My grandmother, on the other hand, spoke only Sami. She spoke Sami to me, and I spoke Norwegian to her. There was also another family in Rafsbotn where the children only spoke Norwegian, but in most families the children of my age spoke Sami, Kven or both. We who only spoke Norwegian were looked upon as a little weird by the other children. There were many children who spoke badly Norwegian, among them several in my class at school. Indeed they did not speak any language quite well, they were half trilingual, but with Norwegian as their weakest language. Myself I can speak some Sami when I have to, Kven is worse, but I understand quite a lot.</p>
<p>- Most peoples in Rafsbotn were Laestadians [Strict Christian sect, mainly popular among Samis, Kvens and Finns. Founded by the Swedish/Sami priest Lars Levi Læstadius in the middle of the 19th century.], but not as strict as they often were in Alta. It was not usual that the children were taken along to the assemblies at the meeting house. My parents did not go there, but I asked to go there together with my aunt, as I wanted to see how it was there. But there were no other children, and I did not go there again.</p>
<p type="title">Schooling in Rafsbotn</p>
<p>Rafsbotn has had its own school for more than hundred years. In the end of the 19th century the School Director of Troms and Finnmark investigated language conditions. At that time there were 20 pupils at Rafsbotn school, 15 with Sami and 5 with Kven as their mother tongue. Nobody mastered Norwegian so well that they could utilize education in Norwegian.</p>
<p>From 1899 to 1902 Anders Larsen was a teacher here. He was a Coast-Sami from Kvænangen and became later on the editor of the Sami newspaper <em type="italic"><span type="quote" xml:lang="smj">"Sagai Muittalægje"</span> </em>(Newsteller). Larsen wrote the first Sami novel, <em type="italic"><span type="quote" xml:lang="sme">"Beaivvi álgu"</span> </em>(Dawn) and the booklet <em type="italic"><span type="quote" xml:lang="sme">"Mearrasámiid birra"</span> / <span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">"Om sjøsamene"</span> </em>(About the Coast-Samis), which is partly based on what he had experienced in Rafsbotn. From Larsen's time as a teacher in Kokelv it is known that he taught in Sami and therefore got into conflicts with the School Director. Larsen's work may have been one of the reasons why the number of people in Rafsbotn declaring themselves Sami increased from 1900 to 1930. </p>
<p>- The earliest I know of local school history, tells Ruth, is that my parents went to school here. I think that my father started in 1905 and my mother in 1908. At that time there was already a permanent school and all education was in Norwegian.</p>
<p>I myself started school in 1931. Then I was 8 years old. There were two reasons why I started a year later than most others. First, we were living far up in the valley and it was a long way to walk down to the school. Second, children of working people at that time could not expect to get more than 7 years of schooling. My father wanted that we should learn as much as possible, and he meant that I would learn more if I was a year older.</p>
<p>The school in Rafsbotn consisted of one classroom and the teacher was living in the other end of the building. The school was divided into three parts, but we had only one teacher in common. Therefore we went one week to school, then we were two weeks off. In most parents' opinion this was OK, because in the free weeks children could help the parents at home or in the slate mountain. The teacher whom we had the first years was educated as a teacher and came from Tverrelvdalen (village in Alta dominated by immigrants from Østerdalen in Southern Norway). He considered himself better than the Samis in Rafsbotn and had little contact with the local population. Later we got another teacher who was very fine. But meanwhile there were many bad substitutes. I remember that one was expelled after having beated pupil severely. The general word said that Rafsbotn school was a terrible school with naughty pupils.</p>
<p>The teacher beated children with twigs of birch and pulled the girls by their braids. He took wall charts with motives from the Bible and covered up the windows, so that nobody could see that he was beating the children. But he did not dare to touch me, because my father was known as one who dared to speak out. While we were at school, I remember that there came a new law telling that teachers no longer were allowed to beat pupils. (Folkeskolelova av 1936 - Act on primary school).</p>
<p>None of the teachers we had could speak any Sami nor Kven. We got a clear message that at school we should only speak Norwegian. It was told that it was not allowed to speak anything but Norwegian at school, but it is not clear to me who had decided it. I can't remember if Samis or Kvens were ever mentioned in the schoolbooks or in the teaching.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="smn">Rafsbotn - a Sami village?</p>
<p>- Today I would say that Rafsbotn was a Sami village. But we did not use the word <span type="quote" xml:lang="sms">"Sami"</span> when I grew up. We at all did not use any words for our own identity. People from outside, on the contrary, told that we were <span type="quote" xml:lang="fra">"Lapps"</span> or <span type="quote" xml:lang="isl">"Finns"</span>. These words were used in mixture. The word <span type="quote" xml:lang="sms">"Sami"</span> was not much in use here until in the 1960's.</p>
<p>There has never been any specific Sami organising in Rafsbotn. The most important local organisation was the sports club. The youth in Rafsbotn was known to be clever in sports and often they won competitions against the sport club in Alta. Then they often got words thrown after them that they were <span type="quote" xml:lang="isl">"tjærrafinn"</span> (Tar Lapp) or other words of abuse.</p>
<p>My first husband came from Kjerringøy in the county of Nordland. He was often visiting my father's family and told that my grandfather used to say: <span type="quote">"We Sami do it so and so"</span>. I remember, I was somewhat anxious about how my husband would react to get it served so directly that we were Samis, even if he must have understood it. It was not something which was talked about loudly at that time.</p>
<p>The Alta Sami Association had just celebrated its 30-years jubilee, when we visited Ruth. She was wearing a T-shirt with the text <span type="quote" xml:lang="sme">"Alta Sámi Searvi 30"</span>. But when the Sami association started in 1972, there were no members from Rafsbotn. There were immigrants from Inner Finnmark and South-Sami areas who started this organising, but gradually also native Alta-Samis joined. Herself Ruth joined in the end of the 70's together with another woman from Rafsbotn, Idun Meli. They got themselves Sami costumes and <span type="quote">"teased people"</span>, as she says. Because then it was not at all popular to be a Sami in public in Rafsbotn.</p>
<p>Idun Meli was a teacher in Rafsbotn, and the first who started teaching Sami language. At first she had only one pupil and together with the pupil she had made a poster with drawings of different Sami costumes and put it up on the school wall. A journalist from the local newspaper Finnmark Dagblad then made a coveragewhich showed this poster, and where Idun Meli told that most people in Rafsbotn had a Sami background. This provoked a hullaballoo in the village. The beautiful drawings disappeared tracklessly. Three boys from Rafsbotn went anonymously to the newspaper and answered, that it was not at all true that we were Samis, we did not want to have that accuse on us. In addition, they claimed, the first who had settled in Rafsbotn, was a Dane.</p>
<p>- I know very well who they were, says Ruth. Two of them are my relatives, and at least they can not free themselves from Sami background. One of them had a grandfather who was reindeer herding Sami from Karasjok. No, everything Sami should be washed away.</p>
<p>Even if many have admitted their Sami bakground now, there are relatively few in Rafsbotn who have joined the Sami census. Herself Ruth is the only among 7 brothers and sisters and Idun the only among 10, who is in the census. On the other hand there has been popular to search for German or Danish ancestors.</p>
<p type="title">From primary school to adult education</p>
<p>In Rafsbotn Ruth got 7 years of schooling, after that she got a year at the <span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">"fylkesskole"</span> (a kind of folk high school) in Bossekop in Alta. There was mainly education in housekeeping. After that her schooling had come to an end - for the next 30 years. She worked with housekeeping, smallholding and later as a school janitor. In 1968 she got the chance to read half a year of trade school in Tromsø. In 1972 she started learning subjects of gymnasium (theoretical further education). It took a long time to complete, besides of work and activity in organisations, but finally she passed the exams nessesary to study at the university. For some time she was a commisionary for Narvesen (chain of kiosks with litterature), later she worked in the office of an electro shop until she reached age of retirement. Only as retired she joined the study of law at University of Tromsø.</p>
<p>- But then I was elected into the Sami Parliament and then I did not get time to study so much. But what I have learnt about law has been very useful for me.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p><em type="bold">Ruth and Eva have both represented NSR (Norwegian Sami Association) in the election district Alta/Kvalsund in the Norwegian Sami Parliament. Ruth in 1989-93 and Eva in 1997-2001. Here are the representatives of the Sami Parliament 1997-2001, with Eva in the second row, no. 5 from the right. </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob">(Photo: Harry Johansen)</p>
<p type="title">2nd generation: Eva Josefsen</p>
<p><em type="bold">Eva Josefsen was born in 1961, grew up in Rafsbotn and lives now in central Alta. She is educated in economy and administration from Finnmark University College and has a master in political science from University of Tromsø. She has been working with several projects for Finnmark University College and Nordic Sami Institute. Presently, she works at the research institution Norut NIBR Finnmark, where she among others has done research on the Sami Parliament as an arena of equality policy. In 2005 she started as a candidate for a Ph.D. </em></p>
<p>Eva has for many years been active in Sami politics and other political work and has among others been leader of the Alta Sami association. In the period 1997-2001 she was a member of the Sami Parliament, as a representative of NSR.</p>
<p>In contrary to her mother, who started school one year later than sceduled, Eva started one year earlier, as 6 year old in 1967. The first six years she went to Rafsbotn school, after that Alta youth school (secondary school) and further education at what at that time was named Alta gymnas.</p>
<p type="title">Etnisity as a non-theme</p>
<p>- In my childhood I heard both Finnish (Kven) and Sami in Rafsbotn. Finnish one could hear at the shop, Sami only in some homes. In spite of that it was not talked about who were who, neither in the family, nor in the village. And least of all at school. It was just not a topic which was talked about. But I had a conception of ranging of the languages, where Norwegian was best, and Finnish was better than Sami.</p>
<p>At school in Rafsbotn I can not remember that we have learnt anything about Samis, at least nothing connected to our village. Most teachers were from outside. But one of the teachers was raised in Rafsbotn. I can remember that we were on a trip to neighbouring village Ruoššaluokta (Russeluft) when I was in the 4th class. Then this teacher told that during the war it was a boy who fooled the Germans, so that they fell down from a steep mountain here. Later I have found out that this can not be true. If this had happened during the 2nd World War, it would of course have been publicly known. The story that lies behind here, must be the old Sami legend where the Russian Chuds were fooled and fell down from the moutain. If that happened here, it can also explain the name Ruoššaluokta or the Russians' bay. In later years I have thought of this as one of the many cases where the history of this area has been falsified and reinterpreted so that the Sami content would disappear.</p>
<p>At the school in Rafsbotn there was one girl who spoke Sami. She had come from Guovdageaidnu (Kautokeino). She taught us a few sentence in Sami, as "Atte munnje cummá!"</p>
<p>- Your mother has told that when youth from Rafsbotn came in to Alta, they were called <span type="quote" xml:lang="isl">"tjærrafinn"</span> (Tar Lapp) and similar depreciatory expressions which pointed to that they were Sami. How was that when you grew up? - Then there was nothing such to be heard. There was no longer any common understanding that there were Samis in Rafsbotn, neither among the people in the village, nor in the neighbouring villages. Myself, I did not have any clear concept of what I was in my childhood.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">Kautokeino costume</p>
<p>- But when I became a teenager, something must have changed. Because in secondary school I wrote a paper about the Kautokeino rebellion, and when I was 14-15, I demanded a Sami costume. My mother got sewn a Kautokeino costume for me, because it did not exist any costumes for the Coast-Samis in the Alta fjord at that time</p>
<p>- I remember that in secondary school there was a teacher who asked if anybody in the class understood Sami. One pupil who spoke Sami almost had to be forced to admit it, she did not want to talk about it. It was not admireable to know the Sami language, rather the opposite.</p>
<p type="title">The Alta struggle</p>
<p>When Eva was in further education, 1976-79, came the struggle about the power plant in Alta river, and among the pupils, as elsewhere in Alta, there were hard discussions, both in the lessons and the breaks. I Eva's class there were pupils whose parents were active on both sides. But still they learnt mext to nothing about Sami affairs at school. About the Coast-Samis around the Alta fjord had neither schoolbooks nor teachers told anything at all.</p>
<p>16 years old Eva started for the first time at a Sami language course. Håkon Henriksen, who was the teacher, was one of the leaders of the Peoples action against the developement of water power plant in Alta-Kautokeino. Later Eva has learnt more Sami, so that she can understand and speak somehow. But in public, she still prefers to express herself in Norwegian</p>
<p>After further education Eva studied economy and administration at Finnmark College. There was absolutely nothing said about Sami affairs. Later she studied political science at University of Tromsø. There was nothing about the Samis in the curriculum at this school either, neither at first, nor second level (grunnfag and mellomfag), but now the students demanded, that it should be. Until the master level Eva had not experienced to get anything about Sami affairs in the curriculum.</p>
<p>As a conclusion one may say that a Sami pupil / student from a Sami village in Coastal Finnmark in the period 1967-2001 could go through 18 years of education with minimal information about her own people. No wonder that when Eva should write her master thesis, she chose to write just about what those who are planning education and other public tasks, know about Sami affairs. Then she found, not unexpectedly, that both in Ministry of Education and Ministry of Fisheries most of the proceedings of importance for Sami regions had been done without any evaluation of how the decisions would influence Sami interests.</p>
<p>Today she is engaged in that her daughter and other children with Sami background who grow up in Alta, shall get a better knowledge of Sami language and culture, than what she has got herself.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">Eva and Irja Marie Josefsen, Alta 2003 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nno">(Photo: Svein Lund)</p>
<p type="title">3rd generation: Irja Marie Josefsen&#13; &#13; Irja Marie Josefsen is born in 1994. She started at Komsa school in 2000. When this is written she is in 4th class.</p>
<p>From before Irja learnt to speak she was in a Sami kindergarden and when she had started speaking, Sami and Norwegian came simultaniously. When she started school, she spoke both these languages approximately same well.</p>
<p>At Komsa school in Alta Irja follows the curriculum for Sami as the first language. The first language pupils are a group of 6 pupils in 3rd and 4th class. One should believe, that first language means education in Sami. But that it not the case in Alta. There Sami as first language means only that she has got Sami as a subject from 1st class and that the education in Sami language as a subject in taught in Sami language. [The pupils who have Sami as second language in Alta gets Sami only from 3rd class and also the Sami language lessons are taught in Norwegian.] All other subjects are taught in Norwegian, and then the pupils follow their respective classes. Up to the present in Alta there has not been offered any education in other subjects with use of the Sami language.</p>
<p>Irja is not very keen on beeing interviewed, so it is mainly her mother who answers for her. She listens carefully, so that she can control that I don’t write anything wrong. It is not only the language which is Norwegian in all other lessons than the Sami language subject. The content is also according to the national curriculum. As Alta municipality is not a part of the management area of Sami language [area of 6 municipalities, where Sami and Norwegian languages have formally equal official status], there is used the national curriculum for all schoolchildren. It means that even pupils with Sami as their first language do not utilize the fact, that there exists a Sami curriculum for primary and secondary school.</p>
<p>- Do you learn anything about Sami affairs in other lessons than the Sami lessons, we ask Irja. - We have a Sami riddle in our Norwegian book, but except that, there is nothing.</p>
<p>Also in the Sami language lessons there is minimal about the Coast-Samis, as the Sami teacher comes from Inner Finnmark and mainly knows that environment. When there also are people from Inner Finnmark who write the schoolbooks, there is not much which connects the Sami education to the local society and to the background of most of the pupils.</p>
<p>Both as a mother and as a member of Alta Sami Association, Eva has been engaged in the Sami education in Alta. Earlier the School Office has been completely negative, but in the later years it has somewhat improved. Anyhow the Sami education is still treated as a wart, not as a natural part of the education at the schools the pupils belong to. First the rest of the timetable is made, then one has to try to adapt the Sami lessons to it. It is still a widespread opinion in the municipality, that Sami education is a question of an offer to pupils from the inland, not to Alta's own Sami population.</p>
<p>Among the parents it has been, and is still, different opinions on, if one should demand an own Sami school district, or if it is better that the pupils get Sami education at the schools to which they geographically belong.</p>
<p>At Rafsbotn school, where Ruth and Eva went, there has now been Sami education since the early 1980's. Today (2003) there are about 15 pupils who have Sami as a subject. That is about one tenth of the children at the school. Even if there has been a great progress from the start with one pupil, it is still a small minority of the parents with Sami background who choose that their children shall learn the language.</p>
<p>More articles from Sami School History 1</p>
</body></document>
