<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Sami school history 2</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2007</year><wordcount>837</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://skuvla.info/skolehist/ssh2-e.htm</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 32948 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nno">På norsk Sámegillii</p>
<p type="title">Sami school history 2</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nno">Samisk skolehistorie 2</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="sme">Sámi skuvlahistorjá 2</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="sma">Samien skuvle-vaajese 2</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="smj">Sámij skåvllåhiståvrrå 2</p>
<p>Reviews and critics (In Norwegian or Sami language)</p>
<p xml:lang="nno"><em type="bold">Cover illustrations by Bjørg Monsen Vars </em></p>
<p>The book is available in Norwegian book stores and can also be ordered from the publisher Davvi Girji .</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="deu">Foreword</p>
<p>This second volume in the book collection</p>
<p><em type="italic">Sami school history </em></p>
<p>is, similar to</p>
<p>the first volume</p>
<p>, a collection of articles, stories, memories and documents from different sides of the school for Sami pupils and students. It is published as a book and an online version, at the address</p>
<p xml:lang="smj"><em type="bold">http://skuvla.info </em></p>
<p>, at the same time. The online version has more or less the same contents as the book, but also a few more pictures.</p>
<p>This book is a result of collaboration between many people and institutions. We would like to profoundly thank everyone who has given their contributions and made it possible for this book to be published; authors, narrators, translators, proofreaders, photographers, artists, the staff at the publisher and libraries, archives, museums and schools. Last but not least we would like to thank the institutions who have contributed in financing the publishing of this volume. They are listed at the back of the book.</p>
<p>With this volume we wish to map what the sami pupils have experienced in Norwegian schools. The map still have some blank spots, and only with help from our readers are we able to fill them. We are still interested in stories and documents for later volumes.</p>
<p>We are also interested in corrections and further particulars to this volume. Changes will in that case be made in the online version and in later editions of the book.</p>
<p>If you have any contributions, please contact the publisher:</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Davvi Girji, Postboks 13, N-9735 Kárášjohka</p>
<p xml:lang="smj">tel 78469500 davvi@davvi.no</p>
<p>or the head of the editing committee: sveilund@online.no</p>
<p type="title">Content</p>
<p>None of these articles are yet translated into English</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Introduction: Jiehkku, petroglyphs (rock carvings), juoŋasteapmi and laestadians</p>
<p><em type="bold">THE CONTINUATION SCHOOL </em>Lydolf Lind Meløy: The continuation school The school board in Karasjok: Sami language and culture in the continuation school Olav Malin: The continuation school in Kautokeino 1950–1966 Compulsory continuation school - resistance and absence </p>
<p><em type="bold">REINDEER HUSBANDRY EDUCATION </em>Bjørn Aarseth: Testing reindeer husbandry as a subject in school – The biggest milestone in the history of reindeer husbandry Paul Fjellheim: The first teacher at the school of reindeer husbandry Loyd Villmo: Pioneer work for teaching reindeer husbandry Inge Andersen: Pupil and teacher at the school of reindeer husbandry Svein Lund: Reindeer husbandry schooling in one room Ánte Mihkkal Gaup: The teaching of reindeer husbandry is diluted </p>
<p><em type="bold">SECONDARY SCHOOL - GUOVDAGEAIDNU </em><span type="quote">"A one of a kind in the whole world"</span> Ragnar Nordby: Practical school for sami people in Norway Lempi Mikalsen: Gakti-sewing teacher and head of household Hans Guttorm: Mechanical subjects in the 1960s Hans Nergård: Headmaster without a board Pupils in high school demands mandatory Sami Svein Lund: Fish on shore - a dáža in Sami school </p>
<p><em type="bold">SECONDARY SCHOOL - KARASJOK </em>Stein Henriksen: Why a Sami high school? Glimpses from the battle of a Sami high school High school students in Karasjok fights for better schooling </p>
<p><em type="bold">PRIMARY SCHOOL - FINNMARK </em>Sigbjørn Hølmebakk: The local pope of Karasjok Ragnhild Ravna: Memories from the school in Tana Siri Broch Johansen: From Norwegian speaking pupil to Sami language teacher Solbjørg Ravna: Experiences from Buolbmát and Deanu sámeskuvla Kirsti Suongir: Norwegian speaking mother in the Sami school Anne Smeland and Svein Kollstrøm: Tana montessori school – from protest to alternative Siv Rasmussen: From the Sami school history in Sør-Varanger Ivar Utsi: Prohibited to speak one's language Ingunn Utsi: The last Sami speaking children at Nordkapp Lone Synnøve Hegg: Existential school history from Loppa Harald Samuelsberg and Leonhard Gamst: The Sami people and the school in Loppa </p>
<p><em type="bold">PRIMARY SCHOOL - TROMS </em>Ragnhild Enoksen: Involuntarily pioneers in Nordreisa Nils Sneberg: – I didn't learn much at school Eliva Isaksen: – No boorish children at that time </p>
<p><em type="bold">PRIMARY SCHOOL - NORDLAND </em>Kaia Kalstad: – A child of my time Karl M. Paulsen: School in Lule Sami in the period of assimilation Frank A. Jenssen: Skull measuring in elementary school </p>
<p><em type="bold">SCHOOL ADMINISTRATION </em>Randi Nordback Madsen and Trygve Madsen: The school for Sami people viewed from several angles Asta Balto: – My loyalty was in the Sami society </p>
<p type="title">Additional articles</p>
<p>In addition to the printed articles we have found some earlier written articles or documents, with connection to the topics in this volum. Some we have not found place for in the book, others we have found after the book was printed. These we publish here, so that readers may read them in connection with the subjects / areas where they belong. Additional articles are primarily published in the original language, then some of them are translated later.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">CONTINUATION SCHOOL </em>Kautokeino: Forsvar for framhaldsskolen </p>
<p xml:lang="nno"><em type="bold">SECONDARY SCHOOL - GUOVDAGEAIDNU </em>Anders Guttormsen: Statens heimeyrkeskole for samar, Kautokeino </p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">PRIMARY SCHOOL - FINNMARK </em>Finnefondssøknad fra Nordkapp </p>
<p>Sami school history 1 Sami school history 3 Sami school history - home</p>
</body></document>