<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Advice for parents, children and youth</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="helsenorge.no" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>1720</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://helsenorge.no/coronavirus/advice-for-parents-children-and-youth?redirect=false</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="raad_om_korona_til_foreldre_barn_og_unge.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="ravvagat_korona_birra_vahnemiidda_manaide_ja_nuoraide.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 180635 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>Advice for parents, children and youth - helsenorge.no</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedmeny</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til innholdet</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Min helse</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="rmn">helsenorge.no</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="pol">Meny</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Søk</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Søk...</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Søk...</p>
<p type="title">Advice for parents, children and youth</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nno">Norsk bokmål</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">Sámi</p>
</list><p>Advice for parents on playdates and how to handle daily life, how to talk to children about corona and how to support the mental health of children and youth.</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sidebilde</p>
<p>Mostphotos/Shalamov (illustration)</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Sideinnhold</p>
<p><em type="italic">The article is being updated </em>​ </p>
<p type="title">Children and corona</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Seksjon 1 Innhold</p>
<p>​Children seem to be less affected by the coronavirus than others. Yet children can infect other people.</p>
<p type="title">Can children play or spend time with other children?</p>
<p>To aviod transmission of the virus, everyone needs to keep a greater distance to others than we usually do. Siblings can socialise as they normally do — this also applies to children living in two homes after a divorce. The main goal is to reduce the number of contacts as much as possible.</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Playdates or gathering in larger groups is not recommended. The goal is to keep distance and thereby avoid transmission.</p>
<p type="listitem">When out-doors, we should limit the size of the group to a maximum of five people. This does not apply to members of the same household.</p>
<p type="listitem">The recommendation is to keep a greater distance to others than we normally do, at least 1 metre.</p>
<p type="listitem">Limit the duration of social contact between playmates (few hours).</p>
</list><p>The reasons for these recommendations are that the risk of transmission increases with the duration of social contact and closer distance between people.</p>
<p>To meet the children's need for playing and socialising with others, you can let them play with 1—2 friends. Try to stick to the same 1—2 friends throughout this period. The same recommendation applies to youth.</p>
<list><p type="listitem">To meet up and play outdoors is preferred, rather than indoor activities.</p>
<p type="listitem">Avoid playgrounds where many children meet at the same time. The recommendation to keep an increased distance to others apply here as well.</p>
<p type="listitem">Birthday parties should be postponed.</p>
<p type="listitem">Limit sleepovers with friends during this period.</p>
<p type="listitem">Wash hands often — both before, during and after being together — and maintain good cough etiquette.</p>
</list><p>Children and youth with symptoms of respiratory infection should stay at home and avoid contact with other children or youth outside of the family. This also applies for mild symptoms. Children living in two homes after divorce should preferably stay in one of the homes until the child has been free om symptoms for 24 hours. The parents are advised to cooperate in order to follow the public guidelines regarding transmission.</p>
<p>Children and youth who are in home isolation or home quarantine should not avoid contact with other children or youth outside the household.</p>
<p>There is a risk that some children may be left out and have no one to play with during this period. Parents can help out by making sure the children stay in touch via other means — over the phone, via video chat etc.</p>
<p type="title">Can grandparents look after their grandchildren?</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Persons over the age of 65 are advised to keep distance from persons with whom they do not live, including children. This may also apply to those who are under 65 and have a chronic underlying illness.</p>
<p type="listitem">Persons who are under the age of 65 and healthy, do not have the same risk and can be around others as long as they follow the general recommendations. New knowledge shows that children become ill less often and have milder symptoms. It is primarily people who have symptoms that are contagious.</p>
</list><p type="title">Children and youth who experience an extra burden when schools and kindergartens are closed</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Seksjon 2 Innhold</p>
<p>​Some children and youth have a challenging home situation. School and kindergarten can be of extra importance to these children to maintain regular contact with other children, youth and grown-ups.</p>
<p>Exceptions to the closure of schools and kindergartens apply for children and youth with special care needs. The individual school and kindergarten must perform specific and individual assessments as to who should receive this service. For more information, see the webpages of the Norwegian Directorate for Education and Training (in Norwegian) .</p>
<p type="title">Do you suspect a child is not doing well?</p>
<p>With schools and kindergartens closed, we know that some children and youth have to spend more time with adults who are not safe for them. The emergency telephone (Alarmtelefonen) of the Child Welfare Services is open to anyone exposed to violence, abuse or neglect, or anyone who is concerned for someone else. The lines are now open 24 hours a day, every day of the week. Call 116 111 and they will assist you.</p>
<p type="title">How to talk to children and youth about corona</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Seksjon 3 Innhold</p>
<p>​Now that their days differ from what they are used to, it is important to talk to children and youth to avoid fear and to build security in this situation.</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Talk to the children as to why schools, kindergartens, and after school clubs are closed. Explain to them that this is to stop the coronavirus from spreading.</p>
<p type="listitem">Ask them what information they have heard or read and if there is anything in particular they are worried about.</p>
<p type="listitem">Give them intelligible and correct information. Make sure you do not exaggerate or trivialise. The disease is serious, but we are well prepared in Norway.</p>
<p type="listitem">Do not unduly stress your children – coughing and sneezing is normal, and the majority of people who are infected by the coronavirus will experience only mild symptoms.</p>
<p type="listitem">Discuss whether there really is a continuous need for checking up on the news, and preferably make an agreement with the child on the frequency. Sit alongside the child and talk about what you see, hear, and read.</p>
<p type="listitem">It is important to listed to the child. Be present in the conversation and let the child speak out.</p>
<p type="listitem">Remember that younger children in particular will <span type="quote">«fill out the blanks»</span> by using their own imagination when they encounter something they do not fully understand.</p>
<p type="listitem">Be concrete, clear and concise. Repeat by using different words.</p>
<p type="listitem">Explain how infection occurs (airborne transmission via droplets by close encounter) – and how to avoid transmission (good hand hygiene, coughing into the crook of your elbow etc.</p>
<p type="listitem">Be clear on how a sense of feeling afraid, sad or angry is totally normal now that their days are so different, and they cannot do the things they are used to.</p>
<p type="listitem">Tell them that thousands of doctors and nurses and others now ensure that those who turn sick will receive the treatment they need.</p>
<p type="listitem">Prepare the children for other adjustments that will occur in the following weeks, e.g. that parents might need to work from home, that there will be fewer visits by friends and family and that travels, birthdays etc. will be postponed.</p>
<p type="listitem">Explain to them that this will now be the situation for a period, that it will return to normal, but that we do not yet know when.</p>
</list><p type="title">Also remember:</p>
<p>Children and youth will often turn to the internet for information. Check on their internet habits and ask if they have read anything online about the coronavirus today.</p>
<p type="title">Youth</p>
<p>Youth and teenagers often talk mostly to their peers and can easily pick up on incorrect information. Make it easy for them to turn to you. Don't forget that teenagers also can be worried and in need of an adult to talk to.</p>
<p>At ung.no you will find updated and useful information for young people between the age of 13 and 20. You can find answers to your concerns and you can post questions at ung.no/oss .</p>
<p>Do you need someone to talk to or chat with? You can find information on available helplines and chat services here (in Norwegian).</p>
<p>This film is made for children and youth. Subtitles are available in several languages by clicking the little wheel at the bottom.</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Click on the cogwheel symbol at the bottom when you open the film.</p>
<p type="listitem">Remove <span type="quote">"Autoplay"</span> if this shows up in red.</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="est">Choose <span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">"Settings"</span></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rmu">Click <span type="quote" xml:lang="nno">"Subtitles"</span></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="est">Choose <span type="quote">"Automatic translation"</span></p>
<p type="listitem">Choose language</p>
</list><p>Subtitles in the language of your choice will appear (sound is in Norwegian only). We cannot guarantee that the auto-translation is completely correct.</p>
<p type="title">Tips for mastering everyday life in the family</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Seksjon 4 Innhold</p>
<p>​Schools and kindergartens are closed as everyone must contribute in order to limit the transmission of the coronavirus. This can lead to a sense of worry and be stressful to many families. Here are some tips that can be of help now that everyday life has taken a different turn:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Keeping a daily rhythm with regular meals and bedtime routines is beneficial.</p>
<p type="listitem">It is recommended to reserve time that would otherwise be spent at school for schoolwork, drawing, reading, or listening to books, and to spend some time outdoors while keeping a distance to others.</p>
<p type="listitem">Focus on activities that are positive and that you can all join in on as a family. Watch a film, listen to music, go for a walk, or play a game etc. Make sure to get together during meals.</p>
<p type="listitem">Keep in mind that you are a role model to your kids. How you handle stress, how the adults talk between themselves about the situation, and how you react will affect the children.</p>
<p type="listitem">A sense of fear, panic, sadness, and loneliness are normal reactions to extraordinary situations. Children are sensitive to the emotions of adults, and thus it is better to be open about how you feel than to hide your feelings.</p>
<p type="listitem">Children will react in different ways. Some may seem at ease when you talk to them, yet later be concerned. Be extra attentive in the evening and at night, when many children will become more anxious.</p>
<p type="listitem">It is important to stay updated with the news, but it can be a good idea to limit the use of social media etc. if this leads to an increased stress level and undue concern.</p>
<p type="listitem">Reach out to others — do not be afraid to ask for help.</p>
</list><p>Discuss what to do if someone in the family feels unwell or should turn ill. Should a quarantine period become necessary: explain what this means and talk about how you can make this period as comfortable as possible.</p>
<p>The National Knowledge Center on Violence and Traumatic Stress (<span type="quote" xml:lang="vep">"NKVTS"</span>) has additional</p>
<p>advice on how to cope with corona in daily life, in several languages</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">.</p>
</body></document>
