<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>Kun pohjoisen matkasta tuli elämän mittainen</title>
    <genre code="science"/>
    <author>
      <person firstname="Outi" lastname="Korpilähde" sex="f" born="" nationality="FI"/>
    </author>
    <year>2015</year>
    <wordcount>350</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <license type="standard"/>
    </availability>
    <origFileName>https://lauda.ulapland.fi/bitstream/handle/10024/62153/Korpilähde_Outi_ActaE_172_pdfA.pdf</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="outi_korpilahde_phd.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="outi_korpilahde_phd.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="outi_korpilahde_phd.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="outi_korpilahde_phd.pdf"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 161400 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>Outi Korpilähde</p>
    <p><em type="italic">When a northern journey became life-long: Finnish wives in Sámi communities.</em> </p>
    <p>The  thesis  examines  the  lives  of  Finnish  women  who have entered and settled in Sámi communities as wives and daughters-in-law.  Of  particular  interest  in  the  research  are public  perceptions  of  the  agency  and  place  of  the  women. Through its analysis of the women’s biographical reports on joining the Sámi community, the study offers space for their voices, the voices of a group that to date has been overlooked in the literatureresearch. The Sámi region has long been a site of intercultural relationships and families. The women studied in the present work  are  older  women  in  the  community  who  came  to  the Sámi area some 60 years ago and have thus have seen many extensive changes. The research contributes to the scientific debate on intercultural relationships and families. My study analyses the degree to which everyday practices explain the course taken by relationships between Sámi and Finnish families. Specifically, it addresses the question: What new knowledge and skills is an entrant required to learn and what kind of resources does she need in settling down in the Sámi region and a Sámi community? I approach the study of everyday experiences through the concept of agency and consider the question of resources in terms of cultural and social capital. The research shows that the essence of settling in a new community is acquiring the necessary cultural and social capital and learning the rules of the game. One challenge that the Finnish women encountered was the community’s need to the women feeling that they were outsiders. Based on the analysis,  I  introduce  a  new  concept,  saamelaistapaisuus,  or Sámi habitus, which the women adopted gradually, but never completely. In light of my findings, I see Finnish wives in Sámi communities as having a significant role as cultural interpreters between  the  Sámi  and  Finnish  cultures.    They  develop  into multicultural  professionals  who  are  both  familiar  with  Finnish culture and actively engaged in acquiring the essential skills and knowledge of Sámi culture.</p>
    <p>KEYWORDS:  biculturalism,  relationship,  family,  Sámi culture, cultural capital, social capital, agency, Bourdieu</p>
  </body>
</document>
