<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Dokumeanttat - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="Government.no" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="nob"/><year>2007</year><publChannel><publication><publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher></publication></publChannel><wordcount>329</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/doc.html?id=439279</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="dok_id_439279.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="dok_id_439279.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="dok_id_439279.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Documents - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>The ministries publishes several types of documents:</p>
<p><em type="italic">Propositions and reports </em>are documents presented to the Storting. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Acts and regulations </em>include laws, regulations, guidelines, etc. related to the Ministry’s areas of responsibility. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Circular </em>are information from the ministry to affected parties about interpretations of laws and regulations. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Norwegian Official Reports </em>are made by committees and work groups appointed by the Ministry. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Reports and plans </em>are usually made by external researchers or a committee, and include reports, analysis and surveys delivered to the Ministry. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Guidelines and brochures </em>inform about the Ministry’s politics and policies, and target a wider audience. </p>
<p type="title">Core values of Norway's defence sector</p>
<p>[Guidelines and brochures, Ministry of Defence, 12.09.2014]</p>
<p>The defence sector defends Norwegian territory, the Norwegian people and Norway’s interests. The defence sector promotes certain general values. This values platform for the sector is aimed to highlight these values.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Health System in Transition, Norway</p>
<p type="title">Health system review</p>
<p>[Report, Ministry of Health and Care Services, 01.09.2014]</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Norway’s fifth national report to the Convention on Biological Diversity</p>
<p>[Report, Ministry of Climate and Environment, 10.07.2014]</p>
<p>The report presents information on status and trends for biodiversity in Norway, measures undertaken to implement the Convention since 2009, successes and remaining Challenges.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nno">Meld. St. 37 (2012–2013)</p>
<p type="title">Integrated Management of the Marine Environment of the North Sea and Skagerrak (Management Plan)</p>
<p>[Report to the Storting, Ministry of Climate and Environment, 27.06.2014]</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Barriers to digitizatioen</p>
<p type="title">Executive summary of KPMG report to the Norwegian Ministry of Local Government and Modernisation</p>
<p>[Report, Ministry of Local Government and Modernisation, 18.06.2014]</p>
<p>On the assignment from the Ministry of Local Government and Modernisation, KPMG has undertaken a mapping and analysis of barriers for digitalization among Norwegian Companies.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="hbs">NOU 2014: 5</p>
<p type="title">MOOCs for Norway</p>
<p>[Norwegian Official Report (NOU), Ministry of Education and Research, 16.06.2014]</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Norway in Europe. The Norwegian Government's Strategy for Cooperation with the EU 2014-2017</p>
<p>[Plan, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 11.06.2014]</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Action plan against Radicalisation and Violent Extremism</p>
<p>[Plan, Ministry of Justice and Public Security, 10.06.2014]</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
</body></document>
