<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>Dásseárvu sohkabeliid gaskkas - regjeringen.no</title>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <person firstname="" lastname="Ministry of Children, Equality and Social Inclusion" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/>
    </author>
    <translator>
      <unknown/>
    </translator>
    <translated_from xml:lang="nob"/>
    <year>2007</year>
    <publChannel>
      <publication>
        <publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher>
      </publication>
    </publChannel>
    <wordcount>829</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/bld/Topics/equality.html?id=1246</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="likestillingsomradet_id_1246.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="dassearvu-sohkabeliid-gaskkas_id_1246.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>Gender equality - regjeringen.no</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Gender equality</p>
    <p>The Ministry of Children and Equality is the ministry with primary responsibility for the government's gender equality policies, but all ministries have a responsibility for gender equality in their own policy areas.</p>
    <p>The ministry deals with issues related to gender equality in employment, women and power, and men and equality. It also participates in international collaborative efforts. The ministry is a proponent of developing a gender-policy perspective in the national budget, and it has overall administrative responsibility for the Equality and Anti-Discrimination Ombud and for the Norwegian Equality and Anti-Discrimination Tribunal.</p>
    <p type="title">Gender Equality - – a key to democracy</p>
    <p type="title">Comprehensive protection against discriminiation (NOU 2009:14)</p>
    <p type="title">Men and gender equality</p>
    <p>Gender equality can only be achieved when men and women work together towards the same goals and agree that traditional masculinities and femininities have aspects that need to be changed.</p>
    <p type="title">A joint machinery against all forms of discrimination</p>
    <p>The Equality and Anti-discrimination Ombud and the Equality and Anti-discrimination Tribunal were established 1 January 2006.</p>
    <p type="title">Balanced gender representation on company boards</p>
    <p>From 1 January 2004, the boards in all state owned companies are obliged to have a minimum of 40 percent representation of each gender. The Parliament has passed corresponding amendments regarding public limited companies in the private sector.</p>
    <p type="title">Norway congratulates new UN head of gender equality</p>
    <p>[Press release, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 15.09.2010]</p>
    <p>Norway congratulates Chile’s former President Michelle Bachelet on her appointment as head of the UN’s new entity for gender equality and the empowerment of women (UN Women).</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Adaption in working life and equality for both women and men</p>
    <p type="title">UN COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN 1 – 12 MARCH 2010</p>
    <p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Children, Equality and Social Inclusion, 20.03.2010]</p>
    <p>Seminar hosted by the Norwegian Consulate in New York, Women`s Forum and Catalyst The last 40 years has seen substantial equality between the genders come true, with great changes in Norwegian culture, politics and economic life. Today, we are discussing men’s roles and rights in terms of parental leave, along with promoting women to the upper echelons of economic life.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Including men for women’s rights and gender equality</p>
    <p type="title">UN COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN 1 – 12 MARCH 2010</p>
    <p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Children, Equality and Social Inclusion, 20.03.2010]</p>
    <p>Gender equality is good business for a country. OECD declared in 2007 that <span type="quote">“gender equality strengthens long-term economic development”</span>. The former European Commissioner Vladimir Spidla said that <span type="quote">“Women are driving job growth in Europe and helping us reach our economics target”</span>.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Equal rights, equal opportunities: Progress for all</p>
    <p type="title">UN COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN 1 – 12 MARCH 2010</p>
    <p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Children, Equality and Social Inclusion, 20.03.2010]</p>
    <p>UN COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN 1 – 12 MARCH 2010 UN – commemoration of the International Women’s Day Equal rights, equal opportunities: Progress for all Beijing + 15: the Unfinished Agenda</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Norway provides NOK 60 million to promote women’s rights</p>
    <p>[Press release, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 24.11.2009]</p>
    <p>Norway will provide NOK 40 million (USD 7 million) to UN efforts to combat female genital mutilation and violence against women in developing countries. At the same time, Norway will contribute NOK 20 million (USD 3.5 million) to the new UN Fund for Gender Equality.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Putting policy into practice</p>
    <p type="title">Conference in Oslo 11.11.2009</p>
    <p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 11.11.2009]</p>
    <p>- For me, women, peace and security is not a gender issue. It is a cross-gender issue. It is a security issue. It is an issue for women and men alike – and an issue of our common interest and future, State Secretary Gry Larsen said in her opening statement at a conference in Oslo on 11.11.09.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">New UN agency for women and gender equality</p>
    <p>[Press release, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 15.09.2009]</p>
    <p>The UN General Assembly yesterday approved the establishment of a new agency designed to intensify UN efforts to promote gender equality and the rights of women. <span type="quote">“This is an important measure to secure the rights and empowerment of women,”</span> said Foreign Minister Jonas Gahr Støre.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Public policies supporting the wish to have children</p>
    <p type="title">societal, economic and personal factors</p>
    <p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Children, Equality and Social Inclusion, 24.06.2009]</p>
    <p>Speach held at the Council of Europe Conference of Ministrers responsible for family affairs June 16th-17th 2009.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">White Paper on male roles and gender equality</p>
    <p>[Editorial article, Ministry of Children, Equality and Social Inclusion, 01.02.2009]</p>
    <p>Read the White Paper Document from the government to Stortinget (Parliament) on male roles and gender equality</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Gender balance on company boards - article on the web site WOMEN-omics</p>
    <p>[Speech/article, Ministry of Children, Equality and Social Inclusion, 01.12.2008]</p>
    <p>The fall of 2008, Director General Arni Hole spent some time in New York and Washington, working for the UN. During her stay, she was asked to write an article regarding the Norwegian legislation on gender balance on company boards for a web site called WOMEN-omics. WOMEN-omics is focusing on the theme of promoting women as an economic opportunity.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>More documents about this subject</p>
  </body>
</document>
