<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Dásseárvu mánáidgárddis, oahpahusas ja dutkamis - regjeringen.no</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="Ministry of Education and Research" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="nob"/><year>2008</year><publChannel><publication><publisher>regjeringen.no</publisher></publication></publChannel><wordcount>408</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="" email="divvun@samediggi.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://regjeringen.no/en/dep/kd/Selected-topics/gender-equality-.html?id=486669</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="likestilling-i-barnehage-utdanning-og-fo_id_486669.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="dassearvu-manaidgarddis-oahpahusas-ja-du_id_486669.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>Gender Equality - regjeringen.no</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Gender Equality in Kindergarten, Education and Research</p>
<p>Gender equality work is a systematic approach work. It starts in kindergarten and continues in schools. Gender equality must be the basis at universities and college institutions and in the research field, in a way that gives both genders the same opportunities.</p>
<p>Ministry of Educationand Research is committed to work to ensure that equality becomes part of the basic values in kindergarten, in educatuion programs and in research.</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">http://www.gender.no/</p>
</list><p type="title">Gender Equality in the Research Sector</p>
<p>In 1992, women accounted for only 21 per cent of all doctorates in Norwegian universities and university colleges. By 2002 the proportion of women had increased significantly to 40 per cent and it has remained stable at this level ever since. However, in 2004 women accounted for only 16 per cent of appointments to professorships, and progress in this area is very slow.</p>
<p type="title">Gender Equality in Higher Education</p>
<p>Norway has a very high proportion of women with higher education degrees. In 2004, almost 60 per cent of registered students at Norwegian universities and colleges were women. More than 21 per cent of Norwegian women have a university or college degree, compared with 16 per cent of Norwegian men.</p>
<p type="title">Gender Equality in Comprehensive Education</p>
<p>Work on achieving gender equality in the Norwegian school system has been given a high priority for many years. The content of educational programmes shall have sufficient focus on the question of gender equality, boys and girls shall receive equal treatment at school, and the gender distribution of staff shall be evened out.</p>
<p type="title">Gender Equality in Kindergartens</p>
<p>From 1 January 2006, day care centres come under the Ministry of Education and Research, rather than the Ministry of Children and Equality. This means that day care centres in Norway are regarded as being part of the educational system, part of the learning process.</p>
<p type="title">The good kindergarten is a gender equal kindergarten</p>
<p>State Secretary Lisbeth Rugvedt’s talk to the national conference for the implementation of the Plan of Action for Gender Equality in Kindergartens 2004-2007, hosted by the Ministry for Education and Research and the governor of Vestfold, 27.11.2006, Tønsberg.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">Action Plan for Gender Equality</p>
<p>Gender equality work requires us to act here and now but also entails systematic and long-term work on attitudes. This Action Plan deals with the most important measures the Ministry wishes to implement to promote gender equality in kindergartens and primary and secondary education and training.</p>
</body></document>
