<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The Order of Merit  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>286</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/artikkel.html?tid=28663</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="artikkel.html_tid=27596.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="artikkel.html_tid=76215_sek=75869.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">The Order of Merit</p>
<p>The Royal Norwegian Order of Merit was founded by King Olav V in 1985. It is conferred on foreign and Norwegian nationals as a reward for their outstanding service in the interest of Norway.</p>
<p>His Majesty The King is the Grand Master of the Order. The Order of Merit is divided into three classes and two sub-classes:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Grand Cross</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Grand Officer <list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Commander</p>
</list></p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Officer <list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Knight</p>
</list></p>
</list><p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Design</p>
<p>The Insignia of the Order is the Cross of St. Olav, wrought in gold or silver, with a plain crown in each of the four corners formed by the arms of the cross, inlaid with a rounded, red cross in the centre with King Olav V’s monogram surmounted by a crown.</p>
<p>Commander of the Norwegian Order of Merit. Photo: Kjartan Hauglid, the Royal Court.</p>
<p type="title">How the insignia is worn</p>
<p>The Insignia of the Order is worn in the same manner at that of the Order of St. Olav:</p>
<p>The Knight’s Cross is worn on the left breast, and the Commander’s Cross is suspended from a ribbon around the neck. The Grand Cross is attached to a broad sash worn passing from the right shoulder to the left side. Women wear the Knight’s Cross and Commander’s Cross on the left breast attached to a bow made from the Knight’s Cross ribbon.</p>
<p>The Insignia of the Order is returned to the Council of the Order in the event of the promotion or death of the recipient.</p>
<p type="title">Nominations</p>
<p>Nominations for order recipients should be addressed to His Majesty The King and submitted via the Department for Culture, Public Diplomacy and Protocol at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">05.04.2017</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
</body></document>