<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The Crown Prince's Coronet  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>291</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/artikkel.html?tid=29288</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="artikkel.html_tid=27827.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="artikkel.html_tid=75805_sek=74949.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">The Crown Prince's Coronet</p>
<p>The Crown Prince's Coronet was made in Christiana (Oslo) in 1846. Originally intended for Crown Prince Carl, the coronet has never been used.</p>
<p>The Crown Prince's Coronet is the crown of the heir to the throne, and is the only object of royal regalia produced in Norway. It was designed for Crown Prince Carl (later King Carl IV) in connection with the planned coronation of his parents, King Oscar I and Queen Josephine. During the coronation of King Carl Johan it had been necessary to borrow the crown of the Swedish crown prince; the time had come for Norway to have its own.</p>
<p>The coronet was fashioned by the goldsmith Herman Colbjørnsen Øyset of Christiania and designed by Johannes Flintoe, who also took part in the embellishment of the Royal Palace under construction at the time.</p>
<p>However, the Norwegian coronation of King Oscar I and Queen Josefine did not take place, and the Crown Princes Coronet has never been used.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Design</p>
<p>The Crown Princes Coronet is an open design consisting of eight cusped spikes decorated with gemstones and pearls. Each cusped spike has a large Norwegian freshwater pearl at the point. The crown ring, cusped spikes and ornaments in between are decked with flowers and leaves of pressed gold. The central stone is a faceted, oval amethyst.</p>
<p>The cap is sewn in violet velvet with embroidery of gilded silver thread.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="deu">Materials</p>
<p>The crown is made of multi-coloured gold inlaid with pearls, gemstones and polychrome glass. The pearls are the Norwegian freshwater variety; the gemstones are amethyst, perodite and citrine.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Height: 15 cm Diameter: 18 cm Weight: 1,030 g</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">17.04.2013</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">The Regalia are on display in Trondheim</p>
</list></body></document>
