<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Royal trusts and patronage  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>361</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/artikkel.html?tid=28658</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="artikkel.html_tid=27595.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="artikkel.html_tid=76201_sek=74935.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Royal trusts and patronage</p>
<p>There is a longstanding tradition of Royal patronage. In earlier, more turbulent times, patronage often involved physical protection by bodyguards or a royal letter of protection.</p>
<p>Today Royal patronage serves to raise public awareness of an organisation or a specific event that supports a worthy cause.</p>
<p type="title">Application for Royal patronage</p>
<p>Applications for Royal patronage are assessed on an ongoing basis and in relation to the Royal Familys programme and individual areas of interest.</p>
<p>To be eligible for Royal patronage, an organisation must be well-established, non-controversial and have a sound financial status. If patronage is granted to an umbrella organisation, it will normally not apply to underlying member organisations.</p>
<p>Royal patronage is generally granted for a period of five years, after which an organisation must submit a new application.</p>
<p>Royal patronage may also be granted for individual events such as exhibitions, tours by performing troupes or conferences.</p>
<p type="title">The Royal Trusts</p>
<p>Support may also be given more directly via grants from royal trusts. There are three Royal Trusts:</p>
<list><p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Crown Princess Märthas Memorial Fund </em>The purpose of the fund is to provide financial support to social and humanitarian initiatives carried out by non-governmental organisations. </p>
</list><list><p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Princess Märtha Louise's Fund </em>The fund provides assistance to disabled children under the age of 16 in Norway. Allocations are earmarked for initiatives designed to enrich the daily lives of children with disabilities. </p>
</list><list><p type="listitem"><em type="italic">The Crown Prince and Crown Princess Humanitarian Fund </em>The Crown Prince Haakon and Crown Princess Mette-Marits Foundation addresses the needs of young people who for various, often complex reasons are at risk of becoming marginalised in society. The foundation seeks to make a difference for young people in Norway. </p>
</list><p xml:lang="vep">08.02.2013</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">The Crown Prince and Crown Princess Foundation (Article)</p>
<p type="listitem">Princess Märtha Louise's Fund (Article)</p>
<p type="listitem">Crown Princess Märthas Memorial Fund (Article)</p>
<p type="listitem">Organisations under the patronage of HM The King (Article)</p>
<p type="listitem">Organisations under the patronage of HM The Queen (Article)</p>
<p type="listitem">Organisations under the patronage of The Crown Prince (Article)</p>
<p type="listitem">Organisations under the patronage of The Crown Princess (Article)</p>
<p type="listitem">Organisations under the patronage of Princess Märtha Louise (Article)</p>
<p type="listitem">Organisations under the patronage of Princess Astrid (Article)</p>
</list></body></document>
