<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Focus: Children and young people   - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>436</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/artikkel.html?tid=89748</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="artikkel.html_tid=91258_sek=91253.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Focus: Children and young people</p>
<p>Improving conditions for children and young people has occupied a central place in the work of the Crown Prince and Crown Princess since the time of their marriage in 2001.</p>
<p>The Crown Prince and Crown Princess Foundation was established in connection with their wedding. The Foundation has enabled the Crown Princess to focus on young people with special needs and on efforts to create a society in which all people feel included.</p>
<p>The Crown Princess has also taken an interest in young asylum seekers in the local community. The Crown Prince and Crown Princess invited a group of young people from Hvalstad reception centre to go bowling, for example, and also took part in a day out sledging. The Crown Princess is concerned with creating secure, beneficial conditions for children and young people where they can be appreciated for their potential, ability and individual qualities.</p>
<p type="title">Young peoples potential</p>
<p>In recent years the Crown Princess has become particularly interested in the role that young people can play in effecting positive change – both in their own lives and in society in general. For Crown Princess Mette-Marit it is important that young people receive support and encouragement to believe in themselves and to fulfil their potential, and that they are given a chance to contribute. This is particularly evident in her HIV and AIDS-related work, where the Crown Princess works actively to support young people carrying out AIDS prevention work – and is keen to see young people take part in setting the agenda for both the strategic and the practical aspects of the global effort.</p>
<p>Mental health is another area of the Crown Princesss work in which her interest in supporting young people is evident. The Crown Princess takes part regularly at events designed to promote openness towards mental health. A key theme in this respect is breaking down taboos surrounding mental health issues.</p>
<p>The Crown Princess also works to support young people in the area of education and creative development. For example, the Crown Princess has attended events held in connection with the Amandus Film Festival for Young Filmmakers in Lillehammer.</p>
<p>The Crown Princess also works on behalf of children through the Norwegian Guide and Scout Association, the child protection services and through visits to schools. She also assists the Crown Prince with events held in connection with the Global Dignity initiative, where the focus is on discussions with schoolchildren about the concept of dignity.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">14.11.2012</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">The Crown Prince and Crown Princess Foundation (Article)</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">The Amandus Festival for Young Filmmakers</p>
</list></body></document>
