<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Princess Ragnhild   - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>372</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/artikkel.html?tid=28752</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="artikkel.html_tid=27577.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="artikkel.html_tid=76318_sek=75017.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="sme">Princess Ragnhild</p>
<p>Princess Ragnhild Mrs Lorentzen was born at the Royal Palace in Oslo on 9 June 1930. She was the oldest child of King Olav V (1903-1991) and Crown Princess Märtha (1901-1954). At an extraordinary meeting of the Council of State after the birth of the princess, King Haakon VII announced that she would be given the name Ragnhild Alexandra.</p>
<p>Princess Ragnhild was not entitled to succeed to the Throne.</p>
<p type="title">Early life</p>
<p>With the exception of a period in 1931, when the main house was being rebuilt after a fire, Princess Ragnhild spent her childhood in the peaceful surroundings of the Skaugum Estate, near Oslo. However, this came to an abrupt end on 9 April 1940, when German troops invaded Norway. To avoid being taken into custody by the occupying forces, the Royal Family, the Government and most members of the Norwegian Storting (national assembly) escaped from Oslo by train.</p>
<p>When they reached Elverum, Crown Prince Olav and his family parted company. Crown Princess Märtha and the three children, Princess Ragnhild, Princess Astrid and Prince Harald, fled to safety across the border to Sweden. After several months in Sweden, the Crown Princess and her children travelled to the USA by sea. While King Haakon and Crown Prince Olav had their base in London, the Crown Princess lived with the children in the outskirts of Washington, DC, until 1945, when peace was declared.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="isl">Family</p>
<p>Princess Ragnhild lived at Skaugum until her marriage to Mr Erling Sven Lorentzen (born 28 January 1923). The couple were wed in Asker Church on 15 May 1953. King Haakon decided by royal resolution that after her marriage the Princesss title would be Her Highness Princess Ragnhild Mrs Lorentzen.</p>
<p>Princess Ragnhild and her husband settled in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</p>
<p>They couple had three children: Mr Haakon Lorentzen, born 23 August 1954, Mrs Ingeborg Ribeiro, born 27 February 1957, and Mrs Ragnhild Lorentzen, born 8 May 1968.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="spa">Funeral</p>
<p>The Princess passed away at her home in Rio de Janeiro on 16 September 2012. The funeral service was held in the Palace Chapel in Oslo on 28 September 2012.</p>
<p>The Princess was laid to rest at Asker Church.</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">28.09.2012</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
</body></document>
