<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>The Royal Wedding in 2001  - The Royal House of Norway</title>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <wordcount>318</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <license type="standard"/>
    </availability>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/artikkel.html?tid=28768</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="artikkel.html_tid=29240.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="artikkel.html_tid=76558_sek=76448.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
    <p>The Royal House of Norway</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">The Royal Wedding in 2001</p>
    <p>Their Royal Highnesses The Crown Prince and Crown Princess were married in Oslo Cathedral on 25 August 2001.</p>
    <p>The wedding ceremony was conducted by Bishop Gunnar Stålsett and featured a performance by the Sami singer Mari Boine. Miss Betina and Miss Emilie Swanstrøm, Miss Kamilla and Miss Anniken Bjørnøy and Miss Tuva Høiby were the bridesmaids, and Master Marius Borg Høiby was the page.</p>
    <p type="title" xml:lang="sme">Bridal gown</p>
    <p>The Crown Princesss bridal gown was the result of a collaboration between the bride, designer Ove Harder Finseth and seamstress Anna Bratland. The gown was of thick silk crêpe and soft silk tulle, custom-dyed ecru. The skirt was flared with a two-metre-long train, inspired by the gowns of Queen Maud.</p>
    <p>The Crown Princess wore a tiara made in 1910, which was a gift from Their Majesties The King and Queen.</p>
    <p type="title">Bridal bouquet</p>
    <p>The idea for the bridal bouquet was developed in close cooperation between the bride and Aina Nyberget Kleppe, the general manager of the florist Passiflora A/S in Oslo. The bouquet was made up of rosary vine (Ceropegia woodii), Wanda orchids (a Phalaenopsis orchid), hydrangeas, roses in pink and mauve tones, bear grass, beads and metal threads.</p>
    <p>The bride and grooms wedding rings were made in collaboration with jewellery designer Ester Helén Slagsvold and were a gift from the Norwegian Association of Goldsmiths.</p>
    <p type="title">Wedding banquet</p>
    <p>Members of the European Royal Houses attended the wedding banquet at the Palace, along with Norwegian officials, representatives of organisations, family and friends. A second wedding banquet was held concurrently at the Oslo Military Society.</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">18.01.2013</p>
    <p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>The wedding of Their Royal Highnesses The Crown Prince and Crown Pricness 25 August 2001 (in Norwegian)  (Photo: NRK archives)</p>
    <p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">The Royal Wedding in 1968 (Article)</p>
      <p type="listitem">The wedding of Princess Märtha Louise (Article)</p>
      <p type="listitem">The Royal Wedding in 1929 (Article)</p>
    </list>
  </body>
</document>
