<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The wedding of Princess Märtha Louise  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>529</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/artikkel.html?tid=28747</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="artikkel.html_tid=27569.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="artikkel.html_tid=76307_sek=76255.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p type="title">The wedding of Princess Märtha Louise</p>
<p>Her Highness Princess Märtha Louise and Mr Ari Behn were married in Nidaros Cathedral on 24 May 2002.</p>
<p>Nidaros Cathedral was decorated with Märtha lilies (a white Easter Lily), yellow and cream lilies, pale roses, marguerites and lilies-of-the-valley.</p>
<p>Ms Marianne Ulrichsen was the maid of honour, and Mr Kåre Conradi was the best man. Miss Madeleine Ferner Johansen, Miss Betina Swanstrøm and Miss Emilie Swanstrøm were the bridesmaids, and Master Ask Andreas Bjørshol Grønsund was the page.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="sme">Bridal gown</p>
<p>Princess Märtha Louise’s two-piece wedding costume was designed by Wenche Lyche. The jacket, with its long train, was made by the designer, while the gown itself was sewn by Anna Bratland.</p>
<p>The costume was inspired by the shape and colour of the Märtha lily. The bridal jacket was of off-white duchesse satin, with a three-metre-long train that ended in a pointed gothic arch. The bridal gown was of white silk crêpe. The silk chiffon veil had the same cut as the train of the gown, and was attached to a tiara that originally belonged to Queen Maud.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Bridal bouquet</p>
<p>Princess Märtha Louise’s bridal bouquet consisted mainly of lilies-of-the-valley, orchids and Märtha lilies. The colours were white and cream, and the bouquet was made by Barbro Kirknes of Wallden &amp; Moum AS in Trondheim.</p>
<p>The wedding rings were hand made by the goldsmith Ulf Larsen in white gold with brilliants.</p>
<p type="title">Wedding banquet</p>
<p>The wedding banquet and ball were held at the Stiftsgården, the Royal residence in Trondheim. There were over 200 guests, including members of the European Royal Houses, Norwegian officials, representatives of organisations, family and friends.</p>
<p type="title">Music during the wedding ceremony</p>
<p>The entrance music:</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Nidaros Cathedral Boys' Choir sang <span type="quote">”I was glad”</span>. Composed by Svein Møller</p>
</list><p>During the ceremony:</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Gregoriran chant: <span type="quote" xml:lang="vep">”Lux illuxit laetabunda”</span>. Text and melody from the 12th century.</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Hymn: <span type="quote">”The love of God is broad like beach and meadow”</span>. Text: Anders Frostenson. Melody: Lars Åke Lundberg.</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nno">Sissel Kyrkjebø and Nidaros Girls' Choir sang <span type="quote">”Lord, let me know your ways and courses”</span>. Text: Jakob Paulli. Melody: Norwegian folk tune.</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Nidaros Cathedral Choir sang <span type="quote" xml:lang="deu">”Amen”</span> from <span type="quote">”Lo, the Full, Final Sacrifice”</span> by Gerald Finzi.</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Nidaros Cathedral Boys' Choir sang <span type="quote">”The Peace of God”</span> by John Rutter.</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">Hymn: <span type="quote">”O God, we pray you, bless these two”</span>. Text: Lars Hætta. Melody: Halvdan Nedrejord.</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">The Nidaros Girls' Choir sang <span type="quote">”Spring”</span>. Text: A. O. Vinje. Melody: Edvard Grieg</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Hymn: <span type="quote">”On your way! Be brave and true”</span>. Text: Christian Richard. Melody: C.E.F. Weyse.</p>
</list><p>Exit music:</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Toccata in F Major from Organ symfony no 5 in f minor by Charles-Marie Widor</p>
</list><p type="title">The menu for the wedding banquet:</p>
<p><em type="italic">Trout tartare </em>with fresh asparagus and poached quails’ eggs </p>
<p><em type="italic">Noisettes of veal </em>with spring vegetables and potato fondant with purée of Jerusalem artichokes </p>
<p><em type="italic">Grilled chèvre </em>and mild white’s goat cheese on spiced biscuits </p>
<p><em type="italic">Vanilla bavarois with raspberries </em>with pomegranate sauce </p>
<p xml:lang="koi">07.11.2012</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Her Highness Princess Märtha Louise and Mr Ari Behn are married 24 May 2002 (Photo: NRK arkiv)</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">The Royal Wedding in 2001 (Article)</p>
<p type="listitem">The Royal Wedding in 1968 (Article)</p>
<p type="listitem">The Royal Wedding in 1929 (Article)</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Stiftsgården (Article)</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">The Nidaros Cathedral</p>
</list></body></document>
