<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>State Visit from India   - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>554</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=122972</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyhet.html_tid=122972.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=122972_sek=74887.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title">State Visit from India</p>
<p>Today, Their Majesties The King and Queen welcomed President Pranab Mukherjee of India and his daughter, Madame Sharmistha Mukherjee, to Norway. The visit began with a formal ceremony on the Palace Square this morning.</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">13.10.2014</p>
<p>This is the first time the head of state of India has conducted a State Visit to Norway. The objective is to further develop the good relations between the two countries and to strengthen cooperation in the industrial and cultural spheres as well as on research and education.</p>
<p>The visit is taking place just a few days after the Norwegian Nobel Committee announced that the Nobel Peace Prize for 2014 would be awarded to India’s  Kailash Satyarthi and Pakistan’s Malala Yosufzai <span type="quote">“for their struggle against the suppression of children and young people and for the right of all children to education”</span>.</p>
<p type="title">Welcoming ceremony</p>
<p>His Royal Highness Crown Prince Haakon accompanied President  Mukherjee and Madame Mukherjee to the Palace Square, where they were received by the King, the Queen and Her Royal Highness Crown Princess Mette-Marit.</p>
<p>The Palace Square was decorated with Indian and Norwegian flags. The  King’s Guard military band played the national anthems of both countries, after which the President inspected the Guard.</p>
<p>Children waving Norwegian and Indian flags had come to watch the ceremony, and President  Mukherjee   took time to greet the children on his way into the Royal Palace to have official photographs taken in the Bird Room. Princess Astrid, Mrs Ferner joined the party for the photographs.</p>
<p type="title">Wreath-laying ceremony at the national monument</p>
<p>King Harald accompanied President Mukherjee  to Akershus Fortress where the president laid a wreath at the national monument commemorating the Norwegians who lost their lives in the Second World War. It is traditional for heads of state paying an official visit to Norway to lay a wreath at the monument.</p>
<p type="title">The Storting and Oslo City Hall</p>
<p>President  Mukherjee is heading a large delegation, including members of the Indian Parliament. The President and Madame Mukherjee visited the Storting, where they met with the President of the Storting, Olemic Thommessen. Afterwards, the King and Queen accompanied their guests to Oslo City Hall.</p>
<p>Mayor of Oslo Fabian Stang welcomed the guests to a guided tour of Oslo City Hall and a cultural performance in the Banquet hall.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="isl">Fram Museum</p>
<p>The afternoon’s programme consisted of a visit to the Fram Museum. The museum houses the polar vessel <em type="italic">Fram </em>, and tells the story of the Norwegian polar explorers. The guests were received by Museum Director Geir Kløver, and provided with insights on the polar areas and climate change.   </p>
<p>The Indian President also got to speak with scientists at the Indian research station in Ny Ålesund and Indian students at the University Centre at Svalbard via videolink during the visit.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Gala dinner</p>
<p>This evening, the King and Queen are hosting a gala dinner at the Royal Palace in honour of the President of India  and Madame Sharmistha Mukherjee. The Crown Prince, the Crown Princess and Princess Astrid, Mrs Ferner will also be present at the dinner, which will be attended by 193 guests.</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Kong Haralds tale under gallamiddagen til ære for Indias president, Pranab Mukherjee. Foto: NRK</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">State visit from India: His Majesty's speech (Speech)</p>
<p type="listitem">Norwegian-Indian cooperation (News article)</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">The Fram Museum</p>
</list></body></document>
