<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Funeral service  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>228</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=102798</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyhet.html_tid=102786.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=102792_sek=74887.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Funeral service</p>
<p>The funeral service for Her Highness Princess Ragnhild, Mrs Lorentzen will be held in the Palace Chapel on Friday, 28 September 2012. The Princess' casket is scheduled to arrive at Oslo Airport Gardermoen on Saturday, 22 September.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">18.09.2012</p>
<p>On 20 September, the Consulate General and the Norwegian Seamans Church will arrange a memorial service in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
<p type="title">Arrival of the casket</p>
<p>The casket bearing the remains of Princess Ragnhild is scheduled to arrive at Oslo Airport Gardermoen on Saturday, 22 September. His Majesty The King and Her Highness Princess Astrid, Mrs Ferner will be in attendance to receive the casket.</p>
<p type="title">Funeral service at the Palce Chapel</p>
<p>The funeral service for Princess Ragnhild will be held in the Palace Chapel on Friday, 28 September 2012, at 12:00 pm. Their Majesties The King and Queen, Their Royal Highnesses The Crown Prince and Crown Princess, Her Highness Princess Astrid, Mrs Ferner and Her Highness Princess Märtha Louise will be in attendance.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Bishop Ole Christian Kvarme and Dean of Oslo Cathedral Olav Dag Hauge will preside over the ceremony.</p>
<p>The funeral service will be followed by a reception at the Palace hosted by Their Majesties The King and Queen.</p>
<p>Princess Ragnhild, Mrs Lorentzen will be laid to rest at Asker Church.</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Her Highness Princess Ragnhild (Subject entry page)</p>
</list></body></document>
