<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The Abel Prize for 2010  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>545</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=85712</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyhet.html_tid=85704.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=85728_sek=74887.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p type="title">The Abel Prize for 2010</p>
<p>His Majesty The King presented the Abel Prize to Professor John Torrence Tate today, for his vast and lasting impact on the theory of numbers. Earlier today, King Harald granted the Abel Laureate an audience at the Royal Palace.</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">25.05.2010</p>
<p>The Abel Prize is named in honour of the mathematician Niels Henrik Abel and is awarded for scientific excellence in the field of mathematics. The Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters decided to award the Abel Prize for 2010 to Professor John Torrence Tate of the University of Texas at Austin</p>
<p type="title">The Abel Committees citation</p>
<p>Beyond the simple arithmetic of 1, 2, 3,  lies a complex and intricate world that has challenged some of the finest minds throughout history. This world stretches from the mysteries of the prime numbers to the way we store, transmit, and secure information in modern computers. It is called the theory of numbers. Over the past century it has grown into one of the most elaborate and sophisticated branches of mathematics, interacting profoundly with other areas such as algebraic geometry and the theory of automorphic forms. John Tate is a prime architect of this development.</p>
<p>(...) Many of the major lines of research in algebraic number theory and arithmetic geometry are only possible because of the incisive contribution and illuminating insight of John Tate. He has truly left a conspicuous imprint on modern mathematics.</p>
<p type="title">The Ceremony</p>
<p>His Majesty The King presented the Abel Prize to Professor John Tate during a formal ceremony at the historic Gamle Logen banquet and concert hall in Oslo, starting at 14:00 PM today.</p>
<p>Praeses of The Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters, Professor Nils Christian Stenseth, gave the opening speech, and the chairman of the Abel committee, Professor Kristian Seip, expanded on the Committee's citation.</p>
<p type="title">The Abel Prize</p>
<p>The Abel Prize is an international award for scientific excellence in the field of mathematics. The prize seeks to enhance the status of mathematics within society at large and heighten interest in the field among children and young people. The prize of NOK 6 million was awarded for the first time in 2003.</p>
<p>The prize is named in honour of the mathematician Niels Henrik Abel, who during his short life developed several theories instrumental to the development of the field. Abel died of tuberculosis in 1829 at age 26.</p>
<p>It is traditional for the Abel Laureate to lay a wreath at the Niels Henrik Abel monument. The monument, sculpted by Gustav Vigeland, stands on Abel knoll in the Palace Park, and Professor Tate laid a wreath there on Monday.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Banquet at Akershus Fortress</p>
<p>In keeping with tradition, this evening the Government will host a banquet at Akershus Fortress in honour of the Abel Laureate. King Harald will attend the banquet, and Sir Michael Atiyah, the Abel Laureate 2004, will be the evening's main speaker.</p>
<p type="title">The Abel lecture</p>
<p>Tomorrow, Professor Tate will give his Abel lecture <span type="quote">"The arithmetic of elliptic curves"</span> at the University of Oslo. Thursday, the Laurerate travels to Kristiansand to meet with students and give a lecture at the University of Agder.</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">The statues in the Palace Park (Article)</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">The Abel Prize website</p>
<p type="listitem">About this year's Abel Prize Laureate</p>
</list></body></document>
