<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Visited Homer, Alaska  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>391</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=127840</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyhet.html_tid=127840.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=127840_sek=74887.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Visited Homer, Alaska</p>
<p>On Tuesday, His Majesty The King continued his official visit to the US, this time in Alaska, where he spoke with local climate researchers in the town of Homer.</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">27.05.2015</p>
<p>Homer is a small town of some 5 000 inhabitants on the Kenai Peninsula in southern Alaska. The town is located along the beautiful Kachemak Bay, an area surrounded by mountains, forests and glaciers. Not surprisingly, tourism is an important industry in Homer, and sport fishing for salmon and halibut is an especially popular activity. Located nearby is Kachemak Bay State Park, which offers many opportunities for outdoor recreation.</p>
<p type="title">Boat trip with researchers</p>
<p>King Harald had the chance to view some of the majestic natural surroundings during a boat trip on the fjord on Tuesday morning. The King was accompanied on board by Heather Renner and Angela Doroff, local researchers who shared information about local climate change.</p>
<p>The boat trip took the King and the researchers to Tutka Bay Lodge in the southern part of the fjord, where a luncheon was served.</p>
<p>King Harald is concerned about the impact of climate change on the natural environment – and on people’s lifestyles – in various parts of the world. In his speech to the students at Pacific Lutheran University on Saturday, the King encouraged the young people to address the problem and make a difference:</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"><em type="italic"><span type="quote">“My generation has little to show for itself when it comes to taking care of the environment and our climate. My hope is that your generation will do better. I feel fortunate to have the opportunity to engage with young people like yourselves. Highly motivated young people are already making a difference and pushing their governments to do more. I hope you will take part in raising awareness about the urgency of the environmental challenges that we are facing.”</span> </em></p>
<p type="title">Dinner with the Governor</p>
<p>On Tuesday evening, King Harald was the guest at an official dinner hosted by Alaska Governor Bill Walker in Anchorage, the state’s largest city.</p>
<p>King Harald’s official visit concludes on Wednesday with a busy programme of activities in Anchorage, where the focus will be on the Northern Areas, climate issues and Arctic conditions.</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Official visit to the US (News article)</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nno">Honorary doctorate from PLU (News article)</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nno">Arctic finale (News article)</p>
</list></body></document>
