<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Visited FMC Technologies   - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>260</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=119870</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyhet.html_tid=119870.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=119870_sek=74887.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p type="title">Visited FMC Technologies</p>
<p>His Royal Highness Crown Prince Haakon concluded his official visit to St. Petersburg today with a short visit to FMC Technologies. The Norwegian company is a leading global supplier of solutions for subsea oil and gas production.</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">27.02.2014</p>
<p>FMC Technologies established activities in Russia in 2009, with a head office in Moscow. In St. Petersburg, the company collaborates on competence-building with St. Petersburg State Polytechnical University, and has established an educational centre, the FMC Polytechnic Center, on the campus. Here, students who have completed a Masters degree in mechanical engineering may take a six-month course in subsea technology. Subsequently, those who qualify may continue with a 12–18 month trainee programme at company headquarters in Kongsberg, Norway. Individuals who complete the programme are offered a position at FMCs Engineering Center in St. Petersburg.</p>
<p>Crown Prince Haakon was given a presentation of the companys background during his visit to the offices near the Winter Palace. Two employees provided him with their insights into the research cooperation and what it is like to be a young Russian engineer in a Norwegian company.</p>
<p type="title">Subsea deliveries</p>
<p>FMC Technologies has delivered all the subsea equipment for Russias first purely subsea field: Gazproms Kirinskoye field off Sakhalin in the easternmost part of the country. The field was opened in 2013, and the system will produce gas from six wells. The installation is the first of its kind in Russia.</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nno">The Crown Prince in St. Petersburg (News article)</p>
<p type="listitem">Opened new production facility (News article)</p>
</list></body></document>
