<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Trade, health and culture   - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>503</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=93870</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="nyhet.html_tid=93813.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=93874_sek=74887.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p type="title">Trade, health and culture</p>
<p>Their Majesties The King and Queen accompanied South African President His Excellency Jacob Zuma and Mrs Tobeka Zuma on a number of visits today. The business sector, health and culture were the focus of the programme for the second day of the State Visit.</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">01.09.2011</p>
<p>King Harald and President Zuma started the day with a visit to the Norwegian company Det Norske Veritas. Minister of Petroleum and Energy, Mr Ola Borten Moe and business representatives from South Africa and Norway attended the meeting, where Veritas presented solutions for the harvesting and storage of CO². This December, the United Nations Climate Change Conference,  COP17, will take place in Durban, South Africa.</p>
<p>After the meeting, The King and President went on to the Gamle Logen meeting centre to join Norwegian and South African representatives for a business seminar.</p>
<p>A number of Norwegian companies have established themselves in South Africa and trade between the two countries is increasing. The seminar was hosted by Innovation Norway, which has an office in Johannesburg and works actively to facilitate contacts between Norwegian and South African companies.</p>
<p>The number of Norwegian tourists visiting South Africa has also grown in recent years, reaching over 23 000 each year.</p>
<p type="title">Lecture by South African President</p>
<p>After the seminar King Harald accompanied the South African President to the Nobel Institute where President Zuma gave a lecture entitled Peace and Reconciliation – a South African Perspective. Later in the day the President had meetings with Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Oslo University Hospital</p>
<p>In a parallel programme, Queen Sonja and Mrs Tobeka Zuma visited Oslo University Hospital, where they were given a presentation of the hospitals international cooperation activities. Dr Eyrun Kjetland spoke particularly of the cooperation Oslo University Hospital has established with various South African groups on diseases affecting women.</p>
<p>The Queen and Mrs Zuma also received an introduction into the work being carried out by Oslo University Hospital in the field of cancer.</p>
<p type="title">Official luncheon</p>
<p>The Government held a luncheon in honour of the President and First Lady at Akerhus Castle today, hosted by Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg and his wife Ingrid Schulerud. The King and Queen were in attendance, as were representatives of the Government and other Norwegian institutions.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Visit to Holmenkollen</p>
<p>This afternoon the King and Queen and the presidential couple visited the Holmenkollen Ski Jump arena. While yesterday at the Nobel Peace Center the emphasis was on Fridtjof Nansen the humanitarian, today the focus was on Nansen the polar explorer.</p>
<p>The Ski Museum is located inside the mountain under the ski jumping hill and presents 4 000 years of skiing history as well as exhibitions on the most important polar expeditions undertaken by Fridtjof Nansen and Roald Amundsen.</p>
<p>The State Visit will be concluded this evening when President Zuma and Mrs Tobeka Zuma meet with members of the press at the Royal Palace.</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">State Visit from South Africa (News article)</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="isl">The Ski Museum</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Ullevål University Hospital</p>
</list></body></document>
