<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>State Visit from Canada  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>218</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=78046</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyhet.html_tid=78016.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=78175_sek=74887.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">State Visit from Canada</p>
<p>On Tuesday Their Majesties The King and Queen welcomed Her Excellency the Right Honourable Michaëlle Jean, the Governor General of Canada, and her husband, His Excellency Jean-Daniel Lafond, to Norway.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">29.04.2009</p>
<p>Their Royal Highnesses The Crown Prince and Crown Princess also took part in the official reception on the Palace Square.</p>
<p>Following the ceremony, the Governor General paid a visit to the Storting, where she met with the Vice President of the Storting.</p>
<p type="title">Wreath-laying ceremonies</p>
<p>Accompanied by King Harald and Queen Sonja, Governor General Jean and Mr Lafond laid several wreaths, first at the national monument at Akershus Fortress and then at the Canadian wartime gravesites at Vestre Gravlund.</p>
<p>In the afternoon Governor General Jean met with Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="smj">Gala banquet</p>
<p>The King and Queen hosted a lunch for the Governor General and her party at 2 pm at the Royal Palace. In the evening a banquet was held at the Royal Palace in honour of the official visitors from Canada. In addition to The King and Queen, other members of the Royal Family in attendance were Crown Prince Haakon, Crown Princess Mette-Marit and Princess Astrid.</p>
<p>The State Visit will last from 28 to 30 April.</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">The Governor General of Canada</p>
</list></body></document>