<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Final day in Bergen  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>386</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=86036</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyhet.html_tid=86019.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=86106_sek=74887.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="deu">Final day in Bergen</p>
<p>Her Majesty Queen Beatrix concluded her three-day State Visit on Thursday in Bergen. Their Majesties King Harald and Queen Sonja accompanied the Queen of The Netherlands on her visit to the former Hanseatic city.</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">04.06.2010</p>
<p>Norway and The Netherlands have much in common, with ties dating back many centuries. In his speech during the gala banquet on Tuesday, King Harald commented on the large trade in timber conducted between the two countries in the 1600s and humorously referred to the fact that the city of Amsterdam had been built on Norwegian wood.</p>
<p>Although the Hanseatic League had several port cities in Norway, Bergen was its crown jewel, as the old, wooden buildings along the wharf still attest. At the time, The Netherlands probably comprised the Hanseatic Leagues keenest competition . On Thursday, Queen Beatrix was given a guided historical tour of the city by Norwegian author Gunnar Staalesen. King Harald and Queen Sonja accompanied Queen Beatrix on the tour, which concluded on board the Norwegian Coast Guard vessel K/V Bergen.</p>
<p type="title">Conference on sustainable fisheries</p>
<p>On board the K/V Bergen, Queen Beatrix, King Harald and Queen Sonja attended a roundtable conference on sustainable fisheries. The Institute of Marine Research organised the conference which brought together researchers and professionals in the fisheries industry for discussion and exchange of information.</p>
<p>Norway and The Netherlands both have much to gain from ensuring sound resource management in the North Sea, and more knowledge is needed about the various fish stocks and their dependence on each other to ensure that sustainable fisheries management regimes are implemented.</p>
<p>In connection with the State Visit, a major business conference focusing on the concept of sustainability was held at the Institute of Marine Research.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nno">Concert at Troldhaugen</p>
<p>Queen Beatrix, King Harald and Queen Sonja rode the Fløibanen Funicular to the top of Fløyen Mountain, where Mayor of Bergen Gunnar Bakke hosted an official luncheon. The entourage then visited Troldhaugen, once home to Norwegian composer Edvard Grieg, where pianist Audun Kayser performed for the guests.</p>
<p>The visit to Troldhaugen was the final stop on Queen Beatrixs itinerary. From there she travelled to Bergen Flesland Airport and returned to Amsterdam.</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">State Visit from the Netherlands (News article)</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">The Royal House of the Netherlands</p>
</list></body></document>
