<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Johan Martin Ferner has died  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>198</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=124700</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyhet.html_tid=124700.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=124700_sek=74887.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Johan Martin Ferner has died</p>
<p>Johan Martin Ferner passed away quietly at Oslo University Hospital, Rikshospitalet, today, 24 January 2015 at 05.25 AM.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">24.01.2015</p>
<p>Message of condolence from His Majesty The King:</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"><em type="italic"><span type="quote">“It is with deep sadness that we have received the news that Johan Martin Ferner has passed away. Our thoughts go to Princess Astrid and her family, who have lost a wonderful husband, father, father-in-law and grandfather.”</span> </em></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Johan Martin Ferner</p>
<p>Johan Martin Ferner was born on 22 July 1927. He pursued an education in business in Norway, England and France, and studied at the London Polytechnic Institute, Bradford Technical College and the University of Lyon. Together with his brother he ran and developed the department store <em type="italic">Ferner Jacobsen </em>, which was a family business. </p>
<p>Mr Ferner was an accomplished sailor, and was part of the crew that won the silver medal in the 6 metre class at the 1952 Summer Olympics in Helsinki.</p>
<p>Her Highness Princess Astrid and Johan Martin Ferner were married in Asker Church on 12 January 1961. The couple had five children together.</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Wedding 1961 (Photo album)</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Her Highness Princess Astrid (Article)</p>
</list></body></document>
