<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Funeral service for Princess Ragnhild  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>347</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=102959</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nyhet.html_tid=102958.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=102979_sek=74887.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nno">Funeral service for Princess Ragnhild</p>
<p>The funeral service for Her Highness Princess Ragnhild, Mrs Lorentzen was held on Friday, 28 September 2012. The Princess passed away at her home in Rio de Janeiro in Brazil on 16 September. She was 82 years old.</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">28.09.2012</p>
<p>Their Majesties The King and Queen, Their Royal Highnesses The Crown Prince and Crown Princess, Her Highness Princess Astrid, Mrs Ferner and Her Highness Princess Märtha Louise were in attendance at the funeral service.</p>
<p>Her Royal Highness Crown Princess Victoria represented the Royal Family of Sweden. Norwegian government officials in attendance included President of the Storting Dag Terje Andersen, Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg, Supreme Court Justice Toril Marie Øie, County Governor of Oslo and Akershus Valgerd Svarstad Haugland, Mayor of Oslo Fabian Stang, and Chief of Defence Harald Sunde.</p>
<p type="title">Funeral service and reception</p>
<p>Draped in the National Flag, the casket bearing the remains of the Princess was placed on a catafalque in the choir of the Palace Chapel. The chapel was filled with flowers and wreaths from family and friends.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Mr Haakon Lorentzen delivered the eulogy for his mother. Bishop Ole Christian Kvarme and Dean of Oslo Cathedral Olav Dag Hauge presided over the ceremony.</p>
<p>The funeral service was followed by a reception hosted by the King and Queen at the Royal Palace.</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">Asker Church</p>
<p>The funeral procession with the Princesss casket and the closest members of the family left the Royal Palace by the main gate at 2:30 pm.</p>
<p>Princess Ragnhild, Mrs Lorentzen was laid to rest at Asker Church, with only close family members in attendance.</p>
<p type="title">Arrival of the casket</p>
<p>On Saturday evening, 22 September, King Harald and Princess Astrid, Mrs Ferner were in attendance to receive the casket of their sister at Oslo Airport Gardermoen. Princess Ragnhilds husband, Mr Erling Lorentzen, and two of their three children were also present.</p>
<p>Princess Ragnhild was born on 9 June 1930 at the Royal Palace in Oslo. She was the eldest child of King Olav and Crown Princess Märtha.</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Princess Ragnhild (Article)</p>
</list></body></document>
