<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Polish-Norwegian cooperation  - The Royal House of Norway</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>373</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.royalcourt.no/nyhet.html?tid=136007</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="nyhet.html_tid=136007.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nyhet.html_tid=136007_sek=74887.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hopp til hovedinnhold</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Polish-Norwegian cooperation</p>
<p>Defence cooperation was the focus of the programme for His Majesty The King and His Excellency the President of the Republic of Poland Mr Andrzej Duda today. However, the second day of the State Visit started off with a business seminar.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">24.05.2016</p>
<p>The King and the President arrived at the <em type="italic">Høyres Hus </em>conference centre this morning for the joint opening of a business seminar on cooperation between Poland and Norway in the offshore, energy and maritime industries. Poland is one of Norway’s ten most important trading partners, and Norwegian exports to Poland are increasing. </p>
<p>Following the opening, King Harald and President Duda continued on to the Norwegian Nobel Institute, where the President gave a lecture.</p>
<p type="title">Defence cooperation</p>
<p>Norway and Poland cooperate closely in NATO, which King Harald pointed out in his remarks during the gala dinner in honour of the President and First lady yesterday evening.</p>
<p><em type="italic"><span type="quote">“Poland plays a crucial role in the defence alliance by virtue of its size and geographical location, and the next NATO summit will be held in Warsaw in July. Our countries enjoy close bilateral cooperation in the defence industry. Cooperation on security and defence is thus a main focus of the President’s visit to Norway,”</span> said the King. </em></p>
<p>Today King Harald accompanied the President to Akershus Fortress, where they were given a presentation of the Norwegian Advanced Surface to Air Missile System at the fortress square. They also witnessed the signing of an agreement between Kongsberg Gruppen and the Polish Armament Group on expansion of their collaboration. The two companies already cooperate on deliveries for a coastal defence system to the Polish navy.</p>
<p type="title">Will travel to Bodø</p>
<p>Following these activities, Prime Minister Erna Solberg hosted a luncheon on behalf of the Norwegian Government on the occasion of the State Visit. King Harald, President Duda, First Lady Mrs Agata Kornhauser-Duda, and Her Royal Highness The Crown Princess attended the luncheon at Akershus Castle.</p>
<p>Later in the afternoon, President Duda and Mrs Kornhauser-Duda will travel to Bodø. King Harald will also accompany them in Nordland county, and will be their guest at an official dinner held in Bodø this evening.</p>
<p type="title">To share this on Twitter or Facebook:</p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p xml:lang="est">Links</p>
<list><p type="listitem">State Visit from Poland (News article)</p>
</list></body></document>
