<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="science"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>532</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>orig/sme/science/uit/phd/ammar_hassan.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="ammar_hassan.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p><em type="bold">SUMMARY </em></p>
<p>Semi-domesticated reindeer ( <em type="italic">Rangifer tarandus tarandus L </em>.) is an important part of the Sami culture and a main constituent of Sami traditional diet. Limited data are available on reindeer as a human foodstuff compared to domestic animals. </p>
<p>The main objective of this thesis was to increase knowledge on reindeer as human foodstuff.</p>
<p>In details, to study concentration of specific fatty acids, total lipids, vitamins, essential and toxic elements in meat, liver, tallow and bone marrow from semi-domesticated reindeer and to study this in relation to recommended dietary allowances (RDA) or maximum levels (ML) and provisional tolerable weekly/monthly intake limits (PTWI/PTMI). Differences between concentrations in meat and the other edible tissues from reindeer, as well as effects of geographical variation and animal population density on these concentrations were studied.</p>
<p>This thesis is based on samples from 131 semi-domesticated reindeer originating from 14 districts distributed across four counties (Finnmark, Troms, Nordland and Sør-Trøndelag) in the mid- and northern Norway.</p>
<p>We have found that semi-domesticated reindeer meat contains higher vitamin B12, iron, zinc and selenium concentrations when compared to Norwegian beef, lamb, mutton, pork and chicken meat. Reindeer meat is lean, but a good source of docosapentaenoic acid (DPA) and α-linolenic acid (ALA). Concentrations of DPA and ALA in reindeer meat are comparable to those formerly reported in crab, scampi, mussels, oysters and DPA in code. In addition, reindeer liver contains concentrations of vitamins A, B9, B12, iron and selenium that are high enough to cover the recommended dietary allowance (RDA). The ratios of ∑PUFA n-6/ ∑PUFA n-3 in meat, tallow and bone marrow are within the RDA ratios of 3-9. The tallow 8 contains a high concentration of vitamin B12, while bone marrow contains the highest concentrations of vitamin E and calcium.</p>
<p>Further, this study has shown that the vast majority of nutrient and toxic element concentrations in reindeer liver, tallow and bone marrow were significantly higher than those found in meat. Concentrations of the toxic elements detected in this study were generally low and below the provisional tolerable weekly/monthly intake limits. Most vitamin concentrations in liver, tallow and bone marrow were significantly positive correlated with the concentrations in meat. Positive correlations were revealed between iron and calcium, and vitamin B12 and zinc. Cadmium and arsenic were the only toxic elements positively correlated between liver and meat.</p>
<p>Geographical variations in nutrients and toxic element concentrations between some districts were revealed, with vitamin E, selenium, arsenic and cadmium demonstrating the largest geographical differences. No clear geographical trend was observed except for the east-west gradient for arsenic, with the highest concentrations measured in the east (near the Russian border). Districts with low animal population density had on average higher selenium than those with medium and high population densities.</p>
<p>The measured concentrations of the studied nutrients demonstrate that reindeer intake (meat, liver, tallow and bone marrow) could contribute significantly to the recommended dietary intakes set for consumers. Furthermore, the consumption of meat, liver, tallow and bone marrow from reindeer is not associated with any health risk for consumers when toxic elements are the issue of concern. The geographical differences revealed in this study were not large and will most likely have no impact for consumers.</p>
</body></document>
