<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title/>
    <genre code="science"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <wordcount>332</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <license type="standard"/>
    </availability>
    <origFileName>orig/sme/science/uit/phd/jorun_kjoelaas.pdf</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="jorun_kjoelaas.pdf"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p><em type="bold">ABSTRACT </em></p>
    <p>The dissertation deals with the reading competence of bilingual children. Taking the L97 Sami Curriculum objective of functional bilingualism as a point of departure, a comparison is made of informants’ reading competence in the two languages. Bilingualism is a complex field and a contextual description provides an important platform for an understanding of the results. The present context is characterized by pupils from bilingual homes in areas dominated by the majority language, yet in an environment characterized by vitalization of the minority language. The parents have chosen the minority language as the language of instruction for a number of reasons. The results from the study of the pupils’ reading competence led to a collaborative project between the school, the pupils’ homes, and teacher’s training college.<em type="bold"> </em>The goal of this joint project was twofold: firstly, to achieve a common understanding of the difference between everyday language used in daily interaction and the cognitive/academic language necessary in order to succeed academically. Secondly, to focus on what schools and homes together can do in order to strengthen the linguistic conditions for developing age adequate reading competence.  </p>
    <p>The main findings from the project may be formulated as three forward-pointing signposts. The first signpost directs attention towards the criteria for choosing educational models in the present context, towards the unsettled roles between homes and schools, and to the role of the local community and mass media in the vitalization of the minority language. The second signpost points towards the research project. Homes and schools need a collaborative partner in their common struggle towards functional bilingualism for the children. The third signpost points to the role of teacher’s training in the education of future teachers. Two areas stand out.<em type="bold"> </em>One is the teacher educators’ role in communicating to students the significance of working towards a development from everyday language to school language. The second concerns the relationship between traditional knowledge and traditional ways of learning and the theorization necessary for the development of the cognitive/academic school language. </p>
  </body>
</document>
