<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="science"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>1057</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>orig/sme/science/uit/phd/mikkel_sara.pdf</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p><em type="bold">The structure of the thesis </em></p>
<p>The dissertation consists of an introductory part 1 written in</p>
<p>Norwegian, and part 2 consisting of published articles, two published in English and one in Sámi. The article which is published in Sámi is translated into</p>
<p>English for use here. A combination of Norwegian and English allows for continuous reading of the thesis. This language choice depends on the university’s and journals’ language use, and also on the intention to broader the readership.</p>
<p>Today the running of the reindeer siida is surrounded and influenced by various accounts and decisions both within siida system and at national and international level. Some would probably argue that all material should be translated into all three languages, or at least to Sámi. This however has been limited by the resources allocated for translation work. Some of the source material on earlier siidas and on traditional Sámi reindeer herding knowledge has on the other hand been published in Sámi at an earlier stage of the work. <em type="bold"></em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Acknowledgement </em></p>
<p>It is not easy to say when and how my PhD project came to be something possible and important, and thus when it really started. It all consists in a gradual and alternating learning of both reindeer herding and a theoretical approach to this field. This also included the challenge of getting a sense of why and how to link these different forms of knowledge together. Now I have got as far as the completion of the work. Time has come to think back on what has brought me to where I am.</p>
<p>First and foremost, I have been in the fortunate situation that I have been able to continuously alternate between different environments with their specific talks and actions. My place of work, Sámi University College, is located almost in the heart of many surrounding siida communities. There have been just a few steps into ongoing talks about reindeer and herding conditions at present.</p>
<p>Conversely, Sámi University College has by offering courses in reindeer husbandry opened its doors to reindeer husbandry youth and practitioners, and by that their experience and knowledge have been allowed to come into and make their contribution to the institution’s ongoing processes of learning and discussions. Moreover I have benefited from being in position to participate in seminars and discussions organized and brought to life as part of the Ealát-project. Through this project’s wide-ranging network, I have had the opportunity to become familiar with different approaches to issues of importance for reindeer husbandry, and also to meet representatives of reindeer herders from different circumpolar regions.</p>
<p>The Ph.D. work has been carried out at the University of Tromsø. I wish to thank my supervisor Ragnar Nielsen for his patient and helpful support to get my work completed.</p>
<p>My colleagues at the Sámi University College have been a great support for my preparatory, first steps to get something down on paper, simply by letting me gain insight in their research projects and take part in their discussions: Inger</p>
<p>Marie Gaup Eira, Ellen Inga Turi, Svein D. Mathiesen and Ole Henrik Magga particularly in connection with the Ealát project, Mathis Bongo in connection with preparation and implementation of courses designed for reindeer herding practitioners and Nils Oskal in connection with our cooperation over time. And there are many others, besides of them mentioned here, whom I recall when thinking of talks about reindeer and siidas and discussions focused on issues related to research and education.</p>
<p>Finally I wish to thank my family members, who have undertaken additional work and commitments at home and in the siida during my work on the thesis. These are things that for my part probably had remained undone or poorly performed.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Abstract </em></p>
<p>The concept of siida is well-known throughout the Sápmi. Far back in time there have been local Sámi communities called siidas. Siidas having reindeer herding as their unifying element are today the only ones representing a continuous practice of traditional siida livelihood and way of life. They represent an ongoing siida tradition up to now, especially the siidas in Guovdageaidnu and</p>
<p>Kárášjohka in Norway, i.e. in the region where the present research has been carried out. This tradition, however, still lives under pressure from the representation of the eastern siidas in literature on the one side and the administrative way of practicing the Reindeer Husbandry Act on the other side.</p>
<p>The image of a stable organization in the eastern siidas and the end of the hunting siidas has veiled the connecting lines between the past and present siidas and also led to an understanding of the siida system as non-existent. On the other hand, legislation on reindeer husbandry has led to construction and development of an alternate organization, the Reindeer Herding District system. The new</p>
<p>Reindeer Husbandry Act now has acknowledged the siida as a basic unit, but issues and governing practices originating from the reindeer herding district system have still been allowed to shape the approach to the siida system.</p>
<p>The process towards rehabilitation of siidas and the siida system contains no ways round the method of picking up the connecting lines between past and present siidas and taking them as our starting points. This implies taking the siida system’s own concepts, premises of thought and priorities as our starting point. Today it means primarily to extract and present the siidas’ shared concepts and traditional herding knowledge, but also to look towards the traditional world view behind the siida practices. This provides, among other things, a basis to elucidate settings and adaptation in the relationship between siida and its natural surroundings, and also issues and ways of settling different matters in the process of rehabilitation of the siida system. Determination of outer limits for reindeer herding districts and siidas has been a thematic meeting point between reindeer herders and government. So far these meetings have not taken the siidas traditional knowledge and ways of thinking as their primary starting point and focus of attention. The present research examines examples of traditional Sámi beliefs and ways to approach siidas based on their own concepts and practices.</p>
<p>These texts are meant to be read by both siida members and others. As the reindeer herder primarily relates to the edges of the herd, likewise these texts relate to important aspects of all siidas and not to the inner life of any specific siida.</p>
</body></document>
