<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="science"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>849</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>orig/sme/science/uit/phd/torkel_rasmussen.pdf</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p><em type="bold">Abstract </em></p>
<p>In this sociolinguistic dissertation I examine the ethno-linguistic vitality of North Sámi in the two neighbouring municipalities of Deatnu/Tana in Norway and Ohcejohka/Utsjoki in Finland.</p>
<p>Different factors on macro, meso, Sámi society and micro level together shape the ethno-linguistic vitality of the Sámi language in these two municipalities. The Sámi language revitalization era began throughout Sápmi in the early 1990s but manifested differently in different areas. I argue this is based on the larger socio-political conditions – thus the macro society influences language on a micro level. My research focuses on how these differences influenced local level revitalization processes. I utilized a variety of qualitative research methods including: document analysis, participant observation and interviews in addition to creating and analyzing questionnaires. Although document analysis and case study analysis proved most informative to locate larger socio-political trends, I used questionnaires to focus on the actual practice of language and language revitalization. Specifically the questionnaires solicited information on the ethnic identities, linguistic history and language skills as well as actual language use of my informants: children and youth age 10-16 years in the primary schools and upper secondary schools in Deatnu/Tana and Ohcejohka/Utsjoki. All together 193 pupils or 71 percents of the pupils took part in the research. The results of the questionnaires have been used to analyse the ethno-linguistic vitality of Sámi language on meso and micro level.</p>
<p>I interviewed 12 families focusing on their roles in language revitalization. The interviews focused on their process in learning Sámi language and their network of linguistic contacts and specifically the role of these networks in the transmitting of Sámi language to the children. The underlying question in most of these interviews is <em type="italic">how </em>parents evaluate the vitality of Sámi language and the role of the new Sámi policy in their home community. </p>
<p>One result of my research is that although there was a language shift in the past away from Sámi to</p>
<p>Norwegian and Finnish among some of the Sámi people this language shift has nearly stopped because most of the Sámi speakers now are speaking Sámi to their children. In fact one can argue there is a reverse language shift occurring where some of the Sámis that had lost their ancestors’ language as children have chosen to learn Sámi as adults and are now speaking it with their own children. There are even cases where the parents haven’t learned the language themselves but encourage their children to do so thus ensuring the Sámi language is alive and developing for the next generation.</p>
<p>The findings of my research indicate that children involved in the Sámi language revitalization processes most often come from homes with at least one, and sometimes two, Sámi speaking parents. Although formal education in Sámi language is important so are larger extended linguistic networks. For the parents that have raised their children as Sámi speakers, kindergarten, extended family and friends are the most important supporters for the language learning of the children.</p>
<p>When it comes to the role of the school, there is a clear difference between the municipalities. The parents in Deatnu/Tana municipality consider the school to play a significant role in the promotion of</p>
<p>Sámi language. In Ohcejohka/Utsjoki most of the parents consider the school as an obstacle for the children’s socialisation as Sámi speakers.</p>
<p>In parents opinion the obstacles have roots both on the macro and meso levels. Linguistically assimilated Sámi children lack legal rights to learn Sámi language through strong forms of bilingual education such as language nest or immersion classes in the formal school setting. Although the state provides provisions for intensive language learning methods the municipalities don’t implement these possibilities for those children who are not already speaking Sámi in the home. And although the state does provide for the possibility of separate Sámi language schools these are also implemented very differently in the two different municipalities. Deatnu/Tana municipality organizes education in Sámi language for the Sámi speakers in separate Sámi schools whereas Ohcejohka/Utsjoki municipality organizes education with Sámi and Finnish as the languages of instruction in the same Finnish schools.</p>
<p>My data from questionnaires with children and youths shows that these ways of organisation Sámi language education influences clearly the use of Sámi language among children. The children on the</p>
<p>Finnish side use Sámi language considerably less than the children on the Norwegian side. As a consequence of these meso level decisions, the children on the Finnish side also feel that they master</p>
<p>Sámi language less fluently than the children on the Norwegian side.</p>
<p>In conclusion I argue there is a need for changes both on the macro and meso levels in order to enhance revitalization of Sámi language in the researched area. The macro level should decide that education in Sámi language shall be given in separate Sámi language schools and furthermore, Sámi children should have a legal right to get strong forms of bilingual education in kindergarten and elementary school. And in addition, the municipalities as the meso level should change their kindergarten and school structure in order to better meet the requirements of the revitalization of Sámi language.</p>
</body></document>
