<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Information to parents of kindergarten children</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="Udir" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>451</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.udir.no/globalassets/filer/kvalitet-og-kompetanse/korona/forelderinfo_engelsk.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="forelderinfo_nynorsk.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="forelderinfo_bokmaal.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="forelderinfo_sorsamisk.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="foreldreinfo_nordsamisk.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 180635 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p><em type="bold">Information to parents of kindergarten children </em></p>
<p>There were no registered cases of infection being spread among children in kindergartens before kindergartens closed in Norway. Compared to adults, few children have been found to be infected in Norway or in the rest of the world. Children and young people have so far also been found to have a very low risk of serious il ness from the coronavirus. The figure is lower than for other respiratory diseases that affect children, such as the flu and RSV.</p>
<p><em type="bold">It is safe for children to go to kindergarten </em></p>
<p type="listitem">We have implemented a number of measures in kindergartens to limit infection. We wil  focus in the time ahead on ensuring appropriate infection control. It is important in this connection that we al  make an effort and fol ow the new advice. We wil  focus on the fol owing in kindergartens in particular:</p>
<p type="listitem">hand-washing and ensuring that children learn good hand-washing techniques</p>
<p type="listitem">ensuring good cleaning procedures in kindergartens</p>
<p type="listitem">washing toys regularly</p>
<p type="listitem">spending more time outside with the children</p>
<p type="listitem">grouping children together in smal er groups with the same staff members</p>
<p><em type="bold">Kindergartens will continue to provide care for the children </em></p>
<p>We wil continue to safeguard children’s needs for physical care and ensure that they al feel safe, that they belong and enjoy kindergarten. It wil stil be important to cuddle and comfort them.</p>
<p><em type="bold">If your child does not feel wel </em></p>
<p>If your child has symptoms of disease, even if they are mild, they must not go to kindergarten. It is now more important than ever to keep children at home for at least one day after their symptoms disappear. Parents who have respiratory symptoms must not take their child to kindergarten or pick them up. Nor must you take your child to kindergarten if a parent or anyone else in your home has been diagnosed with the coronavirus. If your child becomes il at kindergarten, you must pick them up as quickly as possible.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Parents should not follow their child into the kindergarten </em></p>
<p>We wil welcome the children outside as far as possible. Children should wear outdoor clothes when they come to kindergarten.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Do not bring any toys from home </em></p>
<p>Children must not bring their own toys from home. You can bring a cuddly toy that helps your child to fal asleep. However, it is more important than ever that this toy is not shared with other children at the kindergarten.</p>
<p>Hand-washing is just as important at home as it is at kindergarten. Wash your hands before you go to kindergarten, and as soon as you get home.  We recommend that children only play with a few children in their free time and that they preferably play outside.</p>
</body></document>
