<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title/>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <wordcount>566</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.udir.no/globalassets/filer/vurdering/nasjonaleprover/nasjonale-prover-information-for-parents-english.pdf</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="nasjonale-prover-informasjon-til-foreldre-nn.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="nasjonale-prover-informasjon-til-foreldre-bm.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="nasjonale-prover-informasjon-til-foreldre-sorsamisk.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nasjonale-prover-informasjon-til-foreldre-nordsamisk.pdf"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>Information about national tests 2015</p>
    <p>-  For parents with children in Years 5, 8 and 9</p>
    <p>Why national tests?</p>
    <p>National tests are used to assess and develop the pupils' fundamental skills in reading, numeracy and English. The literacy and numeracy tests are not tests in the subjects of Norwegian and mathematics. Rather they test the pupils' literacy and numeracy skills across all subjects. The tests for English test reading comprehension, vocabulary and grammar.</p>
    <p>Who should take which tests?</p>
    <p>The national tests are taken in Years 5, 8 and 9. The general rule is that the tests are obligatory for all pupils. Pupils in Years 5 and 8 shall take national tests in reading, numeracy and English.  Year 9 pupils shall take national tests in reading and numeracy. These tests are the same as for Year 8. The tests in English and numeracy are electronic tests.</p>
    <p>Pupils in Years 5, 8 and 9 with North Sami, South Sami or Lule Sami as their first language, must take the national reading test in Sami. These pupils shall also take the national tests in numeracy in Sami.</p>
    <p>Exemption may be granted to</p>
    <p type="listitem">  pupils with the right to special needs education or pupils with the right to adapted</p>
    <p>education in Norwegian, when it is simultaneously</p>
    <p type="listitem">  clear that the test result will not have much effect on the pupil’s learning</p>
    <p>Even if a pupil is entitled to an exemption, he/she or you as parents may still decide that the pupil should take the test.</p>
    <p>Which tasks will the pupils be asked to solve?</p>
    <p>The numeracy and English tests are electronic tests, while the reading tests are done on paper. The tests comprise a range of texts, pictures and exercises. Short answer questions require the pupils to use their own words or figures, while multiple choice means the pupils must choose one of several available answers. The tests comprise a combination of easy, medium and difficult exercises in order to provide information about the pupils' skills at all levels. Examples of exercises used in the national tests can be found at www.udir.no. There you will also be able to download last year's electronic national tests in English and numeracy.</p>
    <p>Using the test results</p>
    <p>Pupils and parents will receive feedback from the teacher about the test results once they are ready. The results will not be used to mark the pupils, but they will help determine what the pupils should work more with. The results should be seen in combination with other information about the pupil, and they should be used to provide adapted tuition and improve the students’ learning. The school shall provide information about what they are doing to follow up on your child's test results.</p>
    <p>Teachers, school administrators and the Directorate for Education and Training have access to pupils’ individual results. Pupils’ test results must be kept confidential and there are strict regulations concerning pupils’ right to privacy. The results from the tests are used by school owners and school administrators in their work to improve quality within the school.  The Directorate for Education and Training can give researchers access to test results. We always assess the balance of interest between pupils’ right to privacy and the interests of society before we give access to this information.</p>
    <p>What if I have further questions?</p>
    <p>Please contact your school or read more about the national tests on our website:</p>
    <p xml:lang="smj">www.udir.no/nasjonaleprover</p>
  </body>
</document>
