<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Information to parents of school children</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="Udir" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>460</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>https://www.udir.no/contentassets/a7d84e333b6c4391b3e212c1b9af6ef9/udir_forelderinfo_skole_bokmaal-en.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nno" location="udir_forelderinfo_skole_nynorsk.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="udir_forelderinfo_skole_bokmaal.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="udir_forelderinfo_skole_sorsamisk.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="udir_forelderinfo_skole_nordsamisk.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 180635 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p><em type="bold">Information to parents of school children </em></p>
<p>There were no registered cases of infection being spread among children in kindergartens and primary schools before the schools closed in Norway. Compared to adults, few children have been found to be infected in Norway or in the rest of the world. Children and young people have so far been found to have a very low risk of serious illness from the coronavirus. The risk is lower than for other respiratory diseases, such as the flu.</p>
<p><em type="bold">It is safe for children to go to school </em></p>
<p type="listitem">The schools are now set to reopen gradually, and we have implemented a number of measures to limit infection. We will focus in the time ahead on ensuring appropriate infection control. It is important in this connection that we all make an effort and follow the new advice on infection control. We will focus on the following in schools in particular:</p>
<p type="listitem">hand-washing and teaching the pupils good hand-washing techniques</p>
<p type="listitem">ensuring good cleaning procedures are in place</p>
<p type="listitem">washing equipment, such as tablet computers, regularly</p>
<p type="listitem">spending more time outside with the pupils, including during ordinary classes and before and after-school programmes (SFO)</p>
<p type="listitem">grouping and teaching children together in smaller groups</p>
<p type="listitem">keeping a distance from each other</p>
<p>We will continue to ensure a good and safe school environment for the pupils. Everyone working in the schools will keep an eye on the pupils to ensure they are doing okay.</p>
<p><em type="bold">If your child does not feel well </em></p>
<p>If your child has symptoms of disease, even if they are mild, they must not go to school or SFO.</p>
<p>It is now more important than ever to keep children at home for at least one day after their symptoms disappear. If anyone in your home has respiratory symptoms or has been diagnosed with the coronavirus, you must not take your child to school.</p>
<p>If a child becomes ill at school, we will contact the parents. The child must then be picked up or go home from school as quickly as possible.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Parents should not follow their child into the school </em></p>
<p>We will try to welcome children outside, and ask parents not to follow their children into the school or cloakroom.</p>
<p>Hand-washing is just as important at home as it is at school. Wash your hands before you go to school, and as soon as you get home.</p>
<p>Children should only be together with a few children in their free time and preferably play outside.</p>
<p><em type="bold">School transport </em></p>
<p>If the pupils take a school bus, they must remember to keep a good distance, both while they wait and on the bus. This also applies if the pupils take a boat or another form of transport to school. School transport and public transport should be avoided if possible.</p>
</body></document>
