<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>40384</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.doria.fi/bitstream/handle/10024/77529/Raportteja_48_2012_ENG.pdf?sequence=3</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="raportteja_48_2012_fi.pdf_sequence=3.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="raportteja_48_2012_nor.pdf_sequence=3.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="raportteja_48_2012_saam.pdf_sequence=3.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="raportteja_48_2012_sv.pdf_sequence=3.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="fra"><em type="bold">REpoRts 48 | 2012 </em></p>
<p>Northern Landscapes ʻʻImplementation of the European Landscape Convention in the North Calotte Area Municipalitiesʼʼ - Conference in Inari, Finland 7-9.9.2011</p>
<p xml:lang="est"><em type="bold">NooRa Raasakka | saRi sivoNEN (eds.) </em></p>
<p>Northern Landscapes ʻʻImplementation of the European Landscape Convention in the North Calotte Area Municipalitiesʼʼ - Conference in Inari, Finland 7-9.9.2011</p>
<p xml:lang="est"><em type="bold">NooRa Raasakka saRi sivoNEN (eds.) </em></p>
<p xml:lang="est"><em type="bold">REPORTS 48 | 2012 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">NORThERN LaNdScaPES <span type="quote">“IMPLEMENTaTION OF ThE EUROPEaN LaNdScaPE cONVENTION IN ThE NORTh caLOTTE aREa MUNIcIPaLITIES”</span> - cONFERENcE IN INaRI, FINLaNd 7.–9.9.2011centre for Economic development, Transport and the Environment for Lapland </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Layout: Eerika Niemelä cover picture: Tapio heikkilä Place of Publication: Kopijyvä Oy </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="bold">ISBN 978-952-257-537-1 (painettu) ISBN 978-952-257-538-8 (PdF) </em></p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">ISSN-L 2242-2846 ISSN 2242-2846 (painettu) ISSN 2242-2854 (verkkojulkaisu) </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="bold">URN:ISBN:978-952-257-538-8www.ely-keskus.fi/julkaisut | www.doria.fi/ely-keskus </em></p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Disclaimer:</p>
<p>This publication has been published with financial support by the Nordic Council of Ministers. But the contents of this publication do not necessarily reflect the views, policies or recommendations of the Nordic Council of Ministers.www.norden.org1</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Foreword</p>
<p>The common characteristics of the North Calotte area, such as the magnificent riverside scenery and the beautiful fell landscapes formed by the Sámi culture and reindeer management are broadly reflected in the environment. Alongside the traditional forms of land use, many other livelihoods and forms of land use now need to be accommodated in the area. Tourism, energy production, mining industry and new infrastructure create new and manifold challenges to the authorities in charge of land use in these areas. Municipalities need information and support for versatile planning in the future, so that the unique and valuable characteristics of the North can be preserved.</p>
<p>The conference promoting the objectives of the international European Landscape Convention (ELC) was held on 7-9 September in Inari, at the Siida Sámi Museum. The primary aim of the conference was to increase awareness of the ELC and the prospects and requirements it brings to practical planning work, especially at the municipal level. The conference speakers included top experts in the field from Sweden, Norway, Finland and several other European Union countries. In addition to the lectures held at the conference, the speakers have written articles on their topics. These articles are collected in this publication, which aims to support land use planners in their work and encourage municipalities to implement future planning according to the objectives of the ELC. The publication is available in five languages: Finnish, Swedish, Norwegian, Northern Sámi and English.</p>
<p>Organising the conference was agreed on in September 2010, at the international workshop <span type="quote">“Implementing the European Landscape Convention in the North Calotte area”</span>, which was aimed at authorities from Finland, Sweden and Norway. Increasing the awareness of the ELC and its practical implementation among municipal authorities was seen as a common challenge. Another aim was to promote and increase cross-border cooperation. At the invitation of the Centre for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment for Lapland, the workshop welcomed representatives from the various Ministries of the Environment, provincial governments, the Sámi Parliamentary Council, the Council of Europe Steering Committee for Cultural Heritage and Landscape, and Natural Heritage Services from Metsähallitus. It was agreed that an international conference should be arranged for the North Calotte area municipalities to increase information in the municipalities and to support the practical implementation of the ELC. The Nature Protection Unit of the Environment and Natural Resources Section of the Centre for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment for Lapland was in charge of organising the conference and applying for funding for the project. The project was funded by the Nordic Council of Ministers. The Ministries of the Environment from the cooperation countries also participated in the organisation and the funding of the project.</p>
<p>For the organisers of the conference, we would like to thank each of our expert speakers for their outstanding performances, fruitful discussions, and ongoing cooperation in landscape issues. In addition, we thank all conference participants for their activity and interest in this important issue. The contacts created at the conference will form a good basis for further cooperation in the future. We thank the sponsors of the project, especially the Terrestrial Ecosystem Group of the Nordic Council of Ministers for all their support, for the opportunity to deliver this conference and create this publication you are now reading.</p>
<p>Noora Raasakka Project Manager Centre for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment for Lapland2</p>
<p><em type="bold">List of authors and editors </em></p>
<p>Déjeant-Pons Maguelonne, Secretary of the European Landscape Convention, Head of the Cultural Heritage, Landscape and Spatial Planning Division, Council of Europe</p>
<p>Heikkilä Tapio, Environment Counsellor, Ministry of the Environment, Finland Jokelainen Timo, Head of the Land Use Planning Unit, Centre for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment for Lapland</p>
<p>Kantola Erkki, Director, Centre for Economic Development, Transports and the Environment in Lapland Karjalainen Eeva, Dr., Finnish Forest Research Institute Lipponen Merja, Special Planner, Centre for Economic, Transport and the Environment for Lapland Mikaelsson Stefan, President of the Sámi Parliament Assembly, Sweden Mortensen Liv Kirstine, Senior Adviser, Section for Land Use Policy and Municipal Planning, Department of Regional</p>
<p>Planning, Norwegian Ministry of the Environment</p>
<p>Moström Jerker, Senior Adviser, Swedish National Heritage Board Nordli Kristin, Senior Adviser, Section for Land Use Policy and Municipal Planning, Department of Regional Planning,</p>
<p>Norwegian Ministry of the Environment</p>
<p>Pedroli Bas, Associate Professor Land Dynamics, Wageningen University, Director UNISCAPE Raasakka Noora, Project Manager, Centre for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment for Lapland Roué Marie, National Centre for Scientific Research / National Museum of Natural History, Paris, France Sala Pere, Coordinator of the Landscape Observatory of Catalonia Seguin Jean-François, Head of the Landscape office, Ministry of ecology, sustainable development, transports and housing (France), Past president of the conference of Council of Europe for the European Landscape Convention</p>
<p>Sivonen Sari, Planner, Centre for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment for Lapland Tanninen Timo, Director General, Ministry of the Environment, Finland3 <em type="bold">content </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">WELcOME TO ThE cONFERENcE ............................................................................. 5 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="bold">Timo Tanninen </em></p>
<p xml:lang="sma"><em type="bold">EUROPEaN LaNdScaPE cONVENTION IN FINLaNd ............................................. 7 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="bold">Tapio heikkiläa WELcOME FROM ThE ORGaNIZER ..................................................................... 10 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="bold">Erkki Kantola </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">SPEEch BY STEFaN MIKaELSSON TO ThE EUROPEaN LaNdScaPE cONVENTION cONFERENcE, INaRI, FINLaNd 9.9.2011 ....................................... 11 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">Stefan Mikaelsson </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">ThE EUROPEaN LaNdScaPE cONVENTION: 10 YEaRS OF INTERNaTIONaL cO-OPERaTION .......................................................................................................... 15 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fra"><em type="bold">Maguelonne déjeant-Pons </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">TRaNSNaTIONaL aNd TRaNSBORdER cOOPERaTION - aN OPPORTUNITY FOR BETTER LaNdScaPES ..................................................................................... 27 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="est"><em type="bold">Jean-François Seguin </em></p>
<p xml:lang="sma"><em type="bold">EUROPEaN LaNdScaPE cONVENTION IN SWEdEN - EXPEcTaTIONS aNd INTENTIONS ................................................................................................................ 33 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">Jerker Moström </em></p>
<p xml:lang="sme"><em type="bold">IMPLEMENTaTION OF ThE EUROPEaN LaNdScaPE cONVENTION IN NORWaY, WITh a FOcUS ON PLaNNING chaLLENGES IN ThE MaNaGEMENT OF LaNdScaPE VaLUES ............................................................................................... 38 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nno"><em type="bold">Kristin Nordli and Liv Kirstine Mortensena SaaMI REINdEER hERdER’S cULTURaL LaNdScaPE: MEMORY, ThE SENSES aNd EThIcS ................................................................................................. 45 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="sma"><em type="bold">Marie Roué </em></p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">LaNd USE PLaNNING, NORThERN LaNdScaPE aNd WINd POWER ............... 51 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="bold">Timo Jokelainen </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">REGIONaL aNd LOcaL PaRTIcIPaTION aNd cO-OPERaTION IN IMPLEMENTING ThE EUROPEaN LaNdScaPE cONVENTION - ThE EXPERIENcE OF ThE LaNdScaPE OBSERVaTORY OF caTaLONIa ......................................... 55 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">Pere Sala </em>4 </p>
<p><em type="bold">LaNdScaPE aNd hUMaN hEaLTh - Proceedings of the conference: Implementation of the European Landscape convention in the North calotte area Municipalities .............................................................................................................. 67 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Eeva Karjalainen </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">ThE aRcTIc LaNdScaPE aS a LIVING EUROPEaN hERITaGE ........................ 72 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">Bas Pedroli </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">PIcTURESQUE NORThERN VILLaGES - ThE KaIRaLa - LUIRO LaNdScaPE MaNaGEMENT aREa aS aN EXaMPLE OF ThE IMPLEMENTaTION OF ThE EUROPEaN LaNdScaPE cONVENTION aT a LOcaL LEVEL .............................. 78 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="sms"><em type="bold">Merja LipponencONcLUSIONS ............................................................................................................84 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="est"><em type="bold">Noora Raasakka </em>5 </p>
<p>WELCOME TO THE CONFERENCE</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="bold">Timo Tanninen </em></p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, dear participants of the conference.</p>
<p>It gives me great pleasure to welcome you all to this conference on implementation of the European Landscape Convention in the North Calotte Area municipalities.</p>
<p>I am very proud that Finland is hosting the very first international meeting for the European Landscape</p>
<p>Convention here in Inari. Therefore, I would first of all like to thank the organizers of this conference. The Centre for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment for Lapland, along with its partners, has done a great job in preparing and making arrangements for this meeting. Thank you all very much.</p>
<p>It is wonderful to see so many colleagues and guests from all directions of our continent in this room, and especially to see so many representatives from the very northern part of Europe, the North Calotte Area.</p>
<p>Because we Nordic countries have a long and close tradition of international co-operation, it is natural that we here in Finland begin our international attempts in implementing the European Landscape Convention in the form of Nordic co-operation. I would also like to thank the Nordic Council of Ministers and our close friends, Norway and Sweden, for their financial contributions to the arrangements for this conference. There is no more suitable place for this kind of meeting than Lapland, where the three of us share common boundaries and have deep historical ties.</p>
<p>We three Nordic nations have very similar cultural backgrounds. I believe we have many ways in which we can easily broaden and deepen our co-operation in landscape management so that we can move from theoretical issues to the practical level, and probably even to concrete co-operation on follow-up projects.</p>
<p>Our special interest in this conference focuses on the northernmost parts of the European continent: Lapland,</p>
<p>Norrbotten, and Finnmark. This whole region is a very special part of our nations for many reasons. And one of the most important ones is that it is the home region of the Sámi people, who are still maintaining their traditional culture and livelihoods. One could call Sámi traditions a connective cultural force, which is a factor that unites the understanding of landscapes in the Nordic countries. This is something very distinctive and remarkable in the whole of Europe, and we should be very proud of this cultural capital.</p>
<p>The European Landscape Convention defines a landscape as <span type="quote">“... an area, as perceived by people, whose character is the result of the action and interaction of natural and/or human factors”</span>. This characterization reflects echoes from the long European traditions of landscape research. In these traditions both the natural sciences and humanities are included, with their own visions of the concept of landscape. These visualisations are, at the same time, both very different and true as such.</p>
<p>Even though these viewpoints have been embedded in research and experiences for more than a century, I am convinced that it is possible to find new ways to examine landscapes. Could a platform for that be found in the North Calotte area? In the Sámi culture, the landscape, and especially the cultural landscape, is perceived in a very personal way. This interpretation of the landscape could easily enrich and deepen European discussions on landscapes and their importance for different European cultures.</p>
<p>The European continent is a huge mosaic of diverse landscapes which differ not only because of their structures, textures and composition, but also because of their different interpretations. Besides the concept of multifunctional landscapes, one should also define the concept of multicultural landscapes. The North Calotte area is a suitable area to study this kind of phenomenon.</p>
<p>Article 5 of the European Landscape Convention demands that we <span type="quote">“... establish procedures for the participation of the general public, local and regional authorities, and other parties with an interest in the definition and implementation of the landscape policies...”</span>. According to this point of view, our conference offers a good start in the North Calotte area.</p>
<p>It is very important that local authorities and municipalities engage in these kinds of events both here and in other regions in Europe. I hope that the local stakeholders become aware of the demands and opportunities which the convention offers to official institutions, to civic society and to the local people. The outcome of this 6conference should show that this event is not the finish line for implementing the convention, but rather the springboard for practical actions which can and must be done to manage our unique landscapes.</p>
<p>In Article 9 on transfrontier landscapes, the convention tells us — <span type="quote">“The parties shall encourage transfrontier co-operation on local and regional level and, wherever necessary, prepare and implement joint landscape programmes”</span>. I see that this conference will be examining these themes in depth. I hope that you will have interesting discussions on these themes and possibly find new ways to fulfil these demands.</p>
<p>One idea for this could be to look at the need and opportunities for examining the valuable cultural landscapes of the North Calotte area, so as to understand how they are viewed in traditional Sámi culture. Co-operation with the Nordic countries could be a reliable option in this kind of project.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, I wish you all the best of success at the conference, as well as fruitful discussions, and an enjoyable visit. This conference offers a valuable opportunity to interact and absorb information, as there are so many high-quality professionals here from around Europe.</p>
<p>I also hope that all of you take the opportunity to visit Ukonsaari island. This is a very important sacred place for Sámi culture, and it is surrounded by the magnificent landscapes of Lake Inari. It is absolutely the right place to consider the dimensions of cultural landscapes in the North Calotte Area.</p>
<p>Thank you.7</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">EUROPEAN LANDSCAPE</p>
<p xml:lang="sma">CONVENTION IN FINLAND</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="bold">Tapio heikkilä </em></p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, dear participants and organizers of this conference. My name is Tapio Heikkilä and I work at the Ministry of the Environment as a specialist in landscape management issues. I am also the representative of Finland for the European Landscape Convention. Today, I will give a short presentation on the effects of the European Landscape Convention and the landscape actions carried out in Finland. I will also be showing some examples of typical landscapes from different parts of Finland and Northern Europe to illustrate my presentation.</p>
<p>First, I will describe the ratification process of the European Landscape Convention in Finland. Secondly, I will outline which kind of actions can be defined as implementation of the convention, mostly at the government level. And, thirdly, I will evaluate the future challenges and possibilities in the implementation of the Convention.</p>
<p>Ratification of the ELC in Finland</p>
<p>The European Landscape Convention – or the Florence Convention – was adopted on 20 October 2000, almost eleven years ago. In the late 1990s Finland took part, to some extent, in the preparations of the European Landscape Convention, but we were not a central actor in the procedure. We were, however, in agreement with the aims and principles of the Convention. Thus, Finland was among those countries who signed the Convention immediately when it was opened for signature.</p>
<p>The ratification process was also quite smooth in Finland. But why was it so easy for Finland to ratify this convention? I think the main reason was that the previous two decades were quite a fruitful period in our landscape policies – that is, there was much work in developing points of view, regulations and projects concerning landscape management, planning and conservation.</p>
<p>At the beginning of 2000 our Land Use and Building Act came into force. The objective of the act is to ensure that the use of land and water areas and the building activities on them create preconditions for a favourable living environment and promote ecologically, economically, socially and culturally sustainable development. The act lays down a system of planning which takes into account cultural values and also provides opportunities for public participation. Additionally, the act includes the National Land Use Guidelines, which require that all nationally important landscape areas, cultural-historical environments and archaeological monuments and sites with their neighbouring areas must be taken into account in regional plans, which are used to guide the local planning process.</p>
<p>Under the Land Use and Building Act, the Ministry of the Environment may establish national urban parks, which protect valuable urban and semi-urban cultural landscapes such as parks and other green zones in cities and towns. The idea of urban parks was adopted from Sweden, and we follow the model of Nationalstadspark in Stockholm. We now have five national urban parks in Finland.</p>
<p>Our Nature Conservation Act from 1996 also includes provisions on landscape protection. This act aims to protect nature and the landscape as a whole. Under this act it is possible to establish special landscape conservation areas. These can be established to preserve and manage a natural or cultural landscape of outstanding beauty, historical interest or other special value.</p>
<p>In addition to these two important acts, there are also provisions that concern landscapes and their management in several other acts. The most important are the Antiquities Act, the Act on the Protection of Buildings, the Land Extraction Act and legislation on agriculture. Besides the abovementioned legislation, the Finnish government carried out several broad-ranging inventories of landscapes in the late ‘80s and early ‘90s.</p>
<p>In 1993 a working group of the Ministry of the Environment described valuable landscape areas representing rural cultural landscapes. In January 1995, the Government declared 156 landscape areas as nationally valuable landscapes, and it also issued policy guidelines for landscape management. 8</p>
<p>In 1993 the Ministry of the Environment and the National Board of Antiquities completed a report focusing on the built environment. About 1800 nationally important cultural-historical environments were identified. These sites varied from individual buildings and urban blocks to more extensive cultural landscape areas.</p>
<p>From these examples, you can see that it was a simple matter for Finland to ratify the European Landscape</p>
<p>Convention in spring 2006, because we already had legislation in place and some inventories had already been done. In other words, all essential conditions for ratification had been fulfilled.</p>
<p>Landscape actions after ratification of the ELC</p>
<p>The next step after ratification was to pursue new achievements in the field of landscape management. What has happened in Finland during the last five years after ratification of the ELC?</p>
<p>This is very difficult to evaluate. Superficially, it would appear like we are continuing to work on the same issues as before the ratification. Whether this is exactly the case or not, several very important achievements have been reached in the landscape sector in the last few years.</p>
<p>The National Board of Antiquities has recently updated the list of nationally important cultural-historical environments, a task that took nearly ten years. These sites are historically or architecturally valuable, and, in many cases they are also important small-scale landscapes. About 1200 such sites have now been identified. Finland’s Land Use and Building Act requires that these sites are taken into account in regional land use plans and local master plans.</p>
<p>Last year the Ministry of the Environment began updating the list of nationally valuable landscape areas, an effort which in turn will take about five years. In this project, as a new enhancement, regionally valuable landscapes will also be included.</p>
<p>So far, five landscape conservation areas have been established in Finland. Mostly, they include countryside landscapes with traditional rural settlements, fields and meadows. A very important goal is to keep these villages alive and give the local people information about the values of their landscapes and tools to help them manage these areas through conventional means and traditional livelihoods such as farming. The most recent landscape conservation area was designated last year in Lapland, in the Kairala and Luiro villages. Another area in Lapland was established four years ago, and it is located in the municipality of Salla. The participation of the inhabitants and local farms has been a very important part of the preparation process. An essential goal is to safeguard the management of these areas, and without the local people’s help and participation, this would not be possible.</p>
<p>It’s likely that all of these actions and many others, too, would have come about without the Convention, at least to some extent. But, as a civil servant, I can confirm that the European Landscape Convention has definitely helped by serving as an essential background support in strengthening our landscape policies at the Ministry, and in the whole of government, as well. A practical example is competition for resources for different landscape projects. I am sure that without the Convention, the results would have been essentially worse in many cases.</p>
<p>Now, because of the Landscape Convention, every landscape project or initiative is evaluated in connection with it. And every success helps to fulfil the goals of the Convention, and, at the same time, our landscape policies, too.</p>
<p>New actions in the landscape field</p>
<p>Finally, I would like to give a brief summary of new activities and thoughts that came about because of the European Landscape Convention. One very important feature is that the Convention helps to promote general and public discussion on landscape issues. A very simple, but effective, example is the European Landscape Award, which will now be granted for the second time. Last year we held a competition for <span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">“The Best Landscape Project in Finland”</span>. Twelve applications were submitted for this open competition. The minister of the environment declared the winner, which was then the Finnish entry for the European Landscape Award.</p>
<p>All twelve projects promote the Convention’s goals. These projects and the public interest in the competition and its results are likely to reinforce the importance and objectives of landscape management, while, at the 9same time, making the Convention more well known. This time the winner was the Finnish Association for Nature Conversation, which was working to restore meadows and other semi-cultural habitats with financial help from the national railway company. The other honorary prize was given to Kairala village here in Lapland for their landscape management projects.</p>
<p>Another very important element which the European Landscape Convention offers us is theoretical and practical opportunities for international dialogue and co-operation in landscape issues. And this is what we are successfully carrying out here, at this conference.</p>
<p>There are many other topics which I have not had time to explore in my presentation, such as research, training and education, as well as public participation in landscape planning and management. Based on my observations, I am willing to say that the Convention also helps us to increase the level of actions in these fields.</p>
<p>The Nordic countries have a long, close and rich history in extensive co-operation with each other. We have already had several joint projects in landscape issues within the framework of the Nordic Council of Ministers. And now it is possible to enjoy this co-operation at this conference here in Lapland. Actually, it seems that Lapland has been the most active of all regions in Finland in taking the initiative in landscape protection and management. Thus, it is natural that the very first international landscape conference in the framework of the European Landscape Convention is arranged here.</p>
<p>This North Calotte area is remarkable in Europe for many reasons, but one of the most significant features is that it is the Sámi peoples’ home region. The Sámi are our own indigenous people and they still practice their traditional culture and livelihoods, such as reindeer management.</p>
<p>Because of a very tight interrelationship between nature and its use, the Sámi people have a different conceptualization of the cultural landscape, at least to some extent. I am sure that their view will enhance our discussions about landscapes and related phenomena not only at the Nordic level, but in the whole of Europe.</p>
<p>It is obvious that an essential basis of success for the European Landscape Convention will be international discussions on all possible varieties and dimensions of landscapes. The Convention should be seen as a longterm process, rather than as a quick decision or definition of correct contemporary landscape policies. This first decade of the Convention has only planted the seeds for the groundbreaking tasks we have ahead of us.</p>
<p>European cultural landscapes have been shaped during centuries and millennia step by step, through trial and error. I myself would hesitate to claim that this process has even reached the midpoint yet. The Landscape Convention offers us a multidimensional tool for understanding our multifunctional landscapes and the processes that extend beyond their formation. It is also important to recognize the substantial variations in our European landscapes and to maintain these differences, while developing methods for managing these landscapes, so that they will continue to shape our personal identities and, at the same time, contribute to the enrichment of our multicultural identities.</p>
<p>Landscape is a lifelong learning process for everyone. The European Landscape Convention can, at its best, be a progressive process for learning about and understanding our landscapes, as well as a process for promoting responsible landscape management. I am sure that the experiences concerning natural and cultural landscapes among the North Calotte area people are going to contribute new and important flavours to discussions on European landscape concepts.</p>
<p>I will be following this conference with excitement and anticipation, especially the possibilities for continuing actions after this notable meeting. 10</p>
<p>A WELCOME FROM THE ORGANIZER</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="bold">Erkki Kantola </em></p>
<p>Good evening Ladies and Gentlemen. In September 2010, the Centre for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment in Lapland (the <span type="quote">“ELY Centre”</span> for short) organized a workshop in Tornio whose focus was the implementation of the European Landscape Convention and landscape management in transfrontier areas of Finland, Sweden and Norway. The forum included representatives from the ministries of the Environment, county administrations, the Steering Committee for Cultural Heritage and Landscape, the Sámi Parliament and the Natural Heritage Services. In one outcome of the workshop, the participants decided to increase the co-operation between authorities, organize the present conference and apply for funding from the Nordic Council of Ministers for carrying out the project. The ELY Centre of Lapland took responsibility for planning and implementing the project.</p>
<p>So, here we are kicking off the first event related to the Convention and its application in the North Calotte.</p>
<p>The swift progress of the project has been made possible by the supportive attitude of the funding bodies and the determination of those in charge of it. (The principal source funding is the Nordic Council of Ministers, with national contributions from the ministries of the three participating countries). The project began back in April of this year, and the presentations of experts that you will hear over the next few days will provide the basis for a publication. This work, scheduled to appear by the end of the year in five languages (English, Finnish, Swedish, Norwegian and Northern Sámi), will offer a practical tool and set of guidelines for the municipalities of the North Calotte.</p>
<p>The goal of the project and of this conference is to enhance land use planning in municipalities and to provide better tools and information for comprehensive planning. It is of particular importance that we increase knowledge about and render visible the significance of landscapes and cultural heritage for quality of life. The project also aims to strengthen the co-operation between the administrative authorities who work with the Convention and landscape management issues. The transfrontier areas between the countries are extensive, and harmonizing the practices applied in the region can make landscape management and conservation in border areas more effective. The North has distinctive features and a unique culture – characteristics which make the region very attractive indeed and which we should seek to preserve and to incorporate comprehensively in future land use planning. Yet, one must always remember that it is local co-operation and interaction that are of primary significance in creating a foundation for broader co-operation. We have work to do and room for improvement in this respect here in Lapland, too.</p>
<p>Projects do not start on their own; they always require ideas and people ready to roll up their sleeves. With this in mind, I would like to take this opportunity to express my sincere gratitude to all those whose outstanding and brisk efforts have contributed to making this conference happen. Particular thanks are due to the innovators and other <span type="quote">“driving forces”</span> behind this event: Audun Moflag from Norway (Audun has already retired, but is here with us as an honoured guest), Jerker Moström from the Swedish National Heritage Board, Tapio Heikkilä from the Ministry of the Environment and of course the project team from the Lapland ELY Centre, under the leadership of Noora Raasakka.</p>
<p>We have two intensive days ahead of us, with a programme featuring cutting-edge presentations by experts and a venue – Siida – offering a window on Sámi culture and Northern nature. I hope that you will also find time for informal gatherings and that the weather will favour us tomorrow on our excursion, when we set out to see for ourselves the beautiful landscapes and interesting attractions that Inari has to offer. I hope that you enjoy yourselves here.11</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">SPEECH BY STEFAN MIKAELSSON</p>
<p>TO THE EUROPEAN LANDSCAPE</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">CONVENTION CONFERENCE, INARI,</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">FINLAND 9.9.2011</p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">Stefan Mikaelsson </em></p>
<p>Mr Chairman, ELC Conference Participants, Ladies and Gentlemen: My name is Stefan Mikaelsson and I am Chairperson of the Sámi Parliament of Sweden. I would like to take this opportunity to thank the organizers for their kind invitation and to convey the sincere apologies of Lars-Ove Jonsson, who was unfortunately unable to attend.</p>
<p>The Sámi people have inhabited large areas of what are now known as the Republic of Finland, the Kingdom of Norway, the Kingdom of Sweden and north-western areas of Russia for thousands of years since prehistoric times. We Sámi call this area Sápmi, our homeland. One people living in four countries.</p>
<p>At the time of Gustav Vasa’s funeral in 1560, the heraldic coat of arms for the Province of West Bothnia (Västerbotten) was a reindeer, described as ‘Azure, on a semé of stars Or, a reindeer springing argent armed gules’, which represented all the land to the west of the Gulf of Bothnia. At that time, the Province of West Bothnia extended beyond the Torne River. The running silver reindeer surrounded by 13 stars is still the coat of arms for both North Bothnia (Norrbotten) (with two reindeer) and West Bothnia (1 larger reindeer).</p>
<p>In Sweden, the Sámi have exclusive rights to reindeer herding that have also been guaranteed by EU Protocol</p>
<p>No 3 on the Sámi people attached to the EU accession treaty of Sweden. And, since the 1st of January this year, the new Swedish Constitution officially recognises the Sámi as a people. This doesn’t confer any special status on the Sámi; it simply puts them on an equal footing with other people. The establishment of the non-profit Laponiatjuottjudus association, which was formally founded and inaugurated on 22nd of August, means that the Sámi are in a majority on the board that manages the Laponia cultural and world heritage.</p>
<p>Violated rights are restored</p>
<p>It is essential to know this historical background to be able to implement a convention that has been developed and established at the end of the 20th century. It will not be possible to ignore the progress made in various human rights instruments and national legislation. And the legal consequences of decisions taken about the Sámi in Sweden will also affect the situation here in Finland, for instance. Sweden and Finland shared a king for more than 700 years, and 13 kings have lived in Turku/Åbo. These countries share a historical background that makes it easier to achieve a joint future.</p>
<p>But when you realise the problems that obviously have arisen in connection with harmonising the different laws relating to Sámi people in the Nordic countries, you have to feel some apprehension about the ability to implement the intentions set out in the preamble to the European Landscape Conference (ELC):<span type="quote">“Considering that the aim of the Council of Europe is to achieve a greater unity between its members for the purpose of safeguarding and realising the ideals and principles which are their common heritage, and that this aim is pursued in particular through agreements in the economic and social fields.”</span></p>
<p>We, the Sámi people, are dependent on a landscape which is enduring and not dependent on the dominant nations’ energy needs and the free market’s demands for unhindered and unlimited access to natural resources.</p>
<p>Instead, membership of the European Union has escalated the exploitation of what could be called our ancestral lands. Building roads, power lines, prospecting, mining, wind farms, reduction of the minimum age for final felling of forests, introduction of non-native species of tree, etc., have all combined to create what has been described as monocultures and key habitat deserts, especially in the eastern parts of North and West Bothnia. 12</p>
<p>The land and water of our heritage has been fragmentized in a way that is as difficult to comprehend as it is to deal with.</p>
<p>We, the Sámi people, are the indigenous people of Sápmi. Our land has been split into four different countries, extending from Northern Scandinavia all the way to the Kola Peninsula. From time immemorial, our people have inhabited and managed the land and water with great care and respect. Our culture is based on a life in which people and all other living things are interconnected. We see nature as a spiritual living entity. Our view of nature is diametrically opposed to the view of nature prevalent in the western world. The only way to create a common future is through in-depth and mutual understanding and enhanced co-operation.</p>
<p>Clearly, positive changes and essential technical aids have also been introduced in modern times. All these changes in combination have had a powerful effect on us and our way of life. It is important to distinguish between innovations that affect our lives in a positive way and innovations that make us increasingly dependent on the global economy and access to cheap gas and oil.</p>
<p>Global warming and escalating climate change have already changed the everyday life of the Sámi people.</p>
<p>Opportunities for the global market and operators lacking ethical or social responsibility to encroach on traditional Sámi areas have increased. But there are some positive examples to tell you about. One good example is the project established by the National Association of Swedish Sámi in partnership with responsible wind power operators. The goal is to establish a model for co-operating and entering into agreements to establish wind farms. This has got off to a promising start and hopefully the finalization of the project will be satisfactory. This model for co-operation, problem solving and joint solutions benefits the dominant society as well as us, the Sámi people. If involvement in full-scale solutions becomes the norm, this will also mean an improved level of health for Sámi people.</p>
<p>We want to live in a vibrant Sápmi founded on both a healthy natural environment and a flourishing Sámi culture. People and nature should have a long-term ability to renew themselves and to be sustainably developed, even in times of profound changes. Our nature and culture should be perceived by the surrounding world as enriching.</p>
<p>When wind power is used in the right way, it is a renewable energy source that can contribute to meeting future energy needs. But in the wrong location, wind power is neither eco-friendly nor sustainable. It can have a major impact on Sámi society and the natural Sámi environment. Conditions for the Sámi lifestyle are radically changed if construction goes ahead without due consideration of Sámi needs. The report entitled <span type="quote">“The Sámi Parliament’s view of wind power in Sápmi”</span> sets out a Sámi strategy and our basic approach to wind power development.</p>
<p>The Sámi people’s view of their habitat is based on our access to land and water – the interconnectivity of all things. Wind farms gobble up vast areas and fragmentize the landscape. Once the landscape is altered by roads and wind farms, the effect on animals and people is inescapable. Any future expansion of wind power must guarantee that our ability to live and develop in Sápmi is not restricted or prevented.</p>
<p type="listitem">There are a number of points that the Sámi Parliament wants to emphasize to ensure that wind power is an eco-friendly, sustainable and renewable source of energy with a minimal impact on the natural environment,  animals and people:</p>
<p type="listitem">Particularly important habitats should be protected from any large-scale expansion.</p>
<p type="listitem">Suitable locations must be planned jointly.</p>
<p type="listitem">There should be greater restraint regarding expansion in mountain areas.</p>
<p type="listitem">When extending woodlands, the principle of free, prior and informed consent must be applied.</p>
<p type="listitem">The principle of conservative conduct and development must be applied.</p>
<p>The principle for safety precautions and restrictions is defined in the Swedish Environmental Code Chapter 2, Section 3:3 § Persons who pursue an activity or take a measure, or intend to do so, shall implement protective measures, comply with restrictions and take any other precautions that are necessary in order to prevent, hinder or combat damage or detriment to human health or the environment as a result of the activity or measure. For the same reason, the best possible technology shall be used in connection with professional activities.13</p>
<p type="listitem">Such precautions shall be taken as soon as there is cause to assume that an activity or measure may cause damage or detriment to human health or the environment. [Official translation]</p>
<p type="listitem">The Sámi Parliament’s role must be made clearer (consultation and resources).</p>
<p type="listitem">Sámi participation in the decision-making process should include the most nearly affected Sámis.</p>
<p type="listitem">Companies must take responsibility – goodwill and international markets mean that private companies have everything to gain from consulting the Sámi people.</p>
<p type="listitem">Socio-economic perspectives must be considered.</p>
<p>The preamble also states: <span type="quote">“Believing that the landscape is a key element of individual and social well-being and that its protection, management and planning entail rights and responsibilities for everyone”</span>.<span type="quote">“Health is a state of complete physical, mental, and social well-being and not merely the absence of disease or infirmity”</span>. This definition of health by the World Health Organization (WHO) has been used for more than 40 years.</p>
<p>Management in accordance with the aims of the landscape’s objective qualities requires education, including training for specialists, elected representatives and technical personnel at local, regional and national authorities, and that school and university courses address the values attaching to landscapes and the issues raised by their protection, management and planning.</p>
<p>The Swedish Government ratified the European Landscape Convention in November 2010. The Swedish</p>
<p>National Heritage Board was tasked with convening a group of public authorities to draw up proposals for the way the work would be carried out in Sweden.</p>
<p>The authorities in the National Heritage Board submitted a proposal for joint overall co-ordination. Co-ordination responsibility rests with the Swedish Environmental Protection Agency (Naturvårdsverket), the Swedish County Administrative Boards, the Swedish Board of Agriculture (Jordbruksverket), the Swedish Forest Agency (Skogsstyrelsen), the Swedish Agency for Economic and Regional Growth (Tillväxtverket) and the Swedish National Heritage Board. At a regional level, the administrative district concerned is responsible for coordinating the work of implementing the European Landscape Convention.</p>
<p>The Swedish Sámi Parliament would like to make the National Heritage Board aware of the importance of</p>
<p>Sámi influence in the work of implementing the European Landscape Convention in Sweden. The reindeer herding area in the Swedish part of Sápmi covers over 40% of Sweden and includes mountains, forests, marshlands and water. This area constitutes our Sámi habitat in which the surrounding landscape, history, reindeers, language, natural resources and our place in this entirety is the foundation and prerequisite for our culture and our existence.</p>
<p>We have a situation today in which society knows very little about the way the Sámi culture and reindeer herding uses the landscape and are dependent on a continuous landscape, and consequently scant attention is paid to this in different aspects of community planning and effective administration.</p>
<p>European Landscape Convention</p>
<p>The ELC contains a number of points that are particularly important from a Sámi perspective. <em type="italic">Article 5 – General measures </em>Comment: The Sámi people’s relationship with the landscape and its significance cannot be recognised or integrated into policies unless it can be defined and expressed by the Sámi people themselves. In order to make this possible, it is extremely important for the Sámi Parliament to play an active role in the work of implementing the convention. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Article 6 – Specific measures </em>B Training and education Comment: There is widespread ignorance about Sámi cultural landscapes and the Sámi values attaching to landscapes and the issues raised by their protection, management and planning. It is therefore vital that these 14elements are included in all training courses and that Sámi institutions/organizations play an active role in the development of these training courses. </p>
<p>C Identification and assessment Comment: It must be the responsibility of the Sámi Parliament /Sámi organizations to identify, analyse and assess the Sámi area</p>
<p>Existing international instruments</p>
<p>The implementation of the convention shall take into consideration existing international instruments for protection and management of natural resources and cultural heritage, regional and physical planning, local autonomy and cross-border co-operation. In view of this, the Sámi Parliament would like to refer to the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples and to Article 19 in particular.</p>
<p>The United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Peoples</p>
<p>In the Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples, which was adopted by the United Nations General</p>
<p>Assembly in September 2007, the states agreed on the requirements imposed on member states in respect of indigenous people living within the country’s borders. Sweden was one of the 143 countries that signed the Declaration. Several articles address the rights of indigenous people in relation to participation, culture, environmental issues and influence in issues relating to traditional territories.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Article 19 </em>States shall consult and co-operate in good faith with the indigenous peoples concerned through their own representative institutions in order to obtain their free, prior and informed consent before adopting and implementing legislative or administrative measures that may affect them. </p>
<p>The Sámi Parliament believes it is essential that the Sámi Parliament as a government authority is a part of the co-ordination group. It is of significant importance that the value of landscapes is not just based on a Swedish perspective. The Sámi Parliament has a pre-existing legal right as well as a responsibility to make sure that Sámi perspectives and visions also receive protection in the community planning process. A community which is built for two peoples.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">I would like to finish by quoting poet and author Paulus Utsi: “Så länge vi har vatten, där fisken lever</p>
<p xml:lang="swe">Så länge vi har land, där renen betar och vandrar</p>
<p xml:lang="swe">Så länge vi har marker, där det vilda gömmer sig har vi tröst på denna jord</p>
<p>“As long as we have waters where the fish can swim</p>
<p>As long as we have land where the reindeer can graze</p>
<p>As long as we have woods where wild animals can hide we are safe on this earth</p>
<p>When our homes are gone and our land destroyed – then where are we to be?”</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Paulus Utsi [Translation by Roland Thorstensson]</p>
<p>Thank you so much for listening!15</p>
<p>THE EUROPEAN LANDSCAPE</p>
<p>CONVENTION: 10 YEARS OF</p>
<p xml:lang="kal">INTERNATIONAL CO-OPERATION</p>
<p><em type="bold">Maguelonne déjeant-Pons </em>“ The landscape ... ... has an important public interest role in the cultural, ecological, environmental and social fields, and constitutes a resource favourable to economic activity and whose protection, management and planning can contribute to job creation; ... contributes to the formation of local cultures and ... is a basic component of the European natural and cultural heritage, contributing to human well-being and consolidation of the European identity;... is an important part of the quality of life for people everywhere: in urban areas and in the countryside, in degraded areas as well as in areas of high quality, in areas recognised as being of outstanding beauty as well as everyday areas ;... is a key element of individual and social well-being and ... its protection, management and planning entail rights and responsibilities for everyone. “-Preamble to the European Landscape Convention <em type="bold">a territorial dimension of human rights and democracy </em></p>
<p>The European Landscape Convention was adopted by the Committee of Ministers of the Council of Europe on 19 July 2000 in Strasbourg and opened for signature of the member states of the Organisation in Florence (Italy) on 20 October 2000. It came into force on 1 March 2004, with the aim of promoting European landscape protection, management and planning, and encouraging European co-operation in this area. The Convention is the first international treaty to be exclusively concerned with all aspects of European landscape. It applies to the entire territory of the Parties and covers natural, rural, urban and peri-urban areas. It concerns landscapes that might be considered outstanding as well as everyday or degraded landscapes.</p>
<p>The Convention represents an important contribution to the implementation of the Council of Europe’s objectives, namely to promoting democracy, human rights and the rule of law and seeking common solutions to the main problems facing European society today. (Council of Europe, 2006; Council of Europe, 2002.) By taking into account landscape, cultural and natural values, the Council of Europe seeks to protect the quality of life and well-being of Europeans.</p>
<p>The Council of Europe’s Celebration of the 10th Anniversary of the opening of the Convention for signature was organised in Florence on 19-20 October 2010. ‘New challenges and new opportunities’ for landscapes were considered during the event and statements by representatives of member States of the Council of Europe were presented.</p>
<p>To date, 34 Council of Europe member states have ratified the Convention: Armenia, Belgium, Bulgaria,</p>
<p>Croatia, Cyprus, Czech Republic, Denmark, Finland, France, Georgia, Greece, Hungary, Ireland, Italy, Latvia, Lithuania, Luxembourg, Moldova, Montenegro, Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Romania, San Marino, Serbia, Slovak Republic, Slovenia, Spain, Sweden, <span type="quote">“the former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia”</span>, Turkey, Ukraine, United Kingdom. A further five states have signed it: Andorra, Azerbaijan, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Malta, and Switzerland (List in Appendix). 16</p>
<p>PRESENTATION OF THE EUROPEAN LANDSCAPE</p>
<p>CONVENTION</p>
<p>The member states of the Council of Europe signatory to the European Landscape Convention declared their concern to achieve sustainable development based on a balanced and harmonious relationship between social needs, economic activity and the environment. The Convention therefore represents the first international treaty devoted to sustainable development, with the cultural dimension also included therein.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Origins of the convention </em></p>
<p>On the basis of an initial draft prepared by the Congress of Local and Regional Authorities of the Council of Europe, the Committee of Ministers decided in 1999 to set up a select group of experts responsible for drafting a European Landscape Convention, under the aegis of the Cultural Heritage Committee (CCPAT) and the Committee for the activities of the Council of Europe in the field of biological and landscape diversity (CO-DBP). Following the work of this group of experts, in which the principal governmental and non-governmental international organisations participated, the Committee of Ministers adopted the final text of the Convention on 19 July 2000. The Convention was opened for signature in Florence on 20 October 2000 in the context of the Council of Europe Campaign <span type="quote">“Europe, a common heritage”</span>.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Why a convention on landscape? </em></p>
<p>As an essential factor of individual and communal well-being and an important part of people’s quality of life, landscape contributes to human fulfilment and to the consolidation of a European identity. It also has an important public interest role in the cultural, ecological, environmental and social fields, and constitutes a resource favourable to economic activity, particularly to tourism.</p>
<p>The advances in production techniques in agriculture, forestry, industry and mining, together with the practices followed in town and country planning, transport, networks, tourism and recreation, and more generally the global economic changes, have in many cases led to degradation, debasement or transformation of landscapes.</p>
<p>While each citizen should of course contribute to preserving the quality of the landscape, it is the responsibility of the public authorities to define the general framework in which this quality can be secured. The Convention thus lays down the general legal principles, which should guide the adoption of national and community landscape policies and the establishment of international co-operation in this field.</p>
<p><em type="bold">The objectives and specificity of the Convention </em></p>
<p>The aim of the Convention is to respond to the public’s wish to enjoy high quality landscapes. Its purpose is therefore to further the protection, management and planning of European landscapes, and to organise European co-operation in this field.</p>
<p>The scope of the Convention is extensive: it applies to the entire territory of the Parties and relates to natural, urban and peri-urban areas, whether on land, water or sea. It therefore concerns not just remarkable landscapes, but also ordinary everyday landscapes and degraded areas. Landscape is recognised irrespective of its exceptional value, since all forms of landscape are crucial to the quality of the citizens’ environment and deserve to be considered in landscape policies. Many rural and urban fringe areas in particular are undergoing far-reaching transformations and should receive closer attention from the authorities and the public.17</p>
<p>Given the breadth of scope, the active role of the citizens regarding perception and evaluation of landscapes is an essential point in the Convention. Awareness-raising is thus a key issue, in order for citizens to participate in the decision-making process, which affects the landscape dimension of the territory where they reside.</p>
<p xml:lang="fra"><em type="bold">Definitions </em></p>
<p type="listitem">Terms used in the Convention are defined to ensure that they are interpreted in the same way:</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote" xml:lang="rmy-rka">“Landscape”</span> means an area, as perceived by people, whose character is the result of the action and interaction of natural and/or human factors;</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Landscape policy”</span> means an expression by the competent public authorities of general principles, strategies and guidelines that permit the taking of specific measures aimed at the protection, management  and planning of landscapes;</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Landscape quality objective”</span> means, for a specific landscape, the formulation by the competent public authorities of the aspirations of the public with regard to the landscape features of their surroundings;</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Landscape protection”</span> means action to conserve and maintain the significant or characteristic features of a landscape, justified by the landscape’s heritage value derived from its natural configuration and/or human  activity;</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Landscape management”</span> means action, from a perspective of sustainable development, to ensure the regular upkeep of a landscape, to guide and harmonise changes, which are brought about by social,  economic and environmental processes;</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Landscape planning”</span> means strong forward-looking action to enhance, restore or create landscapes.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Undertakings of the contracting Parties </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">National measures </em></p>
<p>In accepting the principles and aims of the Convention, the Contracting Parties undertake to protect, manage and/or plan their landscapes by adopting a whole series of general and specific measures on a national level, in keeping with the subsidiarity principle. In this context, they undertake to encourage the participation of the public and of local and regional authorities in the decision-making processes that affect the landscape dimension of their territory.</p>
<p type="listitem">The Contracting Parties undertake to implement four general measures at national level:</p>
<p type="listitem">the legal recognition of landscape constituting an essential component of the setting for people’s lives, reflecting the diversity of their common cultural and natural heritage and as the foundation of their identity;</p>
<p type="listitem">the establishment and implementation of policies to protect, manage and plan landscapes;</p>
<p type="listitem">procedures for the participation by the general public, local and regional authorities and other parties interested in the formulation and implementation of landscape policies;</p>
<p type="listitem">the integration of landscape into regional and town planning policies, cultural, environmental, agricultural, social and economic policies, and any other policies, which may have a direct or indirect impact on the  landscape.</p>
<p type="listitem">The Contracting Parties further undertake to implement five specific measures at national level:</p>
<p type="listitem">awareness-raising: improving appreciation by civil society, private organisations and public authorities of the value, function and transformation of landscapes;</p>
<p type="listitem">training and education: providing training for specialists in landscape appraisal and landscape operations, multidisciplinary training programmes on landscape policy, protection, management and planning, aimed at 18professionals in the private and public sector, for interested associations, and school and university courses,  which, in the relevant subject areas, cover landscape-related values and questions of landscape protection,  management and planning;</p>
<p type="listitem">identification and evaluation: mobilising those concerned in order to reach a better knowledge of landscape, guiding the work of landscape identification and evaluation through exchanges of experience and methods  between the Parties at European level;</p>
<p type="listitem">setting landscape quality objectives: defining quality objectives for the landscapes, which have been identified and evaluated, after consulting the public;</p>
<p type="listitem">implementation of landscape policies: introducing policy instruments for the protection, management and/or planning of landscapes.</p>
<p><em type="bold">International measures: European co-operation </em></p>
<p>The Contracting Parties also undertake to co-operate at international level in catering for the landscape dimension in international policies and programmes, and to recommend where appropriate the inclusion of landscape considerations in them. They accordingly undertake to co-operate in respect of technical and scientific assistance and exchange of landscape specialists for training and information, and to exchange information on all questions covered by the Convention.</p>
<p>Transfrontier landscapes are covered by a specific provision: the Contracting Parties undertake to encourage transfrontier co-operation at local and regional levels and, wherever necessary, to prepare and implement joint landscape programmes. <em type="bold">council of Europe Landscape award </em></p>
<p>The Convention provides for a <span type="quote">“Council of Europe Landscape Award”</span>. It will recognise a policy implemented or measures to be taken by local and regional authorities or non-governmental organisations to protect, manage and/or plan their landscape which have proved effective in the long term and can thus serve as an example to other authorities in Europe. It should contribute to the stimulation of those working at local level and to the encouragement and recognition of exemplary landscape management.</p>
<p>IMPLEMENTATION OF THE EUROPEAN LANDSCAPE</p>
<p>CONVENTION</p>
<p>The Convention states that existing competent committees of experts set up under Article 17 of the Statute of the Council of Europe should be appointed by the Committee of Ministers of the Council of Europe to be responsible for monitoring its implementation. It also states that, following each meeting of the committees of experts, the Secretary General of the Council of Europe will transmit a report on the work carried out and on the operation of the Convention to the Committee of Ministers and that the said committees should propose to the Committee of Ministers the criteria for conferring, and the rules governing, the Landscape Award of the Council of Europe.</p>
<p>On 19 July 2000, when the European Landscape Convention was adopted, the Ministers’ Deputies <span type="quote">“[…] instructed the Committee for the activities of the Council of Europe in the field of biological and landscape diversity (CO-DBP) and the Cultural Heritage Committee (CDPAT) to monitor the implementation of the European Landscape Convention”</span> (CM/Del/Dec(2000)718, 718th meeting).</p>
<p>The Declaration of the Second Conference of Contracting and Signatory States to the European Landscape</p>
<p>Convention adopted in Strasbourg on 29 November 2002, of which the Committee of Ministers took note on 28 May 2003, also asked the Committee of Ministers to associate the Committee of Senior Officials of the European Conference of Ministers responsible for Regional Planning (CEMAT) in the work of the committees of experts responsible under Article 10 for monitoring the implementation of the Convention.19</p>
<p type="listitem">On 30 January 2008, the Committee of Ministers adopted the terms of reference of the Steering Committee for Cultural Heritage and Landscape (CDPATEP), which was responsible for dealing with natural and cultural  heritage issues.  It had the task of monitoring the following Conventions on cultural heritage and the landscape:</p>
<p type="listitem">the European Convention on the Protection of the Archaeological Heritage and the European Convention on the Protection of the Archaeological Heritage (revised);</p>
<p type="listitem">the Convention for the Protection of the Architectural Heritage of Europe;</p>
<p type="listitem">the European Landscape Convention.</p>
<p>With regard to the follow-up of the European Landscape Convention, the terms of reference stated that the</p>
<p>CDPATEP had also to take into account the work of the periodic Council of Europe conferences on the European Landscape Convention and other work by appropriate experts. This autumn, a new committee on democratic governance of culture, heritage and landscape should be set up.</p>
<p type="listitem">The work done by the Secretariat of the Council of Europe to implement the European Landscape Convention aims at:</p>
<p type="listitem">monitoring the implementation of the Convention;</p>
<p type="listitem">fostering European co-operation;</p>
<p type="listitem">collecting examples of good practice;</p>
<p type="listitem">fostering knowledge and research;</p>
<p type="listitem">raising awareness;</p>
<p type="listitem">fostering access to information.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Monitoring the implementation of the convention </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Recommendation cM/Rec(2008)3 of the committee of Ministers to member states on the guidelines for the implementation of the European Landscape convention. </em></p>
<p type="listitem">Recommendation  CM/Rec(2008)3  of  the  Committee  of  Ministers  to  member  states  on  the  guidelines  for  the implementation of the European Landscape Convention was adopted by the Committee of Ministers on  6 February 2008. The recommendation, which contains a series of theoretical, methodological and practical  guidelines, is intended for parties to the Convention which wish to draw up and implement a national landscape  policy based on the Convention.  It also includes two appendices entitled:</p>
<p type="listitem">Examples of instruments used to implement the European Landscape Convention;</p>
<p type="listitem">Suggested text for the practical implementation of the European Landscape Convention at national level.</p>
<p>Appendix 1 to the Recommendation may be supplemented by the experiences of parties to the Convention on their own territories, which will provide practical and methodological lessons. It is proposed that each party contribute to the setting up of a database to appear on the website of the Council of Europe’s European Landscape Convention, which would be a <span type="quote">“toolbox”</span> to help provide mutual technical and scientific assistance, as provided for in Article 8 of the Convention.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Summary descriptive notes on the landscape policies pursued in council of Europe member states / council of Europe Information System on the European Landscape convention. </em></p>
<p>A document on the landscape policies pursued in Council of Europe member states, giving the key facts concerning the landscape those member states, is regularly updated and a synthesis of the data is prepared. The data gathered are gradually being incorporated in a Council of Europe Information System on the European Landscape Convention. 20</p>
<p><em type="bold">National seminars on the European Landscape convention. </em></p>
<p>Thus are intended for states which have or have not yet ratified the Convention. The national seminars on the European Landscape Convention help generate the debate on landscape. Various national seminars on the European Landscape Convention have been held, with declarations or conclusions adopted at the end of each one:</p>
<p type="listitem">National Seminars</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Spatial planning and landscape”</span>, Yerevan (Armenia), 23-24 October 2003</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Spatial planning and landscape”</span>, Moscow (Russian Federation), 26-27 April 2004</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Sustainable spatial development and the European Landscape Convention”</span>, Tulcea (Romania), 6-7 May 2004</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“The contribution of Albania to the implementation of the European Landscape Convention”</span>, Tirana (Albania), 15-16 December 2005</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="est"><span type="quote" xml:lang="rmy-rka">“Landscape”</span>, Andorra la Vella (Principality of Andorra), 4-5 June 2007</p>
<p type="listitem">Other Seminars were organised with the support of the Ministries in various other countries in 2008-2010:</p>
<p>Italy, Czech Republic... The proceedings of the Seminars are published in the Council of Europe’s European Spatial Planning and</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Landscape Series.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Fostering European co-operation </em></p>
<p>The European Landscape Convention provides that the contracting parties undertake to co-operate internationally at European level when considering the landscape dimension of international policies and programmes. The Council of Europe organises this co-operation through conferences on the European Landscape Convention and the meetings of the workshops for the implementation of the European Landscape Convention.</p>
<p><em type="bold">The council of Europe conferences on the European Landscape convention </em></p>
<p>Several conferences on the European Landscape Convention have already been held. They are attended by representatives of the parties and signatories and representatives of the three Council of Europe bodies – the Committee of Ministers, the Parliamentary Assembly and the Congress of Local and Regional Authorities of Europe. Representatives of Council of Europe member states which are not yet parties or signatories and various international governmental and non-governmental organisations also attend as observers.</p>
<p>With regard to following up the European Landscape Convention, the terms of reference of the CDPATEP as adopted on 30 January 2008 provided that the CDPATEP take into account the work of the periodic Council of Europe conferences on the European Landscape Convention and other work by appropriate experts.</p>
<p type="listitem">Council of Europe Conferences on the European Landscape Convention</p>
<p type="listitem">1. 22-23 November 2001, Council of Europe, Palais de l’Europe, Strasbourg</p>
<p type="listitem">2. 28-29 November 2002, Council of Europe, Palais de l’Europe, Strasbourg</p>
<p type="listitem">3. 17-18 June 2004, Council of Europe, Palais de l’Europe, Strasbourg</p>
<p type="listitem">4. 22-23 March 2007, Council of Europe, Palais de l’Europe, Strasbourg</p>
<p type="listitem">5. 30-31 March 2009, Council of Europe, Palais de l’Europe, Strasbourg</p>
<p type="listitem">6. 3-4 May 2011, Council of Europe, Strasbourg</p>
<p type="listitem">7. ...201321council of Europe Meetings of the workshops for the implementation of the European Landscape  convention</p>
<p>Organised by the Council of Europe on a regular basis since 2002, the meetings of the workshops for the implementation of the European Landscape Convention take a detailed look at the implementation of the Convention. Special emphasis is given to the experiences of the state hosting the meeting. A genuine forum for sharing practice and ideas, the meetings are also an opportunity to present new concepts and achievements in connection with the Convention.</p>
<p>The following of the Council of Europe meetings of the workshops for the implementation of the European</p>
<p>Landscape Convention have been held.</p>
<p type="listitem">Council of Europe Meetings of the workshops for the implementation of the European Landscape Convention</p>
<p type="listitem">1. <span type="quote">“Landscape policies: contribution to the well-being of European citizens and to sustainable development (social, economic, cultural and ecological approaches); Landscape identification, evaluation and quality  objectives, using cultural and natural resources; Awareness-raising, training and education; Innovative tools  for the protection, management and planning of landscape”</span>, Strasbourg, France, 23-24 May 2002</p>
<p type="listitem">2. “Integration of landscapes in international policies and programmes and transfrontier landscapes;</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscapes and individual and social well-being; Spatial planning and landscape”, Strasbourg, France, 27-28 November 2003</p>
<p type="listitem">3. <span type="quote">“Landscapes for urban, suburban and peri-urban areas”</span>, Cork (Ireland), 16-17 June 2005</p>
<p type="listitem">4. <span type="quote">“Landscape and society”</span>, Ljubljana (Slovenia), 11-12 May 2006</p>
<p type="listitem">5. <span type="quote">“Landscape quality objectives: from theory to practice”</span>, Girona (Spain), 28-29 September 2006</p>
<p type="listitem">6. <span type="quote">“Landscape and rural heritage”</span>, Sibiu (Romania), 20-21 September 2007</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">7. <span type="quote">“Landscape in planning policies and governance: towards integrated spatial management”</span>, Piestany (Slovakia), 24-25 April 2008</p>
<p type="listitem">8. <span type="quote">“Landscape and driving forces”</span>, Malmö (Sweden), 8-9 October 2009</p>
<p type="listitem">9. <span type="quote">“Landscape, infrastructures and society”</span>, Cordoba (Spain), 15-16 April 2010</p>
<p type="listitem">10. <span type="quote">“Multifunctional landscapes”</span>, Portugal, 20-21 October 2011</p>
<p type="listitem">The proceedings of the Meetings of the workshops are published in the Council of European Spatial</p>
<p>Planning and Landscape Series. <em type="bold">collecting examples of good practice: the landscape award of the council of </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Europe </em></p>
<p>The Convention (Article 11) provides for a Council of Europe Landscape Award. In particular, it states that, on proposals from the committees of experts supervising the implementation of the Convention, the Committee of Ministers shall define and publish the criteria for conferring the Landscape Award, adopt the relevant rules and confer the award. The Committee of Ministers adopted Resolution CM/Res(2008)3 on the rules governing the Landscape Award of the Council of Europe on 20 February 2008. The award was launched in 2008 and was conferred for the first time in 2009.</p>
<p type="listitem">The criteria for conferring the Landscape Award of the Council of Europe are as follows:</p>
<p type="listitem">Sustainable territorial development: The completed projects submitted must give tangible form to the protection, management and/or planning of landscapes. This means that the projects must have been  completed and open to the public for at least three years when the candidatures were submitted.  They  must also be part of a sustainable development policy and be in harmony with the territorial organisation of  the area concerned; demonstrate their environmental, social, economic, cultural and aesthetic sustainability;  counter or remedy any damage to landscape structures; help enhance and enrich the landscape and 22develop new qualities.</p>
<p type="listitem">Exemplary value: The implementation of the policy or measures that have helped to improve the protection, management and/or planning of the landscapes concerned must set an example of good practice for others  to follow.</p>
<p type="listitem">Public participation: The policy or measures implemented with a view to the protection, management and/or planning of the landscapes concerned should involve the active participation of the public, local and regional  authorities and other players and should clearly reflect the landscape quality objectives.  The public should  be able to participate simultaneously in two ways: through dialogue and exchanges between members of  society (public meetings, debates, procedures for participation and consultation in the field, for example);  through procedures for public participation and involvement in landscape policies implemented by national,  regional or local authorities.</p>
<p type="listitem">Awareness-raising: Article 6.A of the Convention provides that <span type="quote">“each Party undertakes to increase awareness among civil society, private organisations and public authorities of the value of landscapes, their  role and changes to them”</span>.  Action along these lines taken as part of the completed project concerned will  be assessed. Two sessions of the Council of Europe Landscape Award were organised:   1st Session 2008-2009  The following achievements were presented:</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">States</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Candidates</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Project title</p>
<p>Czech Republic</p>
<p xml:lang="fao">Tourist Club</p>
<p>Marking system of the tourist trails</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Finland</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Hämeenkyrö</p>
<p>Landscape Management of Hämeenkyrö National</p>
<p>Landscape Area</p>
<p>France</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Lille Métropole</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Parc de la Deûle</p>
<p xml:lang="fao">Hungary</p>
<p>Public Foundation for Nature</p>
<p>Conservation Pro Vértes</p>
<p>Implementation of the Complex Nature Conservation and Landscape Management Programme in the Zámoly Basin</p>
<p>Italy</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Val di Cornia</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">The Val di Cornia Parc System</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Slovenia</p>
<p>University of Ljubljana</p>
<p>Regional Distribution of Landscape Types</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Spain</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">San Sebastián City Council</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">Parque de Christina Enea</p>
<p>Turkey</p>
<p>Association for Nature</p>
<p>Conservation</p>
<p>Biodiversity and Natural Resources Management</p>
<p>Project</p>
<p type="listitem">At their 1066th Meeting of 23 September 2009, the Committee of Ministers’ Deputies decided:</p>
<p type="listitem">to confer the Council of Europe Landscape Award, under the European Landscape Convention, to the <span type="quote" xml:lang="fra">“Parc de la Deûle”</span>, Lille Métropole (France);</p>
<p type="listitem">to give a special mention of the Council of Europe Landscape Award to the <span type="quote" xml:lang="spa">“Parque de Christina Enea”</span>, San</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">Sebastián (Spain);</p>
<p type="listitem">to congratulate the originators of the projects and the achievements linked with the following briefs:</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Marking system of the tourist trails”</span>, Tourist Club (Czech Republic);</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob"><span type="quote">“Landscape Management of Hämeenkyrö National Landscape Area”</span>, Hämeenkyrö (Finland);</p>
<p type="listitem">“Implementation of the Complex Nature Conservation and Landscape Management Programme in the</p>
<p type="listitem">Zámoly Basin”, Public Foundation for Nature Conservation Pro Vértes (Hungary);23</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote" xml:lang="nno">“The Val di Cornia Parc System”</span>, Val di Cornia (Italy);</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Biodiversity and Natural Resources Management Project”</span>, Association for Nature Conservation (Turkey);</p>
<p type="listitem">to recognise the exemplary value of the work entitled <span type="quote">“Regional Distribution of Landscape Types”</span>,</p>
<p>University of Ljubljana (Slovenia).</p>
<p>The Landscape Award and the Special Mention achievements were officially presented on 8 October 2009 by the representative of the Secretary General of the Council of Europe on the occasion of the 8th Meeting of the Council of Europe on the implementation of the European Landscape Convention (Malmö, Sweden, 8-9 October 2009) and that several press releases were published on this occasion. <em type="italic">2nd Session 2010-2011 </em></p>
<p>On 9 February 2010, the Parties to the Convention were invited to present candidatures to the Secretary General of the Council of Europe by 31 December 2010. The following achievements were presented:</p>
<p>States and National Award</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Candidates</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Project title</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Belgium</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Parc naturel des Plaines de l’Escaut <span type="quote" xml:lang="fra">“Route paysagère réalisée par le Parc naturel des Plaines de l’Escaut”</span></p>
<p>Cyprus</p>
<p>Polystypos Community Council“Hazel orchards located within the</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">CY2000009 Natura 2000 site”</p>
<p>Czech Republic</p>
<p>Regional Land Office Prostejov<span type="quote" xml:lang="vep">“Čehovice, district Prostějov – Moravia”</span></p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Finland</p>
<p>Finnish Association for Nature</p>
<p>Conservation<span type="quote">“Management of endangered traditional biotopes and the preservation of the traditional Finnish rural landscape”</span></p>
<p>France</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Syndicat mixte d’étude d’aménagement et de gestion de la base régionale de plein air et de loisirs du Port aux Cerises<span type="quote" xml:lang="fra">“Le Port aux Cerises”</span></p>
<p xml:lang="fao">Hungary</p>
<p>Kaptárkő Természetvédelmi és Kulturális Egyesület (Beehive rock Nature Conservation and Cultural Association)“Maintaining landscape heritage of</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Bükkalja Region”</p>
<p>Italy</p>
<p>City of Carbonia<span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">“Project Carbonia: Landscape Machine”</span></p>
<p>Netherlands</p>
<p>Foundation Landscape manifesto<span type="quote" xml:lang="deu">“Stichting Landschapsmanifest”</span></p>
<p>Norway</p>
<p>County of Hordaland<span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">“Herand Landscape Park”</span></p>
<p>Serbia (Signatory State) <span type="quote" xml:lang="smj">“Podunav”</span> Backi Monostor<span type="quote" xml:lang="hbs">“Backi Monostor”</span></p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Slovakia</p>
<p>Ekopolis Foundation“The Grant Programs of Ekopolis</p>
<p>Foundation”</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Slovenia</p>
<p>Slovenian Association of Landscape Architects<span type="quote">“We are Making our Landscape”</span></p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Spain</p>
<p>Government of Catalonia’s Ministry of Education and Ministry of Town, Country Planning and Public Works (DPTOP), Landscape Observatory of Catalonia (OPC)<span type="quote">“City, territory, landscape: A project to educate and raise awareness about landscape”</span></p>
<p>United Kingdom</p>
<p>Durham Heritage Coast Partnership <span type="quote" xml:lang="nob">“Durham Heritage Coast”</span></p>
<p>The Committee of Ministers will take a final decision on projects retained for the award or special mentions. All 24the achievements together are presented on the Council of Europe website to a wide public so that they may stimulate comparable initiatives.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Fostering knowledge and research </em></p>
<p>Exploratory reports on issues related to the European Landscape Convention are drawn up by Council of Europe experts and submitted to the relevant committees of experts. To date, reports have been produced on the following subjects:</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rmf">Themes</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape policies: contribution to the well-being of European citizens and to sustainable development (social, economic, cultural and ecological approaches);</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape identification, evaluation and quality objectives, using cultural and natural resources;</p>
<p type="listitem">Awareness-raising, training and education;</p>
<p type="listitem">Innovative tools for the protection, management and planning of landscape;</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape, towns and suburban and peri-urban areas;</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape and transport infrastructures: roads;</p>
<p type="listitem">Selected EU funding opportunities to support the implementation of the European Landscape Convention;</p>
<p type="listitem">European local landscape circle studies;</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape and education;</p>
<p type="listitem">Road infrastructures: tree avenues in the landscape;</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape and ethics;</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape and wind turbines.</p>
<p type="listitem">The reports are available at the Council of Europe Publishing:</p>
<p type="listitem">Council of Europe, Landscape and sustainable development: challenges of the European Landscape</p>
<p type="listitem">Convention, Council of Europe Publishing, 2006</p>
<p type="listitem">Council of Europe, Landscape facets, Council of Europe Publishing (to be published in 2011)</p>
<p><em type="bold">Raising awareness </em><em type="italic"><span type="quote">“Futuropa, for a new vision of landscape and territory”</span>magazine </em></p>
<p>Several information documents and four issues of the Council of Europe’s <span type="quote" xml:lang="ron">“Naturopa”</span> magazine have been devoted to landscape and the European Landscape Convention. The magazine has been renamed <span type="quote">“Futuropa, for a new vision of landscape and territory”</span> so as to highlight the cross-sectoral nature of the themes more clearly.</p>
<p type="listitem">Themes concerning the landscape</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Landscapes:  the setting for our future lives”</span>, Naturopa, 1998, No 86</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“The European Landscape Convention”</span>, Naturopa, 2002, No 98</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Landscape through literature”</span>, Naturopa/Culturopa, 2005, No 103</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Vernacular rural housing: heritage in the landscape”</span>, Futuropa: for a new vision of landscape and territory, 2008, No 1</p>
<p type="listitem"><span type="quote">“Landscape and transfrontier co-operation”</span>, Futuropa: for a new vision of landscape and territory, 2010, No 2  Website of Naturopa / Futuropa: www.coe.int/naturopa/futuropa25<span type="quote">“International Heritage Photographic Experience - Heritage and Landscape”</span> (IHPE) Ceremony</p>
<p>The prize-winning photographs from the “International Heritage Photographic Experience - Heritage and</p>
<p>Landscape” (IHPE) competition are regularly displayed in the Committee of Ministers Foyer at the headquarters of the Council of Europe in Strasbourg along with a prize-winning ceremony involving about a hundred young people from various countries organised. The competition is intended to encourage young people to adopt a creative approach and take a personal look, via the medium of photography, at elements of the cultural heritage around them, in liaison with the landscape.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Fostering access to information: the European Landscape convention website </em></p>
<p>The Council of Europe European Landscape Convention websites includes the following: The site will also offer access to the Council of Europe Information System of the European Landscape Convention provided for in Recommendation CM/Rec(2008)3 of the Committee of Ministers to member states on the guidelines for the implementation of the European Landscape Convention.</p>
<p>Image 1. The Council of Europe European Landscape Convention website www.coe.int/</p>
<p>EuropeanlandscapeConvention; www.coe.int/EuropeanlandscapeConvention/fr26</p>
<p>Conclusion</p>
<p>The Action Plan adopted by the Heads of state and government of the member states of the Council of Europe (Warsaw, 17 May 2005), at the Third Summit of the Council of Europe includes a section on the promotion of sustainable development and states: <span type="quote">“We are committed to improving the quality of life for citizens. The Council of Europe shall therefore, on the basis of the existing instruments, further develop and support integrated policies in the fields of environment, landscape, spatial planning and prevention and management of natural disasters, in a sustainable development perspective”</span>.</p>
<p>As a thoroughly modern concept, landscape combines all four elements of sustainable development: natural, cultural, social and economic. It is also a constantly evolving story. As unique setting and meeting place for populations, landscape is a key factor in the physical, mental and spiritual well-being of individuals and societies. As source of inspiration, it takes us on a journey, both individual and collective, through time, space and imagination.</p>
<p>Any government wishing to implement the principles of good governance needs to give due emphasis to landscape in its national and international policies.</p>
<p type="listitem">The following examples can be given on the progress achieved during the last ten years:</p>
<p type="listitem">the landscape is progressively included in the political agenda of governments,</p>
<p type="listitem">the concept of landscape, as defined by the Convention, is becoming more and more recognised in public policies at international, national, regional and local levels as well as by populations,</p>
<p type="listitem">specific laws and regulations referring to landscape have been developed according to the provisions of the</p>
<p type="listitem">Convention,</p>
<p type="listitem">an important network of co-operation at international level for the implementation of the European</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape Convention has been developed,</p>
<p type="listitem">new forms of co-operation are developed between different levels of authorities (international, national, regional and local) and between ministries or departments of one State or region,</p>
<p type="listitem">States or regions co-operate beyond their borders for transfontier landscapes,</p>
<p type="listitem">specific working structures for landscape (observatories, centers or landscape institutes) have been created,</p>
<p type="listitem">national landscape awards referring to the European Landscape Convention have been launched,</p>
<p type="listitem">university programmes have been developped with a reference to the Convention and summer universities on landscape are organised,</p>
<p type="listitem">biennials, landscape festivals and exhibitions are organised and films referring to the European Landscape</p>
<p>Convention prepared.</p>
<p>The following steps will consolidate the achievements and explore new ways of promoting the ‘landscape approach’.</p>
<p>References Council of Europe, Landscape and sustainable development: challenges of the European Landscape Convention, Council of Europe Publishing, 2006, 213 p.</p>
<p>Council of Europe, Human Rights and the Environment, Council of Europe Publishing, 2002, 341 p.27</p>
<p>TRANSNATIONAL AND TRANSBORDER</p>
<p xml:lang="kal">CO-OPERATION - AN OPPORTUNITY</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">FOR BETTER LANDSCAPES</p>
<p xml:lang="est"><em type="bold">Jean-François Seguin </em></p>
<p>The European Landscape Convention provides that <span type="quote">« These identification and assessment (of landscapes) procedures shall be guided by the exchanges of experience and methodology, organised between the Parties at European level pursuant to Article 8»</span>. The article 8 provides that <span type="quote">“The Parties undertake to co-operate in order to enhance the effectiveness of measures taken under other articles of this Convention, and in particular: to render each other technical and scientific assistance in landscape matters through the pooling and exchange of experience, and the results of research projects.”</span></p>
<p>To effectively implement these provisions and, at the same time, prepare a new version of the method for the <span type="quote" xml:lang="est">« Landscape atlases »</span>, used in France since 1994, the French Ministry of Ecology, in charge of the landscape policy, took the initiative in 2005 to organize transborder workshops. The French practice of the elaboration of Landscape atlases was continuously enriched by these exchanges of experience and methodology.</p>
<p>The idea of these workshops is quite simple: a priori, landscapes form a continuum that is not dissolved at border crossings. The workshops are organized in territories which have, although separated by a border between States, common geography and landscape. These proximity and similarity allow a good comparison of methods used and results obtained.</p>
<p>The work of the workshop begins in fact well in advance: documentation is collected and made available to participants a month before. The workshop itself starts on the ground, where one can compare his reading of the landscape found in the presentation of its description in the methodology of both sides of the border. This essential <span type="quote">“ground work”</span> continues indoors with a discussion and an exchange of views. The workshop ends with the collective formulation of conclusions that are drawn <span type="quote">“live”</span> by projecting on a screen.</p>
<p>To lower the costs, workshops are organized on voluntary basis: every one supports its own travel and subsistence expenses and the regional office of ministry concerned mobilise its resources to support the workshop. The number of participants is limited to thirty for a better participation of everyone. Most of the time, the translation is not provided and everyone is invited to speak in his own language to limit misinterpretation introduced by the use of a <span type="quote">« exchange language »</span> that usually betrays the real meaning of the words of the landscape. Bilingual persons (students most of the time) are invited to specify, when appropriate, the meaning of certain words or concepts used. This is fundamental because the terms related to the landscape in use in various languages are full of <span type="quote" xml:lang="isl">“faux amis”</span>. Experienced by these trans-border workshops, I do not seek the <span type="quote">“literal”</span> translation of a particular word, but, more usefully, I try to understand the equivalence between languages, between cultures, between scientific and technical vocabularies.</p>
<p>Each workshop examine a specific subject of identification and assessment of landscapes: in Wallony, the summary, i.e. the themes and topics studied in Landscape atlases; In Spain, the definition of landscape units, landscape structures and landscape elements; in Italy, how to take into account local perceptions, in England, the landscape dynamics and in Catalonia, the uses of Atlas landscapes. We always invited a few experts or practitioners from other European countries or disciplines cousins (such as landscape ecology). So that, the conclusions are more and more thoughtful. In terms of landscape, it is never useless to call for the collective intelligence.</p>
<p>This principle of collective intelligence is, in my opinion, one of the best gift offered by the Florence Convention.</p>
<p>The transborder workshops are representative of this gift because not only several parties to the European Landscape Convention are involved, but also because they are together representatives of public authorities, states, regions, provinces and municipalities, scientists, practitioners and NGOs. This small and cheap device, where everyone contributes, is effective and is a useful addition to the Workshops of the Council of Europe for the implementation of the European Landscape Convention.28</p>
<p>France-Wallonie transborder workshop</p>
<p>This workshop was located in the <span type="quote" xml:lang="fra">« Pointe de Givet »</span> in France and, in Wallonia, in the <span type="quote">« landscape territory »</span> Dépression de Fagne - Famenne and its southern edge. This part of the Ardennes presents undeniable similarities and obvious differences in either side of the border marked by customs posts, now abandoned. The objective of the study was to validate the guidelines of a process of identification and assessment of landscapes and to specify the conditions for validating information provided. Landscapes, as defined in the European Landscape Convention, should be in relation to the approach proposed by the current landscape ecology, including ELCAI (European Landscape Character Assessment Initiative). The examined documents were <span type="quote">“Regional landscape atlas of Champagne-Ardenne”</span> for France, “Landscape Territories of Wallonia » for Belgium and the map LANMAP2 ELCAI produced by the Wageningen university (Netherlands).</p>
<p>The conclusions of this workshop were a <span type="quote">“reading grid”</span> of the atlas. This grid helps to ensure quality control by checking the atlas produce information on a set of key points:</p>
<p>In France, the use of this <span type="quote">« reading grid »</span> allows to ensure quality control of Landscape atlas published and formulate, when appropriate, recommendations for updating the documents, which must be performed every 10 years. In Wallonia, this grid has been used to precise the document <span type="quote">“Landscape Territories of Wallonia”</span> and to elaborate on every landscape territory a landscape atlas.</p>
<p>France-Spain transborder workshop</p>
<p>This transborder workshop was located in the Pays Basque. This area is an historic and cultural territory that extend in Spain as an autonomous community and in France as a part of the department of Pyrénées-Atlantiques. The documents used during the workshop were Landscape atlas of the Pyrenees-Atlantiques conducted in 2003 by landscape architects Jean-François Morel and Michele Delaigue and Atlas de los Paisajes de España, published the same year by the Autonomous University of Madrid under the direction of Rafael Mata Olmo.</p>
<p>The purpose of this workshop was to define, using French and Spanish experiences, terms of landscape unit, landscape structure and landscape elements. These three <span type="quote">“landscape components”</span> have been introduced into French legislation in 1993 by the Law on the protection and management of landscapes.</p>
<p>The workshop clarified a key issue in terms of landscape: the spatial scales. The definition of landscape units should always be accompanied by the accuracy of the scale on which this term is used. In France, the conventional scale of Atlas landscapes is that of a department, the analysis is performed at 1 / 25 000 and the return data is at 1 / 100 000. There may be aggregations or groupings higher on larger territories (families, groups, types, ....). These two scales of Landscape atlases meet the operational goals.</p>
<p>The conclusions of the workshop (also attended by representatives of Wallonia and Italy, as well as teachers and students of French landscape schools) have reached agreement on the following definitions:</p>
<p><em type="italic">Landscape unit </em>: A landscape unit is a set of spatial components, social perceptions and landscape dynamics which provide a uniqueness to the part of territory concerned. It is distinguished from neighbouring units by a difference in presence, organization or forms of these characters. In Landscape atlases, landscape units are identified at the 1 / 100 000 scale and corresponds to <span type="quote">« specific landscape »</span> of the European Landscape Convention, article 1. <span type="quote">« Landscape unit »</span> is equivalent to <span type="quote">« landscape »</span>. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Landscape structures </em>: The landscape structures are hybrid objects, resulting from the active interaction between biophysical and social dynamics. They correspond to systems formed by objects, material elements of the territory and interrelationships, tangible or intangible, which bind them and their perception by the population. These landscape structures are the characteristic features of a landscape. They contribute primarily to the identification and characterization of a landscape. A <span type="quote">“specific landscape”</span> is characterized by a set of landscape structures, formed during the centuries. The landscape analysis requires the selection of components for their relations, their particular organization, their ability to structure. The landscape structures reflect the interaction between the social, historical and current, and biophysical structures. The landscape structures provide the framework of actions for the protection, management and / or planning. Tools representations of landscape 29structures should be implemented rigorously. They are an allegory of the landscape structure identified. The <span type="quote">“landscape blocks”</span> seem relevant in this regard. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Landscape elements </em>: Firstly, the landscape elements are the components of material objects and structures. </p>
<p>On the other hand, some components of the landscape that are not systems (a single tree for example) can show characteristics of landscape. These elements are seen not only through their concrete materiality, but also through historical filters, naturalists, amenity ... (remarkable tree: tree of liberty or botanical curiosity). The landscape elements are not necessarily dots. For example, the relief is, in itself, a landscape element and may, by coming into relationship with other elements, human settlements, agrarian systems ... participate in a landscape structure.</p>
<p>France-Italy transborder workshop</p>
<p>The theme of this third workshop was the inclusion of perceptions by people in developing knowledge on landscape. This is included in Italy in Landscape Regional Plans and other tools.</p>
<p>Taking into account social perceptions is particularly important with regard to the definitions of landscape (area, as perceived by people, whose character is the result of the action and interaction of natural and/or human factors) and landscape quality objective (formulation by the competent public authorities of the aspirations of the public with regard to the landscape features of their surroundings).</p>
<p>In addition, article 6C of the European Landscape Convention calls <span type="quote">“to assess the landscapes thus identified, taking into account the particular values assigned to them by the interested parties and the population concerned”</span>. It is therefore important to consider how to collect and report these perceptions in Landscape atlases.</p>
<p>The territory of the workshop was the coastal area stretching from Nice (France) to San Remo (Italy). This narrow coastal strip wedged between the Mediterranean Sea and the Alps has been a crossing point, and thus an area of trade. The support documents were Agenda 21 of the Nice municipality and the proposed cycle track between San Remo and Imperia. Colleagues from Wallonia and the United Kingdom were invited, as well as the makers of landscape Atlases of regions Provence-Alpes-Côte d’Azur and Rhône-Alpes.</p>
<p>The conclusions of this workshop were as follows: In application of the definition of <span type="quote">“landscape”</span>, participation is the way to know the perceptions by the public.</p>
<p>To participate the decision making is not to make the decision itself, which remains the responsibility of elected. It is recommended to entrust a real responsibility to the people: to deliver a specific and crucial expertise.</p>
<p>It is necessary to clarify the terms used: <span type="quote">“perception”</span> is a general term that refers primarily to neuro-physiological processes of understanding of the landscape by the body. <span type="quote">“Representation”</span> refers to ways in which individuals, alone or in groups, represent a landscape. This is the term most often used in particular in the context of planning of a landscape. <span type="quote" xml:lang="tur">“Preference”</span> indicates one judgment in which one landscape is placed above the others. Preference is a term used by the economists, including the principle of <span type="quote">“willingness to pay”</span>. Compared to a target of choice, we talk about the exclusive preference between two landscapes. <span type="quote" xml:lang="fra">“Aspiration”</span> refers to the desire or wish for an individual or a community for quality of a specific landscape. This is the definition of a landscape to which we must strive, a sort of utopia. These terms are not exclusive of each other but must be used precisely.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Perceptions over space </em>: It is necessary to spatialize perceptions. They are varying on different scales of the territory. At each scale there are different value systems that correspond to <span type="quote" xml:lang="dan">“models”</span> raised by the people: a global model, a local model and an individual model. Depending on the scale of territory, it is preferable to use different methods as surveys, enquiries, workshops, meetings, exhibitions, scenarios etc. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Perceptions over time </em>: Perceptions are evolving in relation to the evolution of landscapes themselves and the people themselves. Perception has a specific evolution, often linked to social and economic changes or the participation itself. It is therefore important to identify the <span type="quote" xml:lang="ita">“moments”</span> of participation and identification of perceptions throughout a landscape policy and its implementation. Similarly, it is necessary to involve the participation also for monitoring the implementation. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Perceptions, contradictions and conflicts </em>. They are contradictions between models, between actors and between social groups. It is necessary to report them in Landscape atlases. Even if participation solves some 30contradictions and conflicts, all the contradictions are not soluable. It is then necessary to integrate them as a fact in the proposed protection, management or planning. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Perceptions scales </em>: Social representations are structured on three levels: a global scale with references to a common (European?) culture and which refers to large shared landscape models (bucolic, pastoral, picturesque, sublime, regional, etc.). The local scale refers to an empirical culture of the place where we live and where we work. It results from the intimate knowledge of place, social relations and social memory. The individual scale, finally, involves references to the culture that the individual has built during his life. The interaction between these three scales helps to understand the complexity of the relationships to landscape and reveals contradictory perceptions (a landscape can be, for the same person and at the same time, beautiful and ugly). A single landscape can be perceived through different references that are sometimes incompatible. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Variety of methods: </em>The methods discussed during the workshop identify the issue of <span type="quote" xml:lang="spa">“social”</span> scale as the main difficulty. If the territory is small, it is possible to survey residents and neighbouring populations. If the territory is extended it is not possible to interview all people. Finally the need to spatialize perceptions for action should be noted. Indeed, the preference method does not set the right interventions. Its effect is to apply a single model to all landscapes (a green and open landscape, for example) and that model would standardize landscapes and thus reduce their diversity. </p>
<p>France-England transborder workshop</p>
<p>This workshop theme was the inclusion of landscape dynamics in the Atlas of landscapes. The area chosen reflected the large width between France and England, the English Channel. The <span type="quote" xml:lang="swe">“bocage”</span> of Devon (United Kingdom) and Le Cotentin (France) are both rooted in the medieval Norman law. This historical depth seemed a priori appropriate to examine the time scales of the landscape.</p>
<p>The conclusions of this workshop remind that in accordance with the European Landscape Convention, the analysis of landscape dynamics is not separable from knowledge of landscape. Every landscape is constantly changing. It follows the evolution of natural systems and social systems. Every landscape is the result of an historical process. The analysis of the historical dynamics helps to characterize landscapes.</p>
<p>Landscape evolutions must be specified in their nature, their extent, their causes and their rhythms. Therefore, the analysis is based on documentary sources, archives, field work and surveys of populations.</p>
<p>The landscape dynamics must be analyzed in three nested time scales: the past (century, millennium) to understand the long-term interactions between society and nature. The landscape is the product of the actors as well as observers (spectators). The present (decade) to understand, analysing visible signs of change, policies, statistics, economic, cartographic and documentary, developments over the last 10 years. Landscape elements and landscape structures such as patchy, materials and techniques, the frame plant, changes in farming practices, development of housing, the frame rail system, the way of life etc. are reflecting those present changes. Public policy evaluation is done for the changes that have been observed and analyzed. This also gives an opportunity to communicate on the current dynamics, planned and predictable. Finally, future development must also be approached. Sustainable development requires long term projects, but unfortunately today our projects are mostly short term. Every landscape is transformed according to its own pace. But a delay of 10 years seems appropriate to update Landscape atlases.</p>
<p>The dynamics of the landscape reflect global processes and local processes. The global model corresponds to changes at supra regional, national or European scales. The local model corresponds to changes at the scale of landscape units (a landscape). The study of local dynamics allows a better formulation of landscape quality objectives, taking into account the global processes. In Europe, the global dynamics have influenced and still influence the local dynamics in a different manner. In order to preserve the landscape diversity, it is important to identify the local dynamics, especially those that can influence the effects of global dynamics.</p>
<p>On the other hand, the description of the evolutions must distinguish the significant dynamics that affect the landscape structures (conversion of grassland to crops) from the dynamics that are not significant (crop rotation, etc.) and, on the other hand, the transient dynamics and those that are sustainable.31</p>
<p>Representation of the dynamics in the Landscape atlases, as maps, must shift the land use dynamics to landscape dynamics. Landscape dynamics are complex and tangled. On the scale of landscape units will attempt to represent them in 3D (block diagrams etc.). Photographic landscape observatories associated with Atlas allow to illustrate and locate dynamics. Technological advances promise possible animated representations.</p>
<p>France-Catalonia transborder workshop</p>
<p>This fifth workshop was based in Olot (Catalonia), at the invitation of the Landscape Observatory of Catalonia. The theme was <span type="quote">“From characterization to action”</span>. The aim was to specify to whom, for what and under what conditions, the landscape atlases are useful. The area chosen was obviously trans-Pyrenean.</p>
<p type="listitem">The landscape atlases are useful to decision makers:</p>
<p type="listitem">They provide a well-documented public decision because they put in perspective the perceptions and evolutions and identify the major challenges of the landscape. They produce useful information to the  landscape and sectoral policies. They represent an opportunity to integrate landscape into sectoral policies  and develop relevant tools.</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape atlases are reference documents. They are not prescriptive. So, the agreement of the concerned authorities is desirable.</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape atlases produce at their proper scale useful information for the formulation of landscape quality objectives for the protection, management and planning. If knowledge is shared, goals are distributed  among the competent authorities.</p>
<p type="listitem">The landscape atlases are tools for training and awareness of decision makers and technical services.</p>
<p type="listitem">The landscape atlases are useful to people:</p>
<p type="listitem">They allow the public to participate in decision making regarding spatial planning. They must integrate information provided by public participation.</p>
<p type="listitem">They contribute positively to a collective reflection on the importance of landscape, and attached values, and make possible different scenarios of the future.</p>
<p type="listitem">They contribute to achieve educational programs and public awareness.</p>
<p type="listitem">It is necessary to provide multiple access (press, broadcasting, internet, print editions ...): Landscape atlases should be completely free of rights to the widest possible dissemination.</p>
<p type="listitem">The landscape atlases are useful to experts (researchers, professionals ...): They ask new questions to research and provide reference information and guidelines for professionals.</p>
<p type="listitem">Guidelines to elaborate landscape atlases in the context of their use:</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape atlases must be updated to reflect the dynamics and territorial planning documents. 10 years seem to be a good update rate.</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape atlases should have a prospective dimension, including consideration of projects and scenarios reported.</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape atlases are key tools for revealing the landscape diversity at different scales.</p>
<p type="listitem">Relations with landscape plans:</p>
<p type="listitem">Landscape plans (Carta del Paisatge in Catalonia) are the step that follows the atlas of landscapes. But other uses should be sought. Landscape atlases can reduce costs and shorten the elaboration of other  instruments (plans, charters, environmental assessment of plans and programs, impact studies ...).</p>
<p>In conclusion, European Landscape Convention provides a fundamental opportunity to implement the principle of collective intelligence that generates both rapid and significant progress. Transborder workshops are an initiative that is easy to implement and very productive for improving methods of landscape identification and assessment. 32</p>
<p>Simplicity and efficiency are two of the major advantages of the European Landscape Convention, in my view.</p>
<p>The achievement of landscape quality objectives, which are at the heart of the Convention, is a goal primarily qualitative, not quantitative. It requires many scientific, technical and operational progresses. So, the Europeans can <span type="quote">“enjoy high quality landscapes and play an active part in the development of landscapes.”</span>. Initiatives such as transborder workshops are contributing greatly to that.33</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">EUROPEAN LANDSCAPE</p>
<p xml:lang="sma">CONVENTION IN SWEDEN -</p>
<p>EXPECTATIONS AND INTENTIONS</p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">Jerker Moström </em></p>
<p>This article is an attempt to briefly outline the main features of the implementation of the European Landscape Convention in Sweden. It deals with the formal steps leading to ratification, but it also wishes to give a deeper understanding of the process in terms of arguments used, intentions addressed and expectations found.</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Background</p>
<p>Sweden took active part in the preparatory work of the European Landscape Convention (ELC) during the late 1990s. Sweden signed the Convention already in 2001 but the formal process towards ratification made a halt after that. It wasn’t until 2006, when the Swedish National Heritage Board was assigned by the Government to make proposals for implementation of the ELC that the process was resumed. However, during the period, Sweden took part in European initiatives and Nordic co-operation regarding the ELC. In January 2010, Sweden ratified the Convention, which entered into force as of 1 of May 2011.</p>
<p>Preparatory work</p>
<p>The Swedish Ministry for Culture is formally responsible for the ELC, yet in Sweden the operative aspects of the preparation of the Convention has been delegated to the Swedish National Heritage Board, a Governmental advisory body under the auspices of the Ministry. The preparation of the ratification of the Convention has been undertaken in three steps, due to three main Government assignments aiming at outlining the way towards ratification of the Convention.</p>
<p>The 2006 in-depth assessment</p>
<p type="listitem">The 2006 in-depth assessment comprised a study of the preconditions for an implementation of the Convention.  It aimed at identifying weaknesses and strengths in the current system and proposed measures resulting in a  more comprehensive policy frame for landscape. Eight general measures were proposed in order to prepare for  a successful implementation:</p>
<p type="listitem">Ratify the European Landscape Convention as soon as possible</p>
<p type="listitem">Draft a holistic landscape policy</p>
<p type="listitem">Recognise landscape in law</p>
<p type="listitem">Put forth landscape as an asset in local and regional development</p>
<p type="listitem">Strengthen participation</p>
<p type="listitem">Safeguard the provision of knowledge</p>
<p type="listitem">Strengthen international co-operation</p>
<p type="listitem">Promote landscape perspective in research and education.</p>
<p>The conclusions were presented to the Government in the January 2008. 34</p>
<p>Legal assessment</p>
<p>Later the same year, the Swedish National Heritage Board was tasked with a new assignment aimed at the legal aspects of the ratification. The Government wanted to know if, and what, legal changes were necessary to undertake in order to meet the provisions of the Convention in-head of ratification.</p>
<p>Two main legislations with relevance to landscape in Sweden were addressed; The Environmental Code (1999) and the Planning and Building Act (1987/2011). Both legislations already comprises the concept of landscape, however, mainly acknowledged as a backdrop (visual, aesthetic) or as an aspect of <span type="quote">”land”</span>. According to the Swedish National Heritage Board the legislations did not recognise landscape in the inclusive sense stipulated by the ELC. Therefore, upgrading of landscape in both EC and PBA, mainly concerning general provisions, were suggested in order to align with the interpretation of the ELC.</p>
<p>Conclusions were presented to the Government in 2008. In 2009 the Ministry for Culture opened the proposal for consultation. Some 60 institutions responded (governmental agencies, regional and local authorities, NGOs, universities etc.) to the call. The responses proved a strong support for the ELC but on the other hand a lack of acceptance for the legal changes proposed. With regards to this response, the Government decided not to undertake any legal changes in-head of ratification.</p>
<p>Proposal for an implementation framework</p>
<p type="listitem">In November 2010 the Swedish National Heritage Board was tasked with its third Government assignment  regarding the implementation of the Convention in Sweden. The assignment was undertaken in co-operation  with other relevant parties. Fifteen key agencies, municipalities and other institutions were invited to contribute  to the assignment. The outcome of the assignment is a joint statement, proposing a framework for the Swedish  implementation. The assignment was reported to the Government in March 2011. In brief the framework suggests  the following:</p>
<p type="listitem">A shared responsibility between authorities is the key to a successful mainstreaming of the Convention into a broad range of policy areas. All authorities concerned, should therefore be responsible for implementing  and follow up the provisions of the ELC within their respective competences.</p>
<p type="listitem">In order to coordinate the work, a group of authorities chaired by the Swedish National Heritage Board, form a national coordinating body. Besides the Heritage Board, the group comprises the Swedish Environmental  Protection Agency, Swedish National Board of Housing, Building and Planning, Swedish Board of  Agriculture, Swedish Forest Agency, Swedish Transport Administration, Swedish Agency for Economic and  Regional Growth and the County Administrative Boards.</p>
<p type="listitem">No new instruments or institutions will be established and no legal changes will be undertaken due to the ratification of the European Landscape Convention. Focus will lie on enhancing performance of existing  policies and systems. However, there is a need for a recurrent venue devoted to issues concerning the  implementation of the Convention – a National Landscape Forum.  Such forum would be of vital importance  for spreading information and sharing experiences. The forum should provide an inspiring and inclusive  meeting place for reaching a wide circle of stakeholders, such as authorities, municipalities, NGO:s,  universities and other relevant parties.</p>
<p type="listitem">A <span type="quote">“national platform”</span> needs to be drafted. The main objective of such a platform or document is to provide an interpretation of the provisions of the ELC with regard to the specific geographical, political and  administrative settings of Sweden.  The platform is particularly important in order to provide a basis for a  common and widely accepted understanding of the Convention in a context where many authorities have a  joint responsibility for its implementation. It should also address key issues and stakeholders concerned as  well as outline the formal structure of the implementation of the Convention. It could also serve the need for  coordinated communication and information efforts concerning the Convention.35</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Intentions</p>
<p>We knew from the start of our work, that the implementation of the ELC needed to be based on commitment, not compulsion. To introduce the ELC as a duty or law would be contra productive with regards to the aspirations of the Convention and therefore <span type="quote">“needs”</span> were above all the keyword of our work.</p>
<p>However, such an ambition sets high demands for an inclusive and communicative process and we had to find a role in relation to the need of raising awareness and to guide and inspire others to explore the Convention themselves. When approaching the Convention this way, dialogue is crucial. From 2006 until present day (2011) the Swedish National Heritage Board has arranged some 20, and participated in more than 50 seminars, conferences and working groups dedicated to matter of the ELC.</p>
<p>In 2009, the Swedish National Heritage Board on behalf of Sweden hosted the Council of Europe annual meeting for the implementation of the ELC (Eighth Meeting of the Council of Europe of the Workshops for the Implementation of the European Landscape Convention) devoted to the theme <span type="quote">“Landscape &amp; Driving Forces”</span>. More than 300 people from 50 different countries participated in the meeting. During the entire process, some hundred institutions, agencies and organisations have taken part in the work through working groups, workshops and consultation.</p>
<p>Arguments</p>
<p>What is the ELC good for? What does it have to offer? What difference does it make? These questions have been recurrently addressed during our work. One of the key arguments we have promoted is the urge to develop cross-sectorial approaches to landscape. The Convention is offering a strong back-up to the idea of landscape as something holistic, a concept grasping both ecological and social dimensions of the environment in an integrative way, encompassing an ambition to move beyond sectorial policies in order to meet the challenges of the contemporary society. We believe that perhaps this is one of the most significant contributions of the ELC. And even though it may seem utopic or even naïve, the numerous examples of sectorial policy failing to fully deal with the increasing complexity of planning, urban and rural development and management of natural resources, confer that the quest for alternative approaches is highly relevant.</p>
<p>The seeking of solutions based upon a holistic scope of landscape should be understood in analogy with the aims and terms of sustainable development. It is something that can never fully be achieved because it is a moving objective rather than an absolute state, and as such it provides a moral compass for a better world and a better life.</p>
<p>Expectations</p>
<p>If we agree on the fact that implementing a convention is about commitment rather than duty and about awareness raising rather than applying the law, then how to measure achievements? How do we know our work makes a difference? How do we know in what way it makes a difference?</p>
<p>One way would be to consult the Internet community in order to analyse what kind of echoes the work on the</p>
<p>ELC in Sweden has generated in the <span type="quote">“cloud”</span>. When we started off our work in 2006 a simple Google search for ELC (in Swedish <span type="quote" xml:lang="swe">“landskapskonventionen”</span>) returned some 200 hits. In 2008 we started to take note on the number of hits once a month. The chart above illustrates the development during a period of two years. Being aware of the limitation of this blunt and imprecise way of measuring achievements, still it gives an interesting view of an issue on the rise. If we look more into details we’ll find that the content behind the hits have changed over time. During the first year the hits primarily comprises references to the Convention made by public authorities on their web sites, such as policy documents etc. The references indicate a growing awareness on the need to transform knowledge on landscape into policy.36</p>
<p>During the second part of 2009 the curve is climbing steeply upwards, reflecting a breakthrough for the</p>
<p>Convention in media, blogs etc. Thus, the growing number of hits as well as the underlying content reflects an increasing presence of the Convention in public awareness and debates.</p>
<p>A favourable wind for landscape?</p>
<p>In recent years, the challenges of climate change have triggered new interests in the field of landscape. Extensive planning for renewable energy sources, such as wind energy and biogas, has called upon the need to take stock of the landscape and its ability to carry the spatial claims raised by the energy policy. According to the Swedish energy policy, fifty percent of the energy consumption should be based on renewable sources by 2020. The planning objectives for wind power are set to a capacity of 30 TWh by 2020. Considering that the installed capacity today is approximately 5 TWh, the development will be significant during the forthcoming years.</p>
<p>To facilitate the development of the wind power industry and to ensure a more comprehensive assessment of landscape impact due to wind farm establishments, the Government introduced a time-limited planning programme in 2007, coordinated by The National Board of Housing, Building and Planning, to support regions and municipalities in the planning process. The programme is now closed but has successfully rendered a vast number of planning documents where landscape is held a key position. These planning documents represent a new generation of assessments, addressing landscape in a way that goes beyond traditional conceptions and reflects an ambition to meet the aspirations of the ELC. The initiative has also contributed to an injection of cumulated knowledge among consultants and officials.</p>
<p>ELC provides fuel for debate</p>
<p>Despite the good cause and high environmental provisions, the massive scope and scale of the wind power policy has led to resistance. A growing number of people claim windmill farms are causing serious harm to the quality of landscape and that local opinion is not taken properly into account when planning for new wind farms. In the public debate over wind power, the ELC has come to play a significant role. Turning to Google again, a search for <span type="quote">“landscape convention”</span> in combination with <span type="quote">“wind power”</span> generates some 1,700 hits, which is a good illustration of the close correlation between the two.</p>
<p>Image 1. The graph shows the number of hits returned from a Google search on <span type="quote" xml:lang="swe">“landskapskonventionen”</span> resp. <span type="quote" xml:lang="swe">“europeiska landskapskonventionen”</span> per month from January 2008 to January 2010. In September 2011 the number of hits passed 7000.37</p>
<p>The opponents of wind power assert that the ELC is taking their stand, as it underpins that the landscape is a key element of individual and social well-being and that its protection, management and planning entail rights and responsibilities for everyone. Some advocates of the wind power opposition go further and argue that the policy for development of the wind power industry is a violation against the Convention and its democratic aspirations. This matter is also an increasingly common cause of correspondence from the general public to the Swedish National Heritage Board. Since the ratification of the Convention we have received a substantial number of inquiries regarding the possibilities to appeal a case of wind farm establishment with reference to the ELC.</p>
<p>The case of wind power and ELC in Sweden is interesting in many aspects because it brings the challenges of the Convention to a head. On one hand, the inclusiveness and democratic touch of the Convention strikes a chord with people in search for <span type="quote">“tools”</span> to empower the cause of the local community. This is what we want it to be, right? But one the other hand it is not a law and so the Convention itself cannot be used to judge right from wrong. In this case, the wish for a <span type="quote" xml:lang="fra">”quick fix”</span> to complex planning dilemmas is in a sharp contrast to the long-term procedure needed to implement the honourable principles of the Convention. So how to sustain commitment and confidence in the Convention if instant action are expected while long-term solutions are delivered?</p>
<p>The case is also interesting because it illustrates the conflictual nature of landscape and the close relation between landscape and politics. In this respect it very much endorses the position of the ELC that landscape in fact is politics, and as such the Convention must be implemented through politics, not as opposed to it.</p>
<p xml:lang="som">Way ahead?</p>
<p>So, what happens from now on? Is the work finished? Is it time to settle down? Well not quite, ratification is an important mile stone but in fact the work has merely started. On the basis of the proposed framework we have had a busy year, facilitating the continuous dialogue on the implementation, providing guidance and trying to inspire others to explore the Convention themselves. Judging from the requests and response we get, we are even more convinced that the strategy jointly drafted in the framework – based on coordination and joint responsibility - is the right way to go.</p>
<p>A successful implementation is dependent on the ability to sustain and safeguard a long-term commitment, thus the ELC needs to be fueled with a permanent dialogue regarding its aims and provisions. This in turn requires active communities in support of the Convention, both at a European, national regional and local scale.</p>
<p>The Swedish National Heritage Board will continue its work on raising awareness among stakeholders, to help them find out how the Convention may impact their work and to take on an independent responsibility for its implementation. In order to extend the needs for guidance we are now planning for educational and networking initiatives.</p>
<p>Another key issue is an extended responsibility. This fall the national co-ordination group for ELC in Sweden will be set up and have its first meeting. This is an important step towards a more structured and co-ordinated implementation process and we hope for a fruitful outcome.</p>
<p>Equally important for the viability of the Convention is our ability to link it to other topical issues on the political agenda (such as climate change, energy policies, financial crisis, etc.). The mode should be mainstreaming of landscape into a range of policy areas rather than trying to establish a special track for landscape. There is also a need to identify challenges and opportunities, including keeping track of, and understanding, the political landscape and drivers of change. In doing so, the international co-operation is crucial, both on a Nordic and European, but also global scale.</p>
<p>What we have found so far is an overwhelming interest in the Convention but also a huge need for further discussions and dialogue regarding its aims and scope, and last but not least – a need to turn ambitions into action.38</p>
<p>IMPLEMENTATION OF THE EUROPEAN</p>
<p xml:lang="sma">LANDSCAPE CONVENTION IN</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">NORWAY, WITH A FOCUS ON</p>
<p>PLANNING CHALLENGES IN THE</p>
<p>MANAGEMENT OF LANDSCAPE</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">VALUES</p>
<p xml:lang="nno"><em type="bold">Kristin Nordli and Liv Kirstine Mortensen </em></p>
<p>Norway decided to implement the European Landscape Convention in 2001, and it entered into force on 1 March 2004. The overall responsibility for implementing the Convention in Norway lies in the Department of Regional Planning, at the Ministry of the Environment.</p>
<p>The Norwegian landscape is in a state of change. This is partly due to the impacts of natural processes such as wind, rain and snow, and of extreme weather events such as flooding, landslides and fires, which have been occurring more frequently in the last few years. But the great majority of these changes are brought about by human activities, such as forestry and agriculture, urban development, industry, energy production and transport infrastructure. In Norway the extraction of deposits and minerals is one of the main activities that comes into conflict with landscape values, and in North Norway there is sometimes direct conflict between such activities and reindeer husbandry interests.</p>
<p>Image 1. The Norwegian landscape is changing. Photo: Jan Hausken39</p>
<p>It follows from the Landscape Convention that national, regional and local authorities are jointly responsible for landscape policy. Norway supports the principle of subsidiarity (Article 4) and divides roles and tasks between the different administrative levels, so that decisions are made as closely as possible to private citizens. We therefore intend to develop and implement a policy for land-use planning and landscape protection and management at every level that makes use of the measures set out in Articles 5 and 6 of the Convention.</p>
<p>Local and regional authorities are the most important actors in these efforts. About 16% of Norway’s national territory has been designated national parks and other protected areas, and the remaining 84% is managed and controlled by the local and regional authorities under the Planning and Building Act. Norway currently has 430 municipalities with populations ranging from 200 to 575 000, and all of them, regardless of size, have an equal responsibility for local planning and development. This includes supplying primary services, deciding on land use, building and operating municipal technical installations, dealing with building permits and so on.</p>
<p>The 19 counties are responsible for regional planning and development, upper secondary schools and public transport within the county. They also provide planning assistance to the municipalities.</p>
<p>Since Norway does not map land use at national level, the local and regional authorities have the overall responsibility for dealing with land use and landscape issues on the nation’s behalf. This means that the central government authorities have to rely on local and regional planning in addition to specific policy instruments in their sectors to achieve national objectives.</p>
<p>Thus the main challenge in Norway is how to qualify 430 municipalities, of very different sizes and capacities, to manage landscape in accordance with the Landscape Convention. What are the best methods for integrating landscape considerations into regional and municipal plans and land use decisions?</p>
<p>The Ministry of the Environment is responsible for much of the legislation implementing the Landscape</p>
<p>Convention, which enables it to make use of a broad range of policy instruments in the field. The Planning and Building Act of 2008 has a more logical structure than the old one, and clarifies a number of important considerations that must be taken into account in planning. It facilitates participation in planning processes at all levels of decision-making, and incorporates requirements for planning programmes and impact assessments. In Part II of the Act, which deals with planning, new tools are provided for protecting and safeguarding natural and cultural landscapes, and planning is more clearly linked with the provisions in Part IV of the Act, which deals with building and construction. The new Act is one of the main Norwegian instruments for implementing the Landscape Convention and to some extent safeguards Sami interests as well.</p>
<p>In practical terms the Act has provided new opportunities for safeguarding the landscape by explicitly prescribing the inclusion of landscape as a factor to be taken into account in planning and planning tasks under the Act. In summer 2011 a document setting out national expectations – points the Government considers to be important considerations in regional and municipal planning – was issued for the first time. It includes clear guidelines for safeguarding landscape values in land-use planning. Regional and municipal planning strategies are to be developed after the local government elections on 12 September 2011, and to be adopted within one year. These will be a useful tool that regional and municipal authorities can use to assess their planning needs. The 2008 Planning and Building Act also introduced the possibility of designating certain areas in land-use plans as zones where special considerations apply, and there is a greater emphasis in the Act on area zoning plans that can provide integrated solutions. Furthermore the adopted plans are to have more influence on building applications and permits; for example, detailed guidelines may be issued concerning relationship with landforms, height of buildings, etc. Under the new Act, landscape considerations will now be integrated into municipal planning at all stages, from the planning strategy and programme to the development and implementation of the plans themselves.</p>
<p>The purpose of the Nature Diversity Act of 2009 is to protect biological, geological and landscape diversity and ecological processes through conservation and sustainable use and in such a way that the environment provides a basis for human activity, culture, health and well-being, now and in the future, including a basis for Sami culture.</p>
<p>The rules governing protected areas in Chapter V of the Act provide an effective tool for safeguarding landscapes by designating them national parks or protected landscapes. Landscape is explicitly mentioned in the purpose of the Act, which also prescribes that landscape considerations must be taken into account in the interpretation of other legislation. However, landscape is more narrowly defined in the Act than in the Landscape 40</p>
<p>Convention, since under the Act landscape is only one of several elements in the definition of nature diversity. There are also provisions relating to protection of <span type="quote">“selected habitat types”</span>, which may in practice protect some landscapes, but only indirectly.</p>
<p>The Cultural Heritage Act of 1978 replaced the previous legislation on protection of buildings and archaeological sites, and amended the definition of cultural heritage to include cultural environments. Under an amendment of 1992, large continuous areas that contribute to the distinctive character of a cultural landscape may also be protected. Six places in Norway have been classified as cultural environments and are protected by law: Neiden in Finnmark county, Sogndalstrand and the monastery Utstein kloster in Rogaland county, the Kongsberg silver mines in Buskerud county, the Havråtunet Farm in Osterøy in Hordaland county, and Birkelunden square in the Grünerløkka district in Oslo.</p>
<p>Thus Norway has a functioning legal framework for landscape protection. We are now far more aware of, and know far more about, the cultural heritage, cultural and natural landscape values, and the beauty and unique character of our own nature and landscapes. It is the ordinary, everyday landscape in which we live that is our greatest challenge.</p>
<p>Unfortunately not all the built-up areas in Norway’s magnificent landscapes are equally well planned. Land for building is in great demand and strong private interests are involved. These factors sometimes make it difficult for municipal planners to draw up good working land-use plans and have them adopted. Another problem is that in many municipalities there are no architects or planners employed in the administration.</p>
<p>Many Norwegian towns and settlements consist of a haphazard collection of buildings and roads. However, there is now growing awareness of the influence of the quality of people’s surroundings on their health and wellbeing, and several years ago special programmes for improving urban development were introduced.</p>
<p>Thus in Norway’s efforts to implement the Landscape Convention we have chosen to focus on <span type="quote">“the everyday landscape”</span> – the relatively small parts of the country where most people live and work. This is the context in which we are presenting information about the Landscape Convention in brochures, films and seminars, but these obviously have a limited effect. In addition there are various activities and projects focusing on particular landscape values. What we now need is to develop good planning tools that will make it possible to manage all landscapes in accordance with local wishes and national guidelines.</p>
<p>Image 2. The Norwegian planning system41</p>
<p>We have produced a brochure containing a translation of the Landscape Convention into Sami accompanied by an explanatory text, which we hope will be a useful Norwegian contribution to the joint efforts of the various countries to implement the Landscape Convention in the North Calotte area.</p>
<p>Local and regional engagement in the natural and cultural qualities of landscapes has led to the creation of local and regional parks. This is done through arrangements between counties, municipalities, organisations and businesses in a particular area, which enter into a long-term voluntary agreement for establishing a local or regional park. Designating a landscape as a park is an effective tool for implementing a coherent development strategy for protecting natural and cultural landscape values and their sustainable management. Currently three regional parks have been formally established – the Valdres Nature and Culture Park, the Nærøyfjorden World Heritage Park and the Telemark Canal Regional Park – and eight local parks in Hordaland county. The Hordaland model for landscape parks is now being followed in a project for a local park in Grøtøyleia in Steigen, Nordland county.</p>
<p>The UNESCO World Heritage Convention of 1972 was ratified by Norway in 1977. So far seven Norwegian places have been inscribed on the World Heritage List: Bryggen in Bergen (1979), Urnes Stave Church (1979), Røros Mining Town and the Circumference (1980), the Rock Art of Alta (1985), the Vega Archipelago (2004), the West Norwegian Fjords – Geirangerfjord and Nærøyfjord (2005) and the Struve Geodetic Arc (2005).</p>
<p>Inscription on the World Heritage List does not alter the principle of cross-sectoral responsibility, which is embodied in current policy and management. All the World Heritage sites enjoy legal protection. Parts of the sites are protected under the Cultural Heritage Act and/or the Nature Diversity Act and the rest is managed under the Planning and Building Act, depending on the distinctive features of the site concerned.</p>
<p>A number of particularly valuable agricultural landscapes have been designated in order to safeguard outstanding cultural environments and halt the loss of biodiversity through sound management. The measure is being implemented as a result of co-operation between the environmental and agricultural authorities.</p>
<p>In 2009, 20 of these agricultural landscapes were selected, one in each county, followed by a further two in 2010. The aim is to select a representative selection of agricultural landscapes from all over the country that are of exceptional natural and cultural value and where special care and management is realistic over the long term. Site management is carried out at the local level, with the strong involvement of landowners and municipalities. So far most of the experiences and feedback have been positive.</p>
<p>Image 3. Reindeer husbandry is part of the unique cultural heritage of the Sami, and reindeer herding occupies over 40% of</p>
<p>Norwegian territory. Photo: Marianne Gjørv.42</p>
<p>The National Tourist Routes project is mainly funded by the state. The aim is to provide opportunities for enjoying Norway’s breathtaking landscapes by designing viewpoints and rest areas along a selection of scenic roads with notable landscape elements. It is one of the most successful public landscape projects in Norway at the moment, and seems to have raised awareness of contemporary architecture as an integral part of a landscape and of the generally high quality of public and private buildings.</p>
<p>The challenges facing planners are especially obvious when large areas are being developed to adapt them to new uses. The major development of the Bjørvika district in Oslo, which is centred on the new Opera, is a good illustration. The public demand for transparency and public involvement early in the planning process is increasing, together with the demand that the visual impacts of new development on the landscape should be shown beforehand. Once the buildings are under construction and the public can see the results of the planning decisions for themselves, it is too late to discuss them.</p>
<p>Achieving broad participation in land-use planning requires greater awareness among all interest groups, and a coherent approach to planning and building is needed. We believe that this requires an understanding of the qualities of a landscape regardless of whether the plans are concerned with urban or with rural development. We are therefore developing planning tools for landscape assessment by national bodies, counties and municipalities.</p>
<p>Major transport and energy projects often make it a challenging task to maintain landscape quality. The plan for upgrading the stretches of the E6 and the Dovrebanen railway that skirt Lake Mjøsa and traverse the outstanding cultural landscape at Ulvin is a good example of how such challenges can be addressed. A number of local and regional authorities objected to the original plan because of conflicts with landscape and local environment values. Several alternative plans were submitted to the Ministry of the Environment, and the plan that was finally chosen, involved routing the E6 and the railway through tunnels under the landscape around Ulvin Farm. The fact that this solution was adopted in spite of the high costs has shown how important it is to have good planning tools that can reveal conflicts of interest, and to make use of such tools at an early stage in the planning process so that such issues can be addressed effectively.</p>
<p>A large number of wind farms are being planned at various locations in Norway. Wind farms often have major impacts on the landscape, and an example of a particularly difficult case was the Lista wind farm in Farsund municipality in southern Norway. The intention was to build a farm with up to 34 wind turbines with an installed capacity of up to 102 MW. The County Governor of Vest-Agder and the Vest-Agder county administration raised objections, but in spite of well-documented evidence of the consequences for landscape values, the objections</p>
<p>Image 4. Wind farm at Hitra. Photo: Ina Rognerud, MD.43were overruled by the Ministry of the Environment. The case illustrates the need to gain a good overview of the values of a particular landscape at the national and regional level so that large projects are not situated in areas with outstanding landscape qualities.</p>
<p>Such cases illustrate how much people may differ in the values they assign to landscapes and the visual impacts on them of developments like wind farms. Some people feel that wind turbines are an unacceptable intervention in the natural environment, while others find them a fascinating addition to the landscape.</p>
<p>Although the major national and regional power lines are exempt from the planning provisions of the</p>
<p>Planning and Building Act of 2008, the rules for impact assessments still apply. This means that interested parties and relevant authorities must be consulted. The power line between Sima and Samnanger in Hardanger made headlines in summer 2010 because of its potential impacts on the landscape and on tourism in the Hardangerfjord. This raises the question of whether the methods for surveying and assessing landscape values are good enough. How much are people willing to pay for landscape protection? Are the involvement and participation of the public and interested parties being safeguarded during the process?</p>
<p>The increased focus on landscape has led to a greater need for detailed information about landscapes and the impacts of a plan on a particular landscape. We need better tools for identifying and analysing landscape, both as a coherent whole and in terms of its various elements – natural, cultural, spatial and visual. The tools must be suitable for local and regional land-use planning, conducting impact assessments and analysing vulnerability and adaptation. The development of such tools is an essential element of our efforts to meet our obligations under the Landscape Convention. The Ministry of the Environment has therefore provided support for a number of landscape development projects under the auspices of municipalities, counties and directorates.</p>
<p>In Telemark a strategy has been drawn up for developing the Telemark river as a regional park. One of the main aims is to identify landscape values that can be used to promote tourism, commercial activity and settlement.</p>
<p>The Ministry of the Environment is also drawing up guidelines for the inclusion of landscape assessment in the obligatory impact assessments for future plans and projects. Great attention is paid in the Planning and Building Act of 2008 to landscape as an important element of regional and local planning.</p>
<p>In Hordaland a project on the inclusion of landscape as a factor in municipal planning has been conducted by the municipalities of Granvin, Samnanger, Sund and Lindås in consultation with regional experts. In the project the municipalities examined different approaches to landscape issues in municipal planning. They concluded that landscape assessment must be treated as an integral element of municipal planning and that landscape analysis should be used as a tool for landscape management and when deciding on the location of new developments.</p>
<p>The Directorate for Cultural Heritage and the Directorate for Nature Management have issued guidelines for landscape management in municipal planning and impact assessments. The first step was to decide on a common approach to landscape analysis, with an emphasis on the main elements: the description, interpretation and assessment of landscape values. The resulting report is being used as a basic document. Two additional sets of guidelines have also been drawn up on specific themes: the establishment of wind farms (in co-operation with the Norwegian Water Resources and Energy Directorate) and landscape assessment in municipal planning. The guidelines for landscape analysis in municipal planning are currently being tested in the municipalities of Lyngen and Nordreisa in Troms county.</p>
<p>The aim of the latter guidelines is to present objective, verifiable criteria for landscape assessment. It was emphasised that the same importance must be given to cultural features as to landforms, water features, vegetation, land use, buildings and spatial and visual factors. The guidelines on wind power are intended to be used in all impact assessments of wind power projects, and are being tested in five pilot projects. The final report has not yet been published since the evaluation results are not yet available.</p>
<p>The Ministry of the Environment has also initiated a project to examine the methods for identifying landscapes on a scale of 1:50 000. The report on the pilot project; <span type="quote">“Landscape identification in Norway. Methods and strategies”</span> showed that methodological development and a systematic survey of the whole country are needed, and that practical identification methods also need to be developed. A new methodology was tested in Nordland county in autumn 2011, and is being evaluated.</p>
<p>The Hordaland project on the inclusion of landscape as a factor in municipal planning was completed in 2010 and yielded a number of important results. It was found that the use of landscape analysis in planning 44substantially increased knowledge about landscape among municipal politicians and administrations and among the public. An awareness of landscape values and the importance of the natural and cultural heritage were found to be indispensable for achieving good results, and that this had resulted in greater political support for the adoption of municipal guidelines for landscape protection in development projects. This has opened the way for greater predictability in decision-making processes and provided a sound framework for land-use planning.</p>
<p>Conclusions</p>
<p>In spite of the encouraging results, all the projects have revealed a significant need for specific advice and guidance. The concept of landscape is easy to understand at a general level, but its breadth makes it difficult to translate into concrete action. Our current knowledge and competence in this area still leave much to be desired. In order to fully implement the European Landscape Convention, we need to establish more co-operation on regional and local planning and projects. And we need to focus on capacity-building at all levels.</p>
<p>Image 5. Vega, the only World Heritage site in Norway that is inscribed under criterion cultural landscape.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Photo: Elisabet Haveraaen.45</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">A SAAMI REINDEER HERDER’S</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">CULTURAL LANDSCAPE: MEMORY,</p>
<p>THE SENSES AND ETHICS</p>
<p xml:lang="sma"><em type="bold">Marie Roué </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">This is indeed our landour homeour life </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Valkeapää</p>
<p>Article 5 of the European Landscape Convention proposes that we <span type="quote">“recognise landscapes in law as an essential component of people’s surroundings, an expression of the diversity of their shared cultural and natural heritage, and a foundation of their identity”</span>. As such, the Convention presents us with the daunting challenge of understanding the specificity of a people’s landscape, in particular an indigenous peoples’ landscape, through their own worldview. The challenge is a sizeable one, not only because indigenous cultures differ from the mainstream, but also because nature and landscape are central to their very well-being. This is the case for the Saami people who live in the four countries of the North Calotte area, and who have not yet benefitted from a clear recognition of land rights. I will present their view of a Saami landscape through data gathered in the Jokkmokk area (Sweden) where I worked with Saami herders from 2008 to 2011, both in summer and in winter. I also benefited from a much earlier period of work with the Saami of Kautokeino (Norway) from 1969 to 1980.</p>
<p>Is there a Saami landscape? From space to place</p>
<p>Augustin Berque, a landscape specialist, distinguishes civilizations that have landscapes, such as China, Japan or the Western world after the Renaissance, from others that are <span type="quote">“non landscape civilizations”</span>. Four criteria bear witness to the existence of landscape within a culture: (i) a specific word for landscape, (ii) a literature describing landscape, (iii) pictorial representations of landscape, and finally (iv) the creation of gardens. This dichotomy between have’s and have not’s reminds us of the earlier elitist understanding of the term Culture. While culture with a capital ‘C’ is a Western conception of a written and codified culture of the elite, there is another understanding of culture, which concerns all social groups and not only the so-called <span type="quote">“major civilizations”</span>. Culture as described by anthropologists is a way of life and worldview in the same way that anthropology has imposed a broader definition of culture, we argue here for the existence of a Saami landscape.</p>
<p>If we look for theories that open the way for the recognition of indigenous landscapes, we must turn to phenomenology. As early as 1927, Martin Heidegger drew attention to the importance of concepts such as <span type="quote">“being-there”</span> or <span type="quote">“being-in-the-world”</span>. Instead of understanding landscape as a virgin space that is objective rather than subjective, we must grasp its significance as a place, somebody’s place, a place that can only be understood through that person’s own experiences and memory. In this understanding, several groups, even though they may share the same space, do not occupy the same place. We can go further and argue that each living person has their own sense of place, or places, which they combine to conceptualize their landscape. The anthropologist, Tim Ingold, based his ‘Temporality of Landscape’ on a re-interpretation of Heidegger’s conception of dwelling. He writes that a landscape is <span type="quote">“the world as it is known to those who dwell therein, who inhabit its places and journey along the paths connecting them”</span>. This conception of landscape is also apprehended as a phenomenon of in-corporation, the body being the origin of the perception of the world through all its senses. 46</p>
<p>A phenomenological understanding of landscape, by evoking the senses, legitimates the vision from within, an <span type="quote" xml:lang="deu">“emic”</span> vision, rather than an <span type="quote" xml:lang="fra">“etic”</span> or outside one (Buttimer 1980).</p>
<p>The concept of <span type="quote">“cultural landscape”</span></p>
<p>The term <span type="quote">“cultural landscape”</span>, which appears at the beginning of the 20th century, was originally shaped by German historians and French geographers. In 1992, <span type="quote">“cultural landscapes”</span> were recognised as a new category under the UNESCO World Heritage Convention as <span type="quote">“combined works of nature and humankind”</span>. This new category, which subsumes the Western dichotomy between nature and culture and recognizes that societies shape their environments and are shaped by them, was first applied to an indigenous landscape. The Tongariro National Park of New Zealand was classified as a <span type="quote">“cultural landscape”</span> in 1993, in recognition of the great spiritual significance of its mountains for the Maori people. The European Landscape Convention inherited this early recognition of a peoples’ landscape and took it a step further by defining landscape as <span type="quote">“an area, as perceived by people, whose character is the result of the action and interaction of natural and/or human factors.”</span> (Council of Europe 2000).</p>
<p>No longer conceiving nature as virgin wilderness and recognising that landscapes are transformed through centuries of interaction with people – these are considerable achievements. This said, is the category of <span type="quote">“cultural landscape”</span> fully adapted to the worldview of indigenous peoples? To answer this question, we consider the circumstances of the Saami people who live in Laponia, an area designated as a natural and cultural World Heritage Site.</p>
<p>Laponia: a landscape without a human trace</p>
<p>Following a long period of conflict, the Laponia process has finally come to a successful conclusion and has emerged as a major hope for the better governance and co-management of the site with both the state and the Saami involved. Although Laponia was initially presented by Sweden as a cultural and natural site, nowadays it is understood to be a <span type="quote">“cultural landscape”</span>. Early descriptions of the site emphasised the history of several thousand years of Saami occupation. While this emphasis on prehistory and history is important to legitimize Saami use and occupation rights, it nevertheless runs the risk of misleading visitors or outsiders who know little about contemporary Saami, into believing that the relationship of today’s Saami with the area is less intimate than that of their ancestors.</p>
<p>In fact, a particular emphasis on human history is present in the Unesco Convention itself. This bias may originate from the extensive study and use of the concept of cultural landscape by archaeologists. Anthropologists and sociologists have come to recognise the concept’s significance much later. The fact that a Saami archaeologist prepared the first document to justify inclusion of Laponia on the World Heritage list may also have had an influence on the way the site was first represented.</p>
<p>For a Saami woman in Staloluokta, the designation of her home area as a Unesco site did not make much sense. She recalled that her mother had shown her the place where her grandparents had a camp. Later, even though she tried very hard, she was unable to find the site. In her opinion, the search for historical ‘proof of occupation’ by park authorities or programs in order to demonstrate Saami occupation of the territory is a complete cultural misunderstanding. While Western culture searches for physical cultural remains as proof of occupation, the Saami work hard not to leave evidence of their passage behind them. These philosophies and ethics could not be more opposed. She asked: <span type="quote">“What is the purpose of these designations?”</span> Speculating, she put forth the humorous hypothesis that the proponents are actually trying to preserve the landscape from themselves, from their huge mines for example, or from their massive dams. <span type="quote">“As for us Saami, we did not impose ourselves on the landscape where we have lived for centuries, and therefore do not need such conservation programs”</span>.</p>
<p>I encountered a similar response when working with the Cree Indians of James Bay, Quebec, about the social and environmental consequences of hydroelectric development and their mega-dams. The Cree, who were 47invited to produce evidence of their presence on the territory, replied by espousing their own philosophy. When a Cree family leaves a winter or summer camp, they clean it. The aim is to not leave behind a single trace. Nothing should be left on the ground. Every part of an animal is consumed, as the old shamanistic beliefs are still very strongly respected. Animals are not considered as prey. They offer themselves to the hunter and continue to do so as long as the hunter maintains a respectful relationship with them. The Saami have the same spiritual background, and even if they have been Christianised early on, they still hold on strongly to their traditional ethics and values. Every reindeer herder knows that to be lucky or unlucky in reindeer herding is related to the way you yourself behave, your relationship with the reindeer and more generally to the world.</p>
<p>Saami intellectual culture and landscape</p>
<p>If we follow Berque’s criteria and are looking for an intellectual conception of landscape in Saami culture, we will find it in language and song. Saami language is famous for the richness of its snow and ice vocabulary, which allows speakers to make a thorough analysis of the changing states of these elements in winter (Magga 2006). While Italian or Chinese cultures demonstrate their social construction of landscape through paintings, books or gardens - all related to visual conceptions, Saami society conveys its own conception of landscape through a shared oral culture. Saami traditional songs, <em type="italic">juoigos </em>, evoke and describe special places, bringing images to the mind of singer and listeners. <em type="italic">Juoigos </em>put into song and word poetic images of people and places, of the reindeer herd, its colours, movements and sounds. Today, Saami poetry and literature are, in a way, assuming the same role in the modern world. Another cultural trait that we will not develop here, as it is well documented in the academic literature, are the sacred Saami sites or seite, which are always remarkable places from the point of view of landscape. While carefully-chosen stones moved from a stream into a Japanese garden evoke the natural world, the Saami give sacred meaning to rock formations or elements of nature that they encounter as they themselves move across the landscape on their seasonal migrations. </p>
<p>A dynamic landscape of snow and ice – Saami ecological knowledge</p>
<p>More than any other, a winter landscape is different for each person who looks at it. A non-Saami may simply see reindeer moving across a snow-covered land. Saami herders, however, who have a thorough knowledge of ice and snow expressed through the richness of their language, never see just snow. <em type="italic">Oppas </em>is pristine snow, constantly needed by the reindeer throughout the winter (Roturier and Roué 2009). <em type="italic">Čiegar </em>is a <span type="quote">“snowfield which has been trampled and dug up by reindeer”</span> (Nielsen and Nesheim, 1979). Once this has occurred, the reindeer cannot graze here anymore, as the snow has become too compacted to allow them to dig through it to feed on the lichen at the bottom. These areas may be covered again by new snow and appear pristine to a unknowing viewer. But for the Saami and their reindeer the area remains <em type="italic">čiegar </em>and is useless. As a consequence, the reindeer have to leave such an area and find a new <em type="italic">oppas </em>. For a Saami during the wintertime, reindeers move from <em type="italic">oppas </em>to <em type="italic">oppas </em>, leaving <em type="italic">čiegar </em>behind them. </p>
<p>Another important Saami term is <em type="italic">guohtun </em>. It is not easy to translate as it encompasses several levels of meaning. When the Saami talk in Swedish they use the word <em type="italic">bete </em>(pasture). <em type="italic">Bete </em>, however, has a more simple meaning, a place where plant communities are suitable for grazing. The Saami definition of <em type="italic">guohtun </em>, on the other hand, relates to the accessibility of pastures for reindeer grazing. In winter, or during the spring, a warmer period during which snow has melted or it has rained followed by a freeze may lead to the formation of an ice crust that locks away the pastures and prevents the reindeer from reaching their food. Under these conditions what was yesterday a good <em type="italic">guohtun </em>can become overnight a bad <em type="italic">guohtun </em>. A good <em type="italic">guohtun </em>is not only a place where there is lichen, but a certain time and place where the food is actually available to the reindeer. This complex Saami notion is multi-layered and concerns accessibility, time and space. Paradoxically, when the land is covered by a hard ice crust and lichen-rich pastures are locked away, the best grazing is provided by pastures usually considered to be poor because they only contain patches of lichen on a moss soil. This is why Saami 48herders, when asked what is an ideal pasture, often answer <span type="quote">“it depends”</span>, much to the dismay of outsiders who do not understand the complexity and variability of Saami understandings and conceptions of their landscape. </p>
<p>The landscape of all the senses</p>
<p>What is a beautiful landscape - <em type="italic">čappa etnam </em>? It can be described through the shared values and memories of a social group that uses a wealth of geo-morphological terms in the Saami language to describe land formations or to categorize different types of snow and ice. It is also the Saami toponymy which through place names tells local stories, myths about past events that happened at a particular place, and keeps alive the memory of people who were once there. But it is also a more individual landscape. While a local group shares much knowledge and history, a person is always unique. Through the words of Saami who shared their experience with us, we will attempt to convey these two meanings: from individual experience to shared cultural foundations. </p>
<p>For a reindeer herder, <em type="italic">etnam </em>refers to his territory, usually inherited from parents and forefathers, the place where his reindeer pasture. A herder may have a different <em type="italic">etnam </em>for summer, autumn, winter and spring. He can also speak about <em type="italic">mina etnama </em>, my traditional pastures, or about <em type="italic">baya sadan etnam </em>, the land where I grew up. At the beginning of the conflict over Laponia, the Saami created a new association to oppose the top-down management of the state and propose their own scheme to manage their homeland, now distinguished as a Unesco site. They named this organisation Saami etnam, Saami land or territory. </p>
<p>Many people consider Staloluokta to be the most beautiful lake in Sweden. But for a Saami now living in</p>
<p>Jokkmokk who, like many others, had to move with his family from Karesuando when he was young, it is still an ugly place: <em type="italic"><span type="quote">“I am born in Karesuando on a flat land. I love it there and I say o dobbe čappe, there it is beautiful! And people coming from there (Karesuando) say that it is very ugly here.”</span> </em></p>
<p>For him, a beautiful landscape is an evocation of memories from his childhood.</p>
<p>family in the Karesuando area. The whole family was migrating with the herd and the haergit, castrated draft reindeer. He exclaims: <span type="quote">“How beautiful it was!”</span> “Everything is beautiful when you are young. We were migrating with the whole herd. In the evening, when we were erecting the tent for the night, we would hear the bells around the tent.</p>
<p><em type="italic">We were sleeping so well. Some reindeer would even come right up to the tent and scrape the canvas. </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">They were such ‘urine lickers’. We found that pleasant and fun. There was also the sound of the bells, some haergit had bells, and by recognizing the sound of the bells, we could tell which haergit it was. It was beautiful.” </em></p>
<p>The beautiful landscape that he depicts is one of memory, emotion and perception using all the senses. It describes his sense of well-being, experienced as a child lying in a tent that smells and hears the reindeer that almost touch him. His memory is not so much about what he could see than about what he could decipher about the reindeer from familiar sounds and smells. Childhood emotions and perceptions remain powerful throughout life, and perhaps even more so when one’s destiny is to leave your homeland and immigrate to another landscape. What this testimony tells us is that your childhood landscape links you forever to the place where you were born, where your family comes from, a place which defines your very identity.</p>
<p>But as our speaker asks himself - are these no more than naive perceptions of childhood bliss, a nostalgia for an earlier era that was idyllic only for the child that he was 50 years ago? Upon reflection he concludes that this is not the case, as even the Saami that were elders at that time believed life was good. His reflection conveys a sense of disarray in the face of the complexities brought on by the modernization of the Saami way of life. 49</p>
<p>The <em type="italic">rai’do </em>as a symbol of Saami landscape </p>
<p>He evokes yet another image of a remarkable Saami landscape, the <em type="italic">rai’do </em>. A <em type="italic">rai’do </em>is a line of reindeer-pulled sleds tied one after another in single file. This formation is usually used when a family or a group migrates together in winter. Each sled is pulled by a <em type="italic">haergi </em>, a castrated draft reindeer, and a person sits on each sled. The sleds often form a long line, including sleds carrying the tents, tent poles and other equipment required by the party. For centuries, this veritable <span type="quote">“cultural landscape”</span> that depicts the intimate relationship between reindeer and people has been engraved on the knife sheaths that Saami men wear on their belts. </p>
<p>He recalls a particular moment when they met another <em type="italic">rai’do </em>. One of the haergi had a white ribbon in his horns, because he was pulling a sled that carried the body of someone who had recently passed way. Even as a child he understood that this reindeer was to be killed at the end of the journey, as he could no longer be used by the people. </p>
<p>This memory brings forth the essence of Saami culture: the relationship between nomadic reindeer and people, bound together from birth to death in a pact anchored in the world of the sacred. This value system is symbolised by the <em type="italic">rai’do </em>, the long line of sleds pulled by reindeer that tie together man and beast in a long ribbon that snakes across a landscape of migration. </p>
<p>We have been considering the testimony of an adult who recalls his childhood with nostalgia and emotion, and regrets the loss of harmony brought on by modernity. But for a younger herder born in the seventies, who has grown up with snowmobiles, their smell and their noise are included in his personal landscape. Modern <em type="italic">juoigos </em>bring forth the image of a specific herder by referring to the brand of his snowmachine and his licence plate. In the same way, drawings by Saami school children depict today’s reality showing helicopters driving reindeer and using their sirens, an image undoubtedly also associated in the child’s mind with the sirens of police cars in American television series. </p>
<p>The defining character of the Saami is their seemingly boundless capacity to change while remaining true to themselves. Today they still use the <em type="italic">rai’do </em>, still speak to their haergi, but also have snowmachines. And when they migrate, it is as always a close communion between people and reindeer moving across a landscape of known places rich with meaning, that today includes the snowmobile and its new noise. </p>
<p>Values and worldview</p>
<p>I conclude with the words of a great Saami poet, Nils-Aslak Valkeapää, who refers to the tent, <em type="italic">lavvu </em>, in poem 61 of his opus <span type="quote">“The Sun, My Father”</span>. He takes us from the world of the senses, of the perception of wind and the vision of clouds, and transports us on a spiritual and shamanic voyage: </p>
<p>The wind</p>
<p>Talks with the lavvu cloth</p>
<p>Clouds move across the smoke hole</p>
<p>Or is it the lavvu</p>
<p>That flies in the sky</p>
<p>Glides on the clouds</p>
<p>I look down on the sky ocean.</p>
<p>The lavvu transports us beyond. Our human lives are presented with their cultural, natural and spiritual elements. The <em type="italic">lavvu </em>, home, relates the poet to the wind, <em type="italic">biegga olmai, </em>a spirit or a god in Saami traditional religion. Through the smoke hole the spirit of the poet, as the <em type="italic">noaide </em>, the shaman, before him, leaves the human world to fly in the sky that from above now looks to him like the ocean.50 </p>
<p>We have attempted to demonstrate that, contrary to the view of Augustin Berque and other landscape specialists, Saami culture is also a landscape civilization. Landscape plays a central role in their literature, both the oral <em type="italic">juoigos </em>and modern poetry. Being nomadic, they do not create as sedentary people a garden which represents nature in a microcosm, but they give meaning to elements of nature by naming them, and designate remarkable places as sacred. As Ingold, we advocate for an understanding of landscape <span type="quote">“based on the premise of our engagement with the world, rather than our detachment from it”</span> (Ingold 2000:11). And in that direction Saami are ahead of us. </p>
<p>References Berque, A. 1995. Les raisons du paysage : de la Chine antique aux environnements de synthèse. Paris: F. Hazan, 192 p. Fowler, P. J. 2003. World Heritage Cultural Landscapes 1992-2002, UNESCO: World Heritage Centre,140 p. Heidegger, M. 1972. Being and Time, Translated by Macquarrie and Robinson, London: SCM Press. Ingold, T. 1993. The Temporality of the Landscape. World Archaeology 25, no. 2: 24-174. Ingold, T. 2000. The Perception of the Environment: Essays on Livelihood, Dwelling and Skill. London: Routledge. Magga, O.H. 2006. Diversity in Saami terminology for reindeer, snow and ice. In: Roué, M. (ed.), Cultural Diversity and</p>
<p>Biodiversity, International Social Science Journal 187: 25-34.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Nielsen, K. and Nesheim, A. 1979 [1932–1962]. Lappisk (Saamisk) ordbok-Lapp Dictionary, I–V. Universitetsforlaget,</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Instituttet for sammenlignende kulturforskning, Oslo</p>
<p>Roger, A. 1997. Court traité du paysage. Paris NRF Roturier, S. and Roué, M. 2009. Of forest, snow and lichen: Sámi reindeer herders’ knowledge of winter pastures in northern Sweden, Forest Ecology and Management 258: 1960–1967.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Valkeapää, N.A., 1994. Trekways of the Wind. Guovdageaidnu: DAT. Valkeapää, N.A., 1997. The Sun, My Father. Guovdageaidnu: DAT. 51</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">LAND USE PLANNING, NORTHERN</p>
<p>LANDSCAPE AND WIND POWER</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="bold">Timo Jokelainen </em></p>
<p>The Finnish Wind Atlas published in 2009 shows that the windiest areas in Finland are located at the sea areas. Building by the sea is not an easy task. There are several facts that make wind power operators turn their attention to other areas as well; changing ice cover conditions, unpredictability of environmental impacts of building wind power and the uncertainty of economical profitability are all facts that have to be taken into consideration. If we can not go in to the sea areas the next alternative is the sea shore areas that have strong winds. The shore areas have a lot of other use as well so the wind power parks are also planned on inland arctic hilltops as well as on sea and shore areas.</p>
<p>According to Finnish national objectives the total power provided by wind power should rise from the present 200 megawatts to approximately 2500 megawatts by the year 2020. This means building about 800 wind turbines with power of three megawatts during next ten years. The present pace of constructing will not meet the objectives; if we want to achieve the target we need to increase the volume of building wind power significantly.</p>
<p>Rush of wind</p>
<p>There are many wind power projects going on in Finland. Most of them are located close to sea and shore areas but there are also dozens of inland projects. The total number of projects is considerably higher than the national objectives for wind power production. In March 2011 there were publicly known projects for the production of 6300 megawatts. As we also know that there are a lot of unpublished projects, we can say that there is a rush of wind going on; actors in wind power are reserving areas for wind power production. The time for investment decisions will come later on.</p>
<p>The preconditions for carrying out wind power projects depend on many factors. The most important factor is the wind. But in addition to that there must be short enough electricity transmissions and profitable facilities to connect to the grid. Also other infrastructure like roads must support the project. Values of natural and cultural environment as well as landscape will also affect the placement of the projects together with the preconditions in regional plans.</p>
<p>In present situation everyone is in a rush competing for the most windy and otherwise profitable locations.</p>
<p>This is leading to a situation in which the wind power projects are directed quite uncontrollably from the point of view of the entirety. This way of unplanned progress may have unfortunate impacts for example on the tourism in Lapland.</p>
<p>Planning is needed in time</p>
<p>According to the Land Use and Building Act the planning system consists of three different levels of planning – regional land use plans, local master plans and local detailed plans – and national land use guidelines that overrides all other levels of planning. All these levels of planning and also the national land use guidelines have their own role in wind power projects.</p>
<p>According to the national land use guidelines regional land use planning must assign the areas that are best suitable for utilizing wind power. In Lapland the wind power is not a new matter in regional land use planning. Because of the vastness of the geographical Lapland the regional land use plan is drawn in five sections, so they are of different age. In the oldest regional land use plans no wind power areas are assigned and even in the more recent plans the assigning of wind power areas does not meet the requirements of today’s wind power construction. In order to partly correct this matter the Ministry of the Environment is financing a report concerning wind power 52in parts of Lapland. The results of this report can be used in future regional land use planning and also with certain reservations in municipal planning in cases where there are no regional land use plans guiding the wind power. Hopefully the report on the most suitable wind power production areas will be enlarged to cover the whole Lapland in the future.</p>
<p>Construction of wind power has to be guided also on more precise level than regional land use planning. This year there was an amendment done to the Land Use and Building Act; now, with certain preconditions, it is possible to allow a building permit for wind turbine on the basis of local master plans. This makes the planning processes more rational. In Lapland there are several general wind power plans under planning; this has been enabled by the new law. The local detailed plans will also be needed in the future for example in harbour areas and possibly in areas where there are several different forms of land use that have to be reconciled. The local detailed plans can also be used in areas where there are especially sensitive environmental values.</p>
<p>With the help of planning process we can find the least disadvantageous location and form for wind power. A.careful planning process also enables reconciling the different needs of land use. In fact it is hard to imagine a situation where construction of wind power could succeed without the guiding, participatory and solution binding impact of planning process. The existing wind turbines are 150 metres high and the new models reach up to 200 metres. This changes the landscape in a vast area especially when built on the higher ground. The regional land use plans have a decisive role in decision making while we are placing the regionally and nationally important wind power areas. There is a need even for national level review of placement for the wind power production areas.</p>
<p>Image 1. The planning system of land use according to the act of land use and building</p>
<p>Image 2. Wind turbine in Ajos, picture taken from an airplane landing to Kemi-Tornio airport. Photo: Timo Jokelainen.53</p>
<p>Various impacts on the environment</p>
<p>Building of wind power and the infrastructure connected with it has local impacts on the natural environment at the very least. The rotating blades of wind turbines can be death traps especially for large birds of prey as we know from the experiences in Norway. Nevertheless, there is only some local research information and the effects on birds at least in projects in Lapland are not easy to evaluate. There are several hundreds of golden eagles in Lapland and their territories have been taken into account while indicating the wind power parks in the provincial plans. These territories will also affect the projects that are ongoing, especially in Eastern parts of Lapland. The Finnish Game and Fisheries Research Institute has also warned about the risks concerning building wind power in sea areas. Both the building of turbines and the completed wind turbines will cause changes in ice cover, currents and sedimentation and therefore they will also have an affect on other natural processes.</p>
<p>It seems that there is not enough basic information covering all the aspects of nature impacts. Who is responsible for providing this information and what is the schedule? There is also a need for gathering general information on several different topics as it has been discovered with radars used in air control. This matter is being investigated in a project drawn by VTT Technical Research Centre of Finland, Finnish Energy Industries and the Finnish Defence Forces and there are already preliminary results available.</p>
<p>The projects in Lapland that are located in the northern part of the Gulf of Bothnia have an impact on fisheries and the inland projects affect the reindeer herding and livelihood. In order to minimize these impacts we need to have reconciling planning processes. In Lapland there are strong doubts that the wind turbines will have a negative impact on tourism in the area. According to the tourism entrepreneurs the wind turbines that are visible in the landscape will affect the impression of wilderness area and therefore they will hinder the tourism industry.</p>
<p>In public discussions the impacts of wind turbines on landscape seem to exceed the other impacts on the environment. In order to make profitable projects the wind turbines have to be built in the windiest locations. And from these locations they can be seen from far away. There are only limited possibilities to mitigate the effects on landscape for example through reducing the number of wind turbines. Therefore successful wind power production requires extremely careful control in planning the locations.</p>
<p>Image 3. Wind turbines are huge constructions. For example building the foundations takes about 600 m3 reinforced concrete. Also the installation field and other infrastructure built for the wind turbines changes the natural environment greatly especially in sensitive arctic hilltop areas. Photo: Timo Jokelainen.54</p>
<p>What kind of entities and where</p>
<p>In Sweden <em type="bold">, </em>Piteå they are planning a project for 1000 wind turbines. It would be good to discuss the locations of the hundreds of wind power turbines build during future years in Finland. Should they be handled as a one huge project, or as few big projects or as small projects scattered around the country. </p>
<p>It seems that the model of a few large projects is easier to manage than several small projects scattered around Lapland. At least this is the case when the impacts on landscape are concerned. Small project can often be carried out without the environmental impact assessment and even without planning assessment; therefore this may lead into insufficient planning and possibly also to insufficient participatory processes.</p>
<p>At the present the largest projects are planned at the sea areas and there will probably be places for them also in the arctic hilltops. The wind turbines are developing and getting larger in size. When the locations are considered it should be taken into account that the places that are considered to be unprofitable at the moment may well be used with the new technology in the near future.</p>
<p>The industrial environment and harbours are suitable areas for wind power and the constructors of wind power in Lapland are also interested in those areas; for example Röyttä area in Tornio and Ajos area in Kemi. However, they are not suitable for very large projects. Also the suitability of the areas along transport routes should be checked. In some tourism centres the fell areas have already been built for the use of downhill skiing, and it has been suggested that these areas could be used for wind power production as well. One example is in Olostunturi.</p>
<p>The projects that are currently ongoing in Lapland have also been experiencing headwind. People do not want wind power turbines in their landscape. Even if it is easy to have a positive attitude on low-emission wind power on the general level, people do not want to have changes in their own landscapes. In spite of the resistance, hundreds of wind power turbines should be built in our country within the next ten years. We should find the best locations possible for these. Planning has a key role in this process and it can also ensure the genuine participation of the citizens.</p>
<p>Image 4. Wind turbines in Oulusalo Riutunkari. There are plans for a large wind farm in the sea area between Oulunsalo and</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Hailuoto. Photo: Timo Jokelainen. 55</p>
<p>REGIONAL AND LOCAL</p>
<p>PARTICIPATION AND CO-OPERATION</p>
<p>IN IMPLEMENTING THE EUROPEAN</p>
<p>LANDSCAPE CONVENTION - THE</p>
<p>EXPERIENCE OF THE LANDSCAPE</p>
<p>OBSERVATORY OF CATALONIA</p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">Pere Sala </em></p>
<p>Catalonia enjoys a great diversity of landscapes and, fortunately, landscape is now more and more a subject of general interest that transcends specialised fields. It is becoming a fundamental part of territorial planning policies and of even more sectorial policies of a social and cultural character. The following text will develop in two parts. The first part describes in general terms the institutional and regulatory framework that underpins landscape participation and co-operation in Catalonia. The second part shows some examples of these experiences developed by the Landscape Observatory of Catalonia. Finally, some of the challenges facing us today in this field are dealt with in the last part of the paper.</p>
<p>Institutional and regulatory framework for landscape participation and co-operation</p>
<p>The Catalan Parliament joined the European Landscape Convention (ELC) in December 2000, two months after it was approved. Five years later, this Catalan body approved the Act 8/2005 for the Protection, Management and Planning of the Landscape, and set up the Landscape Observatory of Catalonia. The Act is the basic regulation and reference upon which the landscape policies of the Government of Catalonia are founded. The law is a faithful reflection of the aims and spirit of the European Landscape Convention and, in this way, it gives</p>
<p>Image 1. Landscape Observatory offices.56</p>
<p>Catalan landscapes legal protection and establishes the corresponding instruments to confront the challenges and guarantee the quality of the landscape.</p>
<p>Five aspects of the law foster participation and co-operation. Firstly, the law is clear and very easy to understand for citizens, associations and institutions alike. Secondly, the law is pragmatic and tangible, and its results are very easy to see. Thirdly, the spirit of the law is positive, rather than limiting or penalising, making it acceptable to all parties. In the fourth place, the Act has a transverse character: although it is from town planning policies that the Act is developed, it also opens the door to a progressive adaptation to the full integration of landscape into all areas of government action. Finally, the Act guarantees public and social participation and co-operation.</p>
<p>The first and most visible result of the Landscape Act was the creation of the Landscape Observatory of</p>
<p>Catalonia (www.catpaisatge.net), which has been operative since 2005. The Landscape Observatory has been conceived as an advisory body to the Government of Catalonia and for awakening society to matters of landscape. The Observatory has become a meeting place between the administration (at all levels), universities, professional groups and the whole of society regarding everything related to landscape. The main functions are collaborating with the Catalan administration for the implementation of the ELC; making Catalan society aware of the importance of landscape and the right to enjoy it; and acting as a centre for research, documentation, thought and action on landscape.</p>
<p>The Observatory’s structure and organisation are important for fostering the spirit of co-operation and participation. Three aspects can be mentioned in this respect. Firstly, the Landscape Observatory is a public consortium, with its own legal personality. This gives the Observatory an open-ended character, and makes it very flexible in its functions and its activities. Secondly, the composition of the Observatory, which is made up of over thirty public and private institutions gathered in the Governing Board (www.catpaisatge.net/eng/observatori_ organigrama.php). The Observatory also has an Advisory Council made up of several economic, business and social groups, as well as academics involved in the subject. This composition allows for a dynamic dialogue between members of the Governing and Advisory Councils, with voices coming in from different places and often with opposing interests. Finally, the Observatory lies halfway between civil society and the administration. This is interesting insofar as it can advise the administration on drawing up landscape policies for the territory, while at the same time communicating concerns felt by society.</p>
<p>We are still very far from some European countries such as France, the Netherlands or United Kingdom, whose population is more landscape-aware and whose laws are years ahead from ours, but it is undeniable that with the Landscape Act passing and implementation and with the creation of the Landscape Observatory, Catalonia has taken a great step forward.</p>
<p>Some experiences of the Landscape Observatory on participation and co-operation in implementing the ELC</p>
<p>Since the approval of the Landscape Act, landscape policies in Catalonia have accumulated a growing body of experience, though they still have many challenges lined up on the table. Below some experiences on local participation and co-operation in implementing the ELC carried out by the Landscape Observatory are shown. For more details, please check the Observatory’s website (www.catpaisatge.net/eng/activitat.php). Taking into account that the aim of this publication was to open up a debate on the implementation of the ELC, the experiences on local participation and co-operation have been grouped according to the main European Landscape Convention commitments, which are listed in image 2.</p>
<p>The first two commitments (Division of responsibilities and Recognition of landscapes in law) have already been introduced in the first part of this paper.57</p>
<p>Image 2. Participation and co-operation in implementing the ELC in Catalonia. Contribution of the Landscape Observatory to the</p>
<p>ELC commitments.</p>
<p>Image 3. Landscape Catalogues of Catalonia.58</p>
<p>Identification, assessment, and definition of landscape quality objectives</p>
<p>One of the main commitments of the ELC, and indeed the basis for any landscape policy, is learning more about landscapes, about all landscapes. Landscape catalogues (www.catpaisatge.net/eng/cataleg.php) are the tool used for this purpose in Catalonia. Landscape catalogues are used for introducing landscape objectives into spatial planning in Catalonia, as well as into sectorial policies, with the co-operation and participation of all the social agents active in the area.</p>
<p type="listitem">Certain aspects of the catalogues have to be emphasised:</p>
<p type="listitem">The Observatory is preparing seven landscape catalogues with the objective of introducing landscape quality objectives into the seven Territorial Zoning Plans that the Government is also preparing.</p>
<p type="listitem">One of the first main outcomes of the landscape catalogues is the identification of landscapes units (or landscapes), or areas that share the same landscape character. These landscapes are important because  they constitute the basic territorial units to which specific landscape policies are applied. These units are  demonstrably the main point of encounter for public debate on lived and perceived landscapes (http://www. catpaisatge.net/eng/cataleg_mapa.php).</p>
<p type="listitem">The Landscape Catalogues also study the evolution of  historic landscapes.</p>
<p type="listitem">They also identify patent and latent values (aesthetic,  ecological, historic, cultural,  symbolic) attributed to  landscapes by social agents  and the public. Public  consultation has greatly  contributed to identifying  these values.</p>
<p type="listitem">The landscape catalogues study the dynamics of the  landscape, as well as the  natural and socio-economic  factors intervening  in its evolution and  transformation.</p>
<p type="listitem">They also identify, helped by the public consultation,  principal routes and areas  from which landscape can  be observed.</p>
<p type="listitem">Public consultation is a basic aspect of the  landscape catalogues. This  is particularly true regarding assessment and perception of the landscape by individuals and stakeholders  (especially in its intangible aspects, e.g. the sense of place, or the sensations and emotions caused by  a landscape). Various instruments were used during the whole process of preparation, such as in-depth  interviews with the principal actors in the landscape, consultation with experts (e.g. opinions on maps, etc.),  work sessions with local people from the area, Landscape Observatory on-line consultations, yielding over  5.000 opinions, or opinion polls, among others.</p>
<p>Image 4. Map of the landscapes of Catalonia.59</p>
<p>Besides contributing to knowledge of landscapes, the landscape catalogues define landscape quality objectives, obtained from expert analyses and public participation. As their first point of reference, landscape quality objectives are defined for the whole of Catalonia (http://www.catpaisatge.net/eng/objectius.php). On a second level, objectives are defined for the territorial ambit of each landscape catalogue. In an ultimate degree, objectives are defined for each landscape unit. All these quality objectives give rise to a whole heap of criteria and actions which must contribute to achieving them. Criteria and actions are aimed not only at protecting landscapes, but also at managing and planning.</p>
<p>The landscape catalogues, together with public participation, are thus the main tool for getting to know the landscapes of the towns and cities of Catalonia. Complementing the landscape catalogues, the Observatory has been working on PaHisCat, a project based on the evolution of historic landscapes, carried out in cooperation with the Catalan Government and the University of Lleida. The project has been applied to four of the 135 landscapes of Catalonia. The PaHisCat project has great potential as a guideline for cultural, urbanism and heritage policies, as well as for use in education.</p>
<p>Image 5. The publication Landscape and Public Participation describes and evaluates the tools that have been used in Landscape</p>
<p>Catalogue, establishing key elements that must be taken into account when carrying out a participatory process of this kind (www.catpaisatge.net/eng/documentacio_doc_1.php)60</p>
<p>Image 6. Map of the Historic character of the landscape Horta de Pinyana61</p>
<p>Integration of landscape into policies</p>
<p type="listitem">One of the main challenges of the ELC is the integration of landscape into policies. This challenge probably  requires the greatest amount of co-ordination among the different sectors involved. I will now outline four  experiences taking place in Catalonia at a local level:</p>
<p type="listitem">Once the landscape catalogues are approved by the Minister of Land and Sustainability, the Government uses landscape quality objectives to lay down compulsory landscape directives for spatial planning  (www.catpaisatge.net/eng/directrius.php), for the seven territorial zoning plans which it prepares. This in  turn fosters permanent contact between the Landscape Observatory, the Catalan Government and the  municipalities affected. The translation of the landscape quality objectives into landscape directives already  exists but it is, at the same time, one of the principal challenges.</p>
<p type="listitem">The Observatory collaborates with and provides support for other ministries, town councils and other local authorities, by using information from the landscape catalogues, e.g. for tourism and cultural policies, spatial  planning policies, or for creating networks of viewing points, among others.</p>
<p type="listitem">The Observatory collaborates with the Government in laying down guidelines for integrating different types of actions and projects into landscape, after consensus with the main economic sectors involved in specific  areas. Examples include guidelines for the integration of industrial estates and agricultural buildings.</p>
<p type="listitem">Economic policies are of major importance in today’s recession, and landscape is a positive resource for economic activity, as long as it does not end up becoming a sellable commodity in detriment to its  natural, social and cultural values. The Observatory has undertaken a series of initiatives in this direction:  the collaboration with the insurance organization RACC or the farmer trade union Unió de Pagesos;  establishing links with the employers’ organisation Foment del Treball to discuss how landscape protection,  management and planning can contribute to job creation; signing an agreement with an employers’  association EURAM that is attempting to include landscape value in their respective economic activities;  or creating synergies with major wine and grape producing sectors in Catalonia, with the conviction that  landscape quality will benefit this activity. The last consideration of this part is for Landscape Charters (www.catpaisatge.net/eng/cartes.php). These are proving to be a very powerful tool for use at a local level, in certain circumstances. Landscape charters may  be used by local authorities (district councils, municipalities and communities) and/or by associations wishing  to draw up agreements between agents in a certain area (administrations, social and economic agents, etc.) in  order to promote actions and strategies for landscape assessment and improvement. It is important to point out  that the landscape charters require strong leadership, a clear consensual road map, a high level of commitment  from all parties involved, and perseverance in carrying out the tasks. In the absence of these four factors, the  landscape charter is doomed to failure.</p>
<p>Awareness-raising</p>
<p type="listitem">In Catalonia, landscape is causing increasing public concern. However, it is essential to raise the general low  level of landscape awareness. All the above-mentioned initiatives contribute to raise awareness, as do the  following initiatives, which are based on institutional and organisational participation and co-operation:</p>
<p type="listitem">Periodic collaborations with TV3 (the main Catalan public television channel) with different types of programmes to help raise awareness of the 135 landscapes in Catalonia.</p>
<p type="listitem">Collaboration with <span type="quote" xml:lang="nno">“Descobrir Catalonia”</span> (a travel and leisure magazine), with a monthly article on one of the 135 landscapes in Catalonia (http://www.catpaisatge.net/eng/paisatgemes.php). The Observatory  collaborates with other regional and local cultural and leisure magazines.</p>
<p type="listitem">Preparation of seminars, courses and conferences in order to contribute to reflection, training and social sensitisation with respect to the landscape (see also <span type="quote">“Mutual assistance and information exchange”</span>).</p>
<p type="listitem">Prepare publications financed by institutions, foundations and private enterprise (www.catpaisatge.net/eng/publicacions_coleccions.php).62</p>
<p type="listitem">The Landscape Observatory of Catalonia website, with newsletters, published in four languages, containing information submitted from external sources (www.catpaisatge.net).</p>
<p type="listitem">Recent communication and social interaction platforms through Twitter (http://twitter.com/catpaisatge_en) and Facebook (www.facebook.com/catpaisatgeEN), in Catalan, Spanish and English.</p>
<p>Before going on the next points, it is necessary to introduce the on-line project Wikipedra, that is the result of public collaboration. Wikipedra (http://wikipedra.catpaisatge.net/) is an interactive 2.0 version of a Geographical Information System to introduce, visualise and consult data regarding dry stone huts and shelters in Catalonia. This online application will enable, on the one hand, carrying out intuitive and interesting consultations (with maps, photos, files and searches) and, on the other, it will alow people to introduce and modify data regarding dry-stone constructions in Catalonia. The objective is to gather and update data regarding as many as possible dry-stone constructions. In its six months of existence, Wikipedra has made an inventory of more than 5.000 dry stone huts and shelters all over Catalonia. In this project the Observatory is merely an umbrella organisation for promoting</p>
<p>Image 7. The collection <span type="quote" xml:lang="fra">“Plecs de Paisatge”</span>, with two series (‘Reflections’ and ‘Tools’), includes articles, studies, workshops, conferences which consider a particular aspect or problem related to the landscape, regulations, instruments and methods for the protection, management and planning of landscape.63and developing the Wikipedra database. The information comes in from members of the public and associations, for use in landscape policies.</p>
<p>Education</p>
<p>The main education initiative of the Observatory is the production of teaching materials on landscape from an integrated perspective entitled <span type="quote">“City, territory and landscape”</span>, designed for the compulsory secondary education. The project includes an educational website on landscape (www. catpaisatge.net/educacio). Over 450.000 Catalan secondary school pupils aged 12-16 years have this material in their school from 2009.</p>
<p>This project works in coordination with the Ministry of Education and the Ministry of</p>
<p>Territory and Sustainability of the Catalan Government, and the Landscape Observatory. It is a shining example of the transversal collaboration that is so hard to achieve. The Ministry of Education’s contribution is fundamental, not only for guaranteeing the educational goals of the project, but also for introducing it into all schools in Catalonia. On the other hand, it is worth mentioning the fact that dialogue with publishing houses has resulted in the landscape map of Catalonia being included in some Geography textbooks for use in secondary schools.</p>
<p>Mutual assistance and information exchange</p>
<p>The chapter cannot be finished without pointing out the international co-operation within the Observatory. Co-operation with other European regions and states strengthens not only our own landscape policies in Catalonia but also the ELC. Many examples of assistance and information exchange at international and European levels and transborder co-operation (see next section) are being implemented.</p>
<p type="listitem">In the field of mutual assistance and information exchange, the Landscape Observatory of Catalonia has been active in the following ways:</p>
<p type="listitem">Participating in European and international conferences and seminars; organizing conferences with  guest participants from other countries; or co-organizing conferences with other European institutions  (www.catpaisatge.net/eng/jornades.php).</p>
<p type="listitem">Attending the Irish Heritage Council’s <span type="quote">“Landscape Character Assessment”</span> course on a twice-yearly  basis, since 2009.</p>
<p type="listitem">Meetings to exchange experiences with the governments of other regions in Spain and some European  countries (Ireland, Italy, Netherlands).</p>
<p>Participating in the panel of experts on the implementation of the European Landscape Convention Information System (ELCIS), promoted by the Council of Europe.</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nno">Image 8. Wikipedra’s portal.64</p>
<p type="listitem">At an international level, collaborating with the Argentinean Landscape Network (Red Argentina del  Paisaje) in setting up landscape observatories in various provinces of Argentina. In like manner, the  Observatory also collaborates with similar institutions in Brazil, Uruguay and Costa Rica. It is important  to point out that the ELC is the main point of reference for Latin American landscape initiatives, which  of course says a lot about the Convention.</p>
<p>Participating in the European Network of Local and Regional Authorities for the Implementation of the European Landscape Convention (RECEP-ENELC), which provides good opportunities for exchanging information, experiences and university research on ELC implementation.</p>
<p>Image 9. Materials and website of <span type="quote">“City, territory, landscape”</span>65</p>
<p>Transborder co-operation</p>
<p>In 2009, the Observatory collaborates with the French Ministry of Ecology, Energy, Sustainable Development and Land Planning in the organization of the 5th Transborder Workshop, held in Olot (Catalonia), aimed at exchanging points of view and working methodologies comparing French landscape atlases and Catalan landscape catalogues, with the participation of experts from different European countries. The first four editions of the workshop, promoted by the French Ministry, were held in countries or regions sharing borders with France (Wallonia, Spain, Italy and England).</p>
<p>On the other hand, the translation into English and French (the two official Council of Europe languages) of the</p>
<p>Observatory’s website, newsletters, and other information disseminated, helps to share the Catalan experience with the rest of Europe and the world and fosters the participation and co-operation.</p>
<p>Image 20. English version of the Observatory’s website and the <span type="quote" xml:lang="nno">“Landscap-e”</span> newsletter66</p>
<p>Conclusion</p>
<p>Landscape management in Catalonia starts out from an integrated vision of the whole. This vision includes regulations, agendas and policies; the actors and their respective networks; the public, and, finally, institutions and technicians that are committed to the cause. All these elements make for good co-operation experiences. But the challenges faced are many and great: encouraging a climate of dialogue between governments, in order to overcome the fragmentation of the public administration structure; strengthening the dialogue between civil society and the different administrations; fostering co-operation between the public and private spheres, while exploring alternative channels for landscape management and planning, and means of financing them; finding imaginative ways of surmounting the scarcity of economic resources destined for co-operation or solving the convoluted question of governance which is familiar to us all (who does what and at what level regarding landscape?). The Landscape Observatory of Catalonia aspires to continue playing a major role in achieving these important goals. These are collective challenges with no finishing line.67</p>
<p><em type="bold">LaNdScaPE aNd hUMaN hEaLTh </em>- </p>
<p><em type="bold">Proceedings of the conference: </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Implementation of the European </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Landscape convention in the North calotte area Municipalities </em></p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Eeva Karjalainen </em></p>
<p>The effect of nature on human health can be an integral part of the implementation of landscape convention. This article aims at highlighting how landscape surrounding us affects our health and well-being. In the European Landscape Convention, the term landscape is defined in the following way: <span type="quote">“Landscape means an area, as perceived by people, whose character is the result of the action and interaction of natural and/or human factors”</span>. This article concentrates on the perceived natural landscape, i.e. the word <span type="quote">“nature”</span> is used as a synonym to landscape. Word <span type="quote">“forest”</span> is used when a specific study concerns forest environment.</p>
<p>It is not self-evident that nature is good for us. For example in the 1800s in Finland, people often perceived forests as frightening and oppressing, e.g. because of beasts, and the villages were practically treeless. On the other hand, people respected nature and the Romantic Movement idealised wild nature. Nature has been used in helping curing diseases for centuries. In Europe, there have been spas from the 1600s. The closeness of nature was meant to be part of the healing effect of the spa. Later on sanatoria curing tuberculosis were situated in nature to provide not only isolation from other people but also fresh air, sunlight and beautiful views to nature to facilitate the recovery (Hartig et al. 2011). In Japan, people are practicing Shinrin-yoku <span type="quote">“forest bathing”</span> which is presumed to be good for health. It is simply sitting in nature, and walking slowly and breathing air.</p>
<p>Restorative effects of nature</p>
<p>Nowadays, we have scientific evidence that seeing and visiting nature may help both in curing diseases and in preventing diseases although the evidence is still limited. Nature seems to support coping with especially those diseases that are mediated by stress, such as depression, burn-out and cardiovascular diseases. Based on current knowledge, restoration from stress seems to be the central mechanism in the healing effects of nature. In other words, nature may have special qualities and capacities that facilitate the restoration and regulation of stress.</p>
<p>Studies have shown that after stressful or attention demanding situation people usually recover faster and more efficiently in natural environments than in urban settings. A typical example of such research is a study in which people at first watched a video of work accidents. After that, people were shown alternatively videos of natural setting, urban traffic or pedestrian mall. Those who saw the nature videos recovered both physiologically and psychologically faster than those seeing the urban setting did (Ulrich et al. 1991). Many other studies also report that compared to urban environments, natural environments produce positive changes in human physiology after stressful or attention-demanding situations. These studies show for example lower levels of blood pressure, heart rate, skin conductivity and muscle tension in natural environments than in urban settings. Natural settings also improve human mood states, concentration and performance better than urban settings (e.g. Hartig et al. 2003, Laumann et al. 2003, Ulrich 1981). If stress or mental fatigue is substantial, the positive effect of nature is emphasized.</p>
<p>We have two theoretical explanations why nature restores us, both of which are based on evolutionary assumptions. The psychoevolutionary theory (Ulrich 1983, Ulrich et al. 1991) emphasizes recovery from stress. It states that people are still adapted to natural environment. According to this theory, humans have biologically 68prepared readiness for having restorative responses to certain kinds of nature settings, but do not have this for artificial and built environments. The attention restoration theory (Kaplan and Kaplan 1989) states that our concentration and attention gets fatigued when we have to concentrate on specific tasks or things for a long time. It emphasizes the recovery of the capacity to focus attention. The attention can restore better in nature because nature does not require concentration on specific tasks.</p>
<p>There are also other possible explanations for the positive outcomes of nature besides the restoration from stress and attentional fatigue. Forest and trees reduce air pollutants and noise, which in turn affects health positively. Physical activity and social contacts are known to be good for us. Attractive nature might stimulate more physical activity. There are also some indications that nearby nature in the cities may facilitate social contacts, social cohesion and social capital. Therefore, both increased physical activity and social contacts can be mediating variables between the nearby nature and health although we do not yet have clear evidence about that (de Vries et al. 2011).</p>
<p>Examples of studies</p>
<p>Roger Ulrich (1984) published a landmark study in Science showing how nature can facilitate the recovery from illnesses or reduction of symptoms. In this study, patients who had gone through gall bladder surgery were divided into two groups. One group was located in rooms from which they saw a brick wall. The other group had window view on trees. Those seeing the trees from the window needed fewer painkillers, had shorter hospital stays and had fewer complaints than those who saw only the brick wall.</p>
<p>Other studies show that nature can help children having AD/HD symptoms, i.e. disturbance in attention, difficulties to concentrate and impulsiveness. These studies show that children who performed different activities in green outdoor environments had fewer symptoms compared to those children who played indoors or in nongreen outdoors. They were better able to concentrate complete tasks and follow directions (Faber Taylor et al. 2001, Kuo &amp; Faber Taylor 2004).</p>
<p>In urban areas, closeness of green spaces may improve health and increase life expectancy. For example, a Dutch study showed that prevalence rate of diseases is lower in neighborhoods that have more green space in 1 km radius than those having less green areas. This was true especially concerning anxiety disorder and depression (Maas et al. 2006, 2009). Another Dutch study showed that people having higher amount of green space in a 3 km radius were less affected by stressful life events than those having less green areas (van den Berg et al. 2010). The stressful effect could be for example death of close people, break-off of close relationship, financial crises or being fired. Health status was measured by number of health complaints and perceived general health.</p>
<p>In Japan, the relationship between forests and human health has been studied a lot in recent years. Japanese have for example studied the relation between human immune system and forest visits (Li et al. 2007, 2008). Immune system helps us in defending against bacteria, viruses and tumors. Human immune function is known to be weakened by stress. Japanese experiments show that spending time in forest can strengthen the human immune system compared to city environment. In these experiments, people spent either one or three days in a forest, and in a city. Amount and activity of natural killer cells increased in forests but not in the city. The effect could be detected after 7 days, in some cases even after 30 days.</p>
<p>A Finnish survey having 1273 respondents from the cities of Helsinki and Tampere showed that the positive feelings of urban citizens increased when they used urban green areas more than 5 hours per month or visited nature outside the city 2-3 times per month (Tyrväinen et al. 2007).</p>
<p>What kinds of environments may promote our health?</p>
<p>When implementing the landscape convention, it would be essential to know what kind of nature promotes our health. Unfortunately, we have very little knowledge about that so far. The psychoevolutionary theory states that health-promoting environment needs to have moderate and ordered complexity (variability, many different 69things, but not too many), moderate depth (visibility), a focal point (something that draws our attention) and natural contents (Hartig et al. 2011). Attention restoration theory says that environment that helps in the recovery of attention has four qualities. It provides extent, i.e. it should be large enough so that person can feel being inside it. Extent does not mean the physical size, and for example own garden can provide extent. Restorative environment is fascinating and attractive and does not require directed attention. It is suitable for the person in concern, so that the person can do there what she/he desires. Restorative environment also facilitates the sense of being away from the everyday environment (Kaplan and Kaplan 1989).</p>
<p>We have very little empirical research about the types of nature or elements of nature that would be the most beneficial for our health. It is obvious that some natural environments promote the restoration better than others do. It seems that trees and water elements are important. Size of the area, type of nature and level of management might also be essential. A Finnish study showed that natural-like environments were perceived as more restorative that urban parks (Tyrväinen et al. 2007). On the other hand, a Swiss study showed that tended forest had more positive influence on the affective well-being than wild forest (Martens et al. 2010). It is often stated that those natural environments that a person prefers would also be the best for his health, but this relationship is not yet established.</p>
<p>Possible practical implications for rehabilitation and health promotion</p>
<p>There are many possibilities to use nature in health care, rehabilitation of diseases, prevention of diseases and health promotion. Nature can be used as a part of rehabilitation programmes and individual therapy. Rehabilitation programmes, targeted for example to people suffering from depression, burnout, cardiovascular diseases or alcoholism, can include different types of activities performed in nature, such as fishing, tree climbing, inventories of cultural sites and construction of fireplaces. This type of programmes have been implemented for example in Sweden and Norway.</p>
<p>In green care farms, the entrepreneurs provide nature activities for different kind of target groups needing rehabilitation. Green care farms have been established in many European countries. In addition, therapeutic gardens and horticulture therapy is already used in some countries, at least Sweden and Denmark.</p>
<p>Natural environment could also be used in hospitals, clinics and nursing homes to facilitate recovery. Clinics and nursing homes could be located at beautiful places surrounded by nature. They could have window views to green environments, and they could include gardens or green rooms. Nature elements could be used in patient rooms as well as waiting rooms. Healing gardens at hospitals and clinics are already used to some extent. In addition, the medical doctors could adopt a practice in which they would prescribe not only medicine but also nature exposure as part of the treatment. However, nature on prescription is not yet commonly used.</p>
<p>When considering nature in health promotion, it is very important to preserve attractive nature close to homes so that people have easy access to nature. There are also specific programmes and health trails that aim at encouraging and teaching people to use forests for relaxation and physical activity. Finland’s first well-beingthemed forest trail, <span type="quote">”power trail”</span>, was opened in 2010. It is funded by public funds, but it is next to Ikaalinen spa that can use it as part of its services. It is a forest trail that has psychological signposts that guide people to do exercises that can help them enhancing the stress-reducing experience. These signposts aim to induce relaxation, improve mood, induce cognitive reflection and attentional restoration. A study was conducted among the users of the trail (167 respondents). 69% of the respondents experienced that their general well-being was better after walking the trail. However, there was no improvement in attention and concentration. The longer trail (6,6 km) had stronger influence than the shorter (4.4 km) (Vattulainen et al. 2011). However, it is difficult to know if people felt better after walking the trail because of exercise, nature, company, freetime or because of combination of these.</p>
<p>In addition, specific <span type="quote">“therapy forests”</span> could be promoted. In therapy forests, forest would be managed to produce maximum health benefits and other supporting facilities could be provided. For example in Japan and South Korea, there are special forests that are designated as therapy forests. In Japan, these forests have been 70shown by research to have relaxing effects. Some companies already use these forests for their employees’ health care.</p>
<p>Furthermore, workplace health promotion programmes could include nature activities. Healing effects of nature could also be utilized in urban planning and design of buildings. For example, there could be nature spots at stressful places such as airports, city centers and working places.</p>
<p>Conclusions</p>
<p>The research field studying relationships between nature and human health is young and the amount of studies is still limited. Research methodologies are not always convincing for medical researchers and health care professionals. We still need more research and rigorous methodology to have enough bases to set up the practical implications for health care and for environmental management.</p>
<p>We must bear in mind, that it is not only nature that can restore us. According to a Dutch study well-designed and attractive urban setting can be restorative (Karmanov and Hamel 2008). It might be that any activity that a person considers relaxing, such as listening music or meditating, might have as strong or even stronger restorative influences than nature. It might also be that the places and activities that a person enjoys produce the strongest restorative effects. In this sense there probably are individual differences. It is evident that not all people do benefit from nature exposure to the same extent. Some urban people might find forests uncomfortable and alien places and the effect of forest visit might be negative on their well-being (see e.g. Milligan and Bingley 2007).</p>
<p>There are still many unanswered questions. The research on the effect of nature on human health has so far concentrated on urban nature and urban populations. We know very little about the effect of nature on rural populations. It might be that the positive effect is much stronger on people living in large cities than in rural population that are in contact with nature more frequently. We do not know much about the cumulative effects of nature visits or seeing nature. We do not know how often people should be in nature and how long time they should spend there in order to receive the stress-reducing and other healing effects, and which activities they should perform.</p>
<p>However, already based on the current knowledge it seems evident that positive links between nature and human health exist. This provides many possibilities to improve human health and save health care costs. One very important implication is to maintain attractive nearby nature so that people can have everyday contact with it. The effect of nature on human health and well-being should be paid attention to when implementing the landscape convention. It should be part of assessing the landscapes and defining quality objectives. 71</p>
<p>References de Vries, S. Classen, T., Eigenheer-Hug, S.M., Korpela, K., Maas, J., Mitchell. R. &amp; Schanz P. 2011. Contributions of natural environments to physical activity: theory and evidence base. In: Nilsson, K., Sangster, M., Gallis, C., Hartig, T., de</p>
<p>Vries, S., Seeland, K. &amp; Schipperijn, J. (eds.). 2011. Forests, Trees and Human Health. 1st Edition. 452 p. Springer. Pp. 205-243.</p>
<p>Faber Taylor, A., Kuo, F.E., &amp; Sullivan, W.C. 2001. Coping with ADD: The surprising connection to green play settings.</p>
<p>Environment and Behavior, 33(1), 54-77.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hartig, T., Berg, A.E., Hagerhall, C.M., Tomalak, M., Bauer, N., Hansmann, R., Ojala, A., Syngollitou, E., Carrus, G.,</p>
<p>Herzele, A., Bell, S., Podesta, M.T.C., &amp; Waaseth, G. 2011. Health benefits of nature experience: Psychological, social and cultural processes. In: Nilsson, K., Sangster, M., Gallis, C., Hartig, T., de Vries, S., Seeland, K. &amp; Schipperijn, J. (eds.). 2011. Forests, Trees and Human Health. 1st Edition. 452 p. Springer. Pp. 127-168.</p>
<p>Hartig, T., Evans, G.W., Jamner, L.D., Davis, D.S. &amp; Gärling, T. 2003. Tracking restoration in natural and urban field settings. Journal of Environmental Psychology 23: 109-123.</p>
<p>Kaplan, R. &amp; Kaplan, S. 1989. The experience of nature. A psychological perspective. Cambridge University Press. 339 p. Karmanov, D. &amp; Hamel, R. 2008. Assessing the restorative potential of contemporary urban environment(s): beyond the nature versus urban dichotomy. Landscape and Urban Planning 86 (2008): 115-125.</p>
<p>Kuo, F.E. &amp; Faber Taylor, A. 2004. A potential natural treatment for Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder: Evidence from a national study. American Journal of Public Health, 94(9), 1580-1586.</p>
<p>Laumann, K., Gärling, T. &amp; Stormark, K.M. 2003. Selective attention and heart rate responses to natural and urban environments. Journal of Environmental Psychology 23: 125-134.</p>
<p>Li, Q, Morimoto, K., Nakadai, A., Inagaki, H., Katsumata, M., Shimizu, T., Hirata, Y. et. al. 2007. Forest bathing enhances human Natural killer activity and expression of anti-cancer proteins. International Journal of Immunopathology and</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Pharmacology, vol. 20 no. 2 (S2)3-8.</p>
<p>Li Q, Morimoto K, Kobayashi M, Inagaki H, Katsumata M, Hirata Y, et al. 2008. Visiting a forest, but not a city, increases human natural killer activity and expression of anti-cancer proteins. Int JImmunopathol Pharmacol. 2008;21:117–28.</p>
<p>Martens, D., Gutscher, H. &amp; Bauer, N. 2010. Walking in <span type="quote">“wild”</span> and <span type="quote" xml:lang="dan">“tended”</span> urban forests: the impact on psychological well-being. Journal of Environmental Psychology 31(2011): 36-44.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Tyrväinen, L., Silvennoinen, H., Korpela, K. &amp; Ylen, M. 2007. Luonnon merkitys kaupunkilaisille ja vaikutus psyykkiseen hyvinvointiin. Metlan työraportteja 52: 57–77.</p>
<p>Ulrich, R.S. 1981. Natural versus urban scenes. Some Psychophysiological Effects. Environment and Behavior. Vol 13, No 5: 523-556.</p>
<p>Ulrich, R.S. 1983. Aesthetic and affective response to natural environment. In: Altman, I. &amp; Wohlwill, J.F. (eds.). Behavior and the Natural Environment. Vol 6. Plenum Press. p. 85–125.</p>
<p>Ulrich, R.S. 1984. View through a window may influence recovery from surgery. Science 224:420-421. Ulrich, R.S., Simons, R.F., Losito, B.D., Fiorito, E., Miles, M.A. &amp; Zelson, M. 1991. Sress recovery during exposure to natural and urban environments. Journal of Environmental Psychology 11:201-230.van den Berg, A.E., Maas, J., Verheij, R.A.. &amp; Groenewegen, P.P. 2010. Green space as a buffer between stressful life events and health. Social Science &amp; Medicine 70(2010): 1203-1210-</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Vattulainen, K., Sarjala, T., Savonen, E.M. &amp; Korpela, K. 2011. Elpymiskokemuksia metsästä, Voimapolun käyttäjäkysely.</p>
<p>Metlan työraportteja / Working Papers of the Finnish Forest Research Institute 204. 39 s. Saatavissa: http://www.metla.fi/julkaisut/workingpapers/2011/mwp204.htm.72</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">THE ARCTIC LANDSCAPE AS A LIVING</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">EUROPEAN HERITAGE</p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">Bas Pedroli </em></p>
<p>Landscape heritage, how did it originate?</p>
<p>When I visit one of my favourite landscapes in Holland in late autumn I enjoy the wide view over green meadows separated by ditches reflecting the wind-blown clouds in the sky. Many geese are grazing. In the distance a lighthouse and a red-roofed white house accentuate a dike (Image 1). This landscape is the heritage of many centuries of human activities: trading, peat digging, draining, diking, pasturing and finally bird conservation. In the meantime the sea has been pushed back and a freshwater lake and polders have replaced it. Fishermen have left the area long ago, and recently also the farmer left. Sheep are grazing here to keep the meadows short for the wintering geese. As I turn around, the skyline of Amsterdam is surprisingly nearby.</p>
<p>The European landscape consists of a multitude of such typical landscapes, brought about by the commitment of hunter-gatherers, nomads, farmers’ communities, monks and landlords. Landscapes have never been static, but reflected the functions they provided to the communities that lived in them (Renes, 2011). Nowadays, landscapes rather reflect the global exchange of information and market mechanisms. Instead of local space, global flow defines the boundary conditions for landscape development (Primdahl and Swaffield, 2010). But landscape in the end of the day remains a social environment with its own biography, which is an essential European asset (Farina and Napoletano, 2010). This applies for the Sámi landscapes in Lapland as much as for the polders around Amsterdam, albeit in a different way (Jones and Olwig, 2008).</p>
<p>In this paper I reflect on two basically different ways in the development of human relationship to nature and landscape as reflected in places of worship and sacred spaces. This will bring me to the meaning of the arctic landscape for Europe.</p>
<p>Places of the European culture</p>
<p>Although not strictly European, the first large buildings of the stream of civilisation that leads towards Central and Western European culture are the pyramids in Egypt. The astonishingly heavy and solid forms of an austere geometry seem to demonstrate a spiritual differentiation of the human world from the world of the gods, the world</p>
<p>Image 1. Polder IJdoorn near Amsterdam. Photo: Bas Pedroli.73of nature. In other words, fundamental grounding in the earth appears as a basic need of the human mind in a step towards self-consciousness.</p>
<p>In a later phase, the Hellenic culture built open temples for their gods, who still represented the basic powers of nature: Demeter the earth, Poseidon of the sea, Aphrodite of plants and animals, etc. (Image 2). In the amphitheatres of the early Greeks, classical dramas represented the adventures of gods and half-gods, against a stage of the natural landscape. The Roman tradition closed the stage with wings, and slaves and wild animals played the roles in their theatres, separated from nature outside.</p>
<p>In the Middle Ages Christianity built</p>
<p>Romanesque churches, with thick walls and small windows (Image 3). Contemplation took place in the halflight inside. Still, nature was present in the form of animals and gnomes, often decorating the pillars (Image 3). In late Middle Ages and Renaissance, ‘pagan’ creatures were banned from the churches and in the Gothic cathedrals light was welcomed in the church as a heavenly symbol of god (Image 3) (Duby, 1976). Notwithstanding the short-lived impulse of Saint Francis of Assisi in the 13th century to consider the sun, plants and animals as brothers, nature and labour were basically kept outside the churches, culture and exegesis inside (Nolthenius, 1951).</p>
<p>This development continues until present in the modern places of worship, be it the university auditoria that have largely taken over the function of the church, where explanations of the secrets of being can be obtained, or the virtual place to be, the worldwide web. Interestingly, the excursion through the northern taiga around Inari in Finnish Lapland, which was part of the programme of the seminar in September 2011, brought us to an important exponent of local cultural heritage, the Pielpajärvi church (Image 3), originally from the 17th century. It must have been the first permanent construction ever seen in this area, when it was built by monks Christianising the northernmost regions of Europe.</p>
<p>Sacred space</p>
<p>There is another way European people have developed a relationship to the world surrounding them. Especially on the rims of the continent people lived who erected large stones in intriguing patterns all over Europe: Malta, Corsica, Portugal, Ireland, England, Netherlands, Sweden. After Christianity gradually spread over Europe,</p>
<p>Image 2. Hephaestus Temple, Acropolis, Athens. Photo: Bas Pedroli.74in some places they continued for long times to live with nature. In Ireland for example, instead of impressive churches simple crosses were placed in the landscape. The Celtic cross (of which the shape is much older than Christianity) includes a ring that may symbolise the sun or the moon. It appears to me that to the people living in the areas where such crosses were erected, the landscape was just a sacred space, where they could worship nature as a divine creation all around and at the same time be conscious of the significance of Christ’s sacrifice. Mythical stories and sagas describing the adventures of heroes in recognisable landscapes long kept alive in many Nordic areas, like the Edda epic in Iceland, the Saga of the dream of Olaf Åsteson in Norway and the</p>
<p>Image 3. Fonte Avellana monastery- oasis in Apennine nature, Rose window Laon cathedral -northern France, Medieval baptism font in Laon cathedral - northern France and Pielpajärvi wilderness church near Inari - Finnish Lapland. Photos: Bas Pedroli.75</p>
<p>Kalewala epic in Finland (Friberg et al., 1998). This confirms that also in northern Scandinavia the connection of people with nature was more self-evident than in Central Europe for long times, as demonstrated by the existence of many sacred localities (e.g. Ukonsaari Island, Image 4).</p>
<p>As a matter of fact, churches were not very suitable structures anyway for nomadic people like the Sámi.</p>
<p>As has been demonstrated by several authors (Bergman et al., 2008; Gaski, 2011; Häkli, 1999) and especially Ingold &amp; Kurttila (2000) and Roturier &amp; Roué (2009), the Sámi culture is fluid in the denotation of specific places in the landscape. In Sámi tradition, landscape is unlike the modern distant perception in western society (Buijs et al., 2006), a space where you should be involved in to be able to live in it, since <span type="quote">“… the work of memory, and hence people’s sense of continuity with their own past, was intimately tied to their experience of inhabiting particular locales”</span> (Ingold and Kurttila, 2000).</p>
<p>What can we learn from this?</p>
<p>The landscape concept symbolised by places of worship, has been at the basis of modern society, with all its achievements and drawbacks alike. In the end of the day it inevitably leads to detachment and loss of identity (Olwig, 2008; Pedroli et al., 2006; Stobbelaar and Pedroli, 2011). The landscape concept characterised by sacred space, on the other hand, gives a possibility to learn from landscape, to reconnect to our environment and to feel responsible for the actions we undertake. The below scheme summarises these two concepts.</p>
<p type="listitem">In publicity around the European Landscape Convention (Déjeant-Pons, 2004) sometimes the maxim <span type="quote">“landscape – mirror of our innermost selves”</span> is used. If we take that seriously, in many of our landscapes in  Western society we are confronted with distorted images of ourselves. That is certainly also a reason for the  following observations:</p>
<p type="listitem">there is a growing demand in Europe for quality of life based on a healthy and specific environment (Bloemers et al., eds., 2010),</p>
<p type="listitem">landscapes without people connected to them are no longer living landscapes (Priore, 2009),</p>
<p type="listitem">participation in landscape: a right and a responsibility (Jones and Stenseke, 2011),</p>
<p type="listitem">landscape identity is a challenge for modern society, for ourselves and for our children (Stobbelaar and</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Pedroli, 2011).</p>
<p>Landscape concept symbolised by</p>
<p><em type="italic">Places of worship </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Sacred space </em></p>
<p>Nature is out there</p>
<p>We are part of nature</p>
<p>Culture within our buildings and museums</p>
<p>Culture is where we are</p>
<p>Nature is waste land and we can / we must reclaim it</p>
<p>Nature is our homeland and we leave no traces</p>
<p>The ‘priest’ knows what is good for us</p>
<p>Nature teaches us what is good for us</p>
<p>Separation of culture and nature has allowed the development of our modern society</p>
<p>Relation between nature and culture is self-evident</p>
<p>Religion is gradually being replaced by science</p>
<p>Re-ligion is to re-connect, develop self-consciousness</p>
<p>It is increasingly impossible to know all consequences of our actions</p>
<p>Feel responsibility for the actions we undertake</p>
<p>This leads inevitably to detachment, and loss of identity Observing with all senses, taking for real what we perceive, brings a sense of belonging, of identity76</p>
<p>Place and space may have a different meaning for Sámi people than for most European people. And because the Sámi still live a landscape in which every place may be worth to be taken care of, depending on the season, the year, the climate, the abundance of wildlife and fish, and last but not least the snow conditions, we can learn from their connectedness with nature, their inner view instead of the detached consumer’s view of modern society. It can only be in a combination, a synergy of the mentioned two concepts of landscape that sustainable landscapes of the future can evolve.</p>
<p>Epilogue, connecting two worlds</p>
<p>But there are still another reasons why we should be careful with the arctic landscape. It hosts numerous breeding habitats for millions of migratory birds that migrate through Europe or winter in Europe (Alerstam and Christie, 1993). The geese that I observe in my favourite polder landscape from autumn to spring, migrate to northern Scandinavia and Russia for breeding. They bring springtime to Lapland, and return with young birds to more southern regions. Not only migratory birds, but also tourism now connects Lapland to the rest of Europe, which brings money, but at the same time disturbs the sensitive arctic ecosystems, not even counting the undue energy consumption it is causing.</p>
<p>In fact, Lapland is an integral part of Europe, and represents a living European heritage of a very special character. One of the challenges for the Sámi people is how to mobilise the sense of reality this requires from Europeans to feel responsible for the Sámi homeland as well. The European Landscape Convention could be of help here (Olwig, 2007).</p>
<p>Image 4. Ukonsaari sacred island (centre), Inari lake, Finnish Lapland</p>
<p>Photo: Bas Pedroli.77</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">References</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Alerstam, T., Christie, D.A., 1993. Bird migration. Cambridge Univ Pr. Bergman, I., Ostlund, L., Zackrisson, O., Liedgren, L., 2008. Varro Muorra: The Landscape Significance of Sami Sacred</p>
<p>Wooden Objects and Sacrificial Altars. Ethnohistory 55, 1.</p>
<p>Bloemers, T., Daniels, S., Fairclough, G., Pedroli, B., Stiles, R., eds., 2010. Landscape in a changing world. Bridging</p>
<p>Divides, Integrating Disciplines, Serving Society. Science Policy Briefing nr 41. ESF-COST, Strasbourg / Brussels, p. 16.</p>
<p>Buijs, A.E., Pedroli, B., Luginbühl, Y., 2006. From hiking through farmland to farming in a leisure landscape: changing social perceptions of the European landscape. Landscape Ecology 21, 375-389.</p>
<p>Déjeant-Pons, M., 2004. Council of Europe-The European Landscape Convention Entered into Force. Environmental Policy and Law 34, 79-83.</p>
<p>Duby, G., 1976. Le temps des cathédrales : l’art et la société (980–1420). Gallimard, Paris. Farina, A., Napoletano, B., 2010. Rethinking the landscape: new theoretical perspectives for a powerful agency.</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Biosemiotics 3, 177-187.</p>
<p>Friberg, E., Landström, B., Schoolfield, G.C., 1998. The Kalevala: epic of the Finnish people. Otava. Gaski, H., 2011. Song, Poetry and Images in Writing: Sami Literature. Nordlit 27, 33-54. Häkli, J., 1999. Cultures of demarcation: territory and national identity in Finland. Nested Identities. Nationalism, Territory and Scale, 123-149.</p>
<p>Ingold, T., Kurttila, T., 2000. Perceiving the environment in Finnish Lapland. Body &amp; Society 6, 183-196. Jones, M., Olwig, K., 2008. Nordic landscapes: Region and belonging on the northern edge of Europe. Univ Of Minnesota</p>
<p>Press.</p>
<p>Jones, M., Stenseke, M., 2011. The European Landscape Convention: Challenges of Participation. Springer Verlag. Nolthenius, H., 1951. In that Dawn: The Thirteenth Century in Italy. English translation from the original Dutch: Darton</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Longman and Todd, 1968, London.</p>
<p>Olwig, K.R., 2007. The practice of landscape ‘conventions’ and the just landscape: The case of the European Landscape</p>
<p>Convention. Landscape Research 32, 579-594.</p>
<p>Olwig, K.R., 2008. Has ‘geography’ always been modern? Choros, (non) representation, performance, and the landscape.</p>
<p>Environment and Planning A 40, 1843-1861.</p>
<p>Pedroli, B., Pinto-Correia, T., Cornish, P., 2006. Landscape–what’s in it? Trends in European landscape science and prioritythemes for concerted research. Landscape Ecology 21, 421-430.</p>
<p>Primdahl, J., Swaffield, S., 2010. Globalisation and agricultural landscapes: change patterns and policy trends in developed countries. Cambridge Univ Pr.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Priore, R., 2009. No People, No Landscape. La Convenzione europea del paesaggio: luci e ombre nel processo di attuazione in Italia. FrancoAngeli, Milano.</p>
<p>Renes, J., 2011. European landscapes: continuity and change, in: Roca, Z., Claval, P., Agnew, J. (Eds.), Landscapes, identities and development. Farnham, UK, Ashgate. Ashgate, Farnham (UK), pp. 117–136.</p>
<p>Roturier, S., Roué, M., 2009. Of forest, snow and lichen: Sami reindeer herders’ knowledge of winter pastures in northern</p>
<p>Sweden. Forest Ecology and Management 258, 1960-1967.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Stobbelaar, D.J., Pedroli, B., 2011. Perspectives on Landscape Identity: A Conceptual Challenge. Landscape Research 36, 321-339.78</p>
<p>PICTURESQUE NORTHERN VILLAGES - THE KAIRALA - LUIRO LANDSCAPE</p>
<p xml:lang="smj">MANAGEMENT AREA AS AN</p>
<p>EXAMPLE OF THE IMPLEMENTATION</p>
<p>OF THE EUROPEAN LANDSCAPE</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">CONVENTION AT A LOCAL LEVEL</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="bold">Merja Lipponen </em></p>
<p>The European Landscape Convention aims to promote landscape protection, management and planning, among others, and to increase awareness of the value, significance and change of landscapes. The Convention has been in effect in Finland since 2006. This article provides an example of how the ELC has been implemented at a local level in Finland, in two Eastern Lapland villages.</p>
<p>This article is mainly based on the publication Komiat kylät pohjoisen maisemassa –Kairalan ja Luiron maisemanhoitoalueen hoito- ja käyttösuunnitelma (Picturesque northern villages – The management and use plan for the Kairala and Luiro landscape management area) (Kokko et al. 2009). No further references are made to the above-mentioned publication later in the text.The villages of Kairala and Luiro are located in the municipality of Pelkosenniemi in Eastern Lapland, approximately 10 kilometres north of the main population centre. Kairala is located on both sides of the river Kitinen, and Luiro is located to the east along the Luirojoki that flows into the river Kitinen. The villages are typical Lapland riverside villages, where settlement is spread ribbon-like along the river. Unique features of these agricultural villages include the old northern-style log buildings and outbuildings that escaped destruction in the Lapland War in the 1940s. The cultural landscapes are surrounded by wide uninhabited string bogs, interspersed with forest patches. The fell range of Pyhä-Luosto and the Mairivaara fells to the west and Nivatunturi to the east create a spectacular backdrop for the village landscapes (Image 1). Both villages have indeed been declared as valuable landscape areas according to the report of the Ministry of the Environment; Kairala is classified as a nationally valuable and Luiro as a regionally valuable landscape area (Report of the Ministry of the Environment 1993, Decision in Principle of the Council of State 1995).</p>
<p>Image 1. View from Kairala; east of River Kitinen towards Pyhätunturi. Photo: Marjut Kokko.79</p>
<p>Kairala is also included in the nationally significant built cultural environments (National Board of Antiquities 2009).</p>
<p>Man has utilised the areas of Kairala and Luiro for several millennia. In the prehistoric era, the sources of livelihood were mainly connected to hunting, and the place of residence changed with the seasons and the movement of game animals. Although the human impact on the landscape was still minimal, relics from this era are still visible to the discerning eye, such as hut sites and hole traps. Artefacts also give us information about this era. A significant change in the landscape took place as the first people made a permanent settlement on the riverfront at the end of the 17th century. The old culture based on the nomadic way of life disappeared from the area as cultivation and villages developed. During the 18th century at the latest, the Forest Sámi living in the area either adopted the peasant culture or had to move further north. The settlers for their part adopted reindeer management from the Sámi people. (Kehusmaa &amp; Onnela 1995). As the people settled permanently in one place, hunting was no longer the primary livelihood, but just one of many options. The fertile riverside meadows provided the cattle with food and the nutritious lands and nearby bogs were cleared to form fields (Image 2).</p>
<p>Agriculture remained as the primary industry in the villages right up to the 1960s. The population level was also at its highest in this decade. With the structural change, the number of farms and the population of the villages have seen steady decline as young people and people of working age move elsewhere in search of jobs and education. Currently, there are still some cattle farms in the area of Kairala and Luiro. The majority of the working population are employed in the main population centre or in nearby municipalities, or they receive their livelihood from reindeer management or forestry. Even though the population of both villages has declined, some new permanent residents or summer residents have moved into the villages in recent years. Due to the ageing population and changes in agriculture, the previously open cultural landscapes have begun to disappear. Many fields have transformed into grassy areas and bushes full of willow and birch trees. The riverside meadows have become waterlogged and bushy as the dewatering, mowing and grazing culture has ended (Images 3 and 4).</p>
<p>Image 2. In 1960’s there were still wide fields surrounding the Kairala. Photo: Kairala Village Association collection.</p>
<p>Images 3 and 4. View of Kairala in 1990’s and year 2008. Photos: Kari Tallavaara and Marjut Kokko.80</p>
<p>The renovation need of the built heritage has forced the village inhabitants to come up with ways of maintaining their cultural environment and landscape.</p>
<p>Co-operation as a key role</p>
<p>According to section 32 of the Nature Conservation Act, a landscape conservation area can be established in order to preserve and manage a natural or cultural landscape of outstanding beauty, historical interest or other special value. The initiative to establish a landscape conservation area and draw up the required landscape management and use plan came from the Kairala Village Association in 2007 to the Lapland Regional Environment Centre (now the Centre for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment for Lapland). Luiro joined the management and use plan project later that year. The work was done as co-operation between the village associations, coordinated by the Lapland Regional Environment Centre, and it was funded by the Ministry of the Environment and the municipality of Pelkosenniemi. The aim of the management and use plan was to pin down the locations that were seen as important for conserving the cultural history, natural beauty and recreational resources of the villages. In addition to the cultural environment, the nearby forests were noted as an essential part of the management and use plan, as forestry has been a common source of livelihood in the area.</p>
<p>In the early stages of planning, every village resident received an announcement and an invitation to the start-up event of the project. In addition, the residents received a questionnaire on their views of the changes in the landscape and the required maintenance work. The residents were interviewed on the history of land use. Local village working groups were established in both villages. They collected data on the village history, livelihoods and land use. The working groups collected old photos and studied the locations of valuable nature points, old cultural historical locations and routes, such as winter roads and postal trails (Image 5). From this historical viewpoint, the field inventories were aimed to the most central cultural historical locations. The village residents also took part in the work in the field with the experts.</p>
<p>The remaining traditional biotopes and farming areas that are significant for their landscape or biodiversity were surveyed in the field. In addition, the important points of the village landscape, significant nature</p>
<p>Image 5. The regional limits of the landscape management and use plan were marked off together with local people. Photo: Anna Kurkela.81!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!( !(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(!(kjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkjkj kj05001 000m© Maanmittauslaitos lupanro 7/MML/08, SYKE</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Suunnittelualue Maiseman solmukohta Merkittävä luontokohde Kaunis näkymä Avattava näkymä Avoin alue LUMO-kohde Perinnebiotooppi Suo Lehtimetsä Sekametsä Havumetsäkj</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Merkittävä puu tai puuryhmä!(</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Uhanalaisen kasvilajin esiintymä</p>
<p>Image 6. The landscape analysis helped to map the most valuable sites in the village and the sites that required management the most. 82locations, beautiful scenes and views to be opened up were noted. The nearby forests were also inventoried and management recommendations were drawn up. An expert in architectural history also participated in the planning, and cultural heritage points and prehistoric and historic relics were listed. The co-operation of experts and village residents resulted in a landscape analysis, which was used to create maps showing the current status of the landscape (Image 6). The public was notified of the project at all stages, and the employees of the Environment Centre were active in field work, and also visited village fairs and events. Special evening events were also arranged to discuss renovations and forest and landscape management.</p>
<p>In the village of Kairala, the most central and valuable locations were the river Kitinen flowing through the village and the cultivated land and built village environment located alongside it. Even though the banks of old alluvial meadows of Kotiniemi and Yliniemi have become bushy, the farming areas and their buildings still form a varied and consistent landscape. In Luiro, the village road formed on an isthmus by the river acts as a node point for the landscape. The fields and old northern-style buildings and newer buildings on its banks form the most central part of the village landscape (Image 7).</p>
<p>The landscape management recommendations in the plan were always optional and created together with the village inhabitants. The plan also included possible funding options to cover the costs of management work. For the recommended maintenance of farming land, for example, funding can be received from special environmental support for agriculture.</p>
<p>From a plan to a landscape conservation area</p>
<p>The establishment of a landscape conservation area is legislated in Chapter 5, sections 32-36 of the Nature Conservation Act and in Chapter 4, sections 13-16 of the Nature Conservation Decree.</p>
<p>Once the management and use plan required by law was finished, on 17 May 2009 the village associations of Kairala and Luiro made representation to the municipal executive board of Pelkosenniemi to establish a landscape conservation area, which then proposed the issue to the Regional Environment Centre of Lapland and the Ministry of the Environment later that year. In summer 2009, the Environment Centre arranged a circulation for comment for the management and use plan and the draft resolution to the landowners, regional government officials, and other concerned parties.</p>
<p>After the circulation, the Environment Centre made a proposal to the Ministry of the Environment for the establishment of the Kairala-Luiro landscape conservation area. The Ministry of the Environment arranged a second-stage hearing, where the management and use plan, the draft resolution and the proposal of the Environment Centre were sent to ministries, other officials, and organisations. Then the Ministry of the Environment arranged a consultation with the Ministries of Agriculture and Forestry required by the Nature Conservation Decree on the establishment of a landscape conservation area. The decision on the establishment of Kairala-Luiro landscape conservation area was made on 20 April 2010 (Ministry of the Environment decision 2010). It was the third established landscape conservation area in Finland.</p>
<p>Establishing a landscape conservation area provides recommendations for preserving landscape values and it acts as a guide in creating the regional land use plan. It does not limit land use or the rights of the landowners.</p>
<p>Image 7. There are both old northern-style buildings and newer buildings along the paths of Luiro. Photo: Marjut Kokko.83</p>
<p>The landowners and inhabitants still play a central role in the landscape management of the villages. Both Kairala and Luiro have traditional and active village associations. Important types of activity include renovating and painting old buildings and arranging events that promote different traditions (Images 8 and 9). The municipality of Pelkosenniemi has also participated in village landscape management by steering employment to the villages to promote environmental protection and management, such as the renovation and management of the riverbanks and old meadow areas and the milieu of valuable buildings.</p>
<p>Volunteers and farmers have also cleared bushy meadows without external funding. The fragmented land ownership makes it challenging to manage wide areas of land. Although the landscape conservation area status guarantees the availability of funding to conserve valuable cultural landscape, large sums of money are not always required to maintain these locations. For example, a nationally valuable traditional biotope in Kotiniemi, Kairala, is maintained by a sheep farmer from Luiro with no special funding. Volunteers built a fence in 2010 (Image 10).</p>
<p>In addition, the environment of the oldest building in Kairala, the Ollila granary, is maintained by volunteers (Image 11). As an acknowledgement of their valuable work in the village, the Kairala village association received an honourable mention in the competition for the best landscape project in Finland.</p>
<p>Image 8 ja 9. Martini’s house before and after renovation in Kairala. Photos: Kari Tallavaara.84</p>
<p>Image 10. Volunteers building a fence in Kotiniemi in summer 2010. Photo: Annika Kostamo.</p>
<p>Image 11. Volunteers built a traditional fence in Kairala (Ollilla granary).</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Photo: Merja Lipponen.85</p>
<p>Landscape management in Lapland continues</p>
<p>The work to promote the acknowledgement and conservation of landscape values according to the ELC continues, not only in the Kairala-Luiro landscape conservation area, but in other parts of Lapland and Finland as well. In Central and Southern Lapland, this work continues in the Maisemat Ruotuun project, funded by the Ministry of the Environment and the EU. The objective is to inspire people in Lapland and Kainuu to value their local village cultural landscape, help them in practical issues in landscape management and advise them on funding applications to conserve and manage their village landscapes. An updated inventory of nationally and regionally valuable landscape areas is also conducted as a part of the project (Decision in Principle of the Council of State 1995, report of the Ministry of the Environment 1993).</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">References: Kehusmaa, A. &amp; Onnela, S. 1995: Suursodankylän historia 1. Gummerus Kirjapaino Oy, Jyväskylä Kokko, M., Kurkela, A., Pihkala, A. &amp; Tallavaara, K. 2009. Komiat kylät pohjoisen maisemassa - Kairalan ja Luiron maisemanhoitoalueen hoito- ja käyttösuunnitelma. Suomen ympäristö 9/2009. Lapin ympäristökeskus. Helsingin yliopistopaino, Helsinki.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Museovirasto 2009. Valtakunnallisesti merkittävät rakennetut kulttuuriympäristöt. 10 October 2011 at: http://www.rky.fi/read/asp/r_default.aspx.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Tallavaara, K. 2008. Kairavuopiolaiset – 300 vuotta Kairalan kylähistoriaa. Tornion kirjapaino Oy, Tornio. Valtioneuvoston periaatepäätös 1995. Valtioneuvoston periaatepäätös valtakunnallisesti arvokkaista maisema-alueista.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Annettu Helsingissä 5.1.1995.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Ympäristöministeriön mietintö 1993. Arvokkaat maisema-alueet. Maisema-aluetyöryhmän mietintö II. Ympäristöministeriö, ympäristönsuojeluosasto, mietintö 66/1992. Helsinki.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Ympäristöministeriön päätös 2010. Ympäristöministeriön päätös Kairalan-Luiron maisemanhoitoalueesta. Annettu</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Helsingissä 20.04.10.86</p>
<p>CONCLUSIONS Application of the European Landscape Convention in the North</p>
<p>Calotte area municipalities</p>
<p>Landscape protection and management in Finland is mainly guided by the Land Use and Building Act and its National Land Use Guidelines and the Nature Conservation Act. The objectives of the European Landscape Convention are incorporated into the aforementioned acts. In Sweden, the contents of the convention are included in the Environmental Code (1999) and the Planning and Building Act (1987/2011). In Norway, the guiding legislation includes the Planning and Building Act (2008), the Nature Diversity Act (2009) and the Cultural Heritage Act (1978). Landscape protection and management in the landscape areas is executed through area and land use planning, mainly through town planning and the creation of landscape management plans.</p>
<p>In land use and area planning, the municipalities have a significant responsibility. The municipalities in the</p>
<p>North Calotte region have their own partly divergent methods and practices, based on which the various land use processes are executed. The municipalities and inhabitants have a great interest in preserving and protecting their living environments and maintaining and increasing the appeal of the area. In municipalities, landscape is indeed viewed as one of the most significant appealing factors that cannot be lost, but the feeling is that their own expertise is not sufficient to deal with landscape issues, especially the landscape effects of various forms of land use. The different requirements of different forms of land use bring with them such challenges that have not been seen before and that each municipality must resolve themselves.</p>
<p>Digesting new information and putting it into practice is seen as difficult and deviating from common practices is hard without clear instructions and concrete support. A lack of resources and experts hinders the adoption of different practices. The objectives of the ELC are integrated into several laws in the countries of the Northern Calotte area. There is no one clear body in charge of the implementation of the ELC; the responsibility is shared. This is a factor that can lead to avoiding responsibility when the resources are low. All authorities should pay an increasing amount of attention on comprehensively including the principles of the ELC in different functions and practices. New and clear emphasis on the duties of authorities would promote the objectives of the convention. A clear division of roles and responsibilities will have a significant impact on integrating the convention objectives into practice. A clear and direct instruction from a national body to the regional authorities, and from there to municipalities, would bind them to take concrete action. People have wanted to preserve the positive spirit of the convention, which is why a direct instruction has not been seen as necessary. An instruction would not take away the positive spirit but it would make procedures clearer in the municipalities and at the regional government level.</p>
<p>The increasing land use needs in municipalities, for example due to energy production, mining industry and increasing travel, create a need for more multidimensional planning. The reconciliation of the wishes of different interest groups, and traditional and new livelihoods will not be easy. Conflict is inevitable. This will lead to a greater need to engage local bodies to the planning processes right from the start of the projects. Planning requires interaction between the authorities and residents. The mutual dialogue between residents, organisations and authorities has a great impact on the landscape effects of projects. Research will bring additional information on landscapes, their importance and the effects that different forms of land use have on a specific landscape. Data also supports decision-making and finding solutions. Close co-operation between different administrative branches, operators, local bodies and landscape research promote the objectives of the convention.</p>
<p>Landscape inventories support landscape management work. The demands of the municipalities for more specific and deeper landscape classifications and models, and the effects of different forms of land use on the landscape should be possible to implement in the long run, in order to support practical planning. Mapping and different programmes supporting planning make it easier to take landscape values into account. Special attention should be paid to the dissemination of good and functional practices. Knowledge and expertise within municipalities can be increased with special training and instruction. Training for consulting companies used by the municipalities is also important for the promotion of the ELC. In cross-border co-operation it is extremely 87important to continue sharing experiences and finding and promoting common practices. The Sámi area in the North Calotte should be handled as a single unit rather than as separate areas in three different countries.</p>
<p>To ensure that the work continues, a landscape co-operation group is to be established in the North Calotte area. The co-operation group will include members from all three countries, with strong representation from the Sámi area. The primary task of the co-operation group is to promote and develop landscape policy in the area. In the long run, the promotion of landscape protection and management with classifications and mappings in the North Calotte area can be done with project funding. Forming the co-operation group and defining its primary operating principles should be the next step in promoting the ELC in the north. From now on, the group can plan necessary projects and initiatives in the area and arrange instruction and training for local operators and those at the municipal level. Actively sharing positive experiences and information to and between the North Calotte municipalities will make it easier to face future challenges. Understanding the importance of landscapes plays a key role in the practical implementation of the European Landscape Convention.</p>
<p xml:lang="est"><em type="bold">Noora Raasakka </em></p>
<p>Project Manager Centre for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment for Lapland88</p>
<p xml:lang="kal">Annex</p>
<p>Annex1 Member States of the Council of Europe</p>
<p>Status as of: 10/8/2011</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">States</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Signature</p>
<p>Ratification</p>
<p>Entry into force</p>
<p xml:lang="pol">Albania</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Andorra 23/3/2011</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">Armenia 14/5/2003 23/3/2004 1/7/2004</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Austria</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Azerbaijan 22/10/2003</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Belgium 20/10/2000 28/10/2004 1/2/2005</p>
<p>Bosnia and Herze-govina 9/4/2010</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">Bulgaria 20/10/2000 24/11/2004 1/3/2005</p>
<p>Croatia 20/10/2000 15/1/2003 1/3/2004</p>
<p>Cyprus 21/11/2001 21/6/2006 1/10/2006</p>
<p>Czech Republic 28/11/2002 3/6/2004 1/10/2004</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Denmark 20/10/2000 20/3/2003 1/3/2004</p>
<p xml:lang="pol">Estonia</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Finland 20/10/2000 16/12/2005 1/4/2006</p>
<p>France 20/10/2000 17/3/2006 1/7/2006</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">Georgia 11/5/2010 15/9/2010 1/1/2011</p>
<p>Germany</p>
<p>Greece 13/12/2000 17/5/2010 1/9/2010</p>
<p xml:lang="fao">Hungary 28/9/2005 26/10/2007 1/2/2008</p>
<p>Iceland</p>
<p>Ireland 22/3/2002 22/3/2002 1/3/2004</p>
<p>Italy 20/10/2000 4/5/2006 1/9/2006</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Latvia 29/11/2006 5/6/2007 1/10/2007</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Liechtenstein</p>
<p xml:lang="pol">Lithuania 20/10/2000 13/11/2002 1/3/2004</p>
<p>Luxembourg 20/10/2000 20/9/2006 1/1/2007</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Malta 20/10/2000</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Moldova 20/10/2000 14/3/2002 1/3/2004</p>
<p>Monaco</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Montenegro 8/12/2008 22/1/2009 1/5/2009</p>
<p>Netherlands 27/7/2005 27/7/2005 1/11/2005</p>
<p>Norway 20/10/2000 23/10/2001 1/3/2004</p>
<p>Poland 21/12/2001 27/9/2004 1/1/2005</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Portugal 20/10/2000 29/3/2005 1/7/2005</p>
<p xml:lang="pol">Romania 20/10/2000 7/11/2002 1/3/2004</p>
<p xml:lang="kal">Russia 89</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">States</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Signature</p>
<p>Ratification</p>
<p>Entry into force</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">San Marino 20/10/2000 26/11/2003 1/3/2004</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Serbia 21/9/2007 28/6/2011 1/10/2011</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Slovakia 30/5/2005 9/8/2005 1/12/2005</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Slovenia 7/3/2001 25/9/2003 1/3/2004</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Spain 20/10/2000 26/11/2007 1/3/2008</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Sweden 22/2/2001 5/1/2011 1/5/2011</p>
<p>Switzerland 20/10/2000</p>
<p>The former Yugo-slav Republic of</p>
<p xml:lang="pol">Macedonia 15/1/2003 18/11/2003 1/3/2004</p>
<p>Turkey 20/10/2000 13/10/2003 1/3/2004</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Ukraine 17/6/2004 10/3/2006 1/7/2006</p>
<p>United Kingdom 21/2/2006 21/11/2006 1/3/2007</p>
<p>Total number of signatures not followed by ratifications: 5</p>
<p>Total number of ratifications/accessions: 34 90</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Julkaisusarjan nimi ja numero Raportteja 48/2012</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Vastuualue Ympäristö ja luonnonvarat</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Tekijät Noora Raasakka Sari Sivonen (toim.)</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Julkaisuaika Toukokuu 2012</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Kustantaja /Julkaisija Lapin elinkeino-, liikenne- ja ympäristökeskus Hankkeen rahoittaja / toimeksiantaja Pohjoismaiden ministerineuvosto</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Julkaisun nimi <em type="bold">Pohjoiset maisemat </em>”Eurooppalaisen maisemayleissopimuksen toteuttaminen Pohjois-Kalotin kunnissa’’ – Konferenssi Inarissa 7.-9.9.2011 </p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Tiivistelmä</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Kansainvälinen Eurooppalaisen maisemayleissopimuksen tavoitteiden saavuttamista edistävä konferenssi järjestettiin Inarissa 7.-9.9.2011. Konferenssissa käsiteltiin maisemasopimuksen tavoitteita, tarpeita ja mahdollisuuksia Pohjois-Kalotin alueella. Tähän raporttiin on koottu konferenssissa esiintyneiden asiantuntijoiden laatimat artikkelit aiheesta. Raportin toivotaan helpottavan alueiden käytön suunnittelijoita käytännön työssään ja rohkaisevan kuntia toteuttamaan tulevaisuuden suunnittelua Eurooppalaisen maisemayleissopimuksen tavoitteiden mukaisesti. Raportti on saatavissa viidellä eri kielellä: suomeksi, ruotsiksi, norjaksi, pohjoissaameksi ja englanniksi.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Pohjois-Kalotin aluetta yhdistää yhteinen tunnusomainen maisema. Saamelaiskulttuurin sekä poronhoidon muovaamat tunturimaisemat ja upeat jokivarsimaisemat heijastuvat ympäristössä laaja-alaisesti. Alueen maisemalle haasteita tuovat sen moninaiset maankäyttömuodot ja elinkeinot, kuten matkailu, kaivosteollisuus ja energiantuotanto. Arvokkaiden maisemapiirteiden säilyttäminen vaatii erityistä tuntemusta ja tietämystä alueen kunnissa.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Maisemansuojelua ja -hoitoa toteutetaan alueiden- ja maankäytön suunnittelun kautta, pääasiallisesti kaavoituksella ja maisemanhoitosuunnitelmilla. Pohjois-Kalotin alueen kunnissa on erilaiset osin toisistaan poikkeavat toimintatavat ja käytännöt maisemanhoidossa. Kuitenkin alueen asukkailla on yhtäläisiä intressejä elinympäristönsä suojeluun ja säilyttämiseen. Maisema nähdään vetovoimatekijänä, jota ei haluta menettää.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Lisääntyvät maankäyttötarpeet kunnissa luovat tarpeen entistä moniulotteisemmalle suunnittelulle. Paikallisten tahojen osallistaminen suunnitteluprosesseihin aikaisessa vaiheessa ja monimuotoinen vuorovaikutus, niin toimijoiden, kansalaisten kuin viranomaisten välillä vähentää konfliktien muodostumista. Tutkimustiedon tehokkaampi hyödyntäminen ja valtiorajat ylittävä yhteistyö helpottaa päätöksentekoa ja luo yhteisiä linjoja maisemansuojelutyöhön. Yhteiset kokemukset, käytännöt ja tietotaidon jakaminen sekä laajemman maisemakokonaisuuden hahmottaminen parantaa eurooppalaisen maisemayleissopimuksen tavoitteiden toteutumista. Työn jatkuvuuden varmistamiseksi Pohjois-Kalotin alueelle suunnitellaan perustettavaksi maisemayhteistyöryhmä, jonka tehtävä on maisemapolitiikan kehittäminen ja eteenpäin vieminen.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Asiasanat (YSA:n mukaan) maisema, Pohjoiskalotti, Eurooppalainen maisemayleissopimus, aluesuunnittelu, maisemansuojelu, maisemanhoito</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">ISBN (Painettu) 978-952-257-537-1</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">ISBN (PDF) 978-952-257-538-8</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">ISSN-L 2242-2846</p>
<p xml:lang="olo">ISSN (painettu) 2242-2846</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">ISSN (verkkojulkaisu) 2242-2854www www.ely-keskus.fi/julkaisut | www.doria.fi</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">URN URN:ISBN:978-952-257-538-8</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Kieli englanti</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Sivumäärä 87</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Julkaisun tilaukset Lapin elinkeino-, liikenne ja ympäristökeskus, PL 8060, 96101 Rovaniemi puh: 029 503 7000, e-mail: kirjaamo.lappi@ely-keskus.fi</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Kustannuspaikka ja -aika Rovaniemi 2012</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Painotalo Kopijyvä Oy</p>
<p xml:lang="est">K U V A I L U L E H T I91</p>
<p xml:lang="swe">Publikationens serie och nummer Rapporter 48/2012</p>
<p xml:lang="swe">Ansvarsområde Miljö och naturresurser</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Författare Noora Raasakka Sari Sivonen</p>
<p xml:lang="rmy-rlo">Publiceringsdatum Maj 2012</p>
<p xml:lang="swe">Utgivare / Förläggare Närings-, trafik- och miljöcentralen i Lapland Projektets finansiär/uppdragsgivare Nordiska ministerrådet</p>
<p xml:lang="swe">Publikationens titel <em type="bold">Nordig landskapet </em><span type="quote" xml:lang="swe">”Tillämpning av den Europeiska Landskapkonventionen i kommunerna på Nordkalotten”</span> - Konferenssen 7–9.9.2011, Enare, Finland Sammandrag För att kunna nå de uppsatta målen för den europeiska landskapskonventionen anordnades en internationell europeisk konferens den 7–9 september 2011 i Enare. Konferensen var främst inriktad på att öka kunskapen om den europeiska landskapskonventionen och de möjligheter och behov den ger vad gäller det praktiska planeringsarbetet, särkilt på kommunnivå. Den här rapport är samlat artikel skrev av ledande expertes som var föreläsare i konferensen. Vi hoppas att den här rapport underlättar det praktiska arbetet för planerarna av de här områdena och inspirerar kommunerna att genomföra sina framtidsplaner enligt den europeiska landskapskonventionen. Publikationen finns tillgänglig på fem olika språk: finska, svenska, norska, nordsamiska och engelska. Naturen på Nordkalotten återspeglar på bred front de gemensamma karaktäristiska dragen, såsom de fantastiska älvlandskapen och de vackra fjälltrakterna formade av samekulturen och renskötseln. Turism, energiproduktion, gruvnäring och utbyggnad av infrastruktur leder till nya och mångfacetterade utmaningar för dem som är ansvariga för områdena. Kommunerna behöver kunskap och stöd för att kunna förverkliga de allt mer komplexa planerna i framtiden, så att de unika och värdefulla särdragen kan bevaras. Landskapsskyddet och -vården genomförs i landskapsområdena via områdesplanering och planering av markanvändning, i huvudsak genom planläggning och utarbetande av landskapsvårdsplaner. Kommunerna i Nordkalotten har egna, delvis olikartade metoder och praxis, på basis av vilka olika processer i anslutning till områdesanvändningen sköts. Kommunerna och kommuninvånarna har ett stort intresse att bevara och skydda den egna livsmiljön och att upprätthålla och öka områdets attraktionskraft. Landskapet ses ju i kommunerna som en av de viktigaste attraktionsfaktorerna som man inte vill förlora. Kommunernas ökade markanvändningsbehov med avseende på bland annat energiproduktionen, gruvindustrin och den växande turistnäringen skapar ett välgrundat behov av en planering med ännu fler dimensioner. Det är viktigt att lokala intressegrupper deltar i planeringen redan i början av processen. Mångsidigt samarbete mellan medborgare, aktörer och myndigheter kan minska eller hindra konflikter. En dialog mellan medborgare, organisationer och myndigheter har en stor inverkan på många projekts effekter på landskapet. Med hjälp av forskning får vi mer information om landskapen, deras betydelse och hur olika markanvändningsmetoder påverkar landskapen. Gemensamma erfarenheter och praktik, uppdelningen av kunnande (know-how) samt uppfattningen av bredare landkapshelheten dörbättrar tilsammans de möjligheterna att förverkliga målen som definierats i Europeiska landskapkonventionen.För att säkerställa att arbetet fortsätter upprättas en landskapssamarbetsgrupp på Nordkalottens område, som huvuduppgift är att utveckla landskapspolitiken och driva den framåt. Nyckelord (enligt Allärs) landskap, Nordkalotten, Europeisk landskapskonvention, områdesplanering, landskapskydd, landskapsvård </p>
<p xml:lang="nno">ISBN (tryckt) 978-952-257-537-1</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">ISBN (PDF) 978-952-257-538-8</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">ISSN-L 2242-2846</p>
<p xml:lang="swe">ISSN (tryckt) 2242-2846</p>
<p>ISSN (webbpublikation) 2242-2854www www.ely-centralen.fi/publikationer | www.doria.fi</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">URN URN:ISBN:978-952-257-538-8</p>
<p xml:lang="swe">Språk engelska</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Sidantal 87</p>
<p xml:lang="swe">Beställningar Centrum för ekonomisk utveckling, transport och miljö i Lappland, PB 8060, 96101 Rovaniemi telefon: +358 29 503 7000, e-mail: kirjaamo.lappi@ely-keskus.fi</p>
<p xml:lang="swe">Förläggningsort och datum Rovaniemi 2012</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Tryckeri Kopijyvä Oy</p>
<p xml:lang="est">P R E S E N T A T I O N S B L A D92</p>
<p>Publication series and numbers Reports 48/2012</p>
<p>Area(s) of responsibility Environment and Natural Resources</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Author(s) Noora Raasakka Sari Sivonen</p>
<p>Date May 2012</p>
<p>Publisher Centre for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment for Lapland Financier/commissioner The Nordic Council of Ministers</p>
<p>Title of publication <em type="bold">Northern Landscapes </em>ʻʻImplementation of the European Landscape Convention In the North Calotte Area Municipalitiesʼʼ - Conference in Inari, Finland 7-9.9.2011 Abstract </p>
<p>The conference promoting the objectives of the international European Landscape Convention (ELC) was held on 7-9 September 2011 in Inari. The primary aim of the conference was to increase awareness of the ELC and the prospects and requirements it brings to practical planning work, especially at the municipal level. The conference speakers included top experts from Sweden, Norway, Finland, France, Holland and Catalonia. This report is a collection of articles written by the experts in the ELC conference. The report is available in five languages: Finnish, Swedish, Norwegian, Northern Sámi and English.</p>
<p>The common characteristics of the North Calotte area, such as the magnificent riverside scenery and the beautiful fell landscapes formed by the Sámi culture and reindeer management are broadly reflected in the environment. Alongside the traditional forms of land use, many other livelihoods and forms of land use now need to be accommodated in the area. Tourism, energy production, mining industry and new infrastructure create new and manifold challenges to the authorities in charge of land use in these areas. Municipalities need information and support for versatile planning in the future, so that the unique and valuable characteristics of the North can be preserved.</p>
<p>Landscape protection and management in the landscape areas is executed through areal and land use planning, mainly through town planning and the creation of landscape management plans. The municipalities in the North Calotte region have their own partly divergent methods and practices, based on the various land use processes are executed. The municipalities and inhabitants have a great interest in preserving and protecting their living environment and maintaining and increasing the appeal of the area. Landscape is viewed as one of the most significant appealing factors that cannot be lost.</p>
<p>The increasing land use in municipalities, for example due to energy production, mining industry and increasing tourism, create a need for more multidimensional planning. The reconciliation of the wishes of different interest groups, and traditional and new livelihoods will not be easy. Conflict is inevitable. This will lead to a greater need to engage local bodies to the planning processes right from the start of the projects. Close cooperation between different administrative branches, operators, local bodies and landscape research promote the objectives of the convention. To ensure that the work continues, a landscape co-operation group is planned to be established in the North Calotte area. It´s main task is to promote and develop landscape policy in the area.</p>
<p>Keywords landscape, North Calotte, European Landscape Convention, environmental planning, landscape protection, landcape management</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">ISBN (print) 978-952-257-537-1</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">ISBN (PDF) 978-952-257-538-8</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">ISSN-L 2242-2846</p>
<p>ISSN (print) 2242-2846</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">ISSN (online) 2242-2854www www.ely-keskus.fi/julkaisut | www.doria.fi</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">URN URN:ISBN:978-952-257-538-8</p>
<p>Language English</p>
<p>Number of pages 87</p>
<p>Distributor Centre for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment, P.O. Box 8060, 96101 Rovaniemi, Finland Phone: +358 29 503 7000, e-mail: kirjaamo.lappi@ely-keskus.fi</p>
<p>Place of publication and date Rovaniemi 2012</p>
<p>Printing place Kopijyvä Oy</p>
<p xml:lang="est">D O C U M E N T A T I O N P A G E9394</p>
<p><em type="bold">The common characteristics of the North calotte area, such as the magnificent riverside scenery and the beautiful fell landscapes formed by the Sámi culture and reindeer management are broadly reflected in the environment. New forms of land use and different interest to the areas create challenges for the protection of the landscapes. authorities working with the protection work need more guidance and support. Understanding the importance of landscapes plays a key role in the practical implementation of the European Landscape convention. a landscape cooperation group is planned to be established in the North calotte area to ensure that the work continues. It´s main task is to promote and develop landscape policy in the area. </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">The conference promoting the objectives of the international European Landscape convention (ELc) was held on 7-9 September 2011 in Inari. The primary aim of the conference was to increase awareness of the ELc and the prospects and requirements it brings to practical planning work, especially at the municipal level. This report is a collection of articles written by the experts in the ELc conference. The report is available in five languages: Finnish, Swedish, Norwegian, Northern Sámi and English. </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">REPORTS 48 | 2012 NORThERN LaNdScaPES <span type="quote">“IMPLEMENTaTION OF ThE EUROPEaN LaNdScaPE cONVENTION IN ThE NORTh caLOTTE aREa MUNIcIPa-LITIES”</span> - conference in Inari, Finland 7.–9.9.2011centre for Economic development, Transport and the Environment for Lapland </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="bold">ISBN 978-952-257-537-1 (painettu) ISBN 978-952-257-538-8 (PdF) </em></p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">ISSN-L 2242-2846 ISSN 2242-2846 (painettu) ISSN 2242-2854 (verkkojulkaisu) </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="bold">URN:ISBN:978-952-257-538-8www.ely-keskus.fi/julkaisut | www.doria.fi/ely-keskus </em></p>
</body></document>
