<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>SITUASJONEN TIL SAMER MED FUNKSJONSNEDSETTELSE</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2016</year><wordcount>919</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>https://nordicwelfare.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/NorskSamerapportLAYOUT160414.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="samer_med_funksjonsnedsettelse_nob.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="samer_med_funksjonsnedsettelse_sma.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="samer_med_funksjonsnedsettelse_sme.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smj" location="samer_med_funksjonsnedsettelse_smj.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 161400 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p><em type="bold">SUMMARY </em></p>
<p>This report is written on commission by the Nordic Centre for Welfare and Social Issues (NVC) and is the final report of the qualitative Norwegian subproject <span type="quote">”People with Disabilities and Sami Background”</span>. The goal of the project is to increase understanding for the situation of people with disabilities and Sami background. The Norwegian Directorate for Children, Youth and Family Affairs (Bufdir) has previously made public that there is little scientific research-based knowledge in this area.  Bufdir has contributed project funds to NVC, who has been financially responsible for our project.</p>
<p>The project has aimed to answer three questions:</p>
<p type="listitem">•  How do people with disabilities and Sami background experience their daily lives?</p>
<p type="listitem">•  How do people with disabilities and Sami background experience important transitions in their lives?</p>
<p type="listitem">•  How do people with disabilities and Sami background participate in the democratic processes?</p>
<p>The content of the report is based on 31 semistructured interviews with people with disabilities and Sami background and/or their next of kin or custodians. The selection includes children, youths, adults and elderly people; they are primarily located in the Northern Sami, Lule Sami and Southern Sami areas. The study was performed in the period between April 2014 and December 2015. The implementation of the study has been followed by a reference group comprising representatives from Sami organisations and communities, in addition to people with disabilities’ organisations and communities.</p>
<p>The study addresses several conditions within the Norwegian welfare system that can be obstacles for providing people with Sami background and disabilities equal value customised services. The support system offers standardised services tailored to the needs of the majority. This means, among other things, that a focus on diagnosis and disabilities overshadows an approach that values and prioritises the cultural specifics of Sami mentality. Consequentially, people with Sami background might encounter cultural and linguistic barriers within the support system. A lack of knowledge among Norwegian service providers regarding the Sami populations’ indirect way of communicating issues of illness and health, might make the interaction with the Norwegian healthcare system a problematic experience. Additionally, a lack of possibility to use their own language leads to limited access to necessary information. This because Samis (who use a Sami language in their daily life) prefer not to use interpreters, but rather want to speak about illness, health and disabilities in their own native language.</p>
<p>Traditionally, Sami people do not view the world in diagnostic terms. People with disabilities are viewed by many Sami people as a part of the natural variation, and it has been important to give each individual a functional role in society. Despite the large differences between traditional Sami medicine and western medicine, many people with disabilities and Sami background make use of both in parallel and experience benefits from both. Within traditional Sami medicine the use of alternative therapists (guvllár, readers, palm readers), and being read is still alive among Samis with various disabilities.</p>
<p>For many people with disabilities and Sami background important experiences are related to school, also negative ones. For the older informants being sent to boarding school and denied the use of their own language was a great burden, and this has been an additional challenge in their daily lives. Even though young and adult people with disabilities and Sami background have primarily attended school in their local area, it is clear that the access to Sami language education (in spite of being legally mandatory) is still a struggle for many. Across age groups it is revealed that school bullying is extensive. People with disabilities and Sami background are bullied both because of their Sami background and their disability, and by both fellow Norwegian and Sami pupils.</p>
<p>Entering into working life has been a challenging experience for many. The support system’s main focus appears to be on the impairment rather than their Sami background.  Many choose to work in traditional Sami occupations such as tending reindeer, fishing and agriculture, in spite of impairments. For those who acquire impairments as adults, reduced participation or being unable to work is a difficult transition. Among people with disabilities and Sami background many previously worked within non-specialised industries, but are currently employed in local government and public industries such as workshops and activity centres.</p>
<p>In regards to participation in democratic processes, Sami background appears to increase involvement and commitment, while disabilities contribute to reduced or lacking participation. The participation of people with disabilities and Sami background in democratic processes seems not to differ significantly from that of people without disabilities. Additionally, an important finding is the experience of having to defend Sami interests on behalf of the Sami population as a whole in every context. Defending such interests is, at times, perceived as an additional burden.</p>
<p>The conclusion, then, is that it is not possible to talk about the one situation for people with disabilities and Sami background. From the descriptions found in the interviews it becomes clear that it is a great multitude of situations in regards to daily life, important transitions and the participation in democratic processes. The interviews show that the situation of people with disabilities and Sami background varies depending on formative conditions, relation to Sami identity, sex, type of impairment, age, location, and more. At the same time there is within the Norwegian welfare system a great need for more knowledge about Sami culture, language and identity and how to implement this. The aim must be that welfare professionals meet the challenges by understanding and reacting to the differences and specifics of Sami culture.</p>
</body></document>