<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Welcome greeting at Árrans research conference March 21- 22, 2006 at Drag in Tysfjord, Norway by Head of the Board Tone Finnesen</title><genre code="facta"/><author><person firstname="Tone" lastname="Finnesen" sex="f" born="" nationality="NO"/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="nob"/><year>2006</year><wordcount>759</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Trond Trosterud" email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no"/><multilingual/><origFileName>ToneFi210306_E.DOC</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate  1.9 ; file-specific xsl  $Revision: 1.1 $; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p><em type="bold">Welcome greeting at Árrans research conference March 21- 22, 2006 at Drag in Tysfjord, Norway by Head of the Board Tone Finnesen </em> </p>
<p>The President of the Sami Parliament!</p>
<p>Participants of the conference!</p>
<p>On behalf of the Árran lulesami centre I wish all the participants of this conference heartily welcome to Tysfjord, to Drag and to Árran. We are delighted to see that so many are present here to participate in our research conference about language, health, culture and community. Especially the fact that the president of the Sami Parliament has taken time to give a contribution on the role of research in Sami community development, is a great pleasure. Welcome to the other speakers to this conference as well, we look forward to your contribution. And welcome to the representatives from the authorities, the cooperating institutions and all of you others that have come to participate and spend the day with us.</p>
<p>With us today, we have guest who have come a long way for the conference, - all the way from South Africa. It is a great pleasure to welcome Mike and Sabrina Adams, along with their students, to Árran. I hope you will have a good time with us here today. We have composed a separate agenda for you, with special lectures that are partly held as side-events to this conference. With these we hope to be able to share knowledge with you on the work on indigenous issues on our side of the globe. Similarly, we hope to learn about your experiences in your work to create better living conditions in your communities. We wish you good luck with your studies, your work for peace and reconciliation between people, and your stay in Hamarøy and Tysfjord!</p>
<p>Árran, as a Sami institution has reached a turning point today. The board has started the work of evaluating and developing new strategies for Árrans prospective work.</p>
<p>The conference is a part of this work. As for those who are curious on the time schedule of this strategic work, it could be helpful to know that the board will develop the new strategic foundation based on prospective challenges within 2006. This includes Árrans role as a participant, co-worker and manager within the various parts of society.</p>
<p>The themes of this conference cover researching in Sami language, health and social questions, and research on culture and community. To build a foundation for further discussion of these themes, we will hear about the role research has played in Sami society development and about paramount challenges in Sami research. Furthermore we will then deliberate on the various challenges that are tied up to the various themes spoken of. The main idea is to be able to identify areas and approaches to problems that need more attention from Árran and all of those institutions and authorities present here today.</p>
<p>With this in mind, we have with great interest noted that the State Secretary Berit Oskal Eira in the Ministry of Work and Social Inclusion, has expressed  <em type="italic"><span type="quote">“a desire that lulesami and southsami research would become more visible in a prospective profile of a Sami research program”</span> </em> in the conference on sami research facilitated by the Research Council of Norway, February 22-23, 2006. (  <em type="italic">www.odin.dep.no/aidnorsk/aktuelt/taler/politisk_ledelse/dok-bu.html  </em>).  </p>
<p>This is a challenge Árran is willing to face, and I urge you to discuss this in the workshops. There we will furthermore deliberate partnership and institutional cooperation both in a national and trans-national perspective.</p>
<p>On the way down to this meeting room, you might have noticed some pictures hanging on the wall. Those are artwork made by the Sami artist Elle Hansa (Sami name), - Keviselie (Artist name), - Hans Ragnar Mathisen. The exhibition is called <span type="quote" xml:lang="fao">“Gemini”</span> – <span type="quote">“twins”</span> and are hanging in the hallway on the way down to this auditorium. This exhibition is for sale and you are most welcome to buy a picture or two.</p>
<p>A conference is expensive. We thanks the Research Council of Norway and the Norwegian Archive, Library, and Museum Authority for their financial support to this conference.</p>
<p>I hope you all will have beneficial days here in Tysfjord and in Hamarøy. The Chair of the plenary part of this conference is the former head of the board of Árran, Håkon M. Pettersen. Before I leave the podium to him, I just want;</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Once more, to wish you all heartily welcome to Árran.</p>
<p type="listitem">To congratulate one of our employers with her 40  th  birthday to day, Heidi Andersen. Happy Birthday, Heidi! Please, step out of the interpreter booth and receive our congratulations.</p>
</list></body></document>
