<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>431</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index.php?option=com_docman&amp;task=doc_download&amp;gid=1783&amp;Itemid=10</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="eatnu_eadni_eana_koltannos.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 125457 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>Wall relief, Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos, Sámi Parliament hall Solju Eatnu, eadni, eana Juvduu, enni, eennâm Jäänn, jeä´nn, jânnam Eatnu, eadni, eana – virta, emo, maa Eatnu, eadni, eana - stream, mother, ground Outi Peiski 2012, State art collection materials - steel and ceramic with leaf gold plating - ivory, Sámi handicrafts (or ivory, engraved ivory, pearl and tin yarn embroidery) steel components: metalsmith Mikko Ramsi gold plating: Kultaus Oy Snellman spoons: ceramic artist Nathalie Lahdenmäki The artwork consists of several steel plates covered with yellow and white gold, forming a shining multilevel stream on the wall and over the speaker's stand. One visual source of inspiration was the <span type="quote" xml:lang="som">"risku"</span> brooch used in women's traditional Sámi dresses. According to an old legend, the gold-plated discs protect the bearer of the risku, because their shine and tinkle repel evil. I have always admired and drawn inspiration from my grandmother Jovsset Biret, and this piece is a tribute to strong Sámi women like her. The pieces of the artwork are of plate shape, and the drops hanging from them are ceramic spoons featuring an idiom derived from the traditional wooden Sámi spoon. While processing this piece, I was thinking about the stream of generations through time, and the feeling of togetherness with the stream feeding every one of us. The surface of the plates reflects reality in reverse, creating a world of ideas that mirrors the dream of perfection and hope for better that is lodged in us. For me personally, this brings to mind the Sámi folklore about gnomes living underground and leading a life similar to that of us humans, only the other way around. The elements of the piece repeat the perfect circle, and the bright drop is a perfect moment in time. Nevertheless, as an entity, the piece features a random flow, which makes its form stand up to the challenge of time. The artwork also contains details representing the idiom of a traditional Sámi rattle toy. Small reindeer foot bones hanging from a steel ring have faces engraved on them and clothes embroidered with tin yarn and pearls. All components of this artwork are hand-made, demonstrating the skill of professional crafters. This is a tribute to the handicrafts tradition, which is a key driver of the Sámi culture. In the Northern Sámi language, the words for a large river, mother, and ground resemble each other closely. The concepts behind these words are something that I, as a representative of the Sámi people, want to respect: the binding stream of generations, strong Sámi women, and our beloved Sámi land.</p>
</body></document>
