<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>861</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Børre Gaup" email="albbas@gmail.com"/><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.skatteetaten.no/upload/Skjemaer/2013/RF-1224E.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="rf-1224b.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="80337_rf-1224-samisk_utfyll.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>1.17 Calculated personal income for the year before any coordination/carryforward1.19 Deduction for negative calculated personal income transferred from another business with which coordination is possible – see the guidelines1.231.21 Addition for negative calculated personal income that can be coordinated with remuneration for work from an ANS/DA/KS this year – see the guidelines</p>
<p><em type="bold">Allocation between spouses </em>(Allocation of item 1.9 between spouses) </p>
<p><em type="bold">Spouse </em>% sharea)1.10 Allocation between spouses of item 1.9, see the guidelines -+= </p>
<p>Type of business (see guidelines)</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">Sector code</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Name</p>
<p>Personal ID number</p>
<p>Enterprise/ office address (business income from more than one municipality must list item)</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">Postal code</p>
<p>Postal district</p>
<p>See the guidelines for how to use minus or plus signs in the form1.1 Amount transferred from Income Statement 1 (item 0402E), Income statement 2 (item 0402E), Næringsoppgave for billedkunstnere (‘Income Statement for visual artists’ – in Norwegian only) (item 2.90) or from Operating result in the tax return RF-1030.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Basis calculation </em>1.2 Interest on the enterprise’s debt to financial institutions entered under item 2.10 (see guidelines to item 2.10), and interest on operating credits/ overdraft facilities and enterprise loans taken up and repaid during the year.1.3 Capital income (yield and gains, not interest) relating to financial instruments or to real capital that has not been active in the enterprise. (The income must be entered in your income statement or under Operating result in form RF-1030 and be included under item 1.1). See the guidelines for information about interest relief subsidies from Innovation Norway.1.5 Capital expenses (not interest) and losses relating to financial instruments or to real capital that have not been active in the enterprise. (The expense must be entered in your income statement or under Operating result in form RF-1030 and be included under item 1.1).1.7 Total1.8 Risk-free return (positive amount from item 2.11 or 2.12 multiplied by the risk-free interest rate)--+1.9 Calculated personal income for the year before any coordination/carryforward. In cases of allocation between spouses, the amounts in item 1.1.0 will be used for the calculation.=-= </p>
<p>Interest rate %</p>
<p>Fisheries/</p>
<p>Family day care centresin one’s own home</p>
<p>To be transferred to the tax return (form RF-1030) item 1.6.1 or 1.6.2. See the guidelines.</p>
<p>Other commercial activities</p>
<p>Personal income1.341.33</p>
<p><em type="bold">Specification of positive calculated personal income from item 1.23 </em>1.4 Reduction amount for rented property for which a deposit has been paid-a) </p>
<p xml:lang="fra"><em type="bold">Spouse </em></p>
<p>Fisheries/</p>
<p>Family day care centresin one’s own home</p>
<p>Other commercial activities1.361.35</p>
<p><em type="bold">Coordination/carryforward of negative calculated personal income </em>-=+% shareb)1.20 Addition for negative calculated personal income transferred to another business with which coordination is possible – see the guidelines++ </p>
<p><em type="bold">Calculated personal income for the year. </em>1.6 Gain on the realisation of plots of land in agriculture/forestry that is not to be included in personal income. (Amount transferred from form RF-1177 item 453)-1.18 Negative calculated personal income from previous years (negative calculated personal income from an <span type="quote" xml:lang="nno">«ANS/DA/KS»</span> cannot be carried forward) --1.22 Addition for negative calculated personal income that can be coordinated with a share of the proceeds from fishing this year – see RF-1213 item 118++ </p>
<p>If the result is less than zero, this is the calculated negative personal income that can be carried forward for deduction in subsequent years. (Negative calculated personal income is not to be entered in the tax return)1.24 Information item (for those who choose not to use item 1.18 to reduce positive calculated personal income by carrying forward negative calculated income from previous years) – see the guidelines</p>
<p>Postal district</p>
<p>Business address (street address)</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">Date</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Signature</p>
<p>Name of accountant</p>
<p>Issued by the Directorate of Taxes pursuant to the Ministry of Finance’s delegation decision of 28 November 1994, cf. the Tax Assessment Act section 4-4 no 7. Reference is made to a separate set of guidelines (RF-1225) drawn up as an aid to completing the Form for the calculation of personal income (RF-1224).</p>
<p xml:lang="fra"><em type="bold">Signature </em></p>
<p xml:lang="spa">Postal code</p>
<p>Balance group A: Office machinery etc.</p>
<p>Balance group B: Acquired goodwill</p>
<p>Balance group C: Articulated lorries, lorries etc.</p>
<p>Balance group D: Passenger cars, tractors etc.</p>
<p>Balance group E: Ships, vessels etc.</p>
<p>Balance group F: Airplanes and helicopters</p>
<p>Balance group H: Buildings and installations etc.</p>
<p>Balance group I: Commercial premises2.2 Non-depreciable operating equipment2.3 Other acquired intangible rights2.4 Capitalised research and development expenses2.5 Goods (incl. livestock)/ goods under production2.6 Trade debtors2.7 Trade creditors/ advance payments from customers2.8 Total2.9 Total basis for risk-free return (opening + closing values from item 2.8) / 2)method</p>
<p>Opening value++++++++++++=÷</p>
<p>Depreciable operating equipment2.1++++++++++++=÷=</p>
<p>Operating equipment for which straight-line depreciation is used++</p>
<p>Balance group G: Systems for the transmission and distribution of electrical power etc. ++2.10 Enterprise debt to financial institutions and enterprise debt relating to multiple debt instruments. See the guidelines.</p>
<p>Opening value(Open. + clos. value) / 2</p>
<p>The amount shall be transferred to item 1.8 a. If the enterprise was only active during part of the year, the amount shall be transferred to item 2.12.=</p>
<p>Closing value</p>
<p>Closing value2.11 Total2.12=12</p>
<p>If the enterprise was only active during part of the income year, a proportionate share of the deductible risk-free return shall be calculated. Only whole months are included. The amount is transferred to item 1.8 a.</p>
<p>Transferred from item x no of whole months12÷</p>
<p>Balance group J: Fixed technical installations in buildings++</p>
</body></document>
