<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The new coronavirus (COVID-19)</title><genre code="facta"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="FHI" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>357</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>https://www.fhi.no/contentassets/37298bcaf6724377b68018cfd7db4309/vedlegg/english_generell-informasjon-korona.pdf</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 180635 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>The new coronavirus (COVID-19)</p>
<p>The new coronavirus is attracting a lot of attention. Coronavirus disease normal y only gives rise to mild symptoms. Some people, especially the elderly and those who are already il , can become very il . it is therefore vital that everyone helps to slow the spread of infection through the population.</p>
<p>If you have been infected, it can take 0 to 14 days for symptoms to become apparent. It normally takes 5 to 6 days. People are most contagious while they are experiencing symptoms. Fever, coughing and difficulty breathing are the most common symptoms. Some people develop pneumonia, breathing difficulties or other serious il nesses.</p>
<p>Advice for preventing infection:</p>
<p>Keep your distance! </p>
<p>Stay at home if you feel il . </p>
<p>Stay at home if you have been told to (in quarantine or isolation). </p>
<p>If possible, try to maintain at least one metre between yourself and other people.</p>
<p>Practise good hand hygiene! </p>
<p>Wash your hands often and thoroughly  when you been around other people  when you have been to the toilet  when you have coughed, sneezed or blown your nose  before cooking or eating. </p>
<p>Use a disinfectant if no soap and water are available.</p>
<p>Practise good respiratory hygiene! </p>
<p>Avoid coughing or sneezing on other people. </p>
<p>Cough into a paper tissue and then discard the tissue. Wash your hands afterwards! </p>
<p>If you do not have a paper tissue handy, cough into your bent elbow.</p>
<p>If you think you have been infected: </p>
<p>If you suspect you are infected, you must stay at home. </p>
<p>If you are in need of medical assistance, you should first try to contact your doctor by phone. If this is not possible, cal the emergency medical service on 116 117.</p>
<p>Keep yourself updated! </p>
<p>The authorities are asking everyone living or staying in Norway to read the important information and advice provided about coronavirus at www.fhi.no and www.helsenorge.no. This advice is updated regularly. The information is available in both Norwegian and English. If you find it difficult to understand anything, please ask someone you know for help.</p>
</body></document>
