<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>What is a safe distance from other people?</title><genre code="facta"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="FHI" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>497</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>https://www.fhi.no/contentassets/cdd1659c32fd45ecb84aee903cd0ef33/vedlegg/engelsk_-litt-mye-eller-helt-avstand2.pdf</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 180635 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>Litt, mye eller helt avstand? Språk: Engelsk Opprettet: 03/2020 Endret: 16.05.20</p>
<p>What is a safe distance from other people? By maintaining a safe distance from others, we help to slow the spread of coronavirus (COVID-19) <em type="bold">1) General advice for the population </em> People who live together can continue to socialise in the normal way.  You can have visitors, but only a few people at a time.  You can go out, but you should keep a safe distance from other people.  Healthy children can socialise together in small groups.  Remember good hand and cough hygiene!  Do not shake hands or hug anyone other than those you live with.  Show consideration for others; do not stigmatise or shut anyone out. <em type="bold">2) To those at risk </em> The measures being implemented to combat COVID-19 are primarily aimed at protecting those at risk from infection.  Anyone who is at risk must be particularly thorough with their hygiene and maintain a safe distance from others. <em type="bold">3) For anyone who feels well but has been placed in HOME </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">QUARANTINE </em><em type="bold">after travelling or because they have been in close contact with someone who has tested positive for COVID-19 </em> You can socialise normally with people you live with, but you should avoid having visitors.  Do not go to school or work.  Do not travel by public transport.  You can go for a walk provided you maintain a safe distance from other people.  You can go to the grocery store or pharmacy if absolutely necessary.  The people you live with are not in quarantine.  A negative test will not shorten the quarantine period.  You may be partially exempt if you are a key worker.  You must self-isolate immediately if you are experiencing the symptoms of a respiratory infection after having been in close contact with someone else. </p>
<p>Litt, mye eller helt avstand? Språk: Engelsk Opprettet: 03/2020 Endret: 16.05.20 <em type="bold">4) For anyone who has a RESPIRATORY INFECTION but has not </em><em type="bold">tested positive for COVID-19 </em> You must stay at home as soon as you notice the symptoms of a respiratory infection until at least 24 hours after you have completely recovered.  Maintain a safe distance from everyone else in your home.  The people you live with are not in quarantine, but they should monitor their own health. If they experience any symptoms, they should stay at home as well. <em type="bold">5) For anyone who has tested positive for COVID-19 and has </em><em type="bold">been placed in SELF-ISOLATION </em> You must not leave your home.  Maintain a safe distance from everyone else in your home.  Use a separate room and bathroom wherever possible.  Wash surfaces frequently.  Ask someone else to do your shopping.  Agree with your doctor how you should monitor your health.  The people you live with must go into quarantine. </p>
<p><em type="bold">For more translated information about COVID-19, see: </em> https://www.fhi.no/nettpub/coronavirus/fakta/generell-informasjon-koronavirus-pa-flere- sprak/  https://www.fhi.no/nettpub/coronavirus/rad-til-personer-som-er-smittet-eller-har-vart- utsatt-for-smitte/informasjon-om-hjemmekarantene-og-isolasjon-pa-ulike-sprak/  https://helsenorge.no/koronavirus/informasjon-pa-andre-sprak </p>
</body></document>
