<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title/>
    <genre code="science"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <wordcount>6161</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <license type="standard"/>
    </availability>
    <multilingual/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="5.sohkabeal.pdf"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p><em type="bold">4  A Gender Perspective on Sami Statistics </em></p>
    <p>This chapter builds on excerpts from a series of articles on Sami society published in <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller 1,2 and 3. </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"><em type="bold">The  excerpts  come  from  chapters  written  by  Svanhild  Andersen,  Torunn  Pettersen, Magritt Brustad, Øyvind Rustad, Jon Todal and Yngve Johansen. </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Summary </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">We  see  an  uneven  gender  distribution  in  STN-areas  (Sami  Parliament  subsidy  schemes  for business development) in a range of fields. In these areas, there is an excess of women only in the 80 and older age category. Based on data from 2001-2005, the probability of reaching the age  of  75  for  15  year  olds  in  STN-areas  is  about  56%  for  men  and  80%  for  women. Approximately  5%  of  the  population  received  disability  benefits  between  2004  and  2008, slightly  more  men  than  women.  In  2004,  2.1%  of  men  and  1.2%  of  women  received  social security  benefits.  In  reindeer  herding  and  agricultural  areas,  80%  of  men  are  either siidainnehavere  (siida  proprietors)  or  main  users,  and  97%  have  their  main  employment  in fisheries.  The  register  of  voters  has  shown  a  small  but  clear  majority  of  men  in  all  Sami Parliament votes, and in 2009 only the constituency of ‘Sør-Norge’ had a majority of women voters. In 2009, there was a marked majority of women voters between the age of 18 and 29. In the 2010/11 school year, almost 10% more girls than boys were learning Sami as a First of Second  Language  at  the  primary  and  lower  secondary  level.  At  the  high  school  level,  the difference had risen to almost 12%. In STN-areas, 13% more women than men have more than three years of post-secondary education. Boys in STN-areas have a higher high school dropout rate,  especially  for  those  in  vocational  programs,  where  only  about  a  fourth  of  students complete their education within five years.   </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.1  Introduction </em></p>
    <p>This chapter looks at some of the chapters published in <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller 1,2 and 3 </em>as well as some more current information. The goal of the chapter is to focus on gender differences in a variety of fields, within the mandate given by the Sami Parliament and the then Ministry of Employment  and  Inclusion.  The  chapter  is  about  the  following  themes:  <em type="italic">Population Development</em>,  with  excerpts  from  articles  in  <em type="italic">Samiske  tall  forteller</em>  <em type="italic">1</em>  written  by  Svanhild Andersen and Torunn Pettersen and <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller 3</em> by Øivind Rustad, <em type="italic">health</em>, with an excerpt from Magritt Brustad’s article in <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller 2</em>, <em type="italic">Register of voters</em> based on Torunn Pettersen’s article in <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller 3</em>, <em type="italic">disability and social security benefits</em> by Magritt  Brustad  in  <em type="italic">Samiske  tall  forteller  2</em>,  <em type="italic">choice  of  Sami  language  in  primary,  lower secondary  and  upper  secondary  school</em>  by  Jon  Todal  in  <em type="italic">Samiske  tall  forteller  2  and  3</em>,  and <em type="italic">education</em>  by  Yngve  Johansen  in  <em type="italic">Samiske  tall  forteller  2  and  3</em>.  This  chapter  was  edited  by Yngve Johansen and read by the various authors.  </p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.2  Population Development in STN Areas According to Gender </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Summary </em></p>
    <p>The population of STN-areas has decreased by 16% over the last 20 years. There is a majority</p>
    <p>of men in all age categories between the ages of 10 and 79, while there is a majority of women</p>
    <p>in age categories over 80. The difference between the number of men and women is greatest in</p>
    <p>the  age  group  50-59.  Net  migration  in  STN-areas  from  2007-2009  was  450  men  and  560</p>
    <p>women.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.2.1 Introduction </em></p>
    <p>The  population  for  STN-areas  has  decreased  by  16%  over  the  last  20  years.  Over  the  same period, the population of Norway increased by 15%. This development is especially pronounced in Vest-Finnmark, while not so marked in Indre Finnmark. Migration away from STN-areas, with an insufficient migration to STN-areas, is one of the main reasons for the decrease. This leads to fewer births because young people are moving out and starting a family in other places. After the turn of the millennium, in contrast to the 1990’s, there have been more deaths than births  in  STN-areas.  Migration  and  low  birth  rates  result  in  an  aging  population  with  an increasing average age because not enough younger people are moving into the areas.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.2.2 Age Composition in STN-Areas According to Gender </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Figure 4.1 Population in STN-areas, according to gender and age, 2007 </em>The  portion  of  women  in  STN-areas  is  lower  than  the  average  for  the  rest  of  the  country, especially in the 20-29 year old age group. STN-areas also have a lower portion of children in the 0-9 age group and a higher portion of people over the age of 50. There is a majority of men in  STN-areas  in  all  age  categories  from  10-19  to  70-79  years  of  age.  There  is  a  majority  of women only in the over-80 age category. The majority of men is greatest in the 50-59 years of age category. </p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.1 Areas with the Greatest Majority of Men 16-67 years of age, 2010 </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Greatest Majority of Men STN        Greatest Majority</p>
    <p>of Men, Remaining</p>
    <p>(Norway = 51.0 percent)     (Norway  =  51.0</p>
    <p>percent)</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">(STN = 53.6 percent)     (øvrig = 51.8</p>
    <p>percent)</p>
    <p>Extract of STN-areas    Extract  of  municipalities</p>
    <p>outside STN-areas north of</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Saltfjellet</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">Måsøy 59,3   Hasvik 55,8</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">Tromsø 58,6   Moskenes 54,8</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Evenes 56,3   Karlsøy 54,2</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Loppa 55,6   Berg 54,1</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">Nordkapp 55,3   Vardø 53,9</p>
    <p xml:lang="est">Alta 55,3   Ibestad 53,5</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">Gratangen 54,8   Målselv 53,5</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Tysfjord 54,7   Beiarn 53,2</p>
    <p xml:lang="sme">Gáivuotna/Kåfjord 54,2   Sørfold 53,2</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">Kvænangen 54,1   Balsfjord 53,1</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Narvik 54,1   Røst 52,9</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">Meløy 52,8</p>
    <p>Other areas within STN</p>
    <p>municipalities    Torsken 52,6</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">Bardu 52,5</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">Lebesby 55,6   Steigen 52,4</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">Nordkapp 53,3   Salangen 52,2</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">Hamarøy 52,5   Ballangen  52,2</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">Narvik 51,5   Tranøy 52,0</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">Måsøy 51,2   Dyrøy 52,0</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Sørreisa 50,8</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Sør-Varanger 50,2</p>
    <p>Evenes 49,0         Table 4.1 shows the number of men and women between the ages of 16 and 67. This age group is chosen to reflect the ‘adult’ population in the various regions. Because women have a higher life expectancy than men, there is an increasing majority of women in the age groups over 67. In the younger age groups, there is a small majority of men because more boys are born than girls.</p>
    <p>The table shows a ranked extract of the areas. In STN-areas, between 59 and 52 % were men, while in other areas in the same municipalities, there was a lower portion of men, between 56 and 49%. In five of the remaining areas, the male portion of the population is lower than in all STN-areas. The difference was especially pronounced in Måsøy and Evenes. Måsøy has 59% men in STN-areas versus 51% in the rest of the municipality. Evenes has 56% men in STNareas and 49% in the rest of the municipality. These two municipalities, which had a majority of men in STN-areas, had some of the lowest populations of men. The municipality of Lebesby constitutes the only exception. The proportion of men to women in this STN-area was lower than in the rest of the municipality, 54% versus 56%.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.2.3 Migration out of STN-Areas </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.2  Net Migration from STN-Areas from 2007 to 2009, by Gender </em></p>
    <p> <em type="bold">Men Women </em></p>
    <p>Total 2007 - 2009<em type="bold"> </em>450<em type="bold"> </em>560<em type="bold"> </em></p>
    <p>The  distribution  of  men  and  women  varies  from  year  to  year.  To  avoid  random  variation, numbers for the last three years are combined. Between 2007 and 2009, 4,460 people moved into  STN-areas  and  5,470  moved  out.  This  resulted  in  a  net  population  loss  of  1,010.  Net migration among men was 450 and 560 for women. In other words, more women moved out of STN-areas than men. The difference between genders was especially marked in 2009 where 190 women versus 120 men moved. In 2007, net migration of women was also 190 versus 140 for men. The exception was 2008, where more men left than women, 200 versus 180. Numbers according to citizenship are not shown in the above overview but foreign citizens had almost the same ratios of men and women leaving and settling in the areas. Of 1010 people who left the  area,  70  were  foreign,  while  940  were  Norwegians.  In  this  period,  the  net  migration  of women  has  been  markedly  greater  than  that  of  men  in  Øst-Finnmark,  Vest-Finnmark  and Nordre Nordland.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.3  Reindeer Herding, Agriculture and Fisheries in STNAreas by Gender </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Summary </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">In STN-areas, 80% of men are siida-proprietors in reindeer herding and main users in farming. Ninety-seven percent of those who have their main employment in the fisheries are men. This numbers has been stable over the last six years.  </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.3.1 Introduction </em></p>
    <p>This  chapter  presents  data  showing  the  gender  distribution  in  primary  industries  in  Sami communities; limited to reindeer husbandry, agriculture and fisheries.  Data is also presented for several periods in STN-areas north of Saltfjellet.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"><em type="bold">4.3.2 Reindeer Herding by Gender   </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.3  Siida-innehavere* in Norway, by gender and percent in 2000 and </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="nob"> <em type="bold">Men Women Total </em>N % N % N </p>
    <p>*A <em type="italic">siida</em> consists of several <em type="italic">siida-andeler</em> which are defined as ‘a family group or individual who is part of a </p>
    <p><em type="italic">siida</em>, and is involved in reindeer herding under the leadership of an individual or jointly with a spouse or </p>
    <p>common-law partner’ (Reindeer Herding Act 2007).</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.4  Individuals Involved in Reindeer Herding, by gender and percent</em> </p>
    <p xml:lang="nob"> <em type="bold">Men Women Total </em>N % N % N  1 512  51.9 1 402 48.1 2 914  1 463   1 352  2 815  1 563  51.9 1 449 48.1 3 012 </p>
    <p>The portion of women among <em type="italic">siida-andel</em> proprietors appears to have decreased in recent years. In 2000, there were 100 women making up 18% of the 578 <em type="italic">siida-andels </em>proprietors. In 2008, </p>
    <p>the portion of women was 13% (70 of 553). In the same year, women owned 24% of the total number of reindeer. There was relatively little difference between the various reindeer pastures: Vest-Finnmark had the largest number of reindeer with women as owners  – 27 percent, and Nordland had the lowest with 19 percent.</p>
    <p>Gender distribution among the total number of people in <em type="italic">siida-andelene</em> is more balanced than among  <em type="italic">siida-andelsinnehaverne</em>.  In  the  period  2005-2009  the  gender  distribution  was  52/48 percent  (men/women)  in  <em type="italic">siida-andelene</em>,  with  a  small  variation  in  Finnmark:  52/48,  Troms: 57/47 and the rest of the country: 48/52. </p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.3.3  Agriculture by Gender </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.5  Percentage Distribution of Main Land Users in 1989 and 2007</em> </p>
    <p>Men    Women   Non-personal users*</p>
    <p>* Municipalities, counties, institutions</p>
    <p>The number of homestead in STN areas has decreased by 62 percent. Most main users are men (81%  in  1989  and  76%  in  2007).  The  number  of  women  main  users  has  increased  by  2 percentage  points  in  this  period,  while  non-individual  users  (for  example  municipalities, counties or institutions) increased by 3%.</p>
    <p>The average age for both men and women decreased in the same period, from 51.6 to 49.7 for men and from 54.3 to 48.6 for women.3</p>
    <p> Gender distribution figures among <em type="italic">innehavere av driftsenheter (operational unit proprietors)/siida-andeler</em> for </p>
    <p>2000 and 2008 are probably not wholly comparable. There is no category for joint operational units in the <em type="italic">Totalregnskapet</em> 2000 as in the comparable accounting for 2008; the category of spouse, which appears first in the report (see p.95 and table 7.2.4 in <em type="italic">Totalregnskapet</em> 2000 and p. 101 in <em type="italic">Totalregnskapet</em> 2008), is divided into the categories man and woman in 2000. See for example <em type="italic">Ressursregnskaper</em> 2007/08, p. 52 for information regarding measure to strengthen women’s participation in reindeer husbandry and youth recruitment. </p>
    <p>Table 47 in statistikkbanken, tema samer. SSB.  Table 62 (Jordbruksbdrifter, by main user and average age for main users in STN-areas). Samisk statistikk</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">2008, SSB.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.3.4  Fisheries by Gender   </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.6  Number of Fishers living in STN-Areas, by Gender and Participation</em> </p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"> <em type="bold">Main Profession Side Profession Total </em>Men Women Men Women Men Women N % N % N % N % N % N % </p>
    <p>As of  31.12.2004  97.7  13 2.3  319  92.7  7.3  867  95.8  4.2 As of  31.12.2008  97.0  16 3.0  235  94.4  5.6  751  96.2  3.8</p>
    <p>Men  dominate  the  fisheries  in  STN-areas,  especially  when  considering  main  employment. Around 97% of fishers are men, and this number has been very similar in 2004 and 2008. The number of women who had fisher as a side job has nearly halved in the same period, but also the number of men. This number has decreased significantly in the same period. In 2008, 5.6% of those who had fisher as a side job were women versus 7.3% for men.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.5  Gender Difference in Health Statistics </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.4.1   Introduction  </em></p>
    <p>In this chapter, data from published works regarding medical examinations among the Sami in Norway is presented and discussed. The chapter focuses on health statistics regarding incidence of  disease  and  disease  risk  factors  in  the  population.  The  results  are  presented  according  to gender as well as Sami ethnicity.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.4.2   Mortality </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Summary </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">There is a higher incidence of death due to cerebral haemorrhage among Sami women and </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">death due to accidents and suicide among Sami men. Women living in inland Sami areas </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">have  had  a  low  and  steady  mortality  rate.  There  reason  to  be  concerned  about  the  high </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">mortality rate among young men in the Sami areas. </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">4.4.2.1   Introduction  </em></p>
    <p>Mortality  rates  have  been  used  as  a  way  to  measure  of  a  population’s  living  conditions  and health. Mortality rates can be presented in various manners. The most common is number of deaths per 1000 or 100,000 inhabitants in different age groups.</p>
    <p>In Norway, women still live longer than men, but the differences between the genders in steadily decreasing. From 2009 to 2010, life expectancy at birth increased by 0.1 years for women and 0.3 years for men, to 83.2 and 78.9 years respectively. Over the last 25 years, life expectancy has increased by nearly six years for men and a little over three years for women. The difference between life expectancies for men and women has decreased by a little over 2.5%.</p>
    <p><em type="italic">4.4.2.2  Mortality Rates by Gender and Residence </em></p>
    <p>Juxtaposing the mortality rates in the period 1970-1998 and 1970 ethnicity census reports has shown  a  slightly  higher  mortality  rate  for  Sami  men  (6%)  and  women  (10%)  than  for  the regional  reference  population.  Higher  death  rates  due  to  cerebral  haemorrhaging,  especially among women, may explain some of these differences. Men had a higher incidence of so-called violent deaths, especially accidents and suicide</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Figure 4.2  Probability of reaching the age of 75 for 15 year olds nationally and in STN-areas coast and inland, based on mortality rates from various periods for men and women.</em>                                  </p>
    <p>Sourc<em type="italic">e: Brustad et al 2009, Scandinavian Journal of Public Health.</em> </p>
    <p>Men National</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Men – STN-coast</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Men – STN-inland</p>
    <p>Women - National</p>
    <p>Women – STN-coast</p>
    <p>Women – STN-inland</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">1991-19951996-20002001-2005</p>
    <p>Figure 4.2 shows the calculated probability of women and men reaching the age of 75 for 15 year-olds,  based  on  mortality  rate  patterns  in  the  various  periods.  The  figures  distinguish between the rates for those living within and outside STN-areas as well as coast and inland.</p>
    <p>The figures also show no significant difference between geographical areas or periods. For men, however,  there  has  been  an  increase  in  life  expectancy,  which  can  be  explained  by  the decreasing rates of heart and cardiovascular mortality, which have struck men to a great degree than women. Furthermore, the mortality rate for men in STN-areas has been slightly higher than the national average. This is possibly explained by the high mortality rate due to ‘violent death’ in STN areas.  Generally, one can say that mortality rates in Sami areas are very similar to mortality rates in the  non-Sami  portion  of  the  population.  This  may  indicate  that  mortality  rate  patterns  have evened  out  between  areas  with  low  versus  high  density  of  Sami  populations.  This  has  been explained by similar living conditions, education and health care, which is in contrast to the situation for other indigenous populations in circumpolar areas.  There is still reason to be concerned about the relatively high mortality rate among young men in Sami areas.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.4.3   Smoking </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Summary </em></p>
    <p>Studies show a higher rate of smoking among Sami men living inland than among non-Samis. Similar patterns have not been found for women.</p>
    <p><em type="italic">4.4.3.1 Introduction </em></p>
    <p>Smoking  increases  the  risk  of  a  long  list  of  diseases  such  as  lung  cancer,  heart  and cardiovascular  disease  and  chronic  lung  disease.  The  Central  Bureau  for  Statistics  (SSB) conducts annual studies on the use of tobacco. In 1973, over half of adult men smoked, while in 2006, about 21% did  so. The number of daily smokers among women has also decreased from 32% in 1973 to 22% in 2006.</p>
    <p>Nineteen percent  people between the  ages  of 16  and 74 answered that they smoked daily in 2010. The number was the same for men and women. The change last  year dovetails with a pattern we have seen over time, a steady decrease in the number of daily smokers. Men’s and women’s smoking habits were different up until the turn of the millennium, but have since had a  common  falling  curve.  Approximately  a  third  of  women  smoked  daily  in  the  last  decades before 2000. Among men, however, there has been a downward trend for the whole period since 1973, when over half smoked daily. Earlier population studies have shown a higher incidence of daily smokers in Finnmark compared to other counties in Norway. Figures for 2004-2008 show that the number of daily smokers varies greatly from county to county. According to SSB, the lowest number of daily smokers is in Oslo with 19%, and the highest in Finnmark with 32%.</p>
    <p>Violent death is defined as death due to accident, suicide or homicide.</p>
    <p><em type="italic">4.4.3.2 Smoking Relative to Gender and Ethnicity </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Figure 4.3 Smoking Habits for men and women according to Ethnicity based on Data </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">from the SAMINOR study 2003/04. (Sami I = three generations of Sami language, Sami II = at least one Sami indicator such as language or family </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">background.)                                                                                                     </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Source: Broderstad et al. 2007 European Journal of Haematology<em type="bold"> </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="isl">Daily smoker</p>
    <p>Has never smoked</p>
    <p xml:lang="fin">M - Sami I M - Sami II M - nonSami</p>
    <p xml:lang="fin">*W - Sami I W - Sami II W - nonSami</p>
    <p xml:lang="deu">MenWomen</p>
    <p>Generally, great differences in smoking habits have not been demonstrated between Sami and Norwegians, for either adults or youth. For men, studies have shown a slightly higher incidence of smoking among inland Samis than non-Samis. No corresponding trends have been found for women.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.4.4 Alcohol </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Summary </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Both Sami men and women have reported a higher rate of total abstinence from alcohol than non-Samis in Norway. This pattern is especially pronounced among elderly Sami women. </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">4.4.4.1  Introduction </em></p>
    <p>Alcohols  is  the  most  widespread  stimulant  used  by  the  population  and  in  all  likelihood  the stimulant that involves the greatest amount of abuse. Additionally, the consumption of alcohol contributes to an increased risk of accident, injury and death. The total use of alcohol in Norway has increased since 1990, from 4.55 litres per capita in 1993 to 6.37 litres in 2005. The consumption of beer and wine has increased the most over the last 20 years. The increase in the sales of wine has been linked to a so-called ‘continental’ drinking pattern where one drinks often but consumes less per drinking situation. These habits have not replaced, but come in addition to, the Nordic patterns of weekend drunkenness and intoxication.</p>
    <p><em type="italic">4.4.4.2  Alcohol Use relative to Gender and Ethnicity </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Figure 4.4  Alcohol Use in Men and Women according to Ethnicity (SAMINOR study 2003-04). (Sami I = three generations of Sami language, Sami II = at least one Sami indicator such as language or family background.)                           </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="nob"><em type="italic">Source: Broderstad et al 2007 European Journal of Haematology</em> </p>
    <p>Total abstention/not drink in the last year</p>
    <p>Drinks more than twice a week</p>
    <p xml:lang="fin">M-Sami I M-Sami II M - nonSami</p>
    <p xml:lang="fin">*W - Sami I W - Sami II</p>
    <p xml:lang="kal">W - nonSami</p>
    <p xml:lang="deu">WomenMen</p>
    <p>Based  on  data  from  the  SAMINOR  study*,  ethnic  differences  have  been  shown  in  the consumption of alcohol. The figures show that the number of those who answered that  they ‘abstained totally from alcohol’ or ‘didn’t drink over the last year’, was quite a bit higher among</p>
    <p>Sami men and women. The number of respondents who said they drank more than twice a week was a bit lower among Samis with three generations of Sami language than for the other groups. The trend of lower alcohol consumption was more pronounced among Sami women than men.</p>
    <p>*A  2003-2004  Health  and  living  conditions  study  conducted  in  areas  with  mixed  Sami  and  Norwegian communities. The survey was conducted by the Centre for Research on Sami Health, University of Tromsø, in cooperation with the Norwegian Institute of Public Health. <em type="bold"> </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.4.5 Prescription Drug Use </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Summary </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Use of soporifics in the Sami population corresponds to half the amount used by the Norwegian population, with Sami men showing 13% less use than Sami women. </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">4.4.5.1   Introduction </em></p>
    <p>Use of prescription drugs in a particular population is, to a certain extent, an indicator of the presence of disease or illness. Research has also shown that use of prescription drugs can be explained by various lifestyle factors and use of medical services.</p>
    <p><em type="italic">4.4.5.2  Sleeping Problems and use of Soporifics by Gender and Ethnicity </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.7  Use of prescription drugs by ethnicity in Finnmark (n=11061). Figures given in percent. 1987-1988</em>.                                                                                                                  </p>
    <p xml:lang="nob"><em type="italic">Source: Furu K, 1997. Journal of Clinical Epidemiology  </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Ethnicity Men  Women  </em> </p>
    <p><em type="italic">Norwegian </em>43,4  56,9   </p>
    <p xml:lang="kal"><em type="italic">Finnish </em>42,4  58,4   </p>
    <p xml:lang="smn"><em type="italic">Sami </em>43,0  54,9   <em type="italic">Sami/Finnnish </em>49,4  58,9   </p>
    <p>According to research conducted by the Norwegian Institute of Public Health, use of soporifics is relatively common in Norway. Only one study has looked into the use of soporifics among Samis. This study is based on data from the SAMINOR, Health and Living Conditions Survey in areas with mixed Sami and Norwegian communities.</p>
    <p>Prescription drugs are defined as substances designed or prescribed for the treatment or prevention of disease or</p>
    <p>illness. In order to market a substance as a medicine, one must document the effect, safety and technical quality of the product. (Source: www.lovdata.no</p>
    <p>The number of respondents reporting sleeping problems was lower in the Sami population than in the non-Sami. Use of soporifics in the Sami population corresponded to half the amount used in the Norwegian population. The lowest use was found  among those who had the strongest Sami ties who lived in Finnmark.</p>
    <p>Regardless of ethnicity, women used twice as much soporifics as men. The study concludes by saying that the stronger the ties to the Sami community, the lower the use of soporifics. The incidence of sleeping problems is considered to be lower in the Sami population.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.5  Disability and Social Benefits by Gender and Age   </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Summary </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">In the period 2004-2008, a little over 5% of the population of STN-areas between 20 and 66 years of age received disability benefits, slightly more men than women. In 2004, 2.1% of men and 1.2% of women in STN-areas received social benefits</em>.  </p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.5.1 Introduction </em></p>
    <p>Norway has had an increase in the number of people receiving disability pensions. At the end of 2008, there were approximately 340,000 people receiving disability benefits in Norway. That is 70,000 more than in 1999. Some of this increase can be attributed to an aging population, but even  with  adjustment  for  age,  this  is  a  pronounced  increase.  After  the  institution  of  time limitations for disability benefits in 2004, a relatively strong increase in the number of people receiving disability benefits has been registered.  The increase has been greatest among those under the age of 40 (Bjørngaard et al., 2009).</p>
    <p>In 2008, 109,300 people received economic social benefits in Norway. The number of those receiving social benefits reached an apex of 165,000 in 1993, and has since decreased. From 2007 to 2008, the decline has diminished.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.5.2 Disability by Gender and Age </em></p>
    <p>A disability pension is a legally established social security benefit in Norway. The purpose of the pension is to ensure a subsistence income for people whose earning ability has been</p>
    <p>permanently reduced due to illness, injury or disability (NAV, 2010).</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.8  New recipients (per 1000) of Disability Benefits in STN-areas for various periods, men and women </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="est">Age</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Period </em>1994–1998* 1999–2003** 2004–2008*** Men Women Men Women Men Women 20–30 years 11,7 12,5 10,1 7,7 5,0 8,4 31-45 years 37,9 44,9 33,1 37,8 18,5 18,6 46-66 years 109,2 106,0 121,7 106,5 104,7 96,3 Total 20-66 years 55,9 57,7 63,8 58,6 54,9 51,9 </p>
    <p>*     The period goes from February 1994 to January 1999. **   The period goes from February 1999 to January 2004. *** The period goes from February 2004 to December 2008.</p>
    <p>Table 4.8 shows new disability benefits recipients in five-year intervals from 1994 up to and including 2008. It appears that outside of STN-areas, especially in the oldest age group, women accounted for  a somewhat  larger number of new disability cases.  This  difference appears to have evened out in the last period.</p>
    <p>For men in STN-areas, the numbers are higher than outside STN-areas in all the age groups for all periods. In the 45 years and under age group, the number of new recipients between 2004 and 2008 has almost been halved compared to the two previous five-year periods. There has also been a decrease in the 46-66 age category, but not as pronounced.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.5.3 Disability by Gender and Age </em></p>
    <p>Social  benefits  are  a  legally  established  scheme  to  ensure  that  all  have  sufficient  economic resources for subsistence. These benefits are meant to be temporary and should contribute to making the recipient economically self-sufficient (NAV, 2010).<em type="bold"> </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.9  Number of Social Benefits Recipients in Various Periods in STN-areas, men and women. Numbers given in percent.</em> </p>
    <p xml:lang="est">Age</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Period </em>January 1992 January 1999 January 2004 Men Women Men Women Men Women 20–30 years 2,6 2,1 2,1 2,0 2,6 2,0 31-45 years 2,3 1,6 2,4 1,2 2,4 1,5 46-66 years 1,2 0,6 0,9 0,7 1,5 0,5 Total 20-66 years 2,0 1,4 1,8 1,3 2,1 1,2 </p>
    <p>Table 4.9 shows that the number of new receipts of social benefits is markedly higher for those under the age of 30. It is lowest in the oldest age group. The number of recipients has gradually decreased over the last three time intervals shown in the table, for both men and women. This can be partly attributed to the decreasing unemployment rates for the same periods.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.6   Gender Distribution in the Sami Parliament’s Electoral Register </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Summary </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">The registry of voters for all Sami Parliament elections has had a small but stable majority of men.  However,  in  the  2009  election,  the  constituency  of  Sør-Norge  had  a  slight  majority  of women. Also in this election, a majority of women between the ages of 18 and 29 were registered to vote. </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">5.6.1 Introduction </em></p>
    <p>The Sami Parliament in Norway is a representational political body, elected and represented by Samis. In the parliament’s view, it is responsible for all matters that concern Sami people. Samis who  have  registered  in  the  Sami  Parliament’s  electoral  register  are  entitled  to  vote  and  are eligible for election.</p>
    <p>Pursuant to the Sami Act §2-6, one must declare that they perceive themselves as Sami and that either they or at least one parent, grandparent or great grandparent uses or has used Sami as a home language (The Sami Act, 1987). Six elections have been held since the establishment of the Sami Parliament in Norway in 1989. Sami Parliament election are conducted at the same time  as  Norwegian  parliamentary  elections  and  election  years  have  been  1989,  1993,  1997, 2001, 2005 and 2009.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">5.6.2 Gender Distribution, Total and by Constituency </em></p>
    <p>Reliable numbers for the first three elections are not available, but there has been a slight but stable majority of male voters over the last three elections.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.10  Gender Distribution in the Total Register of Voters for the 2001, 2005 and 2009 Elections  </em></p>
    <p> <em type="bold">Men Women Total Total </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Excess of </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="deu"><em type="bold">Percentage </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">Men </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Women </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">45,6</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">46,1</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">46,9</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Figure 4.5  Gender Distribution by Constituency - 2009 Register of Voters </em></p>
    <p>Figure  4.5  shows  that  in  the  2009  elections,  Sør-Norge  was  the  only  constituency  with  a majority of women voters.<em type="bold"> </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.6.3 Increasing Number of Women among the Younger Voters </em></p>
    <p>It is interesting to note that when considering both age and gender distribution, there appears to be a shift towards more women voters, especially in the younger age groups.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">1 Østre2 Ávjovári3 Nordre4 Gáisi5 Vesthavet6 Sørsamisk7 Sør-Norge</p>
    <p xml:lang="isl">Menn</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Kvinner</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Figure 4.6 Number  of  Women  in  Various  Age  Groups  in  2005  and  2009 Register of Voters  </em></p>
    <p>Figure 4.6 shows that in 2009, the Sami Parliament’s Register of Voters had a marked majority of women in  the  youngest  age segment, defined  as  the three age  groups  between 18 and 29 years of age. The other age groups still had a majority of men registered to vote in 2009, but the number of women, with one exception, has increased. The exception for this is women over the age of 60, where the portion of women is still relatively low and where the portion of men increased between the elections in 2005 and 2009.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.7  Choice of Sami Language in Primary and Lower Secondary as well as Upper Secondary School, by Gender </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Summary </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Nearly 10% more girls than boys were learning Sami as a first or second language at the </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">primary and lower secondary level in the 2010/11 school year. At the upper secondary level, </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">this difference had increased to 12%.  </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.7.1 Introduction </em></p>
    <p>With the introduction of Sami as a Second Language 2 and 3, the number of students learning Sami  at  the  primary  and  lower  secondary  level  has  gone  down  from  2,672  to  2,245  in  the 2010/11 school year. The decrease over the last four years has been 16%. See also chapter 2, <em type="italic">Sami Language at Day Care and School</em>, in this edition of <em type="italic">Samiske tall forteller</em>. </p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.7.2 Sami Language at the primary and lower Secondary Level, by Gender and Level </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.11  Students at the Primary and Lower Secondary Level Studying North, Lule and South Sami as a First Language or Second Language 2 or 3, school year 2006/07 and 2010/11, by Gender</em> </p>
    <p xml:lang="nob"> <em type="bold">2006/2007 2010/2011 </em>Boys Girls Total Boys Girls Total N % N %  N % N %  North  Sami  as  a  First Language </p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">51.2</p>
    <p>48.8 North Sami as a Second Language 2</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">42.2</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">57.8</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">42.3</p>
    <p>57.7 North Sami as a Second Language 3</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">38.4</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">61.6</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">38.8</p>
    <p>61.2 Lule  Sami  as  a  First Language</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">55.2</p>
    <p>44.8 Lule  Sami  as  a  Second Language 2</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">54.5</p>
    <p>45.5 Lule  Sami  as  a  Second Language 3</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">39.1</p>
    <p>60.9 South  Sami  as  a  First Language</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">33.3</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">66.7</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">36.8</p>
    <p>63.2 South Sami as a Second Language 2</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">47.4</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">52.6</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">45.2</p>
    <p>54.8 South Sami as a Second Language 3</p>
    <p>Total</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">46.8</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">53.2</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">45.3</p>
    <p>54.7 In the 2010/11 school year, nearly 10 percent more girls than boys were studying Sami at the primary  and  lower  secondary  school  level.  This  difference  has  increased  from  the  2006/07 school year. A small majority of boys chose Sami as a First Language but a larger majority of girls chose Sami as a Second Language 2 or 3.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.7.3 Sami Language at the Upper Secondary Level by Gender and Grade Level </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.12  Choice of Sami as a First or Second Language among Upper Secondary School Students in the country, by Gender</em> </p>
    <p>Table 4.12 shows that more  girls  than boys  choose Sami at  the upper secondary level,  even</p>
    <p>when compensating for Sami as a first Language. The difference between the number of boys</p>
    <p>and  girls  taking  Sami  as  a  second  language  is  still  significant,  where  almost  two  thirds  of students are girls. The reason for this can be that more girls than boys choose general studies,</p>
    <p>which may indicate that girls are more interested in theoretical fields of study. Generally, girls</p>
    <p>also show greater interest for languages.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob"> <em type="bold">2008-2009 School Year 2009/2010 School Year 2010/2011 School Year </em>Boys Girls Boys Girls Boys Girls N % N % N % N % N % N % First Language </p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">83  43.9 106  56.1 105  48.8 110  51.2 126  50.8 122  49.2</p>
    <p>Second Language</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">49  32.2 103  67.8 55  35.7 99  64.3 71  38.4 114  61.6</p>
    <p xml:lang="est">Totalt 132  38.7 209  61.3 160  43.3 209  56.7 197  45.5 236  54.5</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.8   Education among Women and Men in STN-Areas </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">Summary </em></p>
    <p><em type="italic">In STN-areas, approximately 13% more women than men have a post-secondary education of three years or more. At the upper secondary level, boys in STN-areas have a higher dropout rate than girls, especially among those pursuing vocational studies where only a little under a fourth of boys complete their education within five years.  </em></p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.8.1 Introduction </em></p>
    <p>This  chapter  examines  gender  differences  in  STN-areas  in  relation  to  completion  of  upper secondary schooling, educational  level  and current  level  of education  for students  who have started a foundation class in the years 1994 to 1996.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.8.2 Completion of Upper Secondary Education by Program </em></p>
    <p>Fifty-five percent of boys from STN-areas who began their vocational studies in 2003, and 20 percent of those in general studies, withdrew from their program within five years. Of the boys from STN-areas who started upper secondary school in 2003, over 40% quit their schooling. Among girls, the number was about 20%.</p>
    <p>A little over a quarter of boys and almost half of girls completed their vocational studies within five years. For general studies, the numbers are 70% and 78% respectively.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.13  Students who Started a Foundation Course for the first time in 2003  in  STN-Areas  and  Level  of  Upper  Secondary  Education After Five Years. Program and Gender. Percent. </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Program,  gender  and</p>
    <p>geographical area <em type="bold">School Start 2003 </em></p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Absolute</p>
    <p>Percent</p>
    <p>Number</p>
    <p>Total</p>
    <p>Completed in the standard amount of time Took longer than the standard amount of time to complete  Still studying at the upper secondary level Completed their studies but did not pass  Stopped without completing their studies</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">General Studies</p>
    <p>Men STN-areas  57.3 12.5   19.8</p>
    <p>Women STN-areas  58.3 19.4 5.6 10.2 6.5</p>
    <p>Vocational Studies</p>
    <p>Men STN-areas  11.0 16.0 12.0 6.0 55.0</p>
    <p>Women STN-areas  26.0 21.0 13.0 10.0 29.0</p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.8.3 Education Level </em></p>
    <p>The  proportion  of  working-age  women  (24  to  65  years)  with  a  post-secondary  education  is</p>
    <p>relatively high in STN-areas with sparse populations. The total amount is 2 percentage points</p>
    <p>higher than the average for the rest of the country.</p>
    <p>Men in STN-areas clearly have a lower level of education than the rest of the population. The</p>
    <p>portion of men who have completed an upper secondary education, and who live in densely-</p>
    <p>populated areas, is a whole 10 percentage points lower than the national average. The difference</p>
    <p>is smaller in sparsely populated areas, about 2 percentage points.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Table 4.14  Education Level for Men and Women 24 - 65 years of age living in STN-Areas in 2008. Percent.</em> </p>
    <p><em type="bold">Living 1/1-2008 with Education Level 1/10-2007 </em>Men Women </p>
    <p>Level of Education and Geography</p>
    <p>Densely Populated Area</p>
    <p>Spread-out Community</p>
    <p>Densely Populated Area</p>
    <p>Spread-out Community</p>
    <p>Lower Secondary Level     STN-area 27,9 37,6 23,4 31,9 Upper Secondary Level     STN-area 48,7 48,3 39,7 39,6 University and College     STN-area 23,4 14,2 36,9 28,5</p>
    <p><em type="bold">SSB’s definition of a densely populated area </em>A collection of residences is registered as a densely populated area when at least 200 people live  there,  and  the  distance  between  the  residences  does  not  normally  exceed  50  metres.  A distance greater than 50 metres is permitted in areas where residences shall not or cannot be built.  These  areas  can  be  parks,  sports  grounds,  industrial  areas  or  natural  obstacles  such  as rivers or arable land. Clusters of residences that naturally belong to the same densely populated area are included up to a distance of 400 metres from the core of the densely populated area. These are considered to be satellites of the core.    </p>
    <p><em type="bold">4.8.4   Current Levels of Education in STN-Areas for Students who Started a Foundation Course between 1994 and 1996 </em></p>
    <p>In STN areas, 54% of students who started their upper secondary education between 1994 and</p>
    <p>1996 completed their studies within five years. The completion rate was 45.5% for men and 62.5% for women.</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Figure 4.7  Education Level in STN-areas in 2009 for Men and Women who started Upper Secondary School between 1994 and 1996, those who completed their studies within five years and those who did not. Percent.</em> </p>
    <p>The figure shows to what extent completion of upper secondary within five years affects the education level attained later on. Over 60% of those who do not complete their studies within five years still do not have a craft or trade education when they are 30 years of age. Almost 50%  of  those  who  complete  their  upper  secondary  education  within  five  years  have  a  postsecondary education, compared to only 10% of those who not. Those who have completed their upper secondary education within five years, approximately 12% of both men and women, have a post-secondary education of five years or more. However, approximately 16% more women than men have a shorter post-secondary education. For those who did not complete their upper secondary education within five years, approximately 8% more women than men have a shorter post-secondary education.</p>
    <p xml:lang="deu"><em type="bold">References</em> </p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Sámi logut muitalit 1/Samiske tall forteller 1 (2008) Sámi allaskuvla, Sámi University College</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Sámi logut muitalit 2/Samiske tall forteller 2 (2009) Sámi allaskuvla, Sámi University College</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Sámi logut muitalit 3/Samiske tall forteller 3 (2010) Sámi allaskuvla, Sámi University College</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Statistisk sentralbyrå. (2008). Samisk statistikk/Sámi statistihkka 2008.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno">Statistisk sentralbyrå. (2010). Samisk statistikk/Sámi statistihkka 2010. Statistisk sentralbyrå: http://www.ssb.no/</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">100 %</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">90 %</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">80 %</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">70 %</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">60 %</p>
    <p>University/College level, short2</p>
    <p>University/College level, short</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">50 %</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">40 %</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">30 %</p>
    <p>Upper Secondary level</p>
    <p>Lower Secondary level</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">20 %</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">10 %</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">0 %</p>
    <p xml:lang="deu">MenWomenMenWomen</p>
    <p><em type="bold">Completed High School within 5 years</em> <em type="bold">Did not complete high school within 5 years</em> </p>
  </body>
</document>
