<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Sámi oahpahus – sámi dutkan – sámi ásahus Sámi allaskuvla 20 jagi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><person firstname="Jan Henry" lastname="Keskitalo" sex="m" born="" nationality="NO"/></author><author><person firstname="Kristine" lastname="Nystad" sex="f" born="" nationality="NO"/></author><author><person firstname="Torunn" lastname="Pettersen" sex="f" born="" nationality="NO"/></author><year>2009</year><wordcount>808</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual><language xml:lang="sme"/></multilingual><origFileName>http://samas.no/sites/default/files/jubileumsbok_sa_20_jagi_nett.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="ovdasanit_jubileumsbok.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 161400 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="sme"><em type="bold">Sámi oahpahus – sámi dutkan – sámi ásahus</em> <em type="bold">Sámi allaskuvla 20 jagi</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sámi allaskuvlla almmolaš rahpan dáhpáhuvai skábmamánu 1. beaivvi 1989. Dál leat 20 jagi vássán. 20-jagi ávvudeapmi lea vuogas dilálašvuohta čohkket ja čállit vássán dáhpáhusaid birra.</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Dát ávvugirji ii leat oaivvilduvvon Sámi allaskuvlla dievaslaš historján, muhto buktit ovdan soames vásáhusaid fágalaš ja hálddahuslaš bargguin. Seammás doaivut ávvogirjji addit duogáža árvvoštallat allaskuvlla otná dili ja boahtteáiggi hástalusaid ja vejolašvuođaid.</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Girjji esseaid ja artihkkaliid leat čállán Sámi allaskuvlla dála ja ovddeš rektorat, dála professorat ja guvttešvirgehasat ja allaskuvlla ovddeš guvttešvirgehasat. Sámi allaskuvlla ávvuduojár Jon Ole Andersen lea govvejuvvon dujiidisguin čiŋahan girjji ja Sámi allaskuvlla ávvuoahpaheaddji Edel Hætta Eriksen lea searvan juogadit iežas vásáhusaid ja jurdagiid ávvogirjji lohkkiiguin.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Sámi education – Sámi research – Sámi institution</em> <em type="bold">Sámi University College 20 years</em> </p>
<p>The official opening of the Sámi University College took place on November 1st 1989. 20 years have now passed.  This 20-year anniversary is an appropriate occasion for collecting stories and writing about past events.</p>
<p>Even though this anniversary book is not intended to represent the entire history of the Sámi University College, it still brings forward a few stories from the academic- and administrative worlds. We hope that the texts, in the context of past events, will provide an opportunity to critically assess the present situation of the Sámi University College and its future challenges and possibilities.</p>
<p>The essays and articles are written by current and previous Rectors, current professors and adjunct professors II, as well as the previous adjunct assistant professors of the Sámi University College. The Sámi University College Honorary Teacher Edel Hætta Eriksen shares her experiences and thoughts with the readers in the book, which has been illustrated with photographs of the works of the Sámi University College Honorary Duojár (arts and crafts artist) Jon Ole Andersen.</p>
<p>ISBN 978-82-7367-022-9</p>
<p>Preface</p>
<p>Sámi education – Sámi research – Sámi institution</p>
<p>The official opening of the Sámi University College took place on November 1st 1989. This occasion meant that a long time wish among the Sámi people to have a Sámi teacher training program was fulfilled. This was later followed by the creation of other higher education programs taught in a Sámi language in a Sámi setting. An independent Sámi University College also provided opportunities to develop educational alternatives better suited to meet the needs of the Sámi communities.</p>
<p>20 years have now passed.</p>
<p>This 20-year anniversary is an appropriate occasion for collecting stories and writing about past events. Even though this anniversary book is not intended to represent the entire history of the Sámi University College, it still brings forward a few stories from the academic and administrative worlds. We also hope that the texts, in the context of past events, will provide an opportunity to critically assess the present situation of the Sámi University College and its future challenges and possibilities.</p>
<p>Sámi education and Sámi research both lay the grounds and stipulate the activities at the Sámi University College. This is why we often claim that the Sámi University College is a Sámi institution. The opportunities and activities at the Sámi University College have greatly expanded since the foundation of the college. The college has in this way taken part in strengthening the Sámi society. Sámi research has during the same time changed to a great degree and it has also obtained a broader scope. The Sámi University College, along with other institutions, has played a central role in this process.</p>
<p>The two institutions Sámi University College and Nordic Sami Institute were consolidated in 2005. The renewed institution, the Sámi University College, can now finally concentrate its activities from one common building, Diehtosiida. This move provides possibilities; however, it is also more demanding academically and administratively. Another challenge is to intensify the collaboration between the Sámi University College and the Sámi communities. Moving into the Diehtosiida also makes it easier to maintain a close relationship with the other Sámi institutions with which the college shares the building.</p>
<p>The editorial board has welcomed the current and previous Rectors, current professors and adjunct professors II, as well as the previous adjunct assistant professors and students of the Sámi University College to participate with their texts. We wish to thank the contributors who took the opportunity to be a part of this anniversary book.</p>
<p>The Sámi University College Honorary Teacher Edel Hætta Eriksen shares her experiences and thoughts with the readers in the book, which has been illustrated with photographs of the works of the Sámi University College Honorary Duojár (arts and crafts artist) Jon Ole Andersen.</p>
<p>We would like to thank the editorial secretary Brita Stina Sjaggo, the translators and proofreaders. We would also like to thank the financial contributors who supported the publication of the book.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Guovdageaidnu, August 2009</em> <em type="italic">The editorial board of the Sámi University College’s 20-year anniversary book</em> </p>
<p>Jan Henry KeskitaloKristine NystadTorunn Pettersen Chief editorCo-editor Co-editor</p>
</body></document>