<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>A GUIDED TOUR AT SIIDA — Siida</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2013</year><wordcount>795</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/a-guided-tour-at-siida</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="opastetulle-kierrokselle-siidaan.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="siidii-oahpmuhttin.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
<p type="listitem">in English |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
</list><p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
<p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Sections</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Collections |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Nature services |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Restaurant |</p>
<p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
<p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
</list><p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
<p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Info</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">/</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">A GUIDED TOUR AT SIIDA</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="nob">A GUIDED TOUR AT SIIDA</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Jun 26, 2013 12:40 PM</p>
<p>Until mid-September, the Sámi Museum and Northern Lapland Nature Centre Siida will be open every day from 9 a.m. to 8 p.m. Visitors will get more out of a visit to Siida by participating in a guided exhibition tour. You can order either a guided tour of Siida’s basic exhibitions or of the Open-Air Museum. With the help of a local guide who is acquainted with the exhibitions, it is possible to enhance the information content of the exhibitions. We especially recommend that grouölöps book a guided tour.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Guide in the Open-Air Museum</p>
<p>A guided exhibition tour in Siida lasts for 1 hour. The guide is available 15 minutes after guided tour. The tour includes the basic exhibitions of Siida. The language alternatives of a guided tour are Finnish, English and German. An exhibition tour costs € 105/group; the price does not include tickets to Siida. The recommended group size is max. 25 pers./1 guide.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Guided thematic tours in the Open-Air Museum </em></p>
<p>The woman lifts the milk <span type="quote" xml:lang="fra">“pail”</span> on the table in the rear corner of the dim room. A few drops of cow milk are spattered on her palm which is rough from hard work. She licks the drops off her hand, amazed at how thin cow milk is compared to reindeer milk that she is more familiar with. Would cow milk make good cheese? The woman takes a pot and a birch bark strainer and begins to strain the milk. Then she puts the pot on the fire and waits for the milk to warm up...</p>
<p>During a thematic tour, a professional guide will familiarize the participants of the tour with life at Tirro Homestead and in Inari in the 1850s. At the time, both reindeer and cows were kept at Tirro Homestead. Livelihood consisted of fishing, hunting, gathering and smallholding. The guide will lead the visitors 150 years back in time, to the period when there were only a few small houses in Inari and the rhythm of life was determined by eight seasons.</p>
<p>The thematic guided tour in the Open-Air Museum lasts for 1 hour and 15 minutes. It is available in Finnish and German. The price for the thematic tour is € 18/person (minimum price € 180). The price includes entry to Siida, a guided tour in the Open-Air Museum, and an activity (during which the participants make, together with the guide, a sinker for a fishing net). Without the activity, the guided tour costs € 14/person (min. price € 140).</p>
<p><em type="bold">Guided tours in the Open-Air Museum during the Inari Weeks </em></p>
<p>During the Inari Weeks, individual visitors, too, have a chance of participating in a thematic tour of the Open-Air Museum. On Thursday– the 25 th of July 2013 – the guided tour that begins at noon and at 4 p.m. is included in the ticket to Siida. A guided tour is in Finnish.</p>
<p>More information on the guided tours is available at Siida’s Customer Service: Tel.: +358 (0)400 898 212, siida@samimuseum.fi</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sámi museum, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)400 898 212, siida@samimuseum.fi , www.siida.fi</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Document Actions</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Send this</p>
<p type="listitem">Print this</p>
</list><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Contents</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
<p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="fin">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
<p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
<p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
<p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
<p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
<p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
<p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
<p>&gt; opening hours</p>
<p>&gt; tickets</p>
<p>&gt; contact information</p>
<p>&gt; location</p>
<p>&gt; guided tours</p>
<p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">|</p>
<p>photo gallery</p>
<p>tourist info</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
<p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">|</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
<p>Open original size in new window</p>
</body></document>
