<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Nature Centre Siida’s new exhibition takes us to the waters of the North — Siida</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2014</year><wordcount>650</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/nature-centre-siida2019s-new-exhibition-takes-us-to-the-waters-of-the-north</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="luontokeskus-siidan-uusi-nyttely-johdattaa-pohjoisen-vesille.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="luondduguovdd-siidda-oaseamos-jhus-lidesta-davviguovlluid-ziide.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
<p type="listitem">in English |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
</list><p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
<p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Sections</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Collections |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Nature services |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Restaurant |</p>
<p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
<p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
</list><p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
<p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Info</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">/</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
<p>Nature Centre Siida’s new exhibition takes us to the waters of the North</p>
<p type="title">Nature Centre Siida’s new exhibition takes us to the waters of the North</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Feb 18, 2014 08:44 AM</p>
<p>The exhibition On Waters and Upper Reaches takes us on an excursion to the canoe routes of the northernmost Lapland; it also tells about the water cycle of the region – from small brooks to the Arctic Ocean – in an interesting way. The exhibition is open for the public at Northern Lapland Nature Centre Siida from 21 February to 28 September 2014.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Canoeists in river Luttojoki. Photo: Tapio Tynys/Metsähallitus</p>
<p>The water cycle of the northernmost Lapland is introduced to the audience through texts accompanied by beautiful photographs. Water takes the form of fog in the air, raindrops, lakes, ponds, rivers and small brooks. Eventually, it always ends up in the sea. From there water, evaporated by the heat of the sun, ascends into the air – to come later down in the form of rain. This way, water continues its everlasting cycle. In the northernmost Lapland, the waters flow towards the Arctic Ocean.</p>
<p>The exhibition also has another theme: the canoe routes of the Inari–Utsjoki area. Photographs and short texts take us on a trip to the best-known local destinations of paddlers such as the river Ivalojoki and Lake Inari, but also to pearls that are not so well known. Stunning photographs from the rivers Teno and Inarijoki and from Nellim coax to experience these water routes, too, from a canoe or a kayak.</p>
<p>Several videos give life to the exhibition. At a resting place, the visitor can sit down and get acquainted, through the moving images of film, to the canoe routes of Lake Inari and the rivers Ivalojoki and Luttojoki. An interesting sequence is the one shot on substandard film in 1966: a boat trip from Sikovuono Bay via Lake Muddus, the River Kettujoki and Lake Paadar to the River Lemmenjoki. The film has been donated to Metsähallitus from a private collection.</p>
<p>At this exhibition, the visitor will easily be bitten by the canoeing bug!</p>
<p>On Waters and Upper Reaches has been produced by Metsähallitus’s Natural Heritage Services of Lapland.</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Metsähallitus Nature Centre, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)206 39 7740, siida@metsa.fi , www.siida.fi , www.luontoon.fi</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Document Actions</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Send this</p>
<p type="listitem">Print this</p>
</list><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Contents</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
<p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="fin">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
<p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
<p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
<p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
<p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
<p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
<p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
<p>&gt; opening hours</p>
<p>&gt; tickets</p>
<p>&gt; contact information</p>
<p>&gt; location</p>
<p>&gt; guided tours</p>
<p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">|</p>
<p>photo gallery</p>
<p>tourist info</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
<p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">|</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
<p>Open original size in new window</p>
</body></document>
