<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>STILL / LIFE – Tapio Wirkkala Retrospective Exhibition at Siida 24.3.–25.9.2016 — Siida</title>
    <genre code="facta"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <year>2016</year>
    <wordcount>690</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <license type="standard"/>
    </availability>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/still-life-2013-tapio-wirkkala-retrospective-exhibition-at-siida-24.3.201325.9.2016</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="still-life-2013-tapio-wirkkala-retrospective-2013nyttely-siidassa-24.3.-25.9.2016.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="still-life-2013-tapio-wirkkala-retrospective-2013jhus-siiddas-siidassa-24.3.-25.9.2016.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
      <p type="listitem">in English |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
    <p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Sections</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Collections |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Nature services |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Restaurant |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
    </list>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
      <p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
      <p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
    <p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Info</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">/</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
    <p xml:lang="smn">STILL / LIFE – Tapio Wirkkala Retrospective Exhibition at Siida 24.3.–25.9.2016</p>
    <p type="title" xml:lang="smn">STILL / LIFE – Tapio Wirkkala Retrospective Exhibition at Siida 24.3.–25.9.2016</p>
    <p xml:lang="isl">Mar 18, 2016 08:50 AM</p>
    <p>The STILL/LIFE exhibition, which celebrates Tapio Wirkkala’s varied and long career, will be opened at Siida right before Easter. The exhibition is the main exhibit celebrating the centenary of Tapio Wirkkala’s birth, and it gives us the opportunity of acquainting ourselves with Wirkkala’s world, thinking and career. In addition to his classic products, rare objects that have never been shown before are displayed. The exhibition brings Tapio Wirkkala’s art to its source, as he drew his inspiration for many of his works from Lapland.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="fin">Tapio Wirkkala. Photo: Maaria Wirkkala</p>
    <p>The exhibition has been curated and designed by Harri Koskinen, an internationally renowned designer.</p>
    <p>- I saw Tapio’s Iittala products for the first time at the ironmonger’s of Karstula as a teenager, and wondered right away who this guy was, Koskinen tells. -My own career has helped me to see him as a charismatic, persistent aesthete, who had an incredibly comprehensive understanding of the field. It was not just work; it was a way of life.</p>
    <p>The exhibition spotlights the objects and life work of Tapio Wirkkala. It consists of two parts. The part LIFE presents Wirkkala through the themes of work and life, working processes, trips and the background of creative work. It displays, for example, personal objects that were important for Wirkkala, such as the pipe and knife that he always had with him. The part STILL showcases Tapio Wirkkala as a versatile artist, displaying a variety of works from Venetian coloured glass to plywood sculptures.</p>
    <p>Lapland meant a great deal for Tapio Wirkkala. From the 1950s on, he spent all his summers in Inari. Wirkkala was one of the most international Finnish artists of his time, and he often worked simultaneously on several projects. He took his work to the north, too: he was not only on a holiday in Lapland. Being in Lapland became a way of survival for him. Tapio Wirkkala was also interested in the lives and future of the local people. The Sámi Museum had a special meaning for Tapio Wirkkala, as he created, together with his son Sami Wirkkala, the first sketches and scale models of the museum in 1984.</p>
    <p>The exhibition is open at the Sámi Museum and Northern Lapland Nature Centre Siida in Inari from 24 March to 25 September 2016.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sme">Sámi museum, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)400 898 212, siida@samimuseum.fi , www.siida.fi</p>
    <p type="title">Document Actions</p>
    <list>
      <p type="listitem">Send this</p>
      <p type="listitem">Print this</p>
    </list>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Contents</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
    <p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
    <p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
    <p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="fin">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
    <p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
    <p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
    <p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
    <p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
    <p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
    <p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
    <p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
    <p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
    <p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
    <p>&gt; opening hours</p>
    <p>&gt; tickets</p>
    <p>&gt; contact information</p>
    <p>&gt; location</p>
    <p>&gt; guided tours</p>
    <p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
    <p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">|</p>
    <p>photo gallery</p>
    <p>tourist info</p>
    <p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
    <p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
    <p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
    <p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
    <p xml:lang="koi">|</p>
    <p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
    <p>Open original size in new window</p>
  </body>
</document>
