<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida — Siida</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2017</year><wordcount>825</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/the-national-museum-donates-an-important-smi-collection-to-the-smi-museum-siida</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="kansallismuseo-lahjoittaa-merkittvn-saamelaiskokoelman-saamelaismuseo-siidaan.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="lbmotmusea-skeke-stuorra-smeoakkldaga-smemusea-siidii.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
<p type="listitem">in English |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
</list><p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
<p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Sections</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Collections |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Nature services |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Restaurant |</p>
<p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
<p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
</list><p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
<p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Info</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">/</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p type="title">The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Apr 04, 2017 10:00 AM</p>
<p>On 5 April 2017, the National Museum of Finland and the Sámi Museum Siida concluded a letter of intent according to which the National Museum will donate a collection of Sámi artefacts to Siida. The agreement celebrates the centenary year Finland–Sápmi 100 and the many years of co-operation between the two museums. The transfer of the collection greatly increases the attainability and influence of the Sámi cultural heritage in the Sámi area, offering the Sámi better possibilities for maintaining and developing their cultural heritage. The concentration of Sámi objects into Siida follows the principle of documentation responsibility between the museums.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>The Sámi collection of the National Museum has been accumulating since the 1830s. In the 1800s, accumulation was occasional, and a vast majority of the artefacts were acquired during collection trips made in 1902–1939. The most important collectors were T. I. Itkonen, Theodor Schvindt, Ilmari Manninen and Samuli Paulaharju. Artefacts were actively collected again from the 1970s to the 1990s; by this time, the guidelines of collection had already changed. In the Sámi area, the aim was no longer to collect old objects that were invaluable for Sámi culture, but to concentrate on new handicrafts which had been crafted according to old traditions. The National Museum was responsible for the keeping and documentation of the Sámi artefacts until 1998 when Siida was opened.</p>
<p>The National Museum’s Sámi collection comprises approximately 2,600 artefacts, including the oldest Sámi objects found in Finland. In terms of numbers, the largest group consists of clothes and parts of clothes, household objects and equipment meant for transportation and the making of textiles. Almost a half of the artefacts have been collected from the regions of Inari and Petsamo. The big proportion of Skolt Sámi objects makes the collection especially valuable and rare from an international point of view, too.</p>
<p>The National Museum and Siida will in future engage in close co-operation in order to present and document Sámi culture, and the National Museum will go on introducing the public to Sámi history and cultural heritage through its exhibitions after the collection transfer, too.</p>
<p>The collection will be transferred to Siida in connection with the expansion of the museum, which will hopefully be completed in the early 2020s. In addition to modern collection facilities, the expansion will bring the Sámi Museum communal multipurpose facilities; this will enable the museum to present and examine collections interactively with the community. Through the study of artefacts, it will be possible to revive old Sámi crafting traditions and techniques, the Sámi knowledge of materials and words dealing with the crafting and use of objects.</p>
<p>The first artefacts that will be transferred from the National Museum will be at display as early as April 2018 when Siida will launch an exhibition on Johan (Juhani) Nuorgam, the founder of the museum. The Sámi Museum Siida will celebrate its 20 th anniversary on 1 April 2018.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Further information: </em><em type="italic"></em></p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Elina Anttila, Director General, National Museum of Finland, elina.anttila@kansallismuseo.fi, tel. +358 295 33 6131</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sari Valkonen, Museum Director, Sámi Museum Siida, sari.valkonen@samimuseum.fi, tel. +358 40 767 1052</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sámi museum, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)400 898 212, siida@samimuseum.fi , www.siida.fi</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Document Actions</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Send this</p>
<p type="listitem">Print this</p>
</list><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Contents</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
<p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="fin">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
<p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
<p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
<p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
<p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
<p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
<p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
<p>&gt; opening hours</p>
<p>&gt; tickets</p>
<p>&gt; contact information</p>
<p>&gt; location</p>
<p>&gt; guided tours</p>
<p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">|</p>
<p>photo gallery</p>
<p>tourist info</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
<p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">|</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
<p>Open original size in new window</p>
</body></document>
