<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The Living Environment — Siida</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2013</year><wordcount>802</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/the-living-environment</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="ealli-biras-elv-ymprist.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="ealli-biras.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
<p type="listitem">in English |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
</list><p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
<p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Sections</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
<p type="listitem">Collections |</p>
<p type="listitem">Nature services |</p>
<p type="listitem">Restaurant |</p>
<p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
<p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
</list><p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
<p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>Info</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">/</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
<p>The Living Environment</p>
<p type="title">The Living Environment</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Jun 19, 2013 11:30 AM</p>
<p>The exhibition The Living Environment makes Sámi cultural environments visible. It introduces the audience with Sámi cultural landscapes through archaeology, built heritage and landscape-related oral knowledge. The exhibition is realized through the Ealli biras – The Living Environment project, which is funded by the European Regional Development Fund ERDF and gets its national funding from the Regional Council of Lapland.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="sme">A storage hut in <span type="quote" xml:lang="smn">"Kaapin Jouni"</span> (Gábe-Jovnna, Jouni Aikio) farm in Lemmenjoki.</p>
<p>The natural environment in the wide Sápmi region varies greatly, from the bare northernmost fells to the forests and string fens of Central Lapland. The various areas have created different forms of land use, livelihood, and living. With time, these variations that were dependent on the natural conditions also formed borders between languages and cultures. Ealli biras is a tale of the versatile landscapes and cultural environments of the Finnish Sápmi region.</p>
<p>Cultural environment is an umbrella term for the various forms of culture born out of the interaction between humans and the natural environment and the phases it has gone through during the ages. The philosophy in each culture affects which aspects are considered culture and which nature. The northern landscape may seem like a desolate natural view because it may not have any visible signs of human activity. However, the Sápmi region is part of the cultural landscape of the Sámi people, and it has been created through interaction between humans and nature, over the course of many generations.</p>
<p>The archaeological findings of the past few years have given us new information on the phases of habitation in the Sápmi region. The exhibition presents a wide range of archaeological items. Some 20 years ago, the remainders of huts and houses in the winter village in Nukkumajoki, Inari, were studied through archaeological excavations. Some of the items found in these excavations are among the findings presented for the first time in the Sápmi region.</p>
<p>Many kinds of traditional information are related to the landscape, and they are transferred from generation to generation through doing things together, or as stories. A story hut has been built for the Ealli biras exhibition, where visitors can listen to stories related to places around the Sápmi region. The soundscape playing in the background of the exhibition is created by the musician Wimme Saari.</p>
<p>The Ealli biras – the living environment exhibition is part of a project of the same name by the Siida Sámi Museum (1.1.2011–30.9.2013). The project publishes a Sámi cultural environment programme, to which the exhibition is directly related. The project is funded internationally by the European Regional Development Fund (ERDF) and nationally by the Regional Council of Lapland.</p>
<p>The Ealli biras exhibition is open from 15 June 2013 to 25 May 2014. Siida is open from 9 a.m. to 8 p.m. every day during the summer period (1.6.-19.9), and Tuesday to Sunday from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. during the winter period (20.9.-31.5) (closed on Mondays).</p>
<p><em type="italic">For more information, contact: </em>Curator Arja Jomppanen, arja.jomppanen(at)samimuseum.fi, +358 40 579 3313 Project coordinator Päivi Magga, paivi.magga(at)samimuseum.fi,+358 40 180 1501 </p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sámi museum, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)400 898 212, siida@samimuseum.fi , www.siida.fi</p>
<p type="title">Document Actions</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Send this</p>
<p type="listitem">Print this</p>
</list><p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>Contents</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
<p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="fin">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
<p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
<p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
<p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
<p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
<p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
<p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
<p>&gt; opening hours</p>
<p>&gt; tickets</p>
<p>&gt; contact information</p>
<p>&gt; location</p>
<p>&gt; guided tours</p>
<p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">|</p>
<p>photo gallery</p>
<p>tourist info</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
<p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">|</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
<p>Open original size in new window</p>
</body></document>