<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Young Sámi Art Event exhibition will be opened in Siida on the 6th of February — Siida</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2015</year><wordcount>759</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.siida.fi/contents/news/young-smi-art-event-exhibition-will-be-opened-in-siida-on-the-6th-of-february</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="siidassa-avautuu-6.2.-saamelaisnuorten-taidetapahtuma-tutuksi-nyttely.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="siiddas-rahpasa-6.2.2015-smenuoraid-diddadhphus-oahpisin-jhus.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="sme">sámegillii |</p>
<p type="listitem">in English |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fin">suomeksi |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="rus">Русский</p>
</list><p xml:lang="deu">Search Site</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Advanced Search…</p>
<p>Skip to content. | Skip to navigation</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Sections</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Home |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Collections |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Nature services |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="fra">Restaurant |</p>
<p type="listitem">Conferences |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">News |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Skolt Sámi Heritage House</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="deu">Site Map |</p>
<p type="listitem">Contact |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">RSS |</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Newsletter</p>
</list><p xml:lang="nob">SÁMI CULTURE  Sámi Museum</p>
<p>NORTHERN NATURE  Nature Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Info</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Home</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">/</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">News /</p>
<p>Young Sámi Art Event exhibition will be opened in Siida on the 6th of February</p>
<p type="title">Young Sámi Art Event exhibition will be opened in Siida on the 6th of February</p>
<p xml:lang="fkv">Jan 29, 2015 01:45 PM</p>
<p>At the exhibition Sámi Museum Siida and the educational office of Sámi Parliament present the significant event in the Sámi region.</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>The Young Sámi Art Event has been a stage for Sámi young people already for four decades. The event enhances young people’s involvement in cultural hobbies and art, and strengthens their use of the Sámi language, sense of belonging together and Sámi identity. Through images, films and other works of artistic nature, the exhibition shows the significance of this art event as part of living Sámi culture.</p>
<p>The Art Events are colourful occasions that pupils have looked forward to and prepared themselves for at school throughout the school year. Teachers have supported the event by working diligently as leaders. The Young Sámi Art Event offers the young an opportunity to improve their skills and show their talents for others, too. It has also aimed at giving them inspiring response for their involvement in the arts. All the Sámi children and young people as well as the pupils who are taught in or through the Sámi language are invited to the Young Sámi Art Event.</p>
<p>The Young Sámi Art Event has been held since the mid-1970s. The Art Event was originally one of the regional events of the national series of  <em type="italic">Young People’s Art Events </em>. At present, it is one of the regional gatherings of the network  <em type="italic">Nuori Kulttuuri  </em>(“ <em type="italic">Young Culture </em>”), in which representatives are chosen for the national spring gathering.  </p>
<p>The main theme of the Art Event is the same as that of the national gathering, with a focus on dance, music or theatre. In addition, there is another theme that is linked with Sámi culture. The Young Sámi Art Event does not want to have the young people restrict themselves only to traditions: therefore, the events focus on a variety of art forms, for example visual arts, narration, poetry, comics, short films and stage cloths.</p>
<p>The Art Event is arranged by the  <em type="italic">Educational Committee of the Sámi Parliament </em>, where  <em type="italic">TheEducational Office </em> takes care of the practical arrangements. In addition, the municipalities participate in the organisation of the event in their own turn. The Young Sámi Art Event is part of the annual curriculum of the schools, and the event takes place during the school week. The Finnish  <em type="italic">Ministry of Education and Culture </em> provides financial support for participation in the Young Sámi Art Event and the national gatherings connected with it.  </p>
<p>Youn Sámi Art Event exhibition will be at Siida from February 6th, 2015 to May 10 th, 2015</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">More information: Marjo Riitta Rantamäki, marjo-riitta.rantamaki@samimuseum.fi, + 358 (0)40 571 5670  Anni Näkkäläjärvi, anni.nakkalajarvi@samediggi.fi, 040 511 1821</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sámi museum, Siida, Inarintie 46, FI-99870 Inari, tel. +358 (0)400 898 212, siida@samimuseum.fi , www.siida.fi</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="fra">Document Actions</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Send this</p>
<p type="listitem">Print this</p>
</list><p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Contents</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Study Paths exhibition looks at the study programme of Sámi Education Institute</p>
<p>The National Museum donates an important Sámi collection to the Sámi Museum Siida</p>
<p>Learning more about the Sámi narrative tradition and nature</p>
<p>The photographic work <span type="quote" xml:lang="fin">“Raittijärvi – Kaijukan kylä”</span> by photographer Jyrki Kallio-Koski is published in Hetta on 23 March 2017</p>
<p>SKÁBMAGOVAT FILM FESTIVAL: PROGRAMME IS READY AND TICKETS ARE BEING SOLD</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">The 2017 Skábmagovat Film Festival spotlights the Maori</p>
<p>Raittijärvi – the village of Kaijukka, photographs about life in the Sámi village over a span of forty years</p>
<p>Siida switches to winter opening hours</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aili Mattus: An Inari Sámi Doll-Maker</p>
<p>Autumn Festival at Sevettijärvi Heritage House on 8 September 2016 from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., arranged by the Skolt Sámi Heritage House, the Skolt Sámi Cultural Foundation and Sevettijärvi School</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="vep">VISITOR INFO</p>
<p xml:lang="ron"><em type="italic">SIIDA </em>INARINTIE 46, FI-99870 INARI </p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sámi Museum Phone +358 (0)400 898 212</p>
<p>Nature Centre, Metsähallitus Phone +358 (0)206 39 7740</p>
<p>&gt; opening hours</p>
<p>&gt; tickets</p>
<p>&gt; contact information</p>
<p>&gt; location</p>
<p>&gt; guided tours</p>
<p>&gt; Siida in terms of architecture</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">calendar</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">|</p>
<p>photo gallery</p>
<p>tourist info</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Siida</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Siida Shop</p>
<p>for the media | for tour operators</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Copyright Siida 2010</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">|</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Updated 10.6.2010</p>
<p>Open original size in new window</p>
</body></document>
