<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The People Elect the President – the Parliament Elects the Prime Minister - 
	Oikeusministeriö - Oikeusministeriö
</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2016</year><wordcount>228</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.oikeusministerio.fi/en/index/publications/esitteet/perustuslaki/kansavalitseepresidentin-eduskuntavalitseepaaministerin.html</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="kansavalitseepresidentin-eduskuntavalitseepaaministerin.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="albmotvalljepresideantta-riikkabeaivvitvalljejitoaiveministara.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="tur"></p>
<p type="title">Constitution</p>
<p type="title">The People Elect the President – the Parliament Elects the Prime Minister</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">CHAPTER 5</p>
<p>The President of the Republic is elected directly. A candidate has to be a native Finnish citizen entitled to vote.</p>
<p>Candidates nominated by parties and groups of voters participate in the first round of the elections.</p>
<p>If no candidate receives a majority of the votes cast a second round is arranged. The candidates in the run-off are the two who received most votes in the first round. The one receiving more votes is elected President.</p>
<p>The presidential term is six years. The same person may be elected President for no more than two consecutive terms, i.e. for altogether twelve years.</p>
<p>The President takes most decisions on a proposal of the Government.</p>
<p>The Government has to enjoy the confidence of the Parliament. After parliamentary elections the parliamentary groups negotiate and agree on the formation of a new government. The Parliament elects the Prime Minister who is appointed by the President. The other ministers the President appoints on the basis of a nomination by the Prime Minister.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister heads the work of the Government. The most important issues – such as law and budget bills – are decided in governmental sessions.</p>
<p>The ministers see to the drafting of bills concerning their administrative branch and to the enforcement of decisions taken by the Parliament.</p>
</body></document>
