<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Constitution - 
	Oikeusministeriö - Oikeusministeriö
</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2016</year><wordcount>343</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.oikeusministerio.fi/en/index/publications/esitteet/perustuslaki.html</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="perustuslaki.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="st303htav303ldisuomasgull303303lbmogii.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p type="title">Constitution</p>
<p type="title">In Finland Sovereign Power Rests with the People</p>
<p type="title">What is the constitution?</p>
<p>In Finland the Constitution is the basis of all legislation and exercise of government power. It details the fundamental rules, values and principles of Finnish democracy.</p>
<p>The Constitution specifies the foundations of the relationship between the individual and government. It also contains provisions about the principles of the exercise of power by government, government organization and the relationships between the highest organs of government.</p>
<p>The new Constitution entered into force on 1 March 2000. It is based on four old constitutional acts: the Constitution Act of Finland, the Parliament Act and two acts on ministerial liability. These were passed during the first years of independence. The Parliament has amended these acts over the years, but the principal constitutional traits have remained unchanged. Even the new Constitution has been amended after its entry into force.</p>
<p>The new Constitution reiterates the main principle of the old Constitution Act: in Finland sovereign power lies with the people represented by the Parliament in session.</p>
<list><p type="listitem">According to the Constitution, sovereign power rests with the people. Democracy includes the individual right to influence decisions that affect us all. The Constitution guarantees civil rights and liberties.</p>
<p type="listitem">The Constitution emphasises the parliamentary traits of the Finnish political system and the status of the Parliament as the supreme state organ: the Government must enjoy its confidence. The President of the Republic takes decisions on the basis of proposals drawn up and presented by the Government.</p>
<p type="listitem">The Parliament elects the Prime Minister who is appointed by the President. The other ministers the President appoints on a nomination by the Prime Minister.</p>
<p type="listitem">The President of the Republic directs the foreign policy of Finland in conjunction with the Government. Also in foreign policy, presidential acts are based on preparations by and cooperation with the Government.</p>
<p type="listitem">According to the Constitution, Finland participates in international cooperation in order to promote peace and to safeguard human rights.</p>
<p type="listitem">Finland is a Member State of the European Union.</p>
</list><p>Updated on October 19, 2016 <em type="italic"></em></p>
<p type="title">More about the subject</p>
</body></document>