<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The President and the Government Direct Foreign Policy - 
	Oikeusministeriö - Oikeusministeriö
</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2016</year><wordcount>157</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.oikeusministerio.fi/en/index/publications/esitteet/perustuslaki/presidenttijavaltioneuvostojohtavatulkopolitiikkaa.html</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="presidenttijavaltioneuvostojohtavatulkopolitiikkaa.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="presideantajastahtara273273ijo273ihitolgoriikkapolitihka.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p type="title">Constitution</p>
<p type="title">The President and the Government Direct Foreign Policy</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">CHAPTER 8</p>
<p>The Finnish foreign policy is directed by the President of the Republic in cooperation with the Government. If there is a disagreement between the President and the Government in the decisionmaking, the decision is made in accordance with the position adopted by the Parliament.</p>
<p>The President and the ministers responsible for foreign relations discuss the most important matters in the governmental Committee for Foreign and Security Policy.</p>
<p>The Parliament accepts the most important international treaties.</p>
<p>Finland joined the European Union in 1995. The Government leads the preparations for decisions taken by the Union, and sees to the enforcement of the decisions. The Prime Minister represents Finland in activities of the European Union requiring the participation of the highest level of State.</p>
<p>The Government has to inform the Parliament of issues considered by the Union. The Parliament may issue directions to the ministers participating in EU meetings.</p>
</body></document>
