<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>Two Hundred Representatives Are Elected by Vote - 
	Oikeusministeriö - Oikeusministeriö
</title>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <year>2016</year>
    <wordcount>167</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <license type="standard"/>
    </availability>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.oikeusministerio.fi/en/index/publications/esitteet/perustuslaki/vaaleissavalitaan200kansanedustajaa.html</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="vaaleissavalitaan200kansanedustajaa.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="valggainvalljejuvvojit200riikkabeaiveairasa.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p type="title">Constitution</p>
    <p type="title">Two Hundred Representatives Are Elected by Vote</p>
    <p xml:lang="deu">CHAPTER 3</p>
    <p>Everyone entitled to vote may enter as a candidate in parliamentary elections. Only the President, high-ranking legal officials and members of the armed forces may not.</p>
    <p>Two hundred Representatives are elected in parliamentary elections amongst the candidates nominated by parties and groups of voters.</p>
    <p>The Parliament discharges its duties till the next parliamentary elections, which are regularly held every four years. On a proposal of the Prime Minister and after having heard the parliamentary groups, the President may order that new elections be held. Quite seldom – last time in 1975 – the parliamentary term has been shorter than the normal four years.</p>
    <p>The Representatives have to comply with the Constitution. Other rules and regulations do not oblige them. They may not be hindered from performing their duties, and in the Parliament they may speak up about all matters being considered. If a Representative breaks the law the Representative is punished, as any other person would be.</p>
  </body>
</document>
