<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title/>
    <genre code="science"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <wordcount>360</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <license type="standard"/>
    </availability>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="kvammen.pdf"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="kvammen.pdf"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 161400 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p><em type="bold">Abstract  </em></p>
    <p>The aim of this thesis is to investigate online linguistic variations of two Norwegian speakers of  Sami  language.  The  research  is  based  on  the  analysis  of  30  status  updates  and conversation  threads  from  the  internet  community  Facebook.  This  thesis  adopts  a sociolinguistic approach to the analyzed texts and focuses on code-switching between Sami and  Norwegian  languages.  To  collect  and  analyze  the  material,  a  qualitative  method  is applied,  while  the  interpretation  of  the  texts  is  based  on  the  hermeneutical  tradition.  This thesis  employs  a  multilingual  research,  identity  and  language  use  in  computer  mediated communication, as main theoretical approaches. My intention is, in short, to explain what is going  on in  the discourse,  how  and  why.  In doing  so,  I  consider language  use as  an act  of identity  and  the  speakers  as  social  actors  in  a  multilingual  digital  society.  To  explain  this thoroughly, I also examine the language as a form and a structure.     One  conclusion  is  that  code-switching  between  the  language  pair  Sami  and Norwegian  is  very  complex  and  varied.  There  are  not  only  individual  differences  between the two informants, but there are also major differences in how the individuals use language. To  explain  these  differences,  I  analyze  the  textual  samples  on  three  different  levels:  <em type="italic">An individual  level,  a  thread  level</em>  and  <em type="italic">an</em>  <em type="italic">utterance  level</em>.  On  the  individual  level,  I  examine how the two informants relate to their own codes in this context. The thread level focuses on the analysis of the texts in conversation threads. In that case, such factors as participants and topics  are considered as  determinants  that influence the linguistic change. On the utterance level,  I  examine  single  utterances  in  order  to  explain  specific  linguistic  tendencies  in  this context.  The  results  reveal  that  while  many  of  the  code-switching  forms  are  possible  to categorize,  others  seem  to  be  more  spontaneous  and  unconscious,  and  are,  thus,  more difficult  to  categorize.  It  is  also  found  that  the  informants'  choice  of  the  code  plays  an important role in their positioning as multilingual individuals in an online discourse, and that they  actively  use  language  to  achieve  specific  discursive  goals.  In  addition,  the  use  of  the Sami language emphasizes Sami identity and ethnicity. </p>
  </body>
</document>
