<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="science"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>22490</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>orig/sme/science/uit/phd/inger_marie_gaup_eira.pdf</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p><em type="bold">THE STRUCTURE OF THE THESIS </em></p>
<p>This thesis consists of two parts; An introduction and four articles.</p>
<p>The introduction is written in Sámi language to contribute to the development of the Sámi language as a scientific language. The introduction has been translated into English, to broaden the readership, because reindeer herding is an international industry in the circumpolar North. Furthermore the articles are organized by the original language version followed by the translations. Articles 1 and 2 were written in Sámi and then translated into English, while Articles 3 and 4 were written in English, then translated into Sámi. Finally the Appendix 1 is in Sámi language, while Appendix 2, and 3 were written in Sámi and translated into English.</p>
<p><em type="bold">ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </em></p>
<p>I want to thank a number of individuals and institutions because they have supported me in significant ways during my research on this PhD project. First I wish to thank my supervisors’ prof. Ole Henrik Magga and prof. Svein D. Mathiesen who have for the last four years encouraged, supported me, and patiently explained when I have had challenges to better understand ways and means to solve issues. This study has been a part of The EALÁT project financially supported by Norwegian Research Council grant number 176078/S30, Ministry of Government Administration, Reform and Church Affairs, and hosted at and led by Sámi University College and the International Centre for Reindeer Husbandry. I am deeply appreciative and grateful for the role these institutions have played in my research. The previous rector at the Sámi University College May Britt Utsi and previous director Anders JH. Eira are deeply acknowledged for allowing this project to be hosted at the Sámi University College. Reindeer herders in five winter siidas in Western Finnmark have participated in the research and providing me with unique insights in to their daily practical herding, thanks a lot to them all. Furthermore, I acknowledge my colleagues in the EALAT project for fruitful collaboration and for sharing their knowledge. Especially want to thank Dr. Nancy G. Maynard has from the very beginning shown interest for my work and provided me with counsel and assistance. I want also to thank a number of advisors in the EALÁT project, incuding: Dr. Robert W. Corell who have help me broaden my understanding of climate change in the Arctic, Dr. Christian Jaedicke for teaching me about snow metamorphism, and Dr. Dagrunn Vikhamar-Schuler and Dr. Inger Hanssen-Bauer, both whom taught and explained to me the science and practical insights about weather and climate change. Thanks to Dr. Peter Wasilewski and Mr. Allen Lunsford at NASA Goodard Flight space Centre introducing me to the thermochron technology. I am deeply grateful for the 12 field assistants, youth from Sámi Reindeer Herding who have been interviewing elders, in part of the EALAT project called CEAVVI; Ravdna Biret Marja Eira, Johan Aslak Siri, Elle Bals, Anne Marja Magga, Risten R. Eira, Ellen Anna Sara, Nils Jonas Ketola, Aslat Ante Sara, Aslat Mahtte Turi, Ellen Inga Turi, Marit Anne Bongo and Jørgen Eira Solbakke. Futher, a deep thanks also to my colleagues, especially Mathis Bongo, Mikkel Nils Sara, Inger Anne Siri Triumf, Kristine Nystad, Jan Henry Keskitalo, Johan Mathis Turi and Nils Isak Eira with whom I have enjoyed the social and professional discussions for the several years in the OL-building. I wish to thank Anders Oskal and Philip Burgess who have always has provided support throughout my research. I am deeply grateful for the encouragement and support provided by my mother, my brothers, and my sisters in law, and Elle mannji. Elna is acknowledged for encouraging me during the last part of my study. She always said <span type="quote">”Yes, you will manage”</span> regardless how difficult I felt it was. Finally I want to give hearty thanks to my husband Joavnna, who has always been understandable when I have been absent from doing my siida and family duties. Working with this thesis has occupied a lot of my time. Thanks to my dear children, John Einar Jr, Jørn Inge and Mia Carina, and Thomas for being patiently. Inger Marie Gaup Eira Guovdageaidnu, January 2012</p>
<p><em type="bold">THE INTRODUCTION OF THE THESIS IN ENGLISH, TRANSLATED FROM SÁMI LANGUAGE. </em></p>
<p>Part 1</p>
<p><em type="bold">CONTENT </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">FIGURES AND TABLES ......................................................................................................................... 88 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">1. INTRODUCTION .............................................................................................................................. 91 </em>1.1 THE AIM OF THE STUDY ......................................................................................................................... 931.2 REINDEER HERDING AND ITS’ BASIC PREMISES ............................................................................................. 951.3 INDIGENOUS KNOWLEDGE VS. SCIENTIFIC KNOWLEDGE ............................................................................... 96 <em type="italic">1.3.1 The Definition, Form and Characteristics of Indigenous Knowledge ....................................... 96 </em><em type="italic">1.3.2 Traditional Knowledge and Scientific Knowledge .................................................................... 98 </em>1.4. PAST AND FUTURE CLIMATE IN GUOVDAGEAIDNU REINDEER HERDING REGION WESTERN FINNMARK .................. 100 <em type="italic">1.4.1 Past climate in the Guovdageaidnu herding region ............................................................... 100 </em><em type="italic">1.4.2 Future projected climate in Guovdageaidnu .......................................................................... 103 </em><em type="bold">2. THEORETICAL APPROACHES ......................................................................................................... 104 </em>2.1 LINGUISTIC THEORETICAL APPROACH ...................................................................................................... 104 <em type="italic">2.1.1 The basis of Sámi terminology ............................................................................................... 105 </em><em type="italic">2.1.2 The function of language and terminology ............................................................................ 106 </em><em type="italic">2.1.3 Concepts................................................................................................................................. 110 </em><em type="italic">2.1.4 Concept analysis and categorization ..................................................................................... 111 </em>2.2 A SCIENTIFIC APPROACH IN RELATION TO SNOW AND REINDEER HERDING ....................................................... 114 <em type="italic">2.2.1 Snow, its characteristics and its role in winter-ecology ......................................................... 114 </em><em type="italic">2.2.2 Snow transformation ............................................................................................................. 115 </em><em type="italic">2.2.3 Snow classification ................................................................................................................. 118 </em><em type="bold">3. METHODOLOGY ........................................................................................................................... 119 </em>3.1 RESEARCH AREA ................................................................................................................................. 1203.2 DESCRIPTION OF DATA ......................................................................................................................... 1203.3 INFORMANTS ..................................................................................................................................... 1223.4 SNOW PHYSICS AND TEMPERATURE MEASUREMENTS ................................................................................. 124 <em type="bold">4. NORTH SÁMI SNOW CONCEPTS, THEIR CONTENT AND USE.......................................................... 125 </em>4.1 SUMMARY OF THE ARTICLES.................................................................................................................. 1264.2 CHARACTERISTICS OF SÁMI SNOW CONCEPTS ........................................................................................... 1294.3 CATEGORIZATION AND CLASSIFICATION OF THE SÁMI SNOW CONCEPTS ......................................................... 1314.4 GUOHTUN AND BASIC SNOW CONCEPTS FOR REINDEER HERDING .................................................................. 135 <em type="italic">4.4.1 Guohtun ................................................................................................................................. 136 </em><em type="italic">4.4.2 Oppas and čiegar ................................................................................................................... 140 </em><em type="italic">4.4.3 Fieski ...................................................................................................................................... 144 </em><em type="italic">4.4.4 Ritni ........................................................................................................................................ 144 </em><em type="italic">4.4.5 Goavvi .................................................................................................................................... 146 </em>4.5 TRADITIONAL KNOWLEDGE ABOUT SNOW, ADAPTATION AND RESILIENCE THINKING .......................................... 150 <em type="bold">5. CONCLUSIONS .............................................................................................................................. 157 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">FIGURES AND TABLES </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">in Guovdageaidnu from 1889 (Vikhamar-Schuler et al., 2010). ................................................ 101 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 2: Mean winter (Dec, Jan, Feb) A) and spring (March, April, May) B) precipitation in </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Guovdageaidnu from 1889 (Vikhamar-Schuler et al., 2010). .................................................... 101 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">from 1955 (Vikhamar-Schuler et al., 2010). .............................................................................. 102 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 4: Changes in number of days with air temperatures &lt;-15 degree C in Guovdageaidnu from 1955 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">A), and variation of maximum snow depth in Guovdageaidnu B) from 1995. (Vikhamar-Schuler et al., 2010). .............................................................................................................................. 103 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">(Karasjok) winter pastures and coastal Finnmark (Nordreisa) summer pastures, (full drawn lines) and the similar averages calculated from 50 downscaled climate models for the year 2085 (dotted lines) (Magga et al., 2011a). ................................................................................ 104 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">zones.......................................................................................................................................... 120 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 7: Equipment for measuring air temperature............................................................................... 124 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">similarities/differences of Sámi snow and ice concepts in relation to influencing matters. ...... 133 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 9: Variants of oppas, from best level to the worst. ...................................................................... 141 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 10: The concept čiegar, divided in seven sub-concepts. ............................................................... 143 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 11: The fieski-concept with its sub-ordinate concepts. ................................................................. 144 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">temperature. ............................................................................................................................. 145 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 13: Goavvi concept with sub-concepts. ........................................................................................ 147 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">indication and description of the conditions in Guovdageaidnu. ............................................. 149 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">the number of reindeer, the red bar in the graph marks goavvi years and the green bar marks goavvi-springs. (Official data from the Directorate of Reindeer Husbandry). ........................... 153 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">1917, 1967 and 1996 in Guovdageaidnu reindeer herding region, which is correspond to negative NAO phases (Prepared from JIANPING, 2003). ........................................................... 153 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Table 1: Overview of research methods used .......................................................................................... 120 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Table 2: Identification of characteristics of eight snow concepts. ........................................................... 129 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">1981; Ruong, 1964 .................................................................................................................... 134 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">snow term, definition in Sámi language, and classification number ......................................... 135 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Table 5: Snow types that can cause either bad or good grazing conditions ........................................... 137 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Table 6: Sub-variants of guohtun ............................................................................................................ 139 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">years (nealgedálvi), 1967/68 and 68/69 marked in red were goavvi years, and 1958-1961 and 1997 marked in green were goavvi spring ................................................................................ 148 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Table 8: Adaptative strategies during goavvi periodes ........................................................................... 155 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">ABSTRACT </em></p>
<p>This thesis is a linguistic study with an interdisciplinary perspective with the aim to investigate the content and the use of Sámi snow concepts about grazing conditions for reindeer on snow covered ground in Sámi reindeer herding in Guovdageaidnu, Norway. As basis for the analysis of snow concept, interviews, linguistics, and physical aspects and reindeer herders‟ knowledge was used, thus combining indigenous people‟s knowledge and snow physic measurements. <em type="italic"></em>In addition, a <em type="italic">siida </em>-based monitoring system based on herders‟ specialist language was developed, where herders from five different <em type="italic">siidas </em>used herding diaries in monitoring and making daily observation of variations in snow condition, wind, precipitation, topography related to herd behavior and welfare. 318 snow related concepts used by reindeer herders in this area, contain factors that affect reindeer survival and sustainability, wellbeing of reindeer and the human working conditions. The concepts contain a set of characteristics belonging to reindeer herding and snow physics, and their multidimensional content show that some concepts are based on the physical characteristics of snow and can therefore be compared with international snow classification, while others have elements connected to the different herding strategies. Some snow concept are complex categories in the sense that a term contains and includes many factors simultaneously, such as information of snow, snow conditions, snow physics, weather, temperature, location, time and impacts of animals and humans. Snow concepts are central for daily work with the reindeer, and constitute important parts for reindeer herders‟ traditional knowledge. Reindeer herders observe and manage snow from two perspectives; the snow physics and the ecology of herds in the winter grazing area, which reveals a holistic knowledge and view. The data indicate strategic and systematical use of grazing areas in terms of time and space and, shows variability between the <em type="italic">siidas </em>in terms of snow conditions between years and between pasture areas. Every winter <em type="italic">siida </em>has its unique grazing condition, which makes it difficult to compare one <em type="italic">siidas </em>grazing condition with others, and draw general conclusions. The use of Sámi snow concepts mirror reindeer herders‟ traditional knowledge of the management of the herd on snow covered ground and how herders deal with these complex systems. This kind of knowledge has contributed to the survival of reindeer herding since time immemorial. The analysis of snow concepts show the importance of using Sámi reindeer herders‟ specialist language and traditional knowledge in mainstream the governance of reindeer herding. Thus The national adaptive strategies must recognize reindeer herders‟ traditional knowledge, and their cultural and linguistic rights must be included in adaptation strategies for climate change. This requires different ways of knowing, combining both herders‟ experienced-based knowledge and scientific knowledge. </p>
<p>Keywords: <em type="italic">Sámi language, snow concepts, <span type="quote">“guohtun”</span>, reindeer herding specialist language, traditional knowledge, snow physics, climate </em>. <em type="bold">1. INTRODUCTION </em><em type="italic">“When the herd has their needs met, the reindeer herder’s mind is calm and all is well, no matter how much hardship and effort he has experienced. On the other hand, he is seized by hopeless restlessness and despairs if, as sometimes happens the herd cannot find pasture because the ice crust has settled on the lichen. "(Smith 1938:311)1 </em></p>
<p>This thesis investigates a system of Sámi snow-concepts as well as the significance of snow for</p>
<p>Sámi reindeer pastoralism in</p>
<p>Guovdageaidnu/Kautokeino, western Finnmark, Norway. Linguistics, physical science and reindeer herders‟ knowledge have all been used as basis for the Sámi snow concept analysis in this work. This is a first step to gaining insight into the effects of weather conditions on local snow conditions and thereby the grazing conditions for Sámi reindeer herding.</p>
<p>This study is a part of the IPY (International Polar Year Project)</p>
<p><em type="italic">EALÁT Reindeer herders’ vulnerability network study </em>, a following up to the </p>
<p>Arctic Climate Impact Assessment (ACIA) (ACIA, 2004).The IPY was a large scientific program, organized through the International Council for Science (ICSU) and the World Meteorological Organization (WMO) and was actually the fourth international polar year. An estimated 50,000 participants from more than 60 countries have been involved this time in more than 200 projects, in range of physical, biological and social research topics. One of the very few IPY research sites which hosted both projects in 2007/09 (Orheim &amp; Ulstein, 2011) and 1882/83 (Tromholt, 1885) was Guovdageaidnu.</p>
<p>Since 1995 there has been a paradigm shift in Arctic research into a holistic and multidisciplinary perspective, include the human dimension, indigenous knowledge and a more integrated understanding of the Arctic as part 1 Translated from Norwegian: <span type="quote">“Når hjorden har sitt behov tilfredsstilt, er fjellappenes sinn rolig og alt er bra, hvor store strabaser og anstrengelser han enn har hatt. På den annen side gripes han av håpløs uro og fortvilelse, når hjorden, som stundom hends, ikke finner beite fordi isskorpe har lagt seg på laven”</span> (Smith 1938:311) of the world (Bowden <em type="italic">et al., </em>2005). Accordingly The IPY EALÁT is multicultural and multidisciplinary vulnerability study with components from different field of linguistics, social and natural sciences combined with reindeer herders‟ knowledge. The IPY EALÁT sought to examine the impact of future challenges on reindeer herders and their communities and to look at how they can best adapt, develop and prosper to ensure the survival of reindeer husbandry for future generations (Magga <em type="italic">et al., </em>2011a; Mathiesen &amp; Magga, 2011). The project adopted a new methodological approach since the project recognized that reindeer herders‟ ability to adapt to change is based on traditional knowledge embodied in the language, in the institutions of herding and in the action of individual herders (McCarthy <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2005; Tyler <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2007). </p>
<p>During the next 30 - 50 years, the effects of climate change are expected to be most pronounced in the Arctic regions, affecting the circumpolar reindeer herding pastures. Throughout this thesis, the word <span type="quote">“climate change”</span> is used as this phase encompasses the concept of global warming, changes in temperatures and changes in precipitation, land use and land cover change, decade scale climate and weather variability and the impacts and consequences of changes to natural and human societal systems. In Norway, the effects of future climate change are expected to be most strongly felt inland Finnmark, the main winter pastures for Sámi Reindeer herding (McCarthy <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2005; Tyler <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2007; Oskal <em type="italic">el al </em>., 2009). Climate change is causing various forms of vulnerabilities for indigenous and local communities in the Arctic (Henriksen, 2007). Furthermore, Climate and socio-economic change are now evident across the Arctic, and is particularly evident in reindeer herding cultures and in their traditional areas (Magga <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2011a,b,c). The Arctic indigenous peoples, their life, culture and traditional knowledge are adapted to and largely dependent on the cold and extreme physical conditions of the region. As recently stated by </p>
<p>Sheila Watt-Cloutier, the former chair of the Inuit Circumpolar Conference, the culture of the indigenous peoples of the Arctic depends on the cold. Their culture is inseparable from the conditions of their physical surroundings (Bæhr, 2010).</p>
<p>Snow has always been important for the existence and livelihood of the Sámi people (Ruong, 1964; Svonni, 1981; Eira, 1984; 1994, Jernsletten, 1994; Magga, 2006), because it is critical for maintaining a supply of food, tracking, travel (Ruong, 1982; Krupnik <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2010;), and determining the ability of the reindeer to graze for in winter (Saijets &amp; Helander-Renvall, 2009). Since rapid changes, both environmental and social, are predicted for northern regions, (Magga <em type="italic">et al., </em>2011a) it is essential to prepare for these changes in order to reduce the risk of negative impacts in the reindeer herding society. </p>
<p>In various different areas of work in the mainstream society, some specialists use particular specialized words and phrases that are not part of everyday language. Johns (2010:411-13), who has provided a linguistic description of Inuit snow and ice terms, believes that the knowledge behind the vocabulary used to refer to and describe sea ice is important both for indigenous peoples and for others. Communication requires that the speakers are familiar with the relevant concepts, which, in turn, entails a terminology consisting of specialists‟ concept. The Sámi reindeer herders‟ experience of living with nature and from what nature provides has created a specialist language rich in vocabulary for describing natural phenomena (Jernsletten, 1997:234). Reindeer herders‟ understanding is based on the experience of generations, which has been collected and preserved about the specialized work techniques and language of the herders, both on the individual and herding group levels (Joks <em type="italic">et al. </em>2006; Turi, 2009). <em type="bold">1.1 The Aim of the Study </em></p>
<p>The main aim of this study was to examine how key Sámi snow concepts are used in everyday reindeer herding in winter in Guovdageaidnu related to different kinds of weather and herding practices. An additional goal was to identify and to understand the concepts used to assess pasture availability through the snowpack. In this study, linguistic and multidisciplinary approaches were used in order to discover new insights of the concepts. Furthermore, a system of Sámi snow concepts was discussed which might be useful in future adaptive management strategies in times of climate variability and change.</p>
<p>The theses focus on:</p>
<p>An identification of snow terms and concepts related to Sámi reindeer herding in the winter, including a review of the current literature on Sámi snow terms and how the concepts are understood and used locally in Guovdageaidnu (Paper I).</p>
<p>An examination of how each concept is used in the work of the reindeer herders in observation and monitoring of variability and change of snow and how these concepts are used in communicating the practical work with the herd; thus, providing a system of Sámi snow concepts. The aim was to develop a method to map the content and use of these concepts. (Paper II, IV)</p>
<p>An analysis to determine if different kinds of knowledge about snow could be combined and compared. The snow concepts were analyzed according to linguistics, snow physics, and reindeer herding practices. The different Sámi snow concepts of key importance for herding were then compared with snow physical characteristics from the International Classification for Seasonal Snow on the Ground. (Paper III).</p>
<p>A discussion of the importance of the knowledge embodied in the reindeer herders‟ terminology from the perspectives of resilience thinking and adaptive capacity of future reindeer herding management (Paper II, III, IV). <em type="bold">1.2 Reindeer herding and its’ basic premises </em></p>
<p>Approximately 2.5 million reindeer (Rangifer tarandus) graze and are herded in the world‟s tundra and taiga regions (Turi, 1999; Turi, 2002; Oskal <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2009; Maynard <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2010). Reindeer herding is a traditional livelihood in </p>
<p>Eurasia, carried out by more than 20 different ethnic indigenous Arctic peoples in Norway, Sweden, Finland, Russia, Mongolia and China, involving close to 100 000 herders (Oskal <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2009; Magga <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2011) In Norway approximately 3000 Sámi persons have private ownership of reindeer (www.reindrift.no). Reindeer herding has great cultural and economic significance for the indigenous peoples of northern Eurasia as well as for other peoples. </p>
<p>The basic ecological premises of reindeer herding as a pastoral means of subsistence are the variations of the seasons and the learned behavior by reindeer of migrating between and remaining in the same areas at different times of the year (Sara, 2001:81). Central features of pastoral life are the weather and wind. In the passage of the seasons there is certain consistency, yet, at the same time there are uncertainties that a humans cannot predict (Sara, 2007:9).</p>
<p>Reindeer herding consists of three basic components: reindeer, human and ecology. The relationship among these three is dynamic and characteristic of the nomadic way of life (Hågvar, 2006:132). Reindeer herding is an example of a human- environment coupled ecosystem (Turi, 2008; Oskal <em type="italic">et al., </em>2009). Within the basic confines of reindeer herding, there are two types of variations: one is climate variations, i.e., the changing seasons which affect the availability and use of resources, and the other is the variation in human labor input (Sara, 2001). </p>
<p>The basis of Sámi reindeer herding is nomadism, characterized by movement over vast areas along migration routes (Sara, 2001; Joks <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2006:93). Sámi reindeer herding exists in Norway, Finland, Sweden and Russia. </p>
<p>In Norway and in Sweden, reindeer herding is, by law, restricted to the Sámi people, which means that only Sámi are allowed to own individual reindeer. The</p>
<p>Sámi people are the indigenous people in the Sámi areas, and these areas are also identical with areas characterized by the Sámi language.</p>
<p>This study was carried out in western-Finnmark‟ Norway where the winter-grazing area consisted of 53 herding-groups (Sám: <em type="italic">siida </em>) in 2011 occupying an area of about 10787 km2 of winter-grazing land, (Figure 1). These winter herding-groups are divided into three herding zones: eastern, central and western. In the year 2008-2009 in western Finnmark, there were a total of 93603 reindeer, belonging to 1717 persons, who, in turn, belonged to 217 <em type="italic">siidas </em>(www.reindrift.no). <em type="bold">1.3 Indigenous Knowledge vs. Scientific Knowledge </em>1.3.1 The Definition, Form and Characteristics of Indigenous Knowledge </p>
<p>Indigenous communities have always had their own knowledge that has helped them in their everyday lives and enabled them to manage and survive for thousands of years in Arctic regions and in other parts of the world where indigenous peoples live (Magga <em type="italic">et al., </em>2011a). Traditional knowledge is indigenous peoples‟ and local communities‟ cumulative experience, gained through hundreds of years, from a traditional way of life and from the use and conservation of resources in the regions they inhabit and manage (Henriksen, 2002; Turi, 2009). It is through traditional knowledge and local know-how that these communities and cultures have maintained their way of life. </p>
<p>The concepts, <span type="quote">“indigenous knowledge (IK)”</span>, <span type="quote">“traditional knowledge (TK)”</span>, and <span type="quote">“traditional ecological knowledge (TEK)”</span> signify the unified body of knowledge and systems of knowledge. Berkes defines traditional knowledge thus: <span type="quote">“TK is a cumulative body of knowledge, practice and belief, evolving by adaptive processes and handed down through generations by cultural transmission”</span> (Berkes, 2008:7).</p>
<p>Indigenous knowledge is dynamic, because 1) knowledge is adaptable to environmental changes, and each generation can add to it with its own self-experienced knowledge and observations and 2) it incorporates social processes such as exploitation of resources, which vary from community to community (Peloquin &amp; Berkes, 2009:534). The difference between indigenous knowledge and traditional knowledge is that indigenous knowledge, from an indigenous perspective, is something that has been passed on through generations, and contains, as a dimension, in historical, social and cultural contexts, the experience of the relationship between state and the minority population (Keskitalo, 1993; Jannok-Nutti, 2007).</p>
<p>Krupnik <em type="italic">et al. </em>(2010) argues that the indigenous way of knowing about, or being able to do, was traditionally founded on careful attention to what was said and to the stories told by elders or adults. From a young age, children and young people start to accompany learned and experienced members of the community in order to observe and learn how they deal with practical problems and performed tasks. Their daily attention to how things were dealt with, both everyday things as well as dangerous things, taught them how to recognize phenomena such as dangerous ice and how to avoid it, while at the same time learning how to describe and point out these precise situations (Krupnik <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2010:351-52). </p>
<p>Some disciplines, such as ecology, considered a relatively new discipline, have shown their awareness of traditional knowledge. It should be added that this type of knowledge is, of course, also found among other peoples, although in western societies it appears in many respects to have disappeared, from areas such as science and the public arena. In Sámi societies, the demand has come for traditional knowledge to be given more emphasis, for example in the management of biological resources (Joks <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2006). </p>
<p>Reindeer herding knowledge may be defined as the knowledge of how to make use of the reindeer how to maintain an independent <em type="italic">siida </em>throughout and how to manage each individual animal as a resource, as well as of the relationship between the herd and its natural environment (Sara, 2001). </p>
<p>The reindeer herder‟s knowledge and sense of the natural environment is extraordinary, and of a different kind from that of a non-herder, for the herder has come to know the natural environment as a basic condition of life. While following the reindeer, the herder gets to experience nature in all its different situations, suffering bad weather as well as enjoying good weather (Sara, 2003: :94). Comparing the content of reindeer herding knowledge with that of indigenous knowledge and traditional knowledge, reindeer herding knowledge can be characterized as both indigenous and traditional knowledge categories.</p>
<p>Knowledge of nature is of fundamental value to the reindeer herder as it contains both his heritage and his identity (Sara, 2003:94). <em type="bold">1.3.2 Traditional Knowledge and Scientific Knowledge </em></p>
<p>Borgos (1993) believes that scientific knowledge and traditional knowledge are two paradigms of science in the Kuhn sense (Kuhn, 1996). This opinion shows that in the matter of these two models of knowledge, it does not necessarily have to be a question of one or the other (Borgos, 1993:8f.).</p>
<p>Integration of scientific and indigenous knowledge, for example in the domain of renewable resource co-management, purportedly blends the best of two world-views (Nakashima, 2000). Kalstad placed traditional knowledge within a reindeer herding context when discussing fundamental knowledge in connection with a plan for reindeer herding (Kalstad, 1993:40f.). In such knowledge-model systems, there are some features that divide traditional and western systems of knowledge, though it must be emphasized that the two models should not be regarded as separate <span type="quote">“spaces”</span>, which was also Borgos‟ point.</p>
<p>When comparing the characteristics of traditional knowledge with scientific knowledge, we find that traditional knowledge has certain distinctive features that distinguish it from scientific knowledge, such as the holistic way in which traditional knowledge views entire ecological systems (Berkes, 2008;</p>
<p>Peloquin &amp; Berkes, 2009). Knowledge is tested or verified by each person‟s own experiences in the everyday life of the community (Jernsletten, 1997; Berkes, 2008; Krupnik <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2010). Knowledge is constantly growing and developing and this means that things are constantly being learned through work, trial and error and the acquirement of skills (Berkes, 2008). In knowledge, quantifiable aspects are not emphasized, although that does not mean that knowledge is not precise or detailed (Magga, 2010). Knowledge may be mirrored in language, social-organization, norms, values, views, institutions and regulations. </p>
<p>Knowledge comes in the form in which it has been carried by the bearers of traditional knowledge. Therefore, it is important to remember that knowledge grow roots where it is developed and used (Turi, 2009). Broadly speaking, traditional knowledge can be said to differ from scientific knowledge with regard to structure, function, origin, basis and age (Borgos, 1992; Helander, 1993; Jernsletten; 1994; Joks <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2006; Berkes, 2008; Peloquin and Berkes, 2009). </p>
<p>Much research has been done and much is still in progress, aimed gaining a deeper knowledge and understanding of climate change from traditional knowledge models and also to investigate the concept of traditional knowledge (Berkes &amp; Jolly, 2001; Peloquin &amp; Berkes, 2009; Krupnik, <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2010). It is clear that indigenous peoples and their unique systems of values, knowledge and practices have been overlooked. There is an urgent need to correct the imbalance of mainstream-thinking by actively integrating indigenous peoples in the future starting with the framework for action. There is a real need to involve indigenous peoples directly in development processes, whether at local, national or global levels (Nakashima &amp; Chiba, 2006). Several projects have studied systems of traditional knowledge looking at issues such as weather-forecasting, monitoring of the environment, vegetation, animals, survival and adaptation strategies etc. (Nakashima, 1991; Burgess, 1999; Berkes &amp; Jolly, 2001; Davidson-Hunt &amp; O‟Flaherty, 2007). Traditional knowledge has inspired research into complex models of nature (Nakashima &amp; Roue, 2002). Traditional knowledge can also be viewed in the context of power and power relationships. </p>
<p>It has, up until now, hardly been touched on by governing authorities, either being rejected as an element or an argument in their decision-making (Joks <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2006). However, Dr. Robert Corell, who led the Arctic Council‟s work on the <span type="quote">“Arctic Climate Impact Assessment”</span> report, has clearly emphasized the value of including the voice and insights of indigenous peoples in climate research (Aftenposten, June 2006). The ACIA report pioneered the combination of traditional knowledge and western science and is an excellent example of how indigenous knowledge and know-how are important and valuable in understanding natural phenomena. <em type="bold">1.4. Past and future climate in Guovdageaidnu reindeer herding region western Finnmark </em></p>
<p>To better understand how Sámi reindeer herders‟ specialist language about snow and snow change, I will in this section characterize the historical and future winter climate locally in Guovdageaidnu where this language has been developed and used. 1.4.1 Past climate in the Guovdageaidnu herding region</p>
<p>Basic climate parameters such as temperature and precipitation have been recorded in the upper village of Guovdageaidnu in since 1889, and provide a unique set of data for use for characterizing the historical weather and climate conditions (Vikhamar-Schuler <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2010). Sámi reindeer herding has developed in Guovdageaidnu in a relative stable winter climate. The mean average winter (Dec-Jan-Feb) temperature has varied between about -8 and -22 oC (Figure 1a) providing cold and dry winters inland Finnmark for reindeer grazing (Vikhamar-Schuler <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2010). </p>
<p>The coldest mean annual average temperature -5.1 oC measured in</p>
<p>Norway was measured in 1893 and 1985 in the Guovdageaidnu region. The coldest absolute air temperature measured in Guovdageaidnu was -57 oC (not officially recorded) in January 1999. The highest and lowest maximum snow depth was 110 cm in 1936 and 34 cm in 1972 respectively.</p>
<p>Studies of time-series of Guovdageaidnu winter and spring temperatures through the 20th century show large inter-annual and inter-decadal</p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 1: Mean winter (Dec, Jan, Feb) (a) and spring (March, April, May) (b) air temperature measured in Guovdageaidnu from 1889 (Vikhamar-Schuler et al., 2010). </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 2: Mean winter (Dec, Jan, Feb) A) and spring (March, April, May) B) precipitation in Guovdageaidnu from 1889 (Vikhamar-Schuler et al., 2010). </em>variability (Figure 1 a,b) (Vikhamar-Schuler <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2010). The spring air temperatures are the only season for which the long-term temperature trends are statistically significant. In Guovdageaidnu, temperatures in spring increased by 1.5 oC from 1900 to 2000 (Hansen-Bauer, 2010). The average winter temperatures in Guovdageaidnu confirm that the winter temperatures in the inland area are about 10oC lower than they are along the coast. </p>
<p>On average there are 228 days annually with snow on the ground in the reindeer pastures (Vikhamar-Schuler <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2010). The duration of the snow season can be divided in to three main periods: first, a decreasing snow season from 1900 to the 1940‟s, when the snow season was delayed by one month; second, an increasing snow season from the 1950‟s until the 1970s; third, a variable snow season from about 1995 (maximum) followed by a reduction thereafter. The duration of the snow season in Guovdageaidnu decreased mainly as a result of increased air temperatures in the spring from 1955, but no trends were observed in fall (ibid.). ). </p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 3: Variation and change in first A) and last B) day with snow on the ground in Guovdageaidnu from 1955 (Vikhamar-Schuler et al., 2010). </em></p>
<p>There is a negative trend in the numbers of days with temperatures below -15oC over the last 50 years, whereas there is no clear positive or negative trend in the length of the cold season (number of days with temperatures below -15 oc) over the last 100 years (Vikhamar-Schuler <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2010). The air temperature in Guovdageaidnu has increased primarily in spring, while precipitation seems to have increased in all seasons (ibid). 1.4.2 Future projected climate in Guovdageaidnu </p>
<p>The projected future warming of air temperature in winter (Dec-Jan-</p>
<p>Feb), in Guovdageaidnu is more than 7 oC toward the end of the century (Benestad, 2011). The future winter temperatures in Guovdageaidnu may be similar to the present conditions in Nordreisa at the coast (Fig 5). The annual precipitation may increase by 5%, while the snow season may be more than one month shorter (Engen-Skaugen, 2007).</p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 4: Changes in number of days with air temperatures &lt;-15 degree C in Guovdageaidnu from 1955 A), and variation of maximum snow depth in Guovdageaidnu B) from 1995. (Vikhamar-Schuler et al., 2010). </em>-25-20-15-10-505101520 </p>
<p>Annual</p>
<p>Winter</p>
<p>Spring</p>
<p>Summer</p>
<p>Autumn</p>
<p>Temperature (Deg</p>
<p>C)</p>
<p>Nordreisa</p>
<p>Karasjok .</p>
<p>Karasjok Scen <em type="bold">2. THEORETICAL APPROACHES 2.1 Linguistic theoretical approach </em></p>
<p>It is the interdisciplinary nature of a research subject, viewed from an indigenous perspective that determines the theoretical approaches. The starting-point is the reindeer herders‟ specialist knowledge of the reindeer and of snow, how they use the specialized snow vocabulary in herding, how they discuss these matters and how, in their cognitive world, they consider them in relation to the survival of the individual animal and the herd as a whole. The theoretical approaches should describe this specialized vocabulary in linguistic terms as well as the cognitive aspect of the words and their use in a reindeer herding environment. I have chosen to combine linguistic methods of approach with terminology theory and cultural linguistics, and then analyze the data in relation to this. I have emphasized the terminology in the context of terminology science, which is the study of structure, formation, development, use and processing of concepts and terminologies in various subject areas (Myking, 2009). Linguistic methods of approach may support one another to provide patterns and an overview that may, in their turn, present the characteristics of the research</p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 5: Annual and seasonal temperature average for 1961-1990 measured at inland Finnmark (Karasjok) winter pastures and coastal Finnmark (Nordreisa) summer pastures, (full drawn lines) and the similar averages calculated from 50 downscaled climate models for the year 2085 (dotted lines) (Magga et al., 2011a). </em>subject. In this part I will present the theoretical methods of approach that may provide a theoretical explanation of Sámi snow terminology and snow concept analysis. 2.1.1 The basis of Sámi terminology </p>
<p>There is as strong a connection between the Sámi language and Sámi culture as there is between the language and the traditional Sámi livelihoods, since the language is both the language of work and the specialized technical language of these livelihoods (Helander, 1997:22). The concept of culture is wide ranging and includes, among other things, the acts and perceptions of people in their society as well as the values and evaluations made by people in their own life situation. The culture that belongs to a particular specialist subject field is part of a cultural environment‟s heritage and acts (Lauren <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2007:15). The Sámi have, until now, managed to maintain their traditions as a hunter –gatherer society over thousands of years, which have contributed to the survival of traditional knowledge of weather and climate, nature, and animals - knowledge which survives to the present day (Jernsletten, 1997). </p>
<p>Snow terminology is in daily use in winter, at least in reindeer herding (Eira, 2011 submitted). Sámi snow and ice terminological description provides systematic information about snow and ice conditions. Some snow and ice-related words are said to be as old as the Sámi language itself, and their use has been passed down from generation to generation until the present (Roung, 1964; Jernsletten, 1997:234-36), and they cannot therefore be compared to more recently constructed terms, used to designate modern articles or ideas.</p>
<p>Terms and phrases create a specialist language in each specialist field.</p>
<p>A specialist language is a form of language belonging to a certain subject or area of knowledge, which is used by experts (Store Norske Leksikon) and which is not part of everyday speech. A set of terms belonging to specialist language is defined as terminology (Sager, 1990; Lauren <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 1997:47). The development of specialist language is the starting point for the science of terminology and its terms represent the concept system of a particular specialist field (ISO, 1990). </p>
<p>Communication about the content of a specialist subject requires that the speakers are familiar with the relevant concepts and to this end both terms and terminology are necessary. It can therefore be said that communication in a specialist field is more demanding than communication in general language.</p>
<p>According to Jernsletten (1997:235), the Sámi have many specialist fields within their own specialist languages with specialist terms and phrases, which also contain cultural tradition and information from the Sámi‟s own understanding of their life and environment. 2.1.2 The function of language and terminology</p>
<p>Language is the means by which a person describes his or her own environment, acts, objects and events, etc, and concepts and terms are necessary to explain their meaning to other people (Eira <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2010). </p>
<p>Terminology has both a linguistic and a semantic basis (Sager, 1990:1-2) and this also applies to the study of signs like linguistics, semantics and semiotics (Rey, 1995:25). Terminology is, first and foremost, a tool for other functions such as specialist field communication and documentation, etc.</p>
<p>The development of terminology has been influenced by many scientific disciplines, such as, linguistics, logic, ontology, philosophy, theory of science and informatics (Lauren <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 1997:26). </p>
<p>Language has a cognitive function, while at the same time having a textual and communicative function (Temmerman, 2000:61). On the cognitive side, descriptive linguistics defines and describes knowledge (Temmerman, 2000). Specialist language (terminology) also has cognitive, linguistic and social aspects (Rey, 1995:116). Myking (1996:115) argues that terminology is a linguistic discipline that organizes cognitive and communicative knowledge.</p>
<p>Some of the principal researchers into terminology in the Nordic countries are Picht, Myking, Lauren (Lauren <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 1997). They argue that terminology is founded on a basis of Aristotelian philosophy and of semantic and structural field theory, to which, in recent years has been added prototype theory. In this discipline, the emphasis is on disjunction as well as on concept-realization on the synchronic level (ibid.). Palmer combines linguistic anthropological theories, adding cognitive linguistic elements to produce a theory of cultural linguistics. He believes that particular circumstances can reveal language‟s cognitive patterns. These circumstances show that a world view influences basic models, depending on which languages of the world are the template (Palmer, 1996). Both cognitive and cultural linguistics utilize mental models that are memorized thoughts about how things function and fit together, in order to show how cognitive processes produce patterns from what a person thinks and understands. Mental models play a central role in representing objects and phenomena, defining matters and designating events and showing how we understand the world. Mental models are thought memories of how things function and how they fit together. Cognitive researchers have studied mental models in order to understand how a person knows, recognizes, decides and behaves in different environments. Mental models contain a person‟s understanding of things and affect the way he or she is able to predict the consequences of their actions. They are a simplified version of the reality that objects and concepts represent (Palmer, 1996:55-56). Berkes &amp; Berkes (2009) argue that the production of indigenous peoples‟ mental model follows the patterns of people‟s language use, as language generates terms and concepts, the mental process in an information bundle and the concept from production to storage. They present examples from Inuit society, their mental model, how they evaluate the health and quality of animals, e.g. how fat/thin a seal is (ibid). This evaluation is a language-based construction and pays less attention to numerically precise data. The Inuit rarely make simple linear cause-and-effect type of connections as is often the case in western science. Rather, they study empirically environmental changes and make related observations. According to the Inuit world-view, it is childishness and thoughtlessness that generates simplifications and generalizations of complex phenomena (ibid.). If all holistically constructed concept realizations were to be specified, whole thought would become unmanageably complex. There seems to be a mutual connection between the complexity of the system and the preciseness of the definition, and this can be used to describe something meaningfully (Berkes &amp; Berkes, 2009:7-8). The more we study languages, the clearer it becomes how much environment, circumstance and need influence the creation of concepts (Magga, 2004). This was also the opinion of Sapir and Wolf, who proposed the hypothesis used in linguistic realism. They believe that the prerequisite of thought is language, and that people view the world in different ways, according to which language they speak, since they constitute and classify the world according to those categories that our language possesses (Sapir, 1968). </p>
<p>The definition of mental models from an indigenous perspective is termed fuzzy logic and it was initially introduced as a mathematical approach to deal with complex systems (Berkes, 2008; Berkes &amp; Berkes, 2009). In the case of fuzzy logic things need not be precisely defined or quantified before they can be considered mathematically. Information is classified into broad categorizations or groups which show the working of the human mind. The premise is that the most important elements of human thinking are not numbers, but labels containing fuzzy sets (Zadeh, 1973:28; Berkes &amp; Berkes, 2009:7-12).</p>
<p>Fuzzy logic has three main features: 1) the use of linguistic variables rather than, or in addition to, numerical variables; 2) characterization by simple relationships between variables of fuzzy logic; and 3) characterization by complex relationships between fuzzy algorithms. For example <span type="quote">“fat, thin, very thin”</span> values of linguistic are variability for how fat something is (Berkes &amp; Berkes, 2009:9).</p>
<p>These features are also found in the methods used by reindeer-herders to categorize snow, where they use phrases like thick layer of ice instead of 10 cm layer of ice (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2011, submitted). </p>
<p>Berkes &amp; Berkes (2009) argue that like the human mind, fuzzy logic also brings together related objects according to category in order to reduce the complexity for problem solving. Fuzzy logic facilitates classification in extremely wide-ranging or diverse categories or groups. Halfpenny &amp; Ozanne (1989:38) also mention how indigenous peoples (Native Americans and Inuit) use language to precisely define snow conditions that may be dangerous for them. They also write that indigenous peoples did not use numbers to define these conditions, but rather that their rich descriptive vocabulary enabled them to define, both fresh and transformed types of snow and snow conditions. Reindeer herders are in the same situation, since they preside over very many variables.</p>
<p>When herding, they must, at one and same the same time, attend to and watch over the herd, to see how it behaves, how the animals are doing, what the temperature is, how wet it is and from which direction the wind is blowing etc.</p>
<p>This is part of their mental model, the main rule of which is to, check the edge of the herd and assess how hard the snow is (Eira <em type="italic">et al., </em>2011, submitted). </p>
<p>Nils Isak Eira (1994:23) writes that reindeer-herding is arranged in such a way that all the members of a herding-group have to communicate and resolve matters in council for the success of the group and this is why understanding, communication and knowledge are so important. In herding internal communication with respect to the actual herding is of major importance (Sara, 1990:92), and this communication often contains specialist reindeer herding terms, which are used to inform others about the state of the herd, the grazing, the reindeer and the terrain. This includes precise identification and description relating both the reindeer and the terrain and to the prevailing natural conditions. An experienced reindeer herder can, with just a few words, explain in detail to another about, e.g., grazing conditions, a characteristic or easily identifiable reindeer etc., as well as to other matters (Eira, 1994). The content of the information that is most valuable rather than the amount of information, “It isn‟t a question of how many words and explanations or descriptions are presented, but how much information they contain (Eira, 1984). 2.1.3 Concepts</p>
<p>Concepts are mental or logical representations of reality that create a system in the human mind for classifying and understanding the perception of the intellect (Antia, 1999). Linguists of various traditions have long argued about how to define the content of a concept and how to test it. Here we have, on the one hand, those who follow traditional terminological methods and on the other, those who emphasize the cognitive and cultural aspects of language.</p>
<p>Temmerman (2000), who has studied biology texts, believes that the principles and methods of traditional terminology do not take account of the fact that terminology plays an important role in communicative and cognitive settings.</p>
<p>According to her theory, traditional terminology must quire methods that can investigate and describe all the aspects that play an important role in the process of understanding specialist language (Temmerman, 2000:220-221).</p>
<p>A terminologically defined concept may be compared to a semantic structure in which the semantic characteristics are one with the concept‟s intention (Lauren <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 1997:76). Researchers define the concept-concept in many different ways, but central to all these definitions is that the concept at least touches on the cognitive aspect of the word‟s explanation. Magga (2007) states that a concept is something that a person pictures in the mind, and which he/she believes that function in such a way as to require or be suited by a designation. The international terminology standard states that the concept is a unit of thought constituted through abstraction on the basis of properties that is common to a set of objects (ISO, 1990). This may be characterized as a phenomenon (a part of the real world that one wishes to describe), an understanding or thought. Temmerman (2000:42) calls the concept a unit of understanding. Concepts possess characteristics (Suonuuti, 2008), which means that it is the concept‟s characteristics that make the concept. The characteristics are important in the making of the definition (Picht &amp; Draskau, 1985). 2.1.4 Concept analysis and categorization </p>
<p>The content of a concept can be explained with a definition (Lauren <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 1997:107). The oral and/or written definition of a concept helps in distinguishing one concept from another neighboring concept (Suonuuti, 2008:15). In order to define the meaning of a lexical unit, we need a definition that provides the smallest and most important piece of information about the concept (Temmerman, 2000:83). The function of the definition is that, it can show the position of the concept in the concept system in such a way that the term is placed at the level above, in relation to the concept, and that it is given the sufficient number of characteristics necessary to separate and distinguish it from other concepts on the same horizontal plane of the concept-system (Temmerman, 2000). Definition helps to show the concept in relation and with reference to other concepts. </p>
<p>Specialist field concepts, for example, may be analyzed with terminological methods to determine the concept‟s characteristics and to investigate their relationships and connections to other concepts in the same specialist field. Nuopponen, (1994:30; 1996:171) believes that each concept should be able to be place in a concept-system so that it is easier to structure a particular specialist field, and that type of systematic thinking is in accordance with structuralism (for example Saussure and Wüster) (Lauren <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 1997:113-14). </p>
<p>On the terminology side it is believed that a concept should have a term or designation so that its meaning is precise, and best of all is if the definition determines the term‟s meaning so that it can be identified and understood (Wüster, 1985:7). However Temmerman (2000:81) believes that it is impossible to give a clear, unambiguous concept structure that provides a definition including the necessary and extensive characteristics that distinguish the concept from other concepts. A concept-system is a system containing related concepts which together form a whole. In terminology, we cannot study individual concepts as separate units, only in their own concept-context, together with other concepts (Picht &amp; Draskau, 1985:62; Lauren <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 1997). Concepts may be in different concept-systems, depending on what connection there is between the concepts (Nuopponen, 1994:237). </p>
<p>The term <span type="quote">“extension”</span> is used in cultural linguistics to refer to similarities‟ in categorization groups (Palmer, 1996:78). This term is also used in terminology science and has the same meaning there, i.e. the extension of a concept that designates characteristics (referents) which belong to the concept, often shown as a list (Lauren <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 1997:115; Suonuuti, 2008). The opposite term to this is elaboration, which refers to categorization which is entirely re-enforced by the upper level schema (Palmer, 1996:92). In terminology, the opposite term is known as the intention of concept by which the concept‟s distinguishing features and peculiar characteristics are identified and distinguished in relation to other concepts (Lauren <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 1997:116; Suonuuti, 2008:23). These concepts are used in connection with terminology when creating definitions. </p>
<p>It is possible to organize knowledge using category systems. (Davidson, 1984:182) Nuopponen argues that if we wish to present human knowledge that has been produced and developed in a certain specialized field, then not only the concepts must be defined but also the relationship between the concepts, in what she calls a concept-system. Hierarchical concept-analysis assists in transmitting one‟s thoughts to another to communicate with others about one‟s own thoughts (Nuopponen, 1994:36). Concept systems are like maps that show us what the world is made of and how it is put together.</p>
<p>Traditional terminology puts a concept in a concept structure, which is almost like categorization. This concept structure is a logic-based structure, which shows that X is some kind of Y, or an ontological classification, thus X is a part of Y. A category and each category in a cognitive model is produced by the understanding of it (Temmerman, 2000:224). Concepts make categorization possible and provide information about individual, category-related, knowledge concerning entities (Cruse, 2004:127). Temmerman (2000:65) believes that categories are units of mental understanding. Understanding is experienced-based and is built on previous knowledge.</p>
<p>Classification, on the other hand, can provide a systematic overview which shows the similarities and varieties of the matter under investigation (Nuopponen, 1994:33). Indigenous peoples‟ snow and ice terminology contains different classifications and categories. Among the Slave Indians of Northwest</p>
<p>Territories an ice-taxonomy is used for evaluating travel conditions. They have 13 categories divided into three groups: solid ice, melting-ice and cracking ice.</p>
<p>The 13 concepts do not consist of separate or individual words, but are derived from a single root (Silver <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 1997:72-73). Certain types of ice are better for transport in all three kinds of travel; other types do not permit travel at all while others, though not all, do allow passage. There are 39 situations in all and for each there are three possible approaches: 1) cross the ice, 2) make a detour, or 3) proceed cautiously, and examine the ice (ibid). This can be compared with sámi snow classification that includes various ice forms, eg. <em type="italic">cuoŋu, moarri </em>. (Appendix 1) </p>
<p>Temmerman (2000) believes that we are not always able to understand concepts precisely enough, but rather that we have to take into consideration that concepts may be slightly unclear or undefined. This is the feature of general language. Thus, one cannot expect clear boundaries between them.</p>
<p>When analyzing Sámi snow-terminology, consideration must be given to the starting-point of this specialist terminology, which is drawn from oral tradition and not from collected texts or a corpus of written material.</p>
<p>Temmerman explains how, in her area of research, she has worked with words, making particular mention of how she has collected specialist vocabulary from texts, which she has subsequently made into a list (Temmerman. 2000:226).</p>
<p>Terminology can be used as a tool with which to present concepts in a concept-system overview (Nuopponen, 1997), and cognitive linguistics on the other hand can be used to test cognitive structures, such as, for example, images related to mental models. In this study, I have used conceptual analysis based on the language of reindeer herders and the theoretical approaches mentioned to describe Sámi snow terminology. <em type="bold">2.2 A scientific approach in relation to snow and reindeer herding </em>2.2.1 Snow, its characteristics and its role in winter-ecology </p>
<p>In the cold regions of the world, snow covers the land for a large part of the year. The impacts of snow on the climate system and snow cover variability and change have important consequences for nature and for human systems (Armstrong &amp; Brun, 2008:6). The temperatures on and close to the ground, and the melting/freezing process have a major impact on the diversity and productivity of the ecosystem (ibid.).</p>
<p>Snow science distinguishes between snow in the atmosphere and snow on the ground caused by precipitation. Snow and snow-covering2 is built up of different layers of snow and ice of different thicknesses, hardness and types etc. (Pruitt, 1966; Colbeck <em type="italic">et al., </em>1990; Fierz <em type="italic">et al. </em>; 2009). </p>
<p>Snow has a complex structure, which is constantly changing (Armstrong &amp; Brun, 2008:13; Brattlien, 2008:59). Snow is water in <span type="quote">“solid form”</span>. In snow-physics, a snow-grain is a mechanically separate particle in a covering of snow (LaChapelle, 1992:5). The crystals, which make up snow, are ice crystals that form in the clouds. Air, temperature and form affect the changes in the form and type of the crystal as it falls towards the ground (Halfpenny <em type="italic">&amp; </em></p>
<p>Ozanne, 1989:38; Lied &amp; Kristiansen, 2003:39; Landrø, 2007:37). If the air temperature decreases below 0oC, the extra water content turns to ice crystals. 2</p>
<p>Snow in layers on the ground (Hestnes <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2010) </p>
<p>The lower the temperature, the more ice crystals are formed (ibid). All snow crystals are hexagonal, but are constantly changing according to humidity and temperature. There are thousands of different forms of crystals, but the most common are forms resembling stars, plates and needles, while the most common snow crystal of all is a hexagonal, star-shaped crystal (Lied &amp; Kristiansen, 2003:41; Landrø, 2007:35). No two crystals are alike (LaChapelle, 1992:3). 2.2.2 Snow transformation</p>
<p>Snow is divided into three types: 1) Falling snow, 2) snow on the ground and 3) surface ice features. (Halfpenny <em type="italic">&amp; </em>Ozanne, 1989:38-40) Air-temperature, air-humidity, wind and radiation effect transformations of the snow-crystals from the time they reach the ground (Halfpenny <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 1989:41; </p>
<p>Armstrong &amp; Brun, 2008:27). These changes are called metamorphosis, which is basically a geological term meaning structural change, caused by heat or pressure (LaChapelle, 1992:3). A distinction is made between wet and dry snow metamorphism (Armstrong &amp; Brun, 2008:27). There are at least four different processes that transform snow: destructive, constructive, melt/freeze metamorphosis and sintering. These processes can occur at simultaneously (Armstrong &amp; Brun, 2008; Jaedicke, 2009). The first three occur in dry, cold snow while the fourth occurs in wet snow (Brattlien, 2008:60). Dry snow is defined as snow that contains no liquid water, whereas in wet snow more than 0.1 % of the volume is liquid water (Armstrong &amp; Brun, 2008:27-28).</p>
<p>Destructive transformation refers to the process by which hexagonal crystals are turned into smaller, more rounded ones. Where there is little difference in temperature between surface and depth/bottom snow, and where the temperature is sufficiently high, from 0 °C to about -8 °C, is the situation in which the destructive transformation process starts to occur. It is in such weather conditions that the snow crystals change shape, from a pointed-star to a more rounded crystal. This change in shape causes the snow to sink, whereupon the snow is squeezed and pressed and the crystals stick together easily. The density3 of the snow may increase, reaching up to 300kg/m3 in normal circumstances.</p>
<p>The porosity of the snow may be reduced by about 65%, but snow contains, by volume, more air than ice (Halfpenny <em type="italic"></em>&amp; Ozanne <em type="italic">, </em>1989:43; LaChapelle, 1992; </p>
<p>Lied &amp; Kristiansen, 2003:50-51; Landrøe, 2007:36-37).</p>
<p>The constructive metamorphism process occurs where the temperature difference between surface and ground is great. For example, the ground temperature may be close to 0 °C, but at the surface it may be much colder. A temperature gradient will show how much the temperature diverges from a certain given value of the snow depth (°C/m). In a covering of snow, the temperature is measured from the surface to the bottom, right down to the ground, and a small gradient would be, for example, -1 (°C/m) and a steep gradient would be -25 °C (°C/m). The constructive transformation process starts when the gradient is at least -10 °C per meter (Hestnes <em type="italic">et al, </em>2010). When the temperature gradient in the snow is approximately -10 °C per meter, warm air has more water-vapor than cold air. This means that the saturation-pressure is greater near the bottom than in the colder snow above it and, thus the water-vapor rises up through the snow. During this process, the crystals change from a rounded shape to a shape with flat, sharp edges. These crystals sparkle if viewed in the light. The snow crystals increase in size and become square-shaped, and may increase in size by up to 2 -3 mm. (Halfpenny &amp; Ozanne <em type="italic">et al., </em>1989:43; </p>
<p>LaChapelle, 1992:18; Lied &amp; Kristiansen, 2003:53-55; Landrøe, 2007:39-40).</p>
<p>When the surface of the snow freezes hard, the crystals at the surface become square-shaped. Though the destructive process is at work during the day, it is not able to maintain the transformation. The longer this process lasts, the thicker such a layer becomes (Landrøe, 2007:40). Around trees and stones that the snow has covered, there are often hollow spaces. Such places give the crystals room to grow, and if there is little snow as well as freezing temperatures, they increase 3 Density refers to Mass per Volume, specified in kg/m3 quickly in size and the snow quickly turns to <em type="italic">seaŋáš </em>. Following a long, cold-spell, the whole covering of snow may be <em type="italic">seaŋáš </em>(Lied &amp; Kristiansen, 2003:54-55), which means that the snow is porous. </p>
<p>The melt-freeze process occurs when the snow temperature rises above 0 °C. Ice crystals then begin to melt and make the snow wet. The sun, temperature, high air-humidity and rain determine when this process takes place.</p>
<p>As the snow melts, water forms around each crystal, transporting the melt-water from the ends/tips of the crystals to the hollows. When the melting is rapid, the shape of the crystals becomes almost completely round. If it then freezes again, the crystals stick together and the snow and surface of the snow become very dense (Halfpenny &amp; Ozanne, 1989:48; Lied &amp; Kristiansen, 2003:55-56;</p>
<p>Landrøe, 2007:37-38).</p>
<p>Sintering is a transformation process in which the movement of molecules causes the crystals to freeze together, even though the snow has not melted. The crystals are so close to one another that they stick together, bound by threads of ice. The smaller the crystals are, the greater the amount of ice-binding per unit of volume. Before the process of sintering begins, the snow is quite porous, particularly if it has recently been snowing, without drifting. The snow density becomes very high because of the formation of the ice-threads bindings. In drifted snow, the crystals are very small, less than 0.5 mm in diameter (Halfpenny <em type="italic">&amp; </em>Ozanne, 1989:45; Lied &amp; Kristiansen, 2003:53-54). </p>
<p>In general language, the term snow also includes the surface-created ice-features that ecologists believe to be so important (Halfpenny <em type="italic">&amp; </em>Ozanne, 1989:38). Layers of ice occur in three different ways: rolled or compressed by the wind, with the heat of the sun (melting/freezing) and freezing following rain (Halfpenny <em type="italic">&amp; </em>Ozanne, 1989:49). When it snows in different types of weather, it affects the surface of the snow, but also the snow cover in general, so that fresh snow covers the layer that was previously at the surface and thus the snow gains layers (Brattlien, 2008:27). 2.2.3 Snow classification 2.2.3.1 Snow classification based on snow physics </p>
<p>Research into snow has led to the formulation of various different classifications to describe the various different types of snow. Snow has been classified according to its physics (physical properties) (Colbeck <em type="italic">et al. </em>1990; </p>
<p>Fierz <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2009). The International Classification of Seasonal Snow on the </p>
<p>Ground is one of the oldest snow classifications and has recently been revised (Fierz <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2009). The aim of classification is to create qualitative descriptions of the shape and size of the snow grains (Armstrong &amp; Brun, 2008:21), that numerous different user-groups can employ, from researchers to skiers. </p>
<p>Classification is based on observations made using simple equipment or purely by means of visual observation (Hestnes <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2010:2). In these classifications, falling snow is divided into nine categories according to form (morphological classification). They also contain process-based classification as well as additional information on the physical processes behind the various types of snow and how strong the particular type of snow is (Kristensen, 2007; Fierz <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2009). 2.2.3.2 Snow classification based on ecologic traditional knowledge </p>
<p>A classification of Sámi snow-vocabulary has also been produced by separating terms into groups according to meaning, but it was Israel Ruong (1964:76-77) who put a clear dividing line between the various term-groups: 1) amount of snow (how much snow there is), 2) consistency of snow, 3) the snow‟s bearing capacity, 4) snow-conditions (for mobility/transport), 5) untrodden snow and tracks in the snow, 6) rime and coating of ice (on trees and other things), 7) melting and baring (of ground), 8) remaining spots/areas of snow in summer and 9) the various levels of winter-grazing conditions. Ruong describes snow from an ecological perspective, and his point of departure was to explain ecology as knowledge of the relationship of organisms (living and dead) to the environment as well as the connection animals and plants have to one another and to the climate, to food, and to the land. He examined the relationship between herder and reindeer and between reindeer and the land. (Ruong, 1964)</p>
<p>Ruong believes that it is possible to divide snow into many categories according to factors such as amount or quantity of snow, consistency of snow and he created nine categories for his classification,. Using this same classification,</p>
<p>Svonni (1981) and Jernsletten (1994) have also described Sámi snow-terminology.</p>
<p>Svonni has shown that weather-terms have an extremely clear degree of specialization, which demonstrates that the Sámi people have deep knowledge of weather and climate (1981:6-13). Indeed, in his article he has provided an explanation of both weather and snow terminology. He describes weather through snowfall, wind and temperature. Svonni shows, with his own overview of weather-terms, that there are many concepts that are related to weather processes, such as the processes involved in snowfall and wind that affect the snow as well as concepts where temperature is also a factor (Svonni, 1981).</p>
<p>The use of concept analysis on physical and strategic characteristics reveals the details in these snow concepts used in reindeer herding (Eira <em type="italic">et al., </em>2011 submitted). This is also discussed in Chapter 4. <em type="bold">3. METHODOLOGY </em></p>
<p>The starting point of this study is linguistics, i.e. it is an investigation of the content and use of snow terminology in reindeer herding. To gain and achieve the interdisciplinary dimension in the study, it has been necessary to use methods that reflect this. <em type="bold">3.1 Research area </em></p>
<p>The project was carried out in the winter grazing area of Guovdageaidnu in the reindeer herding region of western</p>
<p>Finnmark (Figure 6). The total area (total surface area) covered by the western</p>
<p>Finnmark reindeer herding region is approx. 24,400 km2 and includes the western part of the county of Finnmark as well as the northernmost areas of the county of Troms.</p>
<p>The Guovdageaidnu – Kárášjohka municipal boundary marks the division between the herding regions of western -Finnmark and eastern-Finnmark. <em type="bold">3.2 Description of data </em></p>
<p>The collected data consists of interviews, video recordings, photographs, herding diaries, snow measurements and temperature measurements (Table 1)</p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 1: Overview of research methods used </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Research element /Collection of data types </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Collection method </em></p>
<p>Snow terminology in reindeer herding</p>
<p>Interview and community based workshop</p>
<p>Day to day use of snow terminology</p>
<p>Community based monitoring system in terms of diary use.</p>
<p>Combination of snow concepts and snow physics.</p>
<p>Snow measurements Temperature measurements</p>
<p>Weather and snow observations</p>
<p>Diaries</p>
<p>Data analysis</p>
<p>Collect snow concepts and extract their meaning and content</p>
<p>Collect snow terms from interviews, lists, articles. Make a list of snow terms. Concept analysis and categorization Snow physics</p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 6: western Finnmark reindeer herding region, winter grazing lands, divided into three herding zones. </em></p>
<p>Photographs</p>
<p>Use of snow concepts</p>
<p>Analysis of diaries with meteorological data and compared with snow measurements</p>
<p>Reindeer herders experience and understanding of climate change, their adaptation mechanisms and their understanding and assessment of what constitutes a risk to the herd.</p>
<p>Analysis of interviews and diaries.</p>
<p>The collection of data has been carried out by means of semi-structured interviews in order to obtain detailed information about, and a greater insight into snow and grazing conditions. The semi-structured interview lies somewhere between pure structured interview and loose interview. Here, it is an open, prepared, oral interview (Dalen, 2004). The interviews were conducted in the Sámi language. According to Krupnik <em type="italic">et al. </em>(2010) it is important to use the language spoken by the people interviewed. </p>
<p>The interviews of 34 peoples (from the CEAVVI project, appendix 2) were conducted between 2007 and 2009. The interviews were fully transcribed.</p>
<p>The study has obtained a substantial amount of material, 800 pages of transcriptions.</p>
<p>With regard to monitoring the day-to-day of snow terminology within the <em type="italic">siida’s </em>, a method was developed in which the members of the siida themselves conducted the monitoring by keeping diaries. In unifying the snow concepts with snow physics, we have combined the content in Sámi snow concepts with snow measurements, temperature measurements, weather and snow observations and monitoring diaries (Eira <em type="italic">et al </em>2010; Eira &amp; Mathiesen, 2011 in prep; Eira <em type="italic">et al., </em>2011, submitted). From the analysis of the herding dairies (Eira &amp; Mathiesen, 2011, in prep) we have obtained information about how reindeer herders experience and understand climate change, about their adaptation mechanisms and their understanding and assessment of what might constitute a risk to the herd. </p>
<p>In order to understand and gain insight into how herders manage their herd in winter, I have also accompanied the herders in the field and observed them in their interaction and communication with others in the <em type="italic">siida </em>. This has enabled me to see and better understand how the herders, through their use of concepts and their ecological knowledge, manage the herd, which is a participatory observation (Stene, 1999). It is also possible, using these methods, to discover and to present dimensions that have previously been little understood. In addition to direct observations and conversations, I have also taken notes throughout in addition to visualizing the subject on photograph and film. <em type="bold">3.3 Informants </em></p>
<p>In choosing informants for this study, it was a necessary requirement that each participant should have learned the specialist reindeer herding terminology through working in the field and that each should have been accustomed to using this terminology on a daily basis.</p>
<p>The two focus informants, people having expert knowledge about the issue, were chosen based on the fact that:1) they have worked with reindeer their whole life, from a very early age, 2) they both span two generations, 3) they are both good at presenting and explaining things. The first focus informant was Mr.</p>
<p>Aslak Anders Isaksen Eira, born in 1917, who is a member of the Cohkolat herding district. He has worked with reindeer his whole life and has moved with the reindeer along several of the migration routes. He is no longer part of a herding-group, but he still has reindeer, under his son‟s the supervision. He still works with reindeer, or at least when the herd is corralled. Though he is advanced in years; he still has an extremely good memory. The second informant, Mr. Isak Mathis O. Eira, born in 1942, is a member of the</p>
<p>Fávrrosorda herding district. He is part of a <em type="italic">siida </em>and deals with the herd on a daily basis. He has also long been head of his winter <em type="italic">siida </em>. Their descriptions have formed the basis for the snow conceptual analysis, and therefore these are not marked in the text, except where informants have described specific factors of the concept. </p>
<p>Ten informants from five <em type="italic">siidas </em>belong to one of western Finnmark‟s three herding zones (Eira &amp; Mathiesen, 2011, in prep). With the help of dairies, <em type="italic">siidas </em>have themselves been able to monitor snow conditions affecting grazing. </p>
<p>Monitoring, or keeping track of resources is a process in which the community itself monitors, checks, investigates, and assesses the things that are important to the community. (Eira &amp; Mathiesen, 2011, in prep) The idea of the herding diaries was to obtain daily data showing how reindeer herders manage their herd in winter, how their assessed the conditions affecting reindeer, how their characterized grazing snow conditions and the strategies their used to solve different situations and conditions (ibid.).</p>
<p>In the CEAVVI4 project 12 young Sámi research assistants have collected and documented reindeer herders‟ traditional knowledge of snow and grazing conditions. The aim of this project is, is to collect and document as much of the reindeer herders‟ traditional knowledge as possible. The interviews have been transcribed. Information about the informants is provided in Appendix 2. The research assistants had either completed a course in reindeer herding at the Sámi University College or taken courses as part of the EALÁT project.</p>
<p>They had also received training in how to document traditional knowledge, and how to conduct an interview, in how to find relevant informants.</p>
<p>In the study I have also used historical recordings from the 1970s in order to access historical data subjects such as the way in which herders recounted their experiences and memories of unusual winters and snow conditions, so as to compare snow conditions with historical climate data. 4The project is connected to this research project and also forms a part of the EALÁT project run by the Sámi University College together with the International Centre for Reindeer Herding (ICR).</p>
<p>Most of the informants, with the exception of the focus informants, are anonymous at the request of the informants themselves. The informants were far more open in describing issues and experiences, and in naming persons and areas, because they were confident that they would remain anonymous in accordance with a written agreement. In this study all the informants have been informed of and provided with the facility to review and comment on the data, data analysis and the results to be published (ICR, 2006). <em type="bold">3.4 Snow physics and temperature measurements </em></p>
<p>Snow measurements were made in the herding stations, on the tundra, near Čuonjájávri, approx. 20 km from Guovdageaidnu, and at a test station near the village.</p>
<p>Air– and snow temperature measurements were taken both at the herding stations (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2011, submitted) and the test station, near the village. </p>
<p>For this purpose we used the</p>
<p>Thermochron measuring device, which was fixed to a one and a half meter long impregnated pole (Figure 7). The Thermochrons incorporate two pieces of technology - a micro-chip in a small steel box (iButton) and a program for recording data (1-wire). It is the iButton that is</p>
<p>Thermochron‟s temperature sensor, clock and memory. A 1-wire can be used to read off the data it has recorded. (http://www.thermodata.com.au). Thus, the</p>
<p>Thermochrons measured the temperature every six hours, at: 07.00, 13.00, 19.00 etc. To each snow pole six Thermochrons were placed at: 10 cm, 35 cm, 50 cm, 75 cm and 150 cm to the ground, (Figure 7). A radiation shield was attached to</p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 7: Equipment for measuring air temperature. </em>the most elevated Thermochron which protected against radiation, so that we obtained the most reliable possible data. A snow pole like this was erected in the winter area of each herding station. The project has had 42 Thermochrons attached to poles at the herding stations and at the observation station. The </p>
<p>Thermocrons were used for three winter periods. (Maynard <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2010; Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2011, submitted). <em type="bold">4. NORTH SÁMI SNOW CONCEPTS, THEIR CONTENT AND USE </em></p>
<p>A total of 318 traditional Sámi concepts of various types of snow and snow conditions and snow transformation related to reindeer herding in the</p>
<p>Guovdageaidnu reindeer herding region, are shown in Appendix 1. These concepts can be divided into two main categories: first, snow concepts containing elements of the physical nature of snow and ice (snow type, snow conditions, snow transformation, and also on matters affecting the snow or the result of impact, such as temperature, wind, precipitation, air) and, second, there are snow concepts with a wider meaning than snow physics, which can be defined as basic concepts in reindeer herding related to reindeer survival mobility, tracking conditions and visibility.</p>
<p>A theoretical concept analysis was used to determine the differences between the concepts related to content and use (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2010; Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2011, submitted; Eira &amp; Mathiesen, 2011, in prep). </p>
<p>The study confirms that the Sámi language is probably the language with the richest terminology relating to snow, and even richer than the Inuit languages which since the end of the 1800s have been believed by linguists to have the most snow words of all languages (Krupnik <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2010). <em type="bold">4.1 Summary of the articles </em></p>
<p>The first article on “ <em type="italic">North Sámi snow concepts meaning and usage </em>” (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2010) is a review of the literature and an introductory analysis of </p>
<p>North Sámi snow concepts and snow terminology, their use and definitions. The focus of this article is on explaining the meaning of traditional snow concepts and particularly their usage with respect to the need for communication and to the basic premises of Sámi reindeer herding. Sámi snow concepts are related to factors that affect reindeer survival and sustainability, the well-being of reindeer and the human working conditions. The content and use of the most central snow concepts is discussed on the basis of terminological theory, and in particular on the basis of six basic elements of practical reindeer herding (the reindeer's needs; access to pasture, access to shelter, snow conditions, and mobility; the human tasks and needs; snow conditions, mobility for skiing, tracking, and visibility). The concepts appear to be linked to one another depending on which elements of reindeer herding they are used to describe and communicate. An important finding is that there are frequently two or more critical conditions that regulate the use of Sámi snow concepts: 1) the time when the concept is used and 2) the context of the concept. Analysis shows a pattern in how herders describe Sámi snow concepts, and also that the concept often contains several characteristics, in which at least 7 different factors are mentioned: 1) Weather/snow transformation, 2) Snow quality, 3) Density, 4)</p>
<p>Stratigraphy, 5) The impact of snow on reindeer, 6) Time of use and 7) The behavior of reindeer. The article demonstrates the challenges encountered in defining the conceptual content. The content of snow concepts comprises both a basic definition, which often can be intuitive and not explicit and connected to practical use, but also to communicative functions. In this respect, they differ in an important way from concepts which have been developed to express scientifically defined concepts. It seems that the concepts of a natural traditional language are far more difficult to define than consciously constructed specialized concepts and terms.</p>
<p>The second article is “ <em type="italic">A novel siida-based monitoring system to observe effects of climate variability of winter pastures in Sámi reindeer herding </em>” (Eira &amp; Mathiesen, 2011, in prep). It deals with the question how to monitor effects of climate variability, and changes in reindeer winter pasture based on traditional knowledge embodied in Sámi reindeer herder specialist language. A novel observational system was developed, using a specially designed herding diary which focused on snow conditions and their impact on herding practices in winter. This involved herders from five different <em type="italic">siidas </em>from </p>
<p>Guovdageaidnu in northern Norway monitoring and making their own daily observations of variations in snow condition, wind, precipitation, topography related to herd behavior and welfare for a five-month period over three consecutive winters (2007 - 2009) and expressed through their traditional knowledge. The results indicate that the herders‟ diaries can be used as a monitoring tool to observe variability and diversity in grazing condition between days, grazing locations, and between <em type="italic">siidas </em>, and to document the herders‟ herding strategies in winter. One example of an important finding is that the <em type="italic">siidas </em>use the winter grazing area strategically and systematically in relation to time and space. The ways in which all five <em type="italic">siidas </em>used the same types of topographical areas at the same time of the year were almost identical. </p>
<p>Furthermore the analysis of the monitoring system shows that the snow conditions regulate reindeer ecology, the herders' daily management of the herd and also the herders' economy. The method using the herder diaries is encouraging for a future <em type="italic">siida </em>-based monitoring of snow and grazing resources. </p>
<p>A main finding was that the herders‟ snow knowledge is more holistic and integrated in herding grazing ecology when compared to detailed scientific definitions based on physical characteristics of the snow. The collected data mirrored reindeer herders‟ traditional knowledge of snow and snow change and increased the prevalence of discussion among young herders on these topics.</p>
<p>The third article “ <em type="italic">Traditional Sámi snow terminology and physical snow classification - two ways of knowing </em>” (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2011, submitted) describes how humans understand the natural environment on the basis of their local experience and their interactions with nature in terms of its relevance to their daily lives. These descriptions are incorporated into traditional local languages and form a specialized terminology that is unique and specifically applicable to local needs and practices. Snow defines most of the conditions which must be met to support reindeer pastoralism. Snow is a prerequisite for mobility, tracking, visibility and availability of grazing. The concepts used to describe the snow on the ground include characteristics needed to communicate snow properties relevant to reindeer herding in the region. In this paper, traditional Sámi snow concepts and their definitions are compared with the latest version of the scientific and physical classification of snow on the ground. The study of traditional Sámi snow concepts was carried out by means of interviews with the herders. The results showed that many traditional Sámi concepts describe snow conditions as they are defined by the international standard; whereas other traditional concepts describe the physical processes leading up to certain snow conditions. A third group of snow concepts have as their main purpose the clear communication of the snow conditions for reindeer herding, and these belong to the internal communication within the herding community. </p>
<p>Conceptual analyzes show that the Sámi snow concepts contain a set of characteristics that belong to both reindeer herding and snow physics. Some of the traditional Sámi conceptual descriptions can be compared with the descriptions in the ICSSG (International Classification for Seasonal Snow on the</p>
<p>Ground) classification e.g. <em type="italic">seaŋáš= depth hoar; vahca = Precipitation Particles (class = PP). </em>This study illustrates the importance of using traditional Sámi terminology when developing climate change adaptation governance strategies for Sámi reindeer herding emphasizing the importance of two ways of knowing. </p>
<p>The fourth article is <em type="italic">“Impacts of Arctic Climate and Land Use </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Changes on Reindeer Pastoralism: Indigenous Knowledge and Remote </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Sensing.” </em>(Maynard <em type="italic">et al., </em>2010). This article provides an overview of how indigenous reindeer herders have developed an important initiative to study the impacts of climate change. Furthermore, to develop local adaptation strategies have been developed based upon the reindeer herders‟ traditional knowledge of the land and its uses – in an international, interdisciplinary partnership with the science community, involving extensive collaborations and co-production of knowledge. Some results are presented, as well as a description of the data sharing system including traditional indigenous knowledge and remote sensing, are presented. <em type="bold">4.2 Characteristics of Sámi snow concepts </em></p>
<p>The major linguistic utility in this study is based on the definition of the concepts and the identification of their basic characteristics (Eira <em type="italic">el al </em>., 2010, </p>
<p>Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2011, submitted). Each snow concept has its place and can be clearly defined by their relationships with other snow concepts. The Sámi snow and ice conceptual system is made by a numbers of small conceptual systems covering large and small sub-areas of the field. The Sámi snow concept has a sets of characteristics that includes snow physics and circumstances that are of importance to reindeer herding (Table 2). </p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 2: Identification of characteristics of eight snow concepts. </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Factors </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Distinguishing factors </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Vahca </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Seaŋáš Čearga Cuoŋu Sievlla Soavli Činus Skáva </em></p>
<p>Consistency</p>
<p>Wet </p>
<p>Dry         </p>
<p>Density</p>
<p>Hard </p>
<p>Soft         </p>
<p>Carrying capacity</p>
<p>Carries</p>
<p>Does not carry        </p>
<p>Wind affected</p>
<p>Wind affected Not affected </p>
<p>Layers</p>
<p>Thick  Thin    </p>
<p>Type</p>
<p>Snow Ice      </p>
<p>Metamorphose</p>
<p>Dest.  Sinetr.  Constr.  M/F  /     </p>
<p>Startigraphy</p>
<p>Surface  In themidle Bottom         </p>
<p>Time</p>
<p>Fall-winter  Winter  Spring-winter         </p>
<p>Basic assumptions</p>
<p>I-VI</p>
<p>I, II, III, V</p>
<p>IIIb</p>
<p>IIIa</p>
<p>IIIa</p>
<p>III</p>
<p>Identifications of characteristics of Sámi snow concepts show similarities and differences according to content. Characterization has been done using factors like consistency (whether the snow is wet or dry), density (whether the snow is hard or soft), carrying capacity (whether the snow carries the reindeer/human or not), wind affected, layers (whether the layer is thin or thick), type (whether the snow contains ice particles or not), metamorphosis (to which metamorphic process the snow concept may belong to), stratigraphy (location in the snowpack), (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2011, submitted). In addition there is time (season when the concept is used) (Eira &amp; Mathiesen, 2011, in prep), and the basic prerequisites for herding, I – VI , A. for reindeer: ( I) access to grazing, (II): access to shelter, (IIIa) snow conditions, mobility, B. for humans tasks and assumptions: (IIIb) snow conditions, mobility, (IV) snow conditions, mobility on skis, skis run easily, (V) track snow and (IV) visibility (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2010). </p>
<p>Such analysis (Table 3) can help to ensure relationships between concepts and equally characteristically shows the conceptual similarities and differences. As an example, the concepts <em type="italic">činus </em>and <em type="italic">skáva </em>are perceived as very similar concepts. The similarities between them are that they are both concepts that have characteristics like thin layers and dense snow. The differences between them are that <em type="italic">činus </em>has snow crystals and <em type="italic">skáva </em>has ice crystals; <em type="italic">činus </em>is a result of destructive metamorphosis and <em type="italic">skáva </em>is a result of a melt/freeze metamorphosis. <em type="italic">Činus </em>is used in winter, while the <em type="italic">skáva </em>is used in late winter/spring. Finally <em type="italic">činus </em>belongs to the <em type="italic">guohtun </em>category, while s <em type="italic">káva </em>is used to describe mobility. Taking these factors into account, one can conclude that the concepts are not synonyms names for the same concept, but two separate concepts. </p>
<p>The fact that the various Sámi languages differ significantly from one another is demonstrated by a comparison of snow words in the North Sámi and</p>
<p>South Sámi languages. In the describing the snow crust and ice sheets, Southern</p>
<p>Sámi is more accurate than Northern Sámi. Southern Sámi has 17 terms for different kinds of layers of the snow surface. One reason for this richness of the</p>
<p>South Sámi snow concepts is probably that the shifts in the snow conditions have been and are more frequent in the south than in the inland to the north of</p>
<p>Scandinavia (Magga, 2010). <em type="bold">4.3 Categorization and classification of the Sámi snow concepts </em></p>
<p>One part of the study was focused on categorizing the concepts of snow in terms of relationships. To categorize means to find similar and different characteristics, and thus to establish the differences and similarities. It is important to discuss how the snow conceptual material could be divided, especially in relation to the preparation of the list of snow terms (Appendix I).</p>
<p>Categorization means placing things or phenomena in different groups according to some more or less clear criteria, usually in the form of definitions of the categories (Greve, 2003). A conceptual system is created to cover the different categories of concepts showed by a classification system made of categories.</p>
<p>The classification system consists of a system for example of layers; <em type="italic">'skáva', 'činus', 'geardni' </em>etc., a broader system that covers the section of snow and ice. </p>
<p>Conceptual system is presented in the form of conceptual diagrams that help to illustrate the relationship between concepts and their place in the conceptual system. Categories that are within the same scale, or cycle, such as snow types related to density, belong to the same category for example the category of dense snow layer: <em type="italic">skáva, moarri, cuoŋu, ruovdecuoŋu </em>. </p>
<p>A concept map visualizes where the concepts belong and their relationship between concepts. Such map can be used as a graphical tool for organizing and representing knowledge about snow and ice related to reindeer herding (Figure 8).</p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 8: </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Sámi snow concept system, shown as a graphical concept map, based upon the relationship of similarities/differences of </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Sámi snow and ice concepts in relation to influencing matters. </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Yellow ring indicates snow terms, bright blue ring indicates seasonal/time matters, light green indicates stratigraphical relationships and bright red indicates reindeer herding matters. Text without a ring is about snow physical conditions and snow metamorphism. Arrows indicate processes and changing cycles. </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">The concept system is prepared with Cmap Tools </em><em type="italic">(ht </em><em type="italic">tp: </em><em type="italic">// </em><em type="italic">cmap </em><em type="italic">.i </em><em type="italic">hm </em><em type="italic">c.us </em><em type="italic">(Novak &amp; </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Cañas, 2008). </em></p>
<p>The conceptual map (Figure 8) has contributed to the systematization of the concepts and thus also to their categorization. As a basis for this categorization snow physics is used (snow basic elements of water, ice and air and processes that affect snow) in addition to snow in relation to reindeer herding. The characteristics of snow concept were analyzed by dividing up the components in order to distinguish their properties, located on an ontological level (Nuopponen, 1994), such as shape, hardness, texture, etc. (Table 3). The basis for this work is the snow classification system that is used in snow physics (Fiertz <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2009) and classifications that are found in the Sámi language (Ruong, 1964; Svonni, 1981; Jernsletten, 1994). </p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 3: Classification of Sámi snow concepts based on Fierz et al., 2009, Jernsletten, 1994; Svonni, 1981; Ruong, 1964 </em></p>
<p>PRECIPITATION – AND WEATHER PROCESSES (IN THE AIR) WITH IMPACTS 2.SNOW ON THE GROUND, PROCESSES AND IMPACTS 3.ICE FEATURES IN SNOWPACK, WATER AND OTHER PLACES AND IMPACTS 4.SNOW FACTORS AFFECTED BY REINDEER HERDING 1.a. General (International Classification ) 2.a General (International Classification, dry, wet snow, forms, Metamorphism) 3.a General (Classification system) 4.a. Mechanical impacts 4.a.1 affected by deer and humans 1.a.1 Type, crystal, symbol 2.b Snow types 3.b Types 4b. Track categories 4.b.1 <em type="italic">Fieski </em>4.b.2 <em type="italic">Luottat </em>1.b Parameters 2.b.1 Wet snow 3.b.1 Ice categories 4.c. <em type="italic">Guohtun </em>categories 1.b.1 Temperature 2.b.2 Hard/soft 3.b.1.1 On the ground 3.b.1 .2 On the trees 3.b.1 .3 On things 4.c.1 <em type="italic">Guohtun </em>4.c.2 <em type="italic">Oppas </em>4.c.2 <em type="italic">Čiegar </em>1.b.2 Wind 2.b.3 Thick /thin 3.b.2 Ice features in lakes and water 1.b.3 Rain/snow 2.b.4 Stratigraphy 3. b.3 Melt-freeze layers 1.c Other 2.c Time 3.c.Time 4.d Other </p>
<p>The snow terminology material of is divided into four main categories that all contain subcategories (Table 3). Sub-categories are made up of both snow-physical classifications (forms, metamorphism, stratigraphy etc.) and basic assumptions in reindeer herding (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>2010) marked alphanumerically. The different categories are displayed with the classification numbers in the glossary; the terms are set up alphabetically in a list (Table 4). The list might also be systematized by classification (Appendix 1). </p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 4: Example of how the Sámi snow glossary has been created made. From left; term number, Sámi snow term, definition in Sámi language, and classification number </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">No. Term </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Definition in Sámi language </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Classification </em>302 <em type="bold">šuomir muohta </em></p>
<p>Rušša, roavvasit muohta. 3.b.3312 <em type="bold">veađahat </em>báiki gokko lea unnán ja seakka muohta dahje muohta ii bisán, gokko veađđá, gokko biegga doalvu muohttaga dađistaga. Báikkit gokko sáhttá veađđan leat dábálaččat vađat, jalggat, duoddarat, stuora jeakkit. Veađahat lea dakkár mas lea hirbmat buorre guohtun ja hui buorre ealát. Sullásaš doaba: bieggagaikkohat. 2.a <em type="bold">4.4 Guohtun and basic snow concepts for reindeer herding </em></p>
<p>Some snow concepts like <em type="italic">guohtun </em>, <em type="italic">oppas, čiegar, fieski, goavvi </em>are basic concepts for reindeer herding (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2010). These concepts can be defined as dynamic because the conceptual content is often about processes and conditions that change according to weather, time, location, etc. They can also be expressed as a complex system of traditional knowledge, reflecting the holistic understanding of reindeer herding (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2011, submitted). The complexity of the <em type="italic">guohtun </em>-concept shows that the concept is broader than a purely physical concept of snow; it is broader than just snow type. Snow concepts, in this category, which cannot be defined as pure snow type, are <em type="italic">oppas, čiegar, fieski, goavvi </em>, because they contain characteristics that cover reindeer herding elements, and the physics of snow. </p>
<p>In this section these complex categories, like <em type="italic">guohtun </em>and <em type="italic">čiegar </em>are described and discussed from the starting point for the conceptual analysis of </p>
<p>Sámi snow concept, that a concept is a unit of thought constituted by those characteristics which are attributed to an object or to a class of objects (ISO/DIS 1087). The main linguistic utility in this process relies on the definition of the concepts, obtained from reindeer herders‟ descriptions of them. According to the definitions these concepts have core features and distinctive features (e.g., dense snow, ice layers, bottom ice versus soft snow, depth hoar, dry bottom) as well as more or less fixed prototypical properties (e.g., related to time, space, stratigraphy). <em type="italic"></em><em type="bold">Guohtun </em></p>
<p>The <em type="italic">guohtun </em>-concept describes snow conditions and snow types in relation to herding strategies. <em type="italic">Guohtun </em>is, according to Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>(2010) defined by reindeer herders in the Guovdageaidnu in the following terms: “ <em type="italic">People usually use the concept guohtun to estimate how easily the reindeer is able to dig through the snow to the ground below where the food is to be found. This definition is only used about the snow what it is like and is not used to describe the feed; for this reason it is only used in winter </em>”. </p>
<p>Linguistic <em type="italic">guohtun </em>is not used as a single concept. It is rather, a concept that requires subordinate concepts to describe <em type="italic">guohtun </em>characteristics more clearly. The <em type="italic">guohtun </em>-concept is a super-ordinate concept and its subordinate concepts are phrasal concepts, e.g. „good <em type="italic">guohtun </em>‟ ( <em type="italic">buorre guohtun </em>) or „bad <em type="italic">guohtun </em>‟ ( <em type="italic">heajos guohtun </em>), which means that this is a <em type="italic">guohtun </em>-term connected with an adjectival term. A phrasal term is defined as a term with two or more words separated by a space or multi-word terms as a special case of compounding (Arntz &amp; Picht, 1995). </p>
<p><em type="italic">Guohtun </em>is about the nature of the snowpack, which is comprised of different layers. Each layer has its own unique characteristics in terms of density, formed by diverse snow crystals falling from the sky, developed from drifting and the temperature in the snowpack, and influenced by snow metamorphism. A lot of Sámi concepts of snow types can either cause bad or good grazing conditions (Table 5). Results show that snow types cannot in isolation associate <em type="italic">guohtun </em>characteristics. It is the overall snowpack and the processes that transform the snow which characterize <em type="italic">guohtun </em>. The content of this concept is consequently highly complex and becomes even more complex as it is affected by time, space and weather. The complexity is described as an inter-connected network of components that cannot be described by a few rules (Peloquin &amp; Berkes, 2009). </p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 5: Snow types that can cause either bad or good grazing conditions </em></p>
<p>In order to assess <em type="italic">guohtun </em>conditions, one must deal with many variables simultaneously, like snow-physical variables that determine whether access through the snowpack is easy or difficult. This also includes various different snow types. The overall formation of <em type="italic">guohtun </em>depends on the relationship among snow, precipitation, temperature, wind direction (Halfpenny &amp; Ozanne, 1989), and velocity, as well as other environmental variables such as topography. Thus there are at least four factors that affect <em type="italic">guohtun </em>, that can change from very negative conditions to positive conditions or vice versa: 1) </p>
<p>Weather, temperature and snow metamorphosis, 2) Time of year, 3) Area, ground and/or vegetation and 4) Herding. (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2011, submitted; Eira &amp; </p>
<p>Mathiesen, 2011, in prep).</p>
<p><em type="bold">Snow types </em></p>
<p>Guohtun</p>
<p>Positive</p>
<p>Negative</p>
<p>Precipitation (snow) + -</p>
<p><em type="italic">Vahca </em>+ </p>
<p><em type="italic">Seaŋáš </em>+ </p>
<p><em type="italic">Luotkku muohta </em>+ </p>
<p><em type="italic">Ceavvi </em>- </p>
<p><em type="italic">Cuoŋu </em>- </p>
<p><em type="italic">Skáva </em>+ - </p>
<p><em type="italic">Skárta </em>- </p>
<p><em type="italic">Čearga </em>- </p>
<p><em type="italic">Šalka </em>- </p>
<p><em type="italic">Muovllahat </em>- </p>
<p><em type="italic">Oppas </em>+ </p>
<p><em type="italic">Čiegar </em>- </p>
<p><em type="italic">Fieski </em>- </p>
<p>Weather and temperature can cause the snow or the ground to melt/thaw and then freeze and then become ice: thus the melt-freeze process can cause different melt-freeze layers or crusts in the snowpack (Halfpenny and</p>
<p>Ozanne, 1989). The temperature gradients within the snowpack and snow depth are some important factors which may control the processes resulting in good or bad <em type="italic">guohtun </em>. If <em type="italic">guohtun </em>is bad, it means that the layers on the top or within the snowpack are so hard that the reindeer have difficulties in crushing and digging through the hard layer. The strength in the snow layer increases with the number of melt-freeze cycles, as <em type="italic">geardni, cuoŋu </em>. Thus <em type="italic">guohtun </em>becomes bad (bad <em type="italic">guohtun </em>) because the snow condition is such that reindeer cannot reach the food under the snow. Weather and temperature can also make the <em type="italic">guohtun </em>good, especially if there is little snow and the snow is porous and soft and if the ground is not frozen. Mild weather and mild winds can change <em type="italic">čiegar </em>to <em type="italic">seaŋáš </em>and thus soften the snow so that there will be opportunities in the area for reindeer to dig through the snow. The Sámi reindeer herder, Mr. Nils Henrik Sara, characterizes the result of snow conditions and wind and how they influence the possibility of the reindeer gaining access to the nutrition, thus:”It is a fact that cold weather in winter with strong winds packs the snow, and this snow reduces the pastures because the reindeer cannot access the food. But wind is not always harmful to reindeer herding. Strong wind during mild weather brings the opposite effect; strong wind softens the snow so that the reindeer can access the food.” (Eira <em type="italic">et al., </em>2009). </p>
<p>According to reindeer herders the most essential factor in the characterization of <em type="italic">guohtun </em>, is the ground (Sámi: <em type="italic">bodni </em>). According Routier (2011) the most important aspect of <em type="italic">bodni </em>, is that the snow or the ice should not fasten to the vegetation or <span type="quote">“lock it in”</span>. The types of snow that freeze solid in <em type="italic">bodni </em>, ( <em type="italic">bodneskárta </em>and/or <em type="italic">bodnejiekŋa </em>) (Eng: ground ice), are the worst types because they can lead to major losses and the mass death of reindeer. </p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 6: Sub-variants of </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Guohtun </em>access </p>
<p><em type="italic">Guohtun </em>variants </p>
<p>Density area</p>
<p>Very good <em type="italic">guohtun </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Njunneguohtun </em></p>
<p>Good <em type="italic">guohtun </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Goaivvosguohtun </em></p>
<p>Quite good <em type="italic">guohtun </em></p>
<p>Quite bad <em type="italic">guohtun </em></p>
<p>Bieđggus guohtun</p>
<p>Bad <em type="italic">guohtun </em></p>
<p>Rudneguohtun</p>
<p>Skoavdeguohtun</p>
<p>The <em type="italic">guohtun </em>-concept has sub-varieties that contain characteristics in terms of density and the opportunities for <em type="italic">guohtun </em>in the area. Coupling between the characterization of the access and <em type="italic">guohtun </em>variants shows that sub-variants‟ descriptions of the density belongs to the category of very good/good <em type="italic">guohtun </em>. </p>
<p>In relation to this, the sub-variants related to area belong to the category of quite bad/bad <em type="italic">guohtun </em>(Table 6). In relation to this, the use of the <em type="italic">guohtun </em>-term contains at least two factors: 1) density, ( <em type="italic">njunneguohtun, goaivvos guohtun) </em>, and 2) area-specific, ( <em type="italic">bieđggus guohtun, rudneguohtun, skoavdeguohtun) </em>. The concept is discussed in terms of degrees, for example <em type="italic">njunneguohtun </em>(„nose‟ <em type="italic">guohtun </em>), which is descriptive of fact that the reindeer only uses their nose to get through the snow to graze the vegetation, and <em type="italic">gutnaguohtun </em>(„ash‟ <em type="italic">guohtun </em>"), which compares the snow with ash. These are characterized as the best grazing conditions because the snow is so loose that the reindeer need to use virtually no energy to graze. <em type="italic">Goaivvos guohtun </em>(„easy to dig‟ <em type="italic">guohtun </em>) implies that reindeer easily dig through the snow: These are also considered as quite good grazing conditions. Bad grazing conditions are characterized by <em type="italic">bieđggus guohtun </em>and <em type="italic">rudneguohtun </em>, which explain that the reindeer are just about able to reach to the bottom at a few places in the area. This means that there are holes in the snow cover caused by the melt and freeze process <em type="italic">(njáhcu </em>) in fall/late fall. </p>
<p>The weather in fall has therefore, and especially in snow-ice types that occur in the fall, like <em type="italic">bodneskárta, </em>major consequences for <em type="italic">guohtun </em>. If <em type="italic">bodneskárta </em>occurs, then the reindeer cannot get through the ice to the vegetation, thus making <em type="italic">rudneguohtun </em>in the following winter (Aslak Anders I. Eira). </p>
<p>The characteristic of <em type="italic">guohtun </em>can be compared with „fuzzy logic‟, which is a tool for categorizing information into broad categorizations or clusters, while at the same time showing how the human mind function. It is a mathematical approach for dealing with complex systems where only approximate information of components and connections is available. The distinguishing feature of fuzzy logic is the use of linguistic variables in addition to numerical variables (Berkes &amp; Berkes, 2009). To understand such complex systems, in this case the interconnection between reindeer, human beings and snow, the „key elements of human thinking are not numbers, but labels of fuzzy sets‟ (Zadeh, 1973; Berkes &amp; Berkes, 2009). Phrases such as „very good <em type="italic">guohtun </em>‟, „good <em type="italic">guohtun </em>‟ etc. are language-based variables. They give reindeer herders the possibility of characterizing <em type="italic">guohtun, </em>as well as an understanding of the complexity of the snow-reindeer relationship so that they can adapt their herding strategy accordingly. 4.4.2 <em type="bold">Oppas and čiegar </em></p>
<p>In the conceptual system of the <em type="italic">guohtun- </em>concepts there are also the concepts of <em type="italic">oppas </em>and <em type="italic">čiegar </em>. These are the most important reindeer herding related concepts in the winter with regard to meaning and characteristics, because they explain the evaluation of the survival and sustainability of reindeer (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2010). <em type="italic">Oppas </em>is the reindeer herders‟ winter capital which can contribute to the survival of reindeer during the winter (Nils Isak Eira, 2006, personal communication). The more <em type="italic">čiegar </em>there is in a particular area, the less <em type="italic">oppas </em>there can be, and vice versa, and furthermore the more <em type="italic">čiegar </em>there is in one place, the worse the grazing ( <em type="italic">guohtun </em>) there is an opposite (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2010.) Both concepts have a lot of subordinate concepts which provide a further description of snow conditions that the concept is describing. </p>
<p>The definition of the concept <em type="italic">oppas </em>is a snow area where the snow is untouched, i.e. not trampled by reindeer. <em type="italic">Oppas </em>has not so much to do with the size of area, but how the herder has allowed the herd to graze. For example if the herd has grazed in very dense pattern, then the area is more trampled (Isak </p>
<p>Mathis Eira, 2009). <em type="italic">Oppas </em>is a type of snowpack that is generally composed of very loose snow layers. The entire snowpack, from the surface to the bottom, includes snow types like <em type="italic">vahca, luotkkomuohta, seaŋáš </em>, (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2011, submitted). <em type="italic">Oppas </em>implies that the grazing snow conditions are good. </p>
<p>The herds grazing and the herders‟ management of the herd lead to different variants of <em type="italic">oppas </em>, from the best variant of the positives to the worst variety. The <em type="italic">oppas </em>-concept has at least five sub-concepts that are relative to the variation of <em type="italic">oppas </em>(Figure 9). <em type="italic">Silkeoppas </em>is the best variant of oppas, where the area with this kind of snow is soft, comparable to silk. This is an area where there are no traces of any animal. The snow is so porous that the animal needs only to shake ( <em type="italic">savdnjilit </em>) the snow. <em type="italic">Čavde-oppas </em>or <em type="italic">áinnehisoppas </em>, denotes the area that is not touched by the reindeer. The <em type="italic">suolo-oppas </em>-concept means that oppas is compared with an island. This concept is almost the same as the <em type="italic">dielko-oppas </em>-concept. When there is <em type="italic">dielko-oppas </em>, then the reindeer themselves have selected <em type="italic">oppas </em>when grazing, dug a little, eaten and left the area. <em type="italic">Rámso-oppas </em>denotes that reindeer must graze in spots, for example in situations when there are bottom ice patches in open, treeless level ground ( <em type="italic">vađđa </em>). In such a site there can be <em type="italic">oppas </em>, and yet there is not <em type="italic">guohtun </em>, caused by the malfunction of the bottom, for example because ice patches have occurred in the fall. According to reindeer herders there is something wrong with <em type="italic">guohtun </em>when it is <em type="italic">rámso-oppas </em>(Isak Mathis O. Eira). </p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 9: Variants of oppas, from best level to the worst. </em></p>
<p>The opposite concept of <em type="italic">oppas </em>is <em type="italic">čiegar </em>, which means that the snow in an area has been touched, because the reindeer have grazed and dug in the area. The use of the <em type="italic">čiegar </em>-concept presupposes that there is snow on the ground before it can be said that there is <em type="italic">čiegar </em>. When there is very little snow, then it is almost not possible to be <em type="italic">čiegar </em>. The reindeer has nothing to do in an area where there is <em type="italic">čiegar </em>, because there is no <em type="italic">guohtun </em>. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Čiegar </em>means that the snow is very dense. The process that makes <em type="italic">čiegar </em>is that the reindeer by grazing is destroying the snow crystal structure, so that the sintering process goes much faster. After deposition the process of sintering (molecular growth of bonds between single snow crystals) leads to a hard and dense snow. This snow is even denser than <em type="italic">čearga </em>, with its density of 250-450 kg/m3. The density of <em type="italic">čiegar </em>is more than 500 kg/m3.Thus, the snow in such an area is too dense for grazing. (Eira, <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2011, submitted). In general, <em type="italic">čiegar </em>will make it difficult to use the same area again during the same snow season. </p>
<p>The <em type="italic">čiegar </em>-concept contains three elements, namely 1) it is an area where reindeer have been grazing, 2) in the area there are cold grazing holes ( <em type="italic">suovdnji) </em>and 3) the snow in the area is very hard. This means that in such an area reindeer may not be able to graze because the snow is dense, although this depends on when the mechanical impact has occurred (Sám: <em type="italic">čiegarduvvon </em>). If the impact has taken place before Christmas, the area can usually be used once more later in the winter. But if the impact has occurred in the winter, then the area cannot be used before the snow‟s structure has changed, and become looser. </p>
<p>When <em type="italic">čiegar </em>is frozen (dense), it is so dense that it is possible to can cut a piece of it. According to reindeer herders‟ new <em type="italic">čiegar </em>is not defined as cold (dense). </p>
<p><em type="italic">Čiegar </em>can be divided into at least seven different levels in relation to when and where the <em type="italic">čiegar </em>occurs (Sám: <em type="italic">čiegarduvvon </em>): Seasonal <em type="italic">čiegar </em>may be: 1. <em type="italic">Čakčačiegar </em>(fall <em type="italic">čiegar </em>) which occurs if it has been snowing in fall and the snow has occurred to form <em type="italic">čiegar </em>, 2. <em type="italic">Skábmačiegar </em>, (the dark time <em type="italic">čiegar </em>) which occurs when the reindeer graze on the snow-covered ground before </p>
<p>Christmas (Sám: <em type="italic">skábma </em>), although this type of <em type="italic">čiegar </em>is not yet that bad, 3. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Dálvečiegar </em>(winter <em type="italic">čiegar </em>), which is very hard and this is the worst level of čiegar. Snow consistence; 4. <em type="italic">Njáhcočiegar </em>(thaw čiegar), which occurs when the reindeer graze when there is thaw snow (Sám: <em type="italic">njáhcu </em>). New and old <em type="italic">čiegar </em>; 5. <em type="italic">Varasčiegar </em>(new <em type="italic">čiegar </em>), which is an area where the snow have just transformed to <em type="italic">čiegar </em>. The herder cannot immediately after this transformation leave the herd to graze in such an area, 6. <em type="italic">Boares čiegar </em>(old <em type="italic">čiegar </em>) is <em type="italic">čiegar </em>that has been like that a good while. The weather and snow conditions can softens the snow, which implies that it is possible for the herd to be allowed to graze in the area again. <em type="italic">Čiegar </em>related to area: 7. <em type="italic">Čoahkkečiegar </em>, (compiled <em type="italic">čiegar </em>) is when the grazing has been concentrated in an area without spot of <em type="italic">oppas </em>between the <em type="italic">čiegar </em>spots (Figure 10). </p>
<p>The <em type="italic">čiegar </em>-concept is an old concept, and it has been used by reindeer herding peoples that are geographically far apart, The Sámi, on the one hand, and Nenets on the other (Roung,1964). <em type="italic">Čiegar </em>, such as the <em type="italic">guohtut </em>-concept (Eira <em type="italic">et al. </em>, 2010), is a concept that has been preserved from ancient </p>
<p>Arctic people and their ways of life. According to Ruong (1964), Torneaus (1600-1681), mentioned the <em type="italic">čiegar </em>-concept in relation to <em type="italic">čiegar </em>-hunting. </p>
<p>Linguistically the concept of <em type="italic">čiegar </em>, in the Sámi language indicating the relationship to reindeer herding, is related to equivalents in the Nenets, Mansi and Khanty languages (ibid.). </p>
<p>Figure 10: The concept čiegar, divided in seven sub-concepts. 4.4.3 Fieski</p>
<p>The <em type="italic">fieski </em>-concept denotes an area where reindeer have been and it is possible to track them. The <em type="italic">fieski </em>-concept belongs to the category of tracking. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Fieski </em>is not a typical snow type, but it is snow trampled by reindeer grazing in the area for a short period. <em type="italic">Fieski </em>is characterized in relation to boundaries where the reindeer have been. When the reindeer have barely has been on a place, or the herders have just let the reindeer graze for a short, then it is called <em type="italic">fieskastallan </em>. A lot of reindeer can make <em type="italic">fieski </em>, but so can also a single reindeer. </p>
<p>While herding the reindeer, the reindeer herders drive around old <em type="italic">fieski </em>and look for tracks ( <em type="italic">fieski </em>) to verify that no reindeer are left there. In searching for reindeer that have not been in the herd <em type="italic">( </em>Sám: <em type="italic">meahccečorraga </em>), they do not look firstly for the reindeer but for <em type="italic">fieski </em>. If they see <em type="italic">fieski </em>, then the herders will follow it hoping to find lost reindeer. </p>
<p>Also <em type="italic">fieski </em>have subordinate concepts that are in relation to time, snow consistency and where the <em type="italic">fieski </em>area is: 1. <em type="italic">Ravdafieski </em>( <em type="italic">fieski </em>on the edge) may mean that it is edge <em type="italic">fieski </em>, or <em type="italic">fieski </em>between two reindeer herds ( <em type="italic">fieskkegaska </em>); 2. <em type="italic">Boaresfieski </em>(old <em type="italic">fieski </em>); means that the reindeer have earlier been grazing in the area; 3. <em type="italic">Varasfieski </em>(fresh <em type="italic">fieski </em>) means that it has just occurred, and 4. Njáhcofieski, (thaw <em type="italic">fieski </em>) is encountered during <em type="italic">njáhcu </em>(Figure 11). In fall 2009 there were <em type="italic">njáhcofieski </em>(thaw <em type="italic">fieski </em>) in Guovdageaidnu. 4.4.4 <em type="bold">Ritni </em></p>
<p>The <em type="italic">ritni </em>-concept denotes snow and ice on the trees and belongs to the ice categories: (i) ice on the ground, (ii) ice on the trees, and (iii) ice on </p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 11: The fieski-concept with its sub-ordinate concepts. </em>things. Other concepts that have relation with <em type="italic">ritni </em>are <em type="italic">bihci, šuhči, čođđi </em>. In </p>
<p>English, all these concepts can be compared with <em type="italic">rime </em>. The rime is defined when water vapor freezes into ice-crystals on solid surfaces such as road surface, car window or lawn (www.met.no). In the Sámi language there is a distinguishing difference between the concepts related to the rime-concept. These concepts are more accurate than the rime-concept because they show where the rime occurs: <em type="italic">bihci </em>is rime on the ground, <em type="italic">ritni </em>is rime on the trees, <em type="italic">šuhči </em>is frozen frost on trees and <em type="italic">čođđi </em>is an ice crust on things or rocks. <em type="italic">Ritni </em>occurs in weather that makes rime on trees with snow. Then the <em type="italic">rinádat </em>occurs, which reduces visibility. <em type="italic">Ritni </em>can occur as early as in the late fall, when snow has settled on the ground. In the early winter of 2008 there was a long period of 45 days with <em type="italic">rinádat </em>(rime period). In late October, there was <em type="italic">bihci </em>on the ground and the on the surface of the lakes there was a thin ice layer (Sám. <em type="italic">gavdon </em>). A few days later, there was winter fog ( <em type="italic">murku </em>) and the day after there was <em type="italic">ritni </em>. According to meteorological data, during the period there was less than 50 cm of snow (red graph), with almost no wind and with low temperatures (blue graph). (Figure 12) <em type="italic"></em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 12: The rinádat period lasted for 45 days. In the graph the SD is snow depth and TAN is maximum temperature. </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Ritni </em>is very important for reindeer herding. When there is <em type="italic">ritni </em>, called <em type="italic">rinádat </em>, there are good conditions for reindeer. Reindeer can hide in a <em type="italic">ritni </em>-forest. This gives the reindeer opportunity to graze in peace and quiet without being disturbed because they are <span type="quote">"invisible"</span>. For the reindeer herders <em type="italic">ritni </em>is not very good. <em type="italic">Ritni </em>impedes the work with the reindeer, because it is difficult to see and know where the herd and individual reindeer are, for example when collecting the herd or finding small herds (Herder Station 2). 4.4.5 Goavvi </p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>is a basic snow concept, which is not in everyday use, but which appears in connection with the effects of extreme weather event in winter. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>is defined as extremely bad grazing condition with starvation, loss of reindeer and adverse impacts on herders‟ economy and organization. <em type="italic">Goavvi </em>is not used in describing <span type="quote">"normal"</span> bad winters, when snow concepts like <em type="italic">cuoŋu, čearga, ce </em>avvi etc. are used. The substance of the <em type="italic">goavvi </em>-concept is an image of extreme weather events reflecting changes in a system, in relation to structures, functions, and organization, which are caused by events that create the disaster, and subsequently adverse consequences. One of the first written reports about extreme winter grazing conditions resulting in the death of reindeer was published by Tromholt (1885). Surprisingly, over a period of 100 years, reindeer herders in Guovdageaidnu have experienced <em type="italic">goavvi </em>about 12 times, and the concept is also used presently among reindeer herders in Guovdageaidnu (Table 7). </p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>is caused by thick layers of ice and ice frozen in the soil: <em type="italic">jiekŋa </em>(Eng: ice), <em type="italic">bodneskárta </em>(Eng: the ice is frozen into the vegetation) and <em type="italic">gassa muohta </em>(Eng: deep snow). Factors such as precipitation, wind, snow metamorphism and different ice layers build up inside the snowpack and may affect the degree of <em type="italic">goavvi </em>. These factors are important and influence the grazing conditions in late fall, in the transition from bare ground to snow-covered land. </p>
<p>Reindeer herders characterize adverse conditions in the winter in different ways depending on how great the consequences are for their reindeer and reindeer herding. These snow conditions are typically characterized as worse than very bad <em type="italic">guohtun. </em>Variants of <em type="italic">goavvi </em>are shown in Figure 13, related to the degree of goavvi. The length of the goavvi periode is reflected in the degree of the impact on the reindeer herd. The sub-concepts of <em type="italic">goavvi </em>show their relation to time and season, <em type="italic">goavvegiđđa </em>(Eng: <em type="italic">goavvi </em>spring) lasts one season, <em type="italic">goavvedálvi </em>( <em type="italic">goavvi </em>winter), lasts over two seasons, <em type="italic">goavve </em>jahki ( <em type="italic">goavvi </em>year), lasts a whole year and <em type="italic">nealgedálvi </em>(Eng: starvation year), the worst-level condition (Figure 13). </p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>-spring means a long spring, with a lot of snow and cold weather, and hardly a bare spot at all on the ground. A <em type="italic">goavvi </em>year means a long hard period, which last from fall to spring. Analysis of collected data shows that most informants relate <em type="italic">goavvi </em>condition to grazing in spring or late winter. None of the informants‟ related <em type="italic">goavvi </em>to the fall or late fall, which could be explained by the fact that bad grazing conditions in fall usually is manifested themselves later in the winter. A <em type="italic">goavvi </em>period can actually last until the snow has melted and there is bare ground. The <em type="italic">goavvi </em>conditions can occur over a large area, but may also be very local. When the snow conditions are bad, the reindeer will walk a around lot in search of food (Informant C19), and herders have to herd continuously day and night to keep the herd together. <em type="italic">Goavvi </em>denotes a loss of reindeer that impacts on the reindeer herding economy, organization, and herd welfare. All herders participating in this project reported that their herds were affected and reduced after <em type="italic">goavvi </em>and viewing <em type="italic">goavvi </em>periods in the light of </p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 13: Goavvi concept with sub-concepts. </em>numbers of reindeer (official numbers) in western Finnmark, the number of reindeer was usually reduced after <em type="italic">goavvi. </em>One reindeer herder (Informant C28) explained that <em type="italic">goavvi </em>could be the reason for a large loss of reindeer (reindeer deaths), low calf growth for years after extreme weather events (Sám: <em type="italic">miesehis jagit </em>) owing to low milk production, and reindeer diseases. <em type="italic">Goavvi </em>usually have adverse effect on the energy expenditure of female reindeer, e.g. they may lose milk for production to new born calves and newborn calves might subsequently die according to informant C 28. According to one reindeer herder a <em type="italic">goavvi </em>year can have adverse consequences for the herd for at least five years after the event, (“ <em type="italic">goavvi váikkuha 5 jagi ovddasguvlui </em>”), and the economic consequences of <em type="italic">goavvi </em>could be 30% less calves than in normal years, in other <em type="italic">siidas </em>even more (informant C28). Traditional knowledge indicates that female calves born in such years are negatively affected the next five years. According to Päiviö (2006), <em type="italic">goavvi </em>could also have implications for new patterns of migration in </p>
<p>Sirkas siida.</p>
<p>An analysis of historical descriptions of extreme events in the reindeer herding community in Guovdageaidnu from the early 20th century to present shows different levels of <em type="italic">goavvi </em>. Examples of <em type="italic">goavvi </em>periods are shown in Table 7. Worst level of <em type="italic">goavvi </em>in Guovdageaidnu was reported in 1917/1918. </p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 7: Various goavvi –periods, including 1917/18 marked in yellow were characterized as starvation years (), 1967/68 and 68/69 marked in red were goavvi years, and 1958-1961 and 1997 marked in green were goavvi spring </em></p>
<p>Year</p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>-spring <em type="italic">Goavvi </em>–year Starving year 1907/08 </p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>spring 1917/18 </p>
<p>Starving year 1957/58</p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>spring 1960/61 </p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>spring 1967/68 </p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>year 1968/69 </p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>year 1971 </p>
<p>Long spring 1973</p>
<p>Long spring 1996/97</p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>spring <em type="italic">Goavvi </em>year 1997/98 </p>
<p>Bad spring</p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>year 1998/99 </p>
<p>Bad spring</p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>year 1999/2000 </p>
<p>Bad spring</p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>year </p>
<p>From the oral histories, which are generated by people‟s memories of extreme grazing events, we can provide new knowledge and insights. An example of the resulting impact of extreme weather events is that of 1917/1918, which was characterized as “ <em type="italic">nealgedálvi” </em>by a reindeer herder from </p>
<p>Guovdageaidnu, born in 1909. That year the reindeer starved to death.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Dat ii lean suohtas jahki. Dalle lei nu heitot ahte dat ii oba birgen ge, dalle šadde johttát gosa nu. Sii geat eai bieđganan oalát siiddaiguin, dat johttájedje dainna mii lei báhcán. Muhtimat bieđganedje ja nu dat dušše manne dat bohccot, muoraid mielde ja juohke guvlui. Doppe ii lean ealát.5 </em></p>
<p>He remembered that weather conditions and several periods of mild weather with rain followed until Christmas, which created many thick layers of ice in and under the snowpack. The snowpack became some dense that the reindeer were unable to break the ice and could therefore not reach the lichen through the ice layer, which was as thick as 10 – 15 cm.</p>
<p>The historical meteorological data show the weather conditions in fall 1917 (Figure 14, red circle), which might explain the cause of starvation that year. In early October freezing temperatures and precipitation as snow, resulted in a snow depth of 20 cm. Subsequently there were some days with temperatures 5 Translated from Sámi: This was a terrible year. The pasture conditions were so bad that people were not able to rescue herd, and had to move from area to any place. Those who had not lost all the reindeer, moved with the herd that remained. Some could not keep the deer together, they spread completely. There was not <em type="italic">ealát </em>in the area. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 14: Using temperature, precipitation and snow depth data from Karasjok 1917-1918 can give indication and description of the conditions in Guovdageaidnu. (Vikhamar-Schuler et al., 2010a) </em>above zero, when the snow melted, and finally froze again. Temperatures ranged between plus and minus degrees. The graph shows that the snow melted and there was bare ground from late October to early November, followed with heavy snow fall. </p>
<p>Johan Turi (1933) describes in 1910 the transition from bare ground to snow covered ground using some snow concepts and how these occur.</p>
<p>According to Turi the weather conditions generally in the fall are very important for the grazing conditions in the winter. <em type="italic"><span type="quote">“At that time, when the bulls are worn out, then it generally thaws, and that thaw is called golggonjacco (the debility thaw). And then you generally lose the herds because it is very bad weather, fog and rain, and when it thaws much there is bare ground in some places, and in other places the snow is left lying, and when it freezes, then that snow is turned to ice or, as it is called, bodneskardan (bottom crust), and it remains all through the winter just as it is at the time when the last thawing stop and the cold comes. But if the thaws do not spoil the snow, then it will be a good winter, unless there comes very deep snow, for the reindeer can get to the mosses even if the snow is fairly deep, if only there is a clean bottom, that is, no ice on the bottom. And it is at this time that the Lapps are afraid (wondering) what the winter will be.”</span> (Turi, 1933). </em></p>
<p>This description, which is over 100-year-old, shows that the elements</p>
<p>Turi pointed out as being crucial for <em type="italic">guohtun </em>, such as that <em type="italic">njáhcu </em>(thaw) and freezing temperatures can result in <em type="italic">bodneskárta </em>, is relevant today. This shows continuity in the perception of the content of the concepts, and the descriptions of factors that make such concepts. <em type="bold">4.5 Traditional knowledge about snow, adaptation and resilience thinking </em></p>
<p>The IPY EALÁT project recognizes that the ability of reindeer herders to cope and adapt to changes is based on traditional knowledge, which is embodied in the herders‟ specialized concepts in their language (Tyler <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2007; Eira <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2010; Maynard <em type="italic">et al </em>.; 2010; Magga <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2011,a; Eira &amp; </p>
<p>Mathiesen, 2011, in prep). This section further discusses the response of reindeer herding communities in the face of extreme weather events (or natural hazards), such as <em type="italic">goavvi </em>and other bad grazing conditions in winter through the lens of resilience thinking. Resilience can be shortly described as the <em type="italic">siidas </em>ability to recover after for example <em type="italic">goavvi </em>. Resilience can be defined in different ways, but one definition is the capacity of a system to absorb disturbance and reorganize while undergoing change, retaining essentially the same function, structure, identity, and feedbacks and it is about a system‟s flexibility in the face of change (Berkes &amp; Turner, 2006). Resilient societies are those able to overcome the damage from extreme weather events. According to Gaillard (2006), extreme weather events are natural phenomena that pose a threat to people, structure and economic assets. Extreme weather events include among others, earthquakes, storms, floods and droughts, but have to be considered in local perspectives. The future negative effects of projected global warming on the snowpack and winter grazing conditions in Guovdageaidnu might possible increased effects of extreme weather event for reindeer herding. Extreme weather events and winter grazing conditions is discussed by Turi (1910, 1933). </p>
<p>Snow concepts like <em type="italic">bodneskárta, bearta cuoŋu </em>, and <em type="italic">ceavvi, </em>all contain important traditional knowledge, is used to observe and monitor the snowpack also in times of extreme weather events in winter. <em type="italic">Ceavvi </em>is a snow concept used in </p>
<p>Kautokeino on hard snow in spring (Eira <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2010). Other regions, like some southern Sámi reindeer herding areas, have concepts that can have similarities with North Sámi. In south Sámi they use i.e. a term <span type="quote">"tsievie"</span> (denoting ice layer on the reindeer lichen; hard snow that bears small reindeer) (Laila Matsson </p>
<p>Magga, 2012, pers. communication), that can correlates the north Sámi term <span type="quote">"ceavvi"</span>. According to Turi (1933), who originally was from Guovdageaidnu,</p>
<p>Ceavvi is a description of bad grazing conditions in winter. <em type="italic"><span type="quote">“Tsævve is hard snow with a snow-crust underneath it, and, when the snow is of the consistency, then the reindeer herds spread widely in search for food, and then the Lapps can’t hold the herds together.”</span> </em></p>
<p>The people struggling with such bad grazing condition are called <em type="italic">ceavvit </em>by Turi. <em type="italic"><span type="quote">“They have begun to gather together the reindeer who have run all over the forests...reindeer are obliged by hunger to spread all over the forest in a tsævve-aar (hard-snow year), and when the tsævve Lapps took to tethering a bell-reindeer, the weakened reindeer came to out, and the folk began to feed them with tree-lichens and to watch them.”</span> (Turi, 1933). </em></p>
<p>This could be an example of adaptation to bad grazing condition in winter.</p>
<p>Sámi traditional knowledge about snow is a vital part of the</p>
<p>Kautokeino reindeer herders‟ resilience thinking. Likewise, resilience thinking helps to evaluate hazards holistically (Hewitt, 2004; Berkes, 2007). Resilience deals first with coupled human–environment systems and contributes to a comprehensive vulnerability analysis by avoiding the artificial dividing between a physical and a social part of the system. It deals with the dynamics of response to hazards, and is forward-looking, helps to explore policy options to deal with uncertainty and change (Berkes, 2007). Adaptive responses to dramatic environmental change are often encoded in traditional knowledge Reinert <em type="italic">et al </em>., (2009). There is increasing evidence that many traditional communities pass on from one generation to another experience and knowledge that can be critical in helping them to respond to extreme weather events (Hewitt; 2004 Berkes, 2007). </p>
<p>Based on historical data from reindeer herding, meteorological data and oral stories from old herders, it is possible to gain insight in to how the reindeer herding community coped and adapted during and after extreme weather event like <em type="italic">goavvi </em>. Such knowledge can be of importance to maintain high resilience in the reindeer herders‟ pastoral system in times of projected climate change. All herders participating in this project reported that their herds were affected and reduced after <em type="italic">goavvi </em>and by comparing <em type="italic">goavvi </em>periods with the total numbers of reindeer (official numbers) in western Finnmark, see that the number of reindeer was usually reduced after <em type="italic">goavvi </em>(Figure 15). </p>
<p>Extreme weather events, like <em type="italic">goavvi, </em>have probably occurred in western Finnmark, in time immemorial, regardless of the size of reindeer population, have effected on the grazing conditions in winter. One explanation of <em type="italic">goavvi </em>can be the North Atlantic Oscillation (NAO). NAO is a climatic phenomenon characterized by an oscillation of the difference between the air pressure at sea level over Iceland and the corresponding pressure over the </p>
<p>Azores (Hurrel, 1995). Time series show how the NAO index might vary in a 10-year scale and affect the winter temperature in Scandinavia. It is mostly in late fall, winter and early spring that strong positive or negative NAO phase is prominent in Scandinavia (www.met.no), which is related to when reindeer herders observe bad grazing conditions. In the winter pastures in inland</p>
<p>Finnmark air temperatures show large inter-annual variability, and this variation is partly correlated with the (NAO) (R ≈0,5) (Magga <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2011). Variation in the NAO index is shown in Figure 16. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 15: Numbers of reindeer in western Finnmark from 1945 to the present. The blue line indicates the number of reindeer, the red bar in the graph marks goavvi years and the green bar marks goavvi-springs. (Official data from the Directorate of Reindeer Husbandry). </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Figure 16: The NAO index variation in fall (1873–2000) and orange circles shows historical goavvi years 1917, 1967 and 1996 in Guovdageaidnu reindeer herding region, which is correspond to negative NAO phases (Prepared from JIANPING, 2003). </em></p>
<p>Many animal species throughout the Northern Hemisphere are influenced by NAO (Ottersen, G. <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2001). A positive NAO index is associated with an increased westerly wind field, while negative NAO index is associated with weak westerly or even easterly winds in Scandinavia (www.met.no), but with hitherto unknown effects in western Finnmark. </p>
<p>However, it appears that bad year with extreme grazing conditions in winter extreme weather event ( <em type="italic">goavvi </em>) occurs after very negative NAO phase in the late fall. The common history of Sámi Reindeer Husbandry in western Finnmark indicate that the years 1917/18, 1967/68 and 1996/97 are typical <em type="italic">goavvi </em>years with starvation, loss of reindeer and negative impacts on herders economy. I suggested that these historical <em type="italic">goavvi </em>years in western Finnmark may be explained by a strong negative NAO index in late fall (Figure 16). </p>
<p>Based on reindeer herders‟ observation using snow concepts as indicator, the <em type="italic">Siida </em>communities use various methods to prevent the loss of reindeer. These methods also help them to maintain the herd and subsequently being able to recover from <em type="italic">goavvi </em>. I suggest that the ability of individual reindeer herders and <em type="italic">siidas </em>to recover from extreme weather event show high resilience to change using the traditional knowledge about snow in their daily language and communication. There are stories that reindeer herders could lose almost the whole herd in <em type="italic">goavvi </em>, but being able to recover and subsequently continue as before. According to Päivio, (2008), such bad years occurred in </p>
<p>Sirkas in Sweden in the 1930ths. He shows in an example from Sweden that the <em type="italic">goavvi </em>years changed the <em type="italic">siida </em>organization of reindeer herding in an area and even that some reindeer herders started up with other activities like fishing. </p>
<p>Resilience in the context of such extreme weather event is the measure of a community‟s or individual‟s ability to respond effectively to change. According to O‟Brien <em type="italic">et al </em>. (2009) resilience thinking offers a new way of understanding complex adaptive systems and it can provide key insights into the evolution of the social contracts that underpin many systems of governance. </p>
<p>Reindeer herders indicate their ability to build their adaptive capacity by learning from previous extreme grazing events, and the use of several adaptive strategies is high. Adaptive strategies are the ways in which individuals, households, and communities change their productive activities and modify local rules and institutions to secure livelihoods (Berkes &amp; Jolly, 2001). The herders use at least five different adaptive strategies 1) spread the herd in the grazing land and let individual reindeer themselves find to find adequate guohtun conditions. 2) Increase the mobility (Sám: <em type="italic">sirdit </em>) of the herd from one area to another, 3) migrate to the coast out of season and/or 4) provide additional feeding for reindeer with hay or pellets (Table 8). Furthermore, 5) Long term adaptation to <em type="italic">goavvi </em>includes the herd structure diversity and animal welfare (Oskal, 2000). These methods have contributed to the adaptive capacities of <em type="italic">siidas </em>in Guovdageaidnu following <em type="italic">goavvi </em>. </p>
<p><em type="bold">Table 8: Adaptative strategies during periods </em></p>
<p>Year</p>
<p><em type="bold">Adaptative strategies during periods </em></p>
<p>To let the herd spread</p>
<p>Move from area to another</p>
<p>Migrate to the coast</p>
<p>Additional feeding 1917/1918</p>
<p>X 1958</p>
<p>X 1967/68</p>
<p>X 1996/97</p>
<p>The management strategy for <em type="italic">goavvi </em>in 1917/1918 in western </p>
<p>Finnmark was to let individual reindeer range freely, so that they could find food for themselves. The strategy was then to move to another area to find good <em type="italic">guohtun </em>where it was possible to break through the snowpack. In the late winter of 1958, the coping strategy was to move with the herd south-east in the region, to the area Jávrrášduottar, which was an area that was always kept as a supplementary grazing area in case of <em type="italic">goavvi </em>(Hågvar, 2006). In 1967/68, some <em type="italic">siidas </em>in Guovdageaidnu migrated in early winter to the coast, and the summer grazing area, while others kept the herd in the winter grazing area until summer. </p>
<p>In 1997 the herders started using a new strategy for adapting to <em type="italic">goavvi </em>, which included additional feeding as well as early migration to the summer grazing area. At this time it was not common to provide supplementary feeding according to one of the informants involved. In order to use these strategies in long term adaptation to extreme snow weather events and likewise to the future effects of climate change, the reindeer herding is dependent on flexibility of pasture use and control of mobility. This flexibility allows herders to adapt to climatic variation and to maintain resilience. Studies of the social organization of reindeer pastoralism (Turi, 2008), confirm that reindeer herding has developed an integral resilience for dealing with climatic uncertainty based on traditional ecological knowledge (Magga <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2011a). Reindeer herders adapt constantly to change (Reinert <em type="italic">et al </em>., 2009). Thus, traditional knowledge about variability and changes in the snowpack and the use of about 318 Sámi snow concepts, could build resilience locally to times of projected climate change. </p>
<p>Reindeer herding might maintain high resilience to extreme weather events from the knowledge embodied in reindeer herders‟ language and through daily use of specialized language. During the past 50 years, reindeer herding has undergone changes (Eira, 1984; Saijets &amp; Helander-Renvall, 2009), which may also have affected the language of reindeer herding. Older herders in this study recognize that herding practices changes quickly (J. Magga pers. Com 2003). Climate change will undoubtedly have significant environmental, economic, cultural and linguistic impacts on Sámi reindeer herding. Any breakdown in the language structure signals a breakdown of their conception of the environment, affecting the nature of knowledge and the world view passed on from the previous generation (Näkkälajärvi, 2009). There is a fear that the working methods, language and culture of reindeer-herding could be eroded, and thus the practical herding will also change. Kalstad (1999) states that if the specialist language of reindeer herding disappears from everyday use, it will adversely affect reindeer herders‟ specialist work. Language is an essential tool for culturally-appropriate encoding of knowledge. Traditional knowledge conservation therefore must pass through the pathways of conserving language (Nakashima, 2000; Nakashima &amp;</p>
<p>Roue, 2002).</p>
<p>The decline in use of the language as the basis of herding knowledge could mean a change in the traditional management model, and possibly increased vulnerability. Adaptation to climate change is argued as being something that happens at the local level of reindeer herding: It will in future demand the training of local arctic leaders in long term sustainable thinking, based on the best available adaptation knowledge, both scientific and experienced-based traditional and local knowledge (Turi, 2009). Tailor-made education developed to strengthen herders‟ traditional knowledge, resilience, cultural and linguistic rights could be one way to maintain high resilience and to implement adaptive strategies in response to projected climate change (Bongo, 2010). It is believed that such adaptive strategies could reduce the vulnerability to climate change in reindeer herding in Finnmark. <em type="bold">5. CONCLUSIONS </em></p>
<p>In this interdisciplinary study, snow concepts have been linguistically investigated in relation to practical Sámi reindeer herding and climate variability and future projected climate change. Among the 318 (Appendix 1) snow concepts related to reindeer herding used by Guovdageaidnu herders, selected core concepts were further analyzed in the view of traditional use about different grazing conditions in winter and the physical characteristics of snow. The thesis also documents and discusses two ways of knowing about snow change and pasture availability in reindeer herding.</p>
<p>This study has shown that the reindeer herders‟ use of snow concepts is related to time, context, snow physics and the basic needs for reindeer herding when snow covers the ground in winter. Furthermore, these concepts are often dynamic because they are related to processes and conditions that changes according to weather, time, and location (Article I). Findings indicate that these concepts should be understood in context of practical reindeer herding.</p>
<p>A multidimensional understanding of the snow concepts shows that some concepts are based on the physical characteristics of snow and can therefore be compared with international snow classification, while others have elements connected to the different herding strategies. Reindeer herders observe and manage snow from two perspectives: the snow physics and the ecology of herds in the winter grazing area, which reveals a holistic knowledge and view (Articles II, III).</p>
<p>A <em type="italic">siida </em>-based monitoring system, used in addition to interviews with herders, has provided an insight into the role of snow in daily herding. The data generated indicate the strategic and systematic use of grazing areas in terms of time and space. They also show the variability among the <em type="italic">siidas </em>in western </p>
<p>Finnmark investigated in terms of snow conditions between years and between pasture areas. Every winter <em type="italic">siida </em>has its own unique grazing conditions, which makes it difficult to compare one <em type="italic">siidas </em>grazing conditions with those of others, and to make general conclusions (Article II). </p>
<p>Some basic snow concepts in reindeer herding, are complex categories, in the sense that a term contains and includes many factors simultaneously, such as information about snow, snow conditions, snow physics, weather, temperature, location, time and impacts of animals and humans (Articles I, II, III). These concepts are central for daily work with the reindeer, and constitute important parts for reindeer herders‟ traditional knowledge. Their importance is also expressed by the fact that they also involve sub-concepts, which includes further information about location, time and snow consistency.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Goavvi </em>, is just a such snow concept because it contains information about extreme climate conditions adaptation to climate variability and change and knowledge about resilience thinking and sustainability in reindeer herding. Some </p>
<p>Sámi snow concepts mirror snow changes which are important for reindeer herding. This is believed to be important for observing the future projected effects of a changing climate on reindeer herding. Sámi snow concepts are a part of the reindeer herding specialist terminology used in daily communication in practical herding. The snow concepts reflect the reindeer herders‟ traditional knowledge of the management of the herd on snow-covered ground and how herders deal with these complex systems using mental models and “rules of thumb" (Article II, III). This kind of knowledge has contributed to the survival of reindeer herding since time immemorial and will be essential in the future when reindeer herding is exposed to external influences such as climate change, loss of grazing land and effects of globalization (Article IV). Traditional knowledge is an important basis for the future cultural sustainability of reindeer herding. Further development of a monitoring system for <em type="italic">guohtun </em>can best be carried out through the use of herders‟ own terminology and traditional knowledge in order to support the <em type="italic">siidas </em>in building resilience locally. </p>
<p>This thesis raises concerns about the future use of Sámi reindeer herders‟ specialist language and traditional knowledge in mainstream Norwegian governance of reindeer herding. With a projected 8 degree increase in temperature in West Finnmark in winter (Hanssen- Bauer et al., 2011, in prep, one must also expect changes in snow and grazing conditions stressing the importance of daily use of and the knowledge in reindeer herders‟ specialist language in future. With the projected warming in Guovdageaidnu, some snow concepts might disappear in the herders‟ daily vocabulary, which is commonly used to day. A future sustainable adaptation of Sámi reindeer herding and reindeer herders to climate variability and future projected change must be able to handle uncertainties in nature. This requires different ways of knowing, combining herders‟ experienced-based knowledge with scientific knowledge.</p>
<p>The Sámi language, knowledge and the use of pastures, show how the coupling of systems is manifested. Thus how herders and the environment are coupled.</p>
<p>The study suggests that national adaptive strategies must recognize reindeer herders‟ traditional knowledge, and cultural and linguistic rights must be included in adaptation strategies for climate change. It is therefore important to develop new social contracts between reindeer herders and society where reindeer herders‟ traditional knowledge and language are included.</p>
</body></document>
