<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="science"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>959</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>orig/sme/science/uit/phd/ketil_hansen.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="ketil_hansen.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>increased in recent years, notably after the establishment of the Centre for Sami Health</p>
<p>Research in 2001. Prior to the initiation of activities at the Centre, various public documents constitute the primary source of information. In 1995 the <em type="italic">NOU 1995:6 </em><em type="italic">Plan for health- and </em><em type="italic">social services to the Sami population in Norway </em>(in Norwegian, <em type="italic">Plan for helse- og </em><em type="italic">sosialtjenester for den samiske befolkningen i Norge </em>) was published. This document was the first public document to address the need to establish health- and social services for the Sami population. The plan focused on the demand for additional knowledge about the health and living conditions of the Sami, and suggestions were made that a research-based effort should be launched in the field. Scientific knowledge regarding Sami health and living conditions in </p>
<p>Norway (as well as in Sweden, Finland and Russia) was seen as limited in comparison to the wealth of detailed demographic information on the health and socio-economic conditions of indigenous peoples in, for instance, North America and Greenland. <em type="bold"></em></p>
<p>An extensive and representative health survey was determined to be a precondition for research into health and living conditions in the Sami areas. Such a survey was conducted in 2003-2004 in partnership with the National Health Screening Service (SHUS) (since renamed the Norwegian Institute of Public Health (NIPH)). The health survey in areas containing mixed Sami and Ethnic Norwegian settlements is known as SAMINOR; the study has been the Centre for Sami Health Research’s main priority. Invitations were sent to approximately 28,000 between 30 and 36-79 years of age. In total, nearly 17,000 people participated in the survey (61 percent). Geographically, the survey comprised 24 municipalities in which at least 5 percent of the residents reported in the Census of 1970 to have one or more Sami-speaking grandparents (a clear indicator of Sami ethnicity). In addition to information gained from questionnaires some physical measurements and blood samples were obtained; this material is currently stored in a purpose-built biobank.</p>
<p>Ethnic minorities and native peoples have been exposed to assimilation, racism, segregation, ethnic discrimination and oppression in many Western societies. For numerous indigenous populations the encounter with Western nations has included tremendous consequences in terms of heath. In Sami communities the <em type="italic">Norwegianisation process </em>, by which the Sami were subject to state-sanctioned assimilation policies, has been described as dramatically impacting the Sami culture; large parts of the Sami population lost their Sami language and identity. </p>
<p>Although the historical aspect of the process has been described in detail, in terms of its implications on health the circumstances have not been thoroughly investigated.</p>
<p>The primary objective of this dissertation is to study the prevalence of self-perceived ethnic discrimination and bullying in Sami, Kven and majority-population individuals, and study the hypothetical link between ethnic discrimination and health, and, if so, analyse the association.</p>
<p>Self-reported health (SRH) and psychological stress (HSCL-10) are utilised as health indicators. The dissertation also includes the secondary objective of studying and analysing 19 personal values.</p>
<p>Making statements about the Sami population is conditional on the ability to distinguish between Sami and non-Sami individuals. Operationalising ethnicity has been of great importance to our analysis as ethnicity is not recorded in Norwegian public registries. The</p>
<p>SAMINOR study has been of significance in the effort to clarify different definitions of Sami ethnicity and affiliation. By creating several categories of Sami ethnicity we have revealed that the differences within the Sami population become more apparent in regards to ethnic discrimination, personal values, and health.</p>
<p>The findings in our study indicate that a large proportion of Sami individuals experience discrimination based on their Sami background; roughly four in 10 men and one in three women in the Sami I category (i.e., participants reporting Sami language proficiency over three generations) have experienced being discriminated against <span type="quote">“often”</span> or <span type="quote">“sometimes”</span>.</p>
<p>Moreover, Sami individuals living outside the defined <em type="italic">Administrative Area of the Sami </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Language </em>report the highest levels of discrimination. Compared to the majority population, </p>
<p>Sami participants are twice as likely to respond that they have been subject to bullying.</p>
<p>Among respondents that reported bullying previously, the most common location was public schools. For those who reported bullying in the past year, the most common locations were at work and in the local community. The Sami respondents, furthermore, report more often (than</p>
<p>Kven and ethnic Norwegians) that discriminatory remarks were the most common forms of bullying.</p>
<p>Furthermore, our results show that ethnic discrimination is associated with inferior self-perceived health; Sami participants report somewhat lower health status than Ethnic</p>
<p>Norwegians. We have found that discrimination and lower socio-economic status contributes to the inequality in self-reported health between the Sami and the general population.</p>
<p>Our study finds that Sami and Kven males report higher levels of psychological distress than the general population of males. Interestingly, in women the effect is statistically insignificant. Generally, we know from earlier studies that ethnic discrimination is closely related to poorer mental health in indigenous peoples. Our study supports this conclusion and unveils a strong association between discrimination and psychological distress, as measured using the Hopkins Symptoms Check List (HSCL-10).</p>
<p>The final part of this dissertation deals with 19 questions on the internalisation of values (Appendix B). Thirteen of these questions are only posed to participants of Sami background.</p>
<p>From the 19 values the Sami respondents range the following five values as most important, in descending order: (i) Nature (ii), Utilisation of nature (iii) Family traditions, (iv)</p>
<p>Traditional Sami industries og (v) Sami language. At the opposite end of the scale, modern</p>
<p>Sami art and the <em type="italic">Sameting </em>(Sami Parliament) are considered the least important values. </p>
<p>Through the use of factor analysis, four dimensions were identified: Traditional Sami Values,</p>
<p>Modern Sami Values, Contact with Nature and Experience of Marginalisation. These four dimensions reflect important aspects of contemporary Sami society.</p>
</body></document>
