<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="science"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>246</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>orig/sme/science/uit/phd/margrethe_bals.pdf</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p>This thesis examined common and culture-specific risk and protective factors for internalizing (anxiety and depression) symptoms in Sami and non-Sami adolescents. This is a cross-sectional study, and the data are from The Norwegian Arctic Adolescent Health Study which was conducted among 10th graders in junior high schools in Arctic Norway in 2003-2005. The sample consisted of 4,449 adolescents, of whom 450 (10 %) were indigenous Sami and 3,999 (90 %) were non-Sami. The findings from this thesis were: (1) There were no differences between Sami and non-Sami adolescents in internalizing symptoms; (2) Strong ethnic identity, ethnic discrimination and loss of native language were cultural risk factors associated with increasing internalizing symptoms; (3) In the family socialization context, there were mostly similarities, but also some cultural differences in the impact of family factors on internalizing symptoms; (4) Engaging in cultural activities and ethnic pride were identified as cultural protective factors associated with decreasing symptom level; (5) Gender differences appeared in both ethnic groups in symptom level and in risk and protective factors associated with symptoms; (6) General protective factors, like self-efficacy, may strengthen the impact of the cultural protective factors. Findings from this study indicate both similarities and differences between Sami and non-Sami youth, and point out that the unique experience of indigenous Sami youth is related to symptoms of anxiety and depression. The integration of cultural protective factors with the well-known general protective factors is important when focusing on mental health problems and development in adolescents.</p>
</body></document>
