<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="science"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>1694</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>orig/sme/science/uit/phd/mikkel_sara.pdf</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p><em type="bold">Čállosa huksehus </em></p>
<p>Dán čállosis vuosttaš oasi dahká dárogielat láidehus. Nuppi oasi dahket guokte eŋgelasgillii almmuhuvvon artihkkala ja okta sámegillii almmuhuvvon artihkkala. Sámegillii almmuhuvvon artihkal lea dán čoakkáldahkii maiddái jorgaluvvon eŋgelasgillii. Dárogiella oktan eŋgelasgielain addá vejolašvuođa čađačuovvu lohkamii. Dán giellaválljema leat váikkuhan universitehta ja áigečállagiid giellamáhttu ja giellaválljen ja maiddái dobbelet ja viidát lohkiid oliheami beroštupmi.</p>
<p>Badjesámi siiddastallama váikkuhit ja birastahttet dán áiggi sihke alddeset siskkáldas, riikka almmolašvuođa ja riikkaid gaskasaš almmolašvuođa ságat ja mearrádusat. Livččii muhtumiid mielas soaitán heivvolaš oažžut buot osiid dán barggus jorgaluvvot buot dán golmma gillii, dehe aŋkke sámegillii.</p>
<p>Jorgalanbarggu várit leat gáržžidan dan vejolašvuođa. Barggadettiin dáinna čállosiin lea čálli muđui sámegillii almmuhan muhtun oasi vuođđomateriálas girjjážin ovdalaš siiddaid, siiddastallama ja maiddái árbevirolaš máhtuid birra. <em type="bold"></em></p>
<p><em type="bold">The structure of the thesis </em></p>
<p>The dissertation consists of an introductory part 1 written in</p>
<p>Norwegian, and part 2 consisting of published articles, two published in English and one in Sámi. The article which is published in Sámi is translated into</p>
<p>English for use here. A combination of Norwegian and English allows for continuous reading of the thesis. This language choice depends on the university’s and journals’ language use, and also on the intention to broader the readership.</p>
<p>Today the running of the reindeer siida is surrounded and influenced by various accounts and decisions both within siida system and at national and international level. Some would probably argue that all material should be translated into all three languages, or at least to Sámi. This however has been 4 limited by the resources allocated for translation work. Some of the source material on earlier siidas and on traditional Sámi reindeer herding knowledge has on the other hand been published in Sámi at an earlier stage of the work. <em type="bold"></em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Avhandlingens struktur </em></p>
<p>Avhandlingen består av en introduserende del 1 skrevet på norsk, og en del 2 med publiserte artikler, to publisert på engelsk og én på samisk. Artikkelen som er publisert på samisk, er oversatt til engelsk for bruk i foreliggende artikkelsamling. Kombinasjon av norsk og engelsk gir mulighet for sammenhengende lesning av avhandlingen. Dette er et språkvalg som henger sammen med universitetets og tidsskriftenes språkbeherskelse eller språkvalg, og videre med intensjonen om å nå en videre leserkrets.</p>
<p>Nå er det slik at reindriftssamenes siidautøvelse omgis og påvirkes av ulike framstillinger og beslutninger både innad i siidasystemet og på nasjonalt og internasjonalt nivå. Noen vil antakelig mene at alt materiale burde vært oversatt til alle tre språk, eller i alle fall til samisk. Det er et arbeid som er blitt begrenset av ressurser avsatt til oversettelsesarbeid. Under arbeidet med avhandlingen er på den annen side en del av grunnmaterialet, delvis om tidligere siidaer og delvis om tradisjonell reindriftssamisk kunnskap, publisert på samisk. 6 guhkit áiggi ovttasbarggu olis. Earemuđui leat boazo- ja siidaságaid birrasis ja maiddái dutkan- ja oahpahusságaid birrasis oallugat geat leat muittustan.</p>
<p>De dasto vel bohtet jurdagii dat barggut mat dutkama ja čállima barggadettiinan leat doaimmahuvvon ruovttustan ja siiddastan, muhto mat mu dihte livčče orron beallemuttus dehe dagakeahttá. Danne gullá dása muitit bearrašan nai liigenođiid dien bealis eallimisttán.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Acknowledgement </em></p>
<p>It is not easy to say when and how my PhD project came to be something possible and important, and thus when it really started. It all consists in a gradual and alternating learning of both reindeer herding and a theoretical approach to this field. This also included the challenge of getting a sense of why and how to link these different forms of knowledge together. Now I have got as far as the completion of the work. Time has come to think back on what has brought me to where I am.</p>
<p>First and foremost, I have been in the fortunate situation that I have been able to continuously alternate between different environments with their specific talks and actions. My place of work, Sámi University College, is located almost in the heart of many surrounding siida communities. There have been just a few steps into ongoing talks about reindeer and herding conditions at present.</p>
<p>Conversely, Sámi University College has by offering courses in reindeer husbandry opened its doors to reindeer husbandry youth and practitioners, and by that their experience and knowledge have been allowed to come into and make their contribution to the institution’s ongoing processes of learning and discussions. Moreover I have benefited from being in position to participate in seminars and discussions organized and brought to life as part of the Ealát-project. Through this project’s wide-ranging network, I have had the opportunity to become familiar with different approaches to issues of importance for reindeer 7 husbandry, and also to meet representatives of reindeer herders from different circumpolar regions.</p>
<p>The Ph.D. work has been carried out at the University of Tromsø. I wish to thank my supervisor Ragnar Nielsen for his patient and helpful support to get my work completed.</p>
<p>My colleagues at the Sámi University College have been a great support for my preparatory, first steps to get something down on paper, simply by letting me gain insight in their research projects and take part in their discussions: Inger</p>
<p>Marie Gaup Eira, Ellen Inga Turi, Svein D. Mathiesen and Ole Henrik Magga particularly in connection with the Ealát project, Mathis Bongo in connection with preparation and implementation of courses designed for reindeer herding practitioners and Nils Oskal in connection with our cooperation over time. And there are many others, besides of them mentioned here, whom I recall when thinking of talks about reindeer and siidas and discussions focused on issues related to research and education.</p>
<p>Finally I wish to thank my family members, who have undertaken additional work and commitments at home and in the siida during my work on the thesis. These are things that for my part probably had remained undone or poorly performed.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Takkeord </em></p>
<p>Det er ikke enkelt å si når og hvordan mitt doktorgradsprosjekt kom til som noe som var mulig og viktig, og således når det egentlig startet. Det hele har bestått i en gradvis og vekselvis læring av både arbeid med rein og en teoretisk tilnærming til dette feltet, og videre å danne seg et bilde av hvorfor og hvordan knytte disse ulike kunnskapsformene sammen. Nå når jeg har kommet så langt som til det fullførelsen av arbeidet står for, er anledningen kommet til å tenke tilbake på det som har brakt meg dit jeg er. 10 guorahalan ovdamearkkaid das maid sápmelaččat leat árbevirolaččat diđoštan ja vugiid beassat siiddaid lagabuidda alddeset doahpagiid ja doaibmavugiid bokte.</p>
<p>Dáid čállagiid lean jurddahan lohkamuššan sihke siiddaid olbmuide ja earáide.</p>
<p>Nugo guođoheaddjit bissot ealloravddain, de dáid tevsttaid guorahallamat nai bissot siidaravddaid diđošteapmin, eaige mana guđege siidda sisa.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Abstract </em></p>
<p>The concept of siida is well-known throughout the Sápmi. Far back in time there have been local Sámi communities called siidas. Siidas having reindeer herding as their unifying element are today the only ones representing a continuous practice of traditional siida livelihood and way of life. They represent an ongoing siida tradition up to now, especially the siidas in Guovdageaidnu and</p>
<p>Kárášjohka in Norway, i.e. in the region where the present research has been carried out. This tradition, however, still lives under pressure from the representation of the eastern siidas in literature on the one side and the administrative way of practicing the Reindeer Husbandry Act on the other side.</p>
<p>The image of a stable organization in the eastern siidas and the end of the hunting siidas has veiled the connecting lines between the past and present siidas and also led to an understanding of the siida system as non-existent. On the other hand, legislation on reindeer husbandry has led to construction and development of an alternate organization, the Reindeer Herding District system. The new</p>
<p>Reindeer Husbandry Act now has acknowledged the siida as a basic unit, but issues and governing practices originating from the reindeer herding district system have still been allowed to shape the approach to the siida system.</p>
<p>The process towards rehabilitation of siidas and the siida system contains no ways round the method of picking up the connecting lines between past and present siidas and taking them as our starting points. This implies taking the siida system’s own concepts, premises of thought and priorities as our starting point. Today it means primarily to extract and present the siidas’ shared concepts 11 and traditional herding knowledge, but also to look towards the traditional world view behind the siida practices. This provides, among other things, a basis to elucidate settings and adaptation in the relationship between siida and its natural surroundings, and also issues and ways of settling different matters in the process of rehabilitation of the siida system. Determination of outer limits for reindeer herding districts and siidas has been a thematic meeting point between reindeer herders and government. So far these meetings have not taken the siidas traditional knowledge and ways of thinking as their primary starting point and focus of attention. The present research examines examples of traditional Sámi beliefs and ways to approach siidas based on their own concepts and practices.</p>
<p>These texts are meant to be read by both siida members and others. As the reindeer herder primarily relates to the edges of the herd, likewise these texts relate to important aspects of all siidas and not to the inner life of any specific siida.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Kort sammenfatning </em></p>
<p>Begrepet siida er kjent over hele Sápmi. Så langt tilbake i tid vi kan vite, har siidaer vært der som noe som vi kan forstå som samiske lokalsamfunn. Det som i dag gjenstår av videreførte næringsutøvende og levemåtepraktiserende siidaer, er siidaer som har arbeidet med reinflokker som sitt sammenbindende element. Denne siidatradisjonen har vært levende frem til i dag spesielt i</p>
<p>Kautokeino- og Karasjokområdet i Norge, det vil si i det området hvor det foreliggende studiet er gjort. Imidlertid lever den fortsatt i krysspresset mellom representasjonen av tidligere østlige siidaer i litteraturen og den forvaltningsmessige praktisering av reindriftsloven. Bildet av en fasttømret organisering i de østlige siidaer og opphør av de såkalte veidesiidaene har usynliggjort forbindelseslinjene mellom tidligere og dagens siidaer og også ført til oppfattelse av siidasystemet som ikke-eksisterende. Reindriftslovgivningen har på sin side skapt og utviklet et alternativt reinbeitedistriktssystem. Etter at siidaen i prinsippet ble anerkjent ved reindriftsloven av 2007, har</p>
</body></document>
