<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="science"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>420</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>orig/sme/science/uit/phd/solveig_joks.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="nob" location="solveig_joks.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="solveig_joks.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p>SUMMARY</p>
<p>This  thesis  is  based  on  ethnographic  studies  of  traditional  knowledges  in  the  area  of Sirbmá, where people have traditionally lived from agriculture, reindeer herding, salmon fishing in the river, fishing in the lakes and hunting. These livelihoods have given rise to  knowledges  that  are  expressed  in  practices  and  stories  and  are  also  to  be  found  in concepts. Knowledge is articulated through its use. The continuity that is created over time can become relevant to management practices in the form of stories and practices, and  also  exists  within  communities  of  practice.  This  implies  that  there  is  space  for flexibility. Some stories work as pathfinders for how people need to behave in specific situations. Other stories deal with displacement from home areas and lack of understanding for the way of life of local people. Common to all the stories is that they perform knowledges. They exist in a social space and this implies that the stories both address other stories, and trigger new accounts.  Traditional knowledges are clearly visible in the practices of salmon fishing. This thesis makes visible the continuity in practices and communities of practice. The knowledges are  expressed  by  the  observations  that  people  make  by  being  on  the  Deatnu  (Deatnu river), and through the relations that they have to the salmon. Different kinds of relations are  established  through  different  kinds  of  fishing  methods.  The  Deatnu  is  therefore, experienced differently by different actors. The Sámi concepts that describe the water levels in the Deatnu have different meanings. They are dependent on how people fish and where in the Deatnu the fishing takes place. The Deatnu comes into being and takes its  shape  through  practices,  observations  and  stories.  The  local  peoples’  knowledges about salmon and the Deatnu, however, have not come to form part of the knowledge base in the official management of the Deatnu, despite the fact that this has been under local  management  for  some  years,  and  despite  the  fact  that  the  use  of  traditional knowledge  in  the  management  of  Sámi  and  other  indigenous  areas  is  mandated  in international conventions and Norwegian law (<em type="italic">Naturmangfoldloven)</em>. </p>
<p>It seems that it can be difficult to bring traditional knowledges into management without changing the practices of the latter. Traditional knowledge practices are different from the  management  practices  which  are  mostly  based  on  scientific  knowledges.  If traditional  knowledges  are  to  be  brought  into  official  management,  the  differences between knowledge practices have to be recognized. Those differences require space for expression. Traditional knowledges will only become available to management if this can be achieved.</p>
</body></document>