<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Conference on Sámi Intanigble Cultural Heritage May 23rd – May 24th, 2018 - Preliminary Program - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2018</year><wordcount>1092</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/conference-on-sami-intangible-cultural-heritage-may-23rd-may-24th-2018-preliminary-program/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="saamelaisen_aineettoman_kulttuuriperinnon_konferenssi_23_-24_5_2018_ohjelma.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="sami_njalmmalas_arbevieruid_konfereansa_-_programma.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">CONFERENCE ON SÁMI INTANGIBLE CULTURAL HERITAGE</p>
<p><em type="italic">May 23 rd – May 24 th , 2018 </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">PRELIMINARY PROGRAM </em></p>
<p type="title">May 23, 2018</p>
<p><em type="italic">10:00 – 10:30 OPENING SESSION </em></p>
<p>10:00 – 10:10 Opening words – moderator</p>
<p>10:10 – 10:15 The president of Sámi Parliament in Finland – Tiina Sanila-Aikio</p>
<p>10:15 – 10:20 The president of Sámi Parliament in Norway – Aili Keskitalo</p>
<p>10:20 – 10:25 The Sámi Parliament in Sweden – Marina Nilsson Ederlöv</p>
<p><em type="italic">10:30 – 11:30 START </em></p>
<p>10:30 – 10:50 UNESCO/WIPO – Rasul Samadov / Jon Petter Gintal</p>
<p>10:50 – 11:10 The challenges of the Intangible Cultural Heritage on Sámi point of view – Petra Laiti</p>
<p>11:10 – 11:30 Misuse of the Sámi Culture in Finnish tourism – Kirsi Suomi</p>
<p type="title">1st Topic: Duodji, the Sámi handicraft</p>
<p>11:30 – 11:50 The challenges of the Intangible Cultural Heritage in Duodji – Mari-Ann Nutti, Samesløydstiftelsen</p>
<p>11:50 – 12:10 The Soul of Duodji – Maarit Magga</p>
<p><em type="italic">12:10 – 13:10 Lunch </em></p>
<p>Opening of the Duodji Exhibitions</p>
<p>Fia Kaddik: Short Course on Tin Thread Weaving</p>
<p type="title">1st Topic: Duodji, the Sámi handicraft</p>
<p>13:05 – 13:25 The challenges of the Intangible Cultural Heritage in teaching – Samuli Valkeapää</p>
<p>13:25 – 13:45 Work in progress: The Sámi Duodji Trademark – Ellen Berit Dalbakk, Saami Council</p>
<p>13:45 – 13:55 MIS of Sápmi cooperative – Marit Guttorm Graven</p>
<p>13:55 – 14:05 Comments</p>
<p><em type="italic">2 nd topic: Archive Objects: Approach to the Intangible Cultural Heritage </em></p>
<p>14:05 – 14:25 The Heritage Returns Home – Eeva-Kristiina Harlin (Outi Pieski)</p>
<p>14:25 – 14:35 Repatriation and Revitalization – Eeva-Kristiina Harlin</p>
<p>14:35 – 14:50 Project AIDA – Hanna Helander/Sunna Valkeapää, Sámi Archive</p>
<p>14:50 – 15:00 Comments</p>
<p><em type="italic">15:00 – 15:30: Coffee </em></p>
<p type="title">3rd Topic: The Cultural Memories of the Intangible Cultural Heritage</p>
<p>15:30 – 15:55 Protection of the Sámi Intangible Cultural Heritage – Klemetti Näkkäläjärvi</p>
<p>15:55 – 16:15 Intangible Cultural Heritage in place names – Marit Myrvoll</p>
<p>16:15 – 16:35 Names of the sacred Sámi sites in written and oral sources – Jelena Porsanger</p>
<p>16:35 – 16:55 Intangible heritage on Mountain Rástegáisá – Toralf Henriksen</p>
<p>16:55 – 17:00 Comments</p>
<p type="title">EVENING PROGRAM:</p>
<p>17:45 – 19:30 <em type="italic">Cultural Program </em></p>
<p>Publication of the 6th Poetry Collection of Niillas Holmberg – DAT</p>
<p>Niillas Holmberg reading his poems and yoiking</p>
<p>Inga Victoria Påve: Presentation of the photos in the Poetry Collection</p>
<p><em type="italic">20:00 – 22:00 Dinner (self-paid) </em></p>
<p type="title">May 24, 2018</p>
<p type="title">4th Topic: Passing on the Intangible Singing Heritage – Yoik</p>
<p>10:05 – 10:25 The status of Yoik – Challenges and Rights – Biret Risten Sara</p>
<p>10:25 – 10:45 Saami Culture and Evolving Copyrights – Piia Nuorgam</p>
<p>10:45 – 11:05 How to Take Livđe back – Anna Morottaja</p>
<p>11:05 – 11:25 The Challenges of Yoik and the Recruit – Domna Khomjuk</p>
<p>11:25 – 11:45 Sámi Music Academy – SOGSAKK/Sámi Allaskuvla – Annukka Hirvasvuopio-Laiti</p>
<p>11:45 – 12:00 Comments</p>
<p><em type="italic">12:00 – 13:00 Lunch </em></p>
<p>Näyttelynavaus – Inarinsaamen puhujat – valokuvanäyttely</p>
<p type="title">5th Topic: Passing on the Story-telling Heritage</p>
<p>13:05 – 13:25 Perspectives on protection – Pauliina Feodoroff</p>
<p>13:25 – 13:45 Story-telling with the Creatures of the Sámi Mythology – Kirsti Paltto</p>
<p>13:45 – 14:05 Sámi Short Film: <em type="italic">Eatnanvulo </em><em type="italic">š lottit </em>by Marja Helander </p>
<p>14:05 – 14:25 Stage Text on the Sámi Stories – Sara Margrethe Oskal</p>
<p>14:25 – 14:45 ISFI: – Ethical Regulations for the movie makers and movie companies from outside – Liisa Holmberg</p>
<p>14:45 – 15:00 Comments</p>
<p><em type="italic">15:00 – 15:30 Coffee </em></p>
<p type="title">6th Topic: Rights and the Intangible Heritage</p>
<p>15:35 – 15:55 The Ethical Regulations and the Understanding of the Intangible Cultural Heritage Brought for the Outside Professionals – Anni-Helena Ruotsala</p>
<p>15:55 – 16:15 Is there a Place for Traditional Knowledge in the Mastery of Natural Resources? – Solveig Joks, Sámi University College</p>
<p>16:15 – 16:35 Traditional Economical Knowledge in Reindeer Herding – Berit Inga</p>
<p>16:35 – 17:00 Challenges in Passing on the Traditional Fishing skills – Ásllat Holmberg / Ivan Matrekhin</p>
<p>17:00 – 17:10 Comments</p>
<p><em type="italic">17:10 – 17:30 </em><em type="italic">Greetings to Sápmi </em></p>
<p>Rasul Samadov (UNESCO); Hildegunn Bjørgen (NOR), Leena Marsio (FIN); Marina Nilsson Ederlöv (SWE)</p>
<p><em type="italic">17:30 – 17:45 </em><em type="italic">Closure: the Protection of the Cultural Heritage </em></p>
<p>Panel discussion</p>
<p><em type="italic">EVENING EVENT IN SAJOS: </em></p>
<p>20:00 – 21:00 – Film night with Skábmagovat</p>
<p><em type="italic">Call and response </em>Canada, 2014, 5’ Director: Craig Commanda </p>
<p>An Anishnaabe musician of the digital era – the director himself – faces features of his nation’s heritage in the forest at night.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Gobmemainnas </em>Sápmi/Finland, 2017, 6’ Director: Niki Rasmus </p>
<p>Aslak Pieski tells a frightening story about his childhood.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Juuret on – Under Two Skies </em>Sápmi/Finland, 2016, 13’ Director: Suvi West &amp; Anssi Kömi </p>
<p>A short film about leaving, love and the meaning of roots.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Half &amp; half </em>Kalaallit Nunaat, Denmark, 2015, 3’ Director: Aka Hansen </p>
<p>Director Aka Hansen ponders her mixed heritage by posing well-struck questions about how others perceive her, which in contrast to the filmic symmetry suggests that identity cannot be split neatly in half.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Morit Elena Morit – Wake up Elena Wake Up </em>Sápmi/Sweden, 2017, 5’ Director/Screenwriter /Production: Inga-Wiktoria Påve &amp; Anders Sunna </p>
<p>An awarded animation (imagineNATIVE Media + Arts Festival, Skábmagovat Film Festival) shows how colonialisation has sneaked upon the Sámi people and gives other young Sámi a shout out to wake up and rebuild their connection to nature and traditions.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Three thousand </em>Canada, 2017, 14’ Director: Asinnajaq </p>
<p>‘’My father was born in the spring – half snow, half skin. I was born in a hospital, with jaundice and two teeth’’. In a fascinating time travel by an Inuk director, the past, the present and the future of the Inuit become an impressive mixture of archive pictures and animation. Three thousand received Best Global Indigenous Short film award at Skábmagovat 2018.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Smoke That Travels </em>USA, 2016, 13’ Director: Kayla Briët </p>
<p>Language, dance, music and Potowatomi history are woven into a wise weft by a self-taught young director in this beautiful homage to the teachings and cultural heritage of the director’s father.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Heidi – Kaissi-U’lljan-Mä’rjj-U’lljan </em>Sápmi/Finland, 2016, 10’ Director: Aleksi Ahlakorpi, Production: Sámi Education Institute </p>
<p>A short documentary on Heidi Gauriloff, a Skolt Sámi craftsmaker, who was already an adult when she finally got the chance to learn the language and culture of her family.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Sää’nte’mes Saakk </em>Sápmi/Finland, 2016, 7’ Director: Sámi Education Institute student group / Production: Erkki Feodoroff / Sámi Education Institute </p>
<p>Anna Lumisalmi sings in the first Skolt Sámi leu’dd music video in the world.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Mu nieidaskihpára áhkku – My girlfriend’s Grandma </em>Sápmi, Finland, 2016, 8’ </p>
<p>An amusing story about a boy who meets his girlfriend’s grandmother for the first time. Will he and the grandmother find a common language? And what does jelly have to do with this story?</p>
<p type="title">WE WOULD LIKE TO THANK ALL WHO HAVE FUNDED OUR CONFERENCE!</p>
</body></document>
