<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Finished projects - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>263</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/finished-projects/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="paattyneet_hankkeet.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nohkan_proseavttat.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="nuuham_haavah.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="puuttam_ha_ngkkoozz.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p><span type="quote">Culturally Responsible Sámi Tourism</span></p>
<p>Tourism has grown fast, both globally as well as in Finnish Lapland. The growth of tourism has increased challenges to cultural sustainability, especially in the context of Sámi culture. The Sámi who are the only indigenous people in the E.U reside in four countries, that is, Finland, Sweden, Norway and Russia. The Sámi Parliament in Finland has received funding from <em type="italic">the Ministry of Education and Culture </em>to carry out Culturally Responsible Sámi Tourism project. One of the main objectives of the project is to develop ethical guidelines from the Sámi point of view for responsible socially, culturally, ecologically and economically sustainable Sámi tourism product development and presentation in Finland. The ethical guidelines are due in 2018. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Read more… </em></p>
<p><span type="quote">Giellagáldu project and Sámi Giellagáldu</span></p>
<p>Giellagáldu is a cooperation project between the Sámi parliaments of Finland, Sweden and Norway, which operates within the Sámi Parliamentary Council, the cooperational body for the Sámi parliaments. The project started on 1 August 2015, and ends on 31 May 2018. The Giellagáldu project is funded by Sámi Giellagáldu, the Nordic Resource Centre for the Sámi languages. A key aim of the project is to secure the permanent operation of Sámi Giellagáldu by obtaining permanent funding for the activities of the centre. The Giellagáldu follow-up project is funded by the Sápmi sub-area of the EU’s Interreg V Nord programme, the Regional Council of Lapland, the province of Tromsø, and the Sámi parliaments of Norway, Sweden and Finland. The project is headed by the Sámi Parliament of Finland, and the total budget is EUR 3,062,052.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Read more… </em></p>
</body></document>
