<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>General Office - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2016</year><wordcount>238</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/general-office/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="guovddasdoaimmahat.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">General Office</p>
<p>The purpose of the General Office is to attend to the financial, personnel and other general administrative issues, as well as issues that have not been assigned to other offices. The appointments in the General Office include Executive Director, Cultural Secretary, Legal Secretary, Social Affairs and Health Secretary, Financial Secretary, Office Secretary and the planner of a Sámi Unit. The job descriptions are defined in the standing orders of the Sámi Parliament. The Plenum can establish other posts, if necessary. The Sámi Unit of the Social Affairs Learning Centre of Northern Finland also functions within the General Office. Other personnel can also work at the General Office. The director of the General Office is the Executive Diractor.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Personnel: </em>Executive Director Pia Ruotsala Legal Secretary Kalle Varis Cultural Secretary Riitta Orti-Berg Social Affairs and Health Secretary Anne Länsman-Magga Environment secretary Anni-Helena Ruotsala Youth secretary Kaisa Tapiola-Länsman Planner, Sámi Unit of the Social Affairs Learning Centre in Northern Finland Coordinator, The Sámi Childrens Center Petra Biret Magga-Vars The Sámi Cultural Centre Johanna Alatorvinen Project planner, Skábma – The Indigenous Peoples’ Film Centre Tarja Porsanger Project planner, Sámi music centre Oula Guttorm Financial Secretary Hilkka Kukkonen Administrative Secretary Anneli Länsman Office Secretary Laila Aikio Systems specialist vs. Pietari Seppänen Audio visual technician Joonas Saari Audio visual technician Janne Lappalainen Premises manager Pauli Saijets Facilities generalist Pirkko Pieski </p>
<p type="title">Contacts</p>
<p><em type="italic">General Office </em></p>
<p>Sajos FI-99870 Inari Finland</p>
<p>Tel. +358 10 839 3100</p>
</body></document>
