<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Greetings in Sámi Languages - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>300</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/greetings-in-sami-languages/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="tervehdyksia_saamen_kielilla.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="dearvvahusat_iesgudege_samegillii.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="tiervattasah_suomast_sarnum_samikielan.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="tiorvtoozz_saa_mkiolin.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">Greetings in Sámi Languages</p>
<p type="title">Valentine’s Day (Friend’s Day)</p>
<p>North Sámi: Ustibabeaivi / Ustitbeaivi Inari Sámi: Ustevpeivi Skolt Sámi: Naʹzvaanpeiʹvv</p>
<p type="title">Happy Valentine’s Day!</p>
<p>North Sámi: Buori ustibabeaivvi/ Buori ustitvuođabeaivvi! Inari Sámi: Pyeri ustevpeivi! Skolt Sámi: Šiõǥǥ naʹzvaanpeiʹvv!</p>
<p type="title">Wishing you all a Happy Valentine’s Day!</p>
<p>North Sámi: Sávan buori ustibabeaivvi buohkaide! Inari Sámi: Tuáivum šiev ustevpeeivi puohháid! Skolt Sámi: Tuäivtam pukid šiõǥǥ naʹzvaanpeeiʹv!</p>
<p type="title">Happy Midsummer!</p>
<p>North Sámi: Buriid mihcamáraid!/ Buori jonssoha! Inari Sámi: Pyeri jonsahpeivi! Skolt Sámi: Šiõǥǥ evvanpeeiʹv!</p>
<p type="title">Happy summer for everyone!</p>
<p>North Sámi: Buori geasi buohkaide! Inari Sámi: Pyeri keesi puohháid! Skolt Sámi: Šiõǥǥ ǩieʹss pukid!</p>
<p type="title">Happy Independence Day!</p>
<p>North Sámi: Buori iehčanasvuođabeaivvi! Inari Sámi: Šiev jiečânâsvuođâpeivi! Skolt Sámi: Šiõǥǥ jiõččnažvuõttpeiʹvv!</p>
<p type="title">Merry Christmas and Happy New Year!</p>
<p>North Sámi: Buriid juovllaid ja lihkolaš ođđa jagi! Inari Sámi: Pyereh juovlah já luholâš uđđâ ihe! Skolt Sámi: Šiõǥǥ rosttvid da leklvaž ođđ eeʹjj!</p>
<p><em type="italic">Greetings for the Sámi National Day on 6 February </em></p>
<p type="title">Happy Sámi National Day for everyone</p>
<p>North Sámi: Buori sámi álbmotbeaivvi buohkaide Inari Sámi: Pyeri säämi aalmugpeivi puohháid Skolt Sámi: Šiõǥǥ saaʹmi meersažpeiʹvv pukid</p>
<p type="title">Sámi National Day on 6 February</p>
<p>North Sámi: Sámi álbmotbeaivi Inari Sámi: Säämi aalmugpeivi Skolt Sámi: Saaʹmi meersažpeiʹvv Swedish: Samiska nationaldagen</p>
<p><em type="italic">Greetings for European Day of Languages on 26 September </em></p>
<p type="title">Septmber 26 is European Day of Languages</p>
<p>North Sámi: 26. beaivi čakčamánu lea Eurohpá gielaid beaivi Inari Sámi: 26. čohčâmáánu lii Euroopkielâi peivi Skolt Sámi: Čõhččmannu 26. peeiʹv lij Euroop ǩiõli peiʹvv</p>
<p type="title">Happy European Day of Languages</p>
<p>North Sámi: Buori Eurohpá gielaid beaivvi Inari Sámi: Pyeri Euroopkielâi peeivi Skolt Sámi: Šiõǥǥ Euroopp ǩiõli peeiʹv</p>
<p><em type="italic">More information: </em></p>
<p>At the initiative of the Council of Europe, Strasbourg, the European Day of Languages has been celebrated every year since 2001 on 26 September.</p>
<p>http://edl.ecml.at/</p>
<p type="title">Jaa tämä kirjoitus</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Share on Facebook</p>
<p type="listitem">Share on Twitter</p>
<p type="listitem">Share on WhatsApp</p>
<p type="listitem">Share by Mail</p>
</list></body></document>
