<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>II Vice President Juuso Attends the Arctic Council Meeting in Rovaniemi - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2019</year><wordcount>325</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/2019/05/07/ii-vice-president-juuso-attends-the-arctic-council-meeting-in-rovaniemi/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="ii_varapuheenjohtaja_juuso_osallistuu_arktisen_neuvoston_kokoukseen_rovaniemella.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="ii_varresagajodiheaddji_juuso_oassalasta_arktalas_radi_coahkkimii_roavvenjarggas.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">II Vice President Juuso Attends the Arctic Council Meeting in Rovaniemi</p>
<p>Tuomas Aslak Juuso, the II Vice President of the Sámi Parliament in Finland, participates in the Arctic Council Meeting in Rovaniemi on May 6 th and 7 th , 2019. Finland’s two-year Chairmanship of the Arctic Council will end at the Foreign Ministerial Meeting that is held in Rovaniemi on May 7 th .</p>
<p>Along with the Arctic States, the Arctic Council’s Permanent Participants will be attending the meeting. Council’s six indigenous Permanent Participants are the Aleut International Association (AIA), Arctic Athabaskan Council (AAC), Gwich’in Council International (GCI), Inuit Circumpolar Council (ICC), Russian Association of Indigenous Peoples of the North (RAIPON) and Saami Council (SC).</p>
<p><span type="quote">“Arctic Council is a good example how regional as well as cross border co-operation can be exercised together with people from the region”</span>, says Tuomas Aslak Juuso, the II Vice President of the Sámi Parliament in Finland.</p>
<p><span type="quote">“I would like to congratulate the Arctic Council, under the Finnish Chairmanship, on a good co-operation with indigenous peoples, focusing on climate change and meteorological co-operation joined with traditional knowledge. I hope that Arctic Council continues to be one of the leading actors on the climate change mitigation. We, the indigenous peoples, that live on the frontlines of the effects of climate change, see the importance of focusing on the mitigation of climate change.”</span></p>
<p>Finland’s two-year Chairmanship Program focused on the mitigation of climate change and the implementation of the UN Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) in the Arctic regions. The priorities of the Finnish Chairmanship have included strengthening of the meteorological cooperation; environmental protection, including reduction of black carbon emissions; knowledge and education; and regional cooperation. Read more from the Ministry for Foreign Affairs of Finland’s news: <em type="italic">Finland’s Arctic Council Chairmanship comes to an end in Rovaniemi </em><em type="italic">. </em></p>
<p type="title">More information:</p>
<p>Tuomas Aslak Juuso, the II Vice President of the Sámi Parliament in Finland, tel. +358 40 187 1331, tuomas.juuso(at)samediggi.fi</p>
<p><em type="italic">Picture: Ville-Riiko Fofonoff </em></p>
</body></document>
