<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id">
  <header>
    <title>Samediggi - Saamelaiskäräjät - Opening of the Anniversary exhibition of Petteri Laiti is held on Thursday 25th of June at Sajos</title>
    <genre code="admin"/>
    <author>
      <unknown/>
    </author>
    <translator>
      <unknown/>
    </translator>
    <translated_from xml:lang="fin"/>
    <wordcount>322</wordcount>
    <conversion_status type="standard"/>
    <availability>
      <free/>
    </availability>
    <multilingual/>
    <origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index2.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=1072&amp;lang=english</origFileName>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=1072_lang=finnish.html"/>
    <parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=1072_lang=davvi.html"/>
    <metadata>
      <uncomplete/>
    </metadata>
    <version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>Opening of the Anniversary exhibition of Petteri Laiti is held on Thursday 25th of June at Sajos</p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p xml:lang="nno"></p>
    <p>Sámi Cultural Center Sajos, located in the village of Inari, opens exhibition spaces for Sámi artists. The opening of the first exhibition is held on Thursday 25th of June 2015, when the anniversary exhibition of Petteri Laiti will be opened for public. The exhibition will be on display at Sajos until 30th of September 2015.</p>
    <p>The opening day starts with a ceremony at 5 pm for invited guests. After the ceremony doors will be opened for the public at 6 pm when a concert starts. Performers at the concert are Niillas Holmberg &amp; Roope Mäenpää, who play Arctic folk music in Northern sámi and joikers from Norwegian side of Sápmi; Johan Anders Baer and Iŋgor Ántte Áilu Gaup (Áilloš). After the concert, there is a possibility to explore the Anniversary exhibition of Petteri Laiti with the guidance of the artist himself. Tickets to the concert can be bought at Sajos info or at web-store www.lipputoimisto.fi . Tickets: 10 €.</p>
    <p>From the music of Niillas Holmberg and Roope Mäenpää you may hear the natural beauty and bareness of the nature of Sámi, the Sámi philosophy and beliefs, as well as the endless wonder of Western man’s unending need for ownership. Johan Anders Bær, from Karasjok and Magerøya in Northern Norway, is solidly in the classical Sami joik singing tradition. He is a master in the art of maintaining the sound and soul of traditional joik while blending it with new music forms and styles. Iŋgor Ántte Áilu Gaup in one of the founders of Beaivváš Sámi Theatre with experience from multiple productions. He is a well renowned joiker and is an active musician beside his work as an actor. <em type="italic">Concert </em>When? 25th of June at 6 pm Tickets: 10 €, </p>
    <p>Sajos info and www.lipputoimisto.fi Organiser: Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos, The Sámi Parliament of Finland</p>
    <p>Press photo</p>
  </body>
</document>
