<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Samediggi - Saamelaiskäräjät - Handicraft workshops bring visitors to the heart of Sámi culture</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="fin"/><wordcount>475</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index2.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=713&amp;lang=english.html</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=713_lang=finnish.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=713_lang=davvi.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=713_lang=anaras.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>Handicraft workshops bring visitors to the heart of Sámi culture</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p xml:lang="mdf"></p>
<p>Located at the heart of Inari, the Sajos Sámi Cultural Centre caters to the need in the modern humanist to be personally engaged in the production of a cultural experience, or to be part of the experience. The workshop concept for Sajos was designed with these needs in mind. This summer, Sajos is arranging workshops that introduce traditional and modern Sámi handicraft techniques, giving visitors the opportunity to make their own Sámi souvenirs to take home.</p>
<p><em type="italic">A great opportunity for the young Sámi craftsmen, the duojári </em></p>
<p>Sajos recruits young, newly graduated Sámi arts and crafts professionals – duojári – to create memorable hands-on experiences for visitors, especially tourists. Visitors get to choose from a variety of materials and techniques, and create their own handcrafted souvenir. Besides offering work instructions, the duojári also tell visitors about the history of Sámi arts and crafts, and about their own handicraft techniques. - We came up with the idea of setting up workshops in response to the growing interest customers have expressed in Sámi culture and traditions. Another driving force was Aune Musta, Managing Director of Duodji Shop in Sajos, which sells authentic Sámi handicrafts. She encouraged us to develop a different concept around arts and crafts, explains Marja Männistö, Marketing Manager at Sajos.</p>
<p>Juha Guttorm, Administration Manager at the Sámi Parliament, elaborates on the idea, explaining that the objective is to use new methods to develop cultural content production at Sajos, to enhance the recognition of Sámi arts and crafts and thereby raise awareness of the indigenous Sámi people. In addition, it is designed to promote the sales of Sámi handicrafts and provide a better livelihood for the craftsmen.- We also want to make Sajos a place where people can meet and get together, and to provide jobs to young Sámi arts and crafts professionals in their home region.</p>
<p>Inari has always been a hub of Sámi arts and crafts, as evidenced by the large number of handicraft galleries, shops and workshops. The difference between ordinary galleries and Sajos workshops is that in Sajos, visitors get a hands-on experience and learn to appreciate the value of a handcrafted item.</p>
<p><em type="italic">A wide range of handcrafted items </em></p>
<p>Depending on how much time they can spend, visitors can make a tin or a pearl bracelet, a reindeer antler necklace, a handloom woven scarf, a reindeer leather pouch, or various reindeer bone and antler items. Arts and crafts workshops are arranged in the main foyer at Sajos for a fee. Groups should book their workshops in advance in case additional instructors are needed. Sajos arts and crafts workshops are organised on weekdays from 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. between 17 June and 12 August 2013.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Further information: </em></p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Aune Musta, Managing Director, Duodji Shop, www.samiduodji.com</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Marja Männistö, Marketing Manager, Sajos Sámi Cultural Centre,</p>
</body></document>
