<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Samediggi - Saamelaiskäräjät - Ijahis idja's 10th anniversary brings generations together in Inari</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="fin"/><wordcount>461</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Børre Gaup" email="albbas@gmail.com"/><multilingual><language xml:lang="fin"/><language xml:lang="eng"/></multilingual><origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index2.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=723&amp;lang=english.html</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=723_lang=finnish.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=723_lang=davvi.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p>Ijahis idja's 10th anniversary brings generations together in Inari</p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"></p>
<p>The Ijahis idja Music Festival of Indigenous Peoples publishes its full programme today. The theme of this year's festival is Generations, and the programme will be more varied than ever.</p>
<p>The 10th anniversary of Ijahis idja will be celebrated with the Generations jubilee concert at the Auditorium of Sajos Sámi Cultural Centre. The concert gathers Sámi musicians of different generations together to play Sámi classics as well as newer production. The concert features performances by Niko Valkeapää, one of the most well-known Sámi artists, as well as the the traditional yoik artist Niiles-Jouni Aikio, the renowned Sámi musician Annukka Hirvasvuopio-Laiti and, representing the young generation, Sunná Länsman. The performances are accompanied by the Ijahis idja band conducted by the veteran musician Janne Lappalainen.</p>
<p>Ijahis idja concerts are also streamed live on the Internet. Last year's streams were followed by approximately 900 viewers across the world. Live streaming will be arranged at least for the main event on Saturday featuring Sámi artists from Finland, Norway and Sweden. The main event is opened by the enchanting rhythmic yoik and energetic performance of the ever-so-popular Sámi band Angelit. The evening continues with the Sápmi and Chukotka concert featuring traditional yoik, livđe and leuddi, as well as traditional Chukotkan throat singing and dancing performed by Veronica Usholik and the dance group Ener. The most upbeat performance at Ijahis idja will be given by Lovisa Negga, whose song Mihá ja gievrra has delighted people throughout the Sámi region. The programme is concluded with Intrigue from Norway, a band combining hard rock and yoik in a unique way. Friday's programme for children and youngsters includes the Ijahis ija násttážat concert with performances by Máret Hildur Stueng and her band, and the Chukotkan throat singer Veronika Usholik, among others. Niko Valkeapää will give a concert at the Sajos Auditorium on Friday night, and after the concert, the night will continue at the ČSV theme club with Niiles-Jouni Aikio as the main artist. The traditional Ijahis idja music seminar will take place in Siida on Saturday. In keeping with the festival's theme, the seminar will contain speeches on the meeting of generations. At the Saturday night club, festival visitors will be entertained with recorded Sámi music played by the Norwegian DJ duo DJ Šielat.</p>
<p>Ijahis idja is jointly organised by Anára Sámisearvi ry, the Sámi Parliament, the Sámi Education Institute, Sámi Museum Siida, the Giellagas Institute, the University of Oulu, Yle Sápmi, the municipality of Inari, the Sámi children's culture centre, the Lapland division of the Arts Promotion Centre Finland, Hotel Kultahovi and Restaurant Galla.For the detailed programme, see the Ijahis idja website at www.ijahisidja.fi.</p>
<p>Further information:</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Anu Magga</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">+358 50 567 22 04</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">anu.magga@samediggi</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Anna Näkkäläjärvi-Länsman</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">+358 295 330856</p>
</body></document>
