<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Samediggi - Saamelaiskäräjät - Sámi handicraft market and flea market take over Sajos at 21st of November 2015</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="fin"/><wordcount>209</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index2.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=1124&amp;lang=english</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=1124_lang=finnish.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=1124_lang=davvi.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>Sámi handicraft market and flea market take over Sajos at 21st of November 2015</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p>Sámi Duodji association organizes in cooperation with Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos Sámi handicraft market and flea market at Sajos, Inari, 21 st of November 2015 at 10 a.m. – 5 p.m.</p>
<p>Sellers all around the Sámi land gather to the lobby of Sajos. The market is a great place to explore the latest trends of Sámi handicrafts and make Christmas gift shopping.</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p>Come to the flea market for bargains! Brooch (risku), earrings or any other handicraft that is no longer needed by someone, can be a treasure for you. You may also find Sámi handicraft materials such as fabrics, threads, silk, skins and much more.</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p>Also kids are very welcome to the market! Sámi Children’s Center Mánnu organizes a craft workshop at 10 a.m. to 12 p.m. to prepare a keychain. When you get hungry, Restaurant Lyeme offers market food for smaller and bigger hunger.</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p>The day does not end to the market, but after the market at 17 o’clock starts Kaamosjazz concert at the concert hall of Sajos. Performers at the concert are Sámi artists Hilda Länsman and Wimme Saari.</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p>More information</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos, Inari, tel. +358 (0)10 839 3168, sajos(at)samediggi.fi</p>
<p xml:lang="koi"></p>
<p xml:lang="fin">www.sajos.fi</p>
</body></document>
