<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Samediggi - Saamelaiskäräjät - Past events 2015</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><translator><unknown/></translator><translated_from xml:lang="fin"/><wordcount>1498</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.samediggi.fi/index2.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=984&amp;lang=english</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=984_lang=finnish.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=984_lang=davvi.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p>Past events 2015</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="nno"><em type="bold">Sat 21.11.2015 at 10 am   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="kal"><em type="bold">SÁMI HANDICRAFT MARKET AND FLEA MARKET  </em></p>
<p>Sámi Duodji association organizes in cooperation with Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos Sámi handicraft market and flea market at Sajos, Inari, 21 st of November 2015 at 10 a.m. – 5 p.m.   Sellers all around the Sámi land gather to the lobby of Sajos. The market is a great place to explore the latest trends of Sámi handicrafts and make Christmas gift shopping. Read more</p>
<p xml:lang="kal"><em type="bold">Sat 21.11.2015 at 5 pm   </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">KAAMOSJAZZ PRESENTS HILDA LÄNSMAN AND WIMME SAARI </em> </p>
<p>This year's Kaamosjazz will once again provide full weekend for Jazz lovers. At the Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos people get to enjoy evening of Sámi music as the stars of Sámi music Hilda Länsman and Wimme Saari perform at the concert hall of Sajos starting at 5 p.m. Read more</p>
<p xml:lang="kal"><em type="bold">Sat 14.11.2015 at 3 pm   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="deu"><em type="bold">FRESH LOCAL THEATRE WITHOUT ADDED INGREDIENTS  </em></p>
<p>Local theatre comes to Sajos to chear up your winter. Theatre group iValoiset plays <span type="quote">"Ministerial visit"</span> (Ministerin vierailu) and Kaamasen kotitarveorkesteri plays <span type="quote">"Sensation soiree"</span> (Kohu-iltamat).</p>
<p xml:lang="kal"><em type="bold">Sat 24.10.2015 at 5 pm   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="italic">BEAIVVÁŠ SÁMI NAŠUNÁLATEÁHTER <span type="quote" xml:lang="vep">"SKOAVDNJI"</span>  </em></p>
<p>The play <span type="quote" xml:lang="smj">"Skoavdnji"</span> addresses both the good and evil sides of human nature. The original source of the play was a ghost story from the eastern coast of Finnmark, dramatized and re-written by the Sami playwright Inger Margrethe Olsen (1956-2010). The setting of the play is in a coastal Sami environment in the 1920’s.</p>
<p>The recommended age limit is 14 years. Read more</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">6.10.2015 at 9.30 a.m. </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">THE OPENING CEREMONY OF SÁMI GIELLAGÁLDU PROJECT </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>The Sámi Giellagáldu brings Sámi language experts and invites language users to seminar at Sajos, Inari 6th of October. The kick-off seminar is open to all. The seminar will be interpreted from Sámi languages to Finnish and Swedish. Location: Solju - Sajos, Inari 06/10/2015. More information: Sámi Giellagáldu</p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">26.6.-30.9.2015   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p><em type="italic">ANNIVERSARY EXHIBITION OF PETTERI LAITI </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>Sámi Cultural Center Sajos, located in the village of Inari, opens exhibition spaces for Sámi artists. The opening of the first exhibition is held on Thursday 25th of June 2015, when the anniversary exhibition of Petteri Laiti will be opened for public. The exhibition will be on display at Sajos until 30th of September 2015. Read more</p>
<p xml:lang="kal"><em type="bold">Thu 10.9.2015 at 7 pm   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p><em type="italic">REMU AALTONEN AND HIS ALL STARS </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>The legend of Finnish rock music Remu aaltonen starts a tour to celebrate his Roadrunner album. Remu and His All Stars assembly celebrates the 40 year history of Roadrunner album in nine concerts all around Finland. To Inari and to Sajos Remu and his band comes Thu 10th of September at 7 pm.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Thu 3.9.2015 at 6 and 9 pm   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p><em type="italic">SAMI HEDBERG 365 - world record tour 2015 </em> </p>
<p>The best known Finnish stand up comedian Sami Hedberg strives for world record. The man intends to break the Guinness record for making the most shows during the year, all together 365 shows. The record is made when over 200 shows that last over an hour is exceeded. Sami comes to Sajos on Thursday 3th of September at 6 and 9 pm. (Age limit 13 years).</p>
<p><em type="bold">1.7.-14.8.2015 Mon-Fri at 11 am - 5 pm   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="deu"><em type="italic">SÁMI HANDICRAFT WORKSHOPS </em> </p>
<p>Sajos will organize Sámi handicraft workshops also this summer – workshops that have been organized for two summers now. Visitors have the opportunity to make their own Sámi souvenir to take back home and learn about the history and traditions from the instructor. Read more</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="kal"><em type="bold">Thu 23.7.2015 at 6 pm   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="italic">SKÁBMAGOVAT PRESENTS </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>Sajos takes part to Inariweeks! Skábmagovat presents, among others document by Harry Johansen Ivnnit ja eallin (colours and life). Sajos auditorium, Sápmi movies from 6 pm. Free of charge!</p>
<p><em type="bold">Thu 25.6.2015 at 10 am   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p><em type="italic">PLENUM OF SÁMI PARLIAMENT 3/2015 </em> </p>
<p>The Plenum represents the supreme authority of the Sámi Parliament. It meets 4-5 times per year. The Plenum decides mainly on the statements, proposals, and other comments. Live stream broadcast can be followed at sogku.fi/live . The meeting can be followed also at the parliament hall Solju at Sajos. Read more</p>
<p xml:lang="kal"><em type="italic">Thu 25.6.2015 at 6 pm   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="italic">KONSERTTI | KONSEARTA | CONCERT  </em></p>
<p>The concert is held at Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos and there will perform Niillas Holmberg &amp; Roope Mäenpää, who play Arctic folk music in Northern sámi and joikers from Norwegian side of Sápmi; Johan Anders Baer and Igor Ántte Áilu Gaup (Áilloš). After the concert, there is a possibility to explore the Anniversary exhibition of Petteri Laiti, which will be opened at Sajos, with the guidance of the artist himself. Tickes: 10 €. Organisers: Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos &amp; The Sámi Parliament of Finland.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">1.5.-31.5.2015   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="deu"><em type="italic">PHOTOGRAPHY EXHIBITION: WATER VOICES </em> </p>
<p>Vesien kertomaa, <span type="quote">"Water voices"</span> -exhibition deals with the Finns and Peruvian children's and young people views of their own surrpunding from water by means of photography. The exhibition is open 1.5.-31.5. at Sajos, Inari. Organiser: The Finnish Tinku association.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Thu 28.5.2015 at 10 am and 12.15 pm   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p><em type="italic">SÁMI CHILDREN AND YOUTH THEATRE </em> </p>
<p>Theatre for children and youngsters on Thu 28th of May at Sajos, Inari. Children´s play: Pilvi in love at 10 am (duration 40 min). Youth play (5. class and upwords): Girls, that nobody could bully at 12.15 pm (duration 80 min). The shows are free. Organiser: MÁNNU Sámi Children's Cultural Centre/ The Sámi Parliament. Read more</p>
<p xml:lang="rmf"><em type="bold">Thu 19.4.2015 18.00   </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">PHOTO CONCERT: <span type="quote" xml:lang="vep">"KAIROJEN KAUNIS MAA"</span> NATURE PHOTO CONCERT OF HANNU HAUTALA AND LASSE HOIKKA &amp; SOUVARIT  </em></p>
<p>Northern Lapland Nature Centre Siida arranges the nature photo consert in Sámi Cultural Centre Sajos in Inari.    Nature photo –concert is a new kind of a nature evening. Hannu Hautala - The Grand-old-Man of the Finnish nature photographing and Lasse Hoikka with his Souvarit-band will play their nature photos and music at the same time on the stage. There are also nature photos of photographer Tomi Valo in the nature photo concert.    Tickets to the concert in advance 25€ and at the door on hour before the concert starts 30€. Organiser:</p>
<p>Northern Lapland Nature Centre Siida. Read more</p>
<p xml:lang="sme"><em type="bold">Sat 4.4.2015 19.00   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p><em type="bold"><span type="quote" xml:lang="fkv">"TÄSSÄ ELÄMÄSSÄ"</span> - IN THIS LIFE- CONCERT </em></p>
<p>The concert will feature music from Topi Sorsakoski production performed by local orchestra Peippo ja Ajomiehet. Tickets 15 €.</p>
<p xml:lang="rmf"><em type="bold">Thu 2.4.2015 20.00   </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="nno"><em type="bold">STAND-UP SHOW: KELEKKA 2015 </em></p>
<p>Stand-up show:  Kelekka  2015 -tour  drives by  snowmobiles  around  Lapland from  gig to another  and comes  to Sajos  on Thursday  02/04/2015  .  Included  are four  comedians:</p>
<p>Riku Suokas, Mika Eirtovaara, Tommi Mujunen ja Jussi Simola. Tickets: 18/15 € . The recommended age-limit 15 years.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="smn"><em type="bold">Sun 29.3.2015  </em></p>
<p xml:lang="smn"><em type="bold">REINDEER RACE AT INARI </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">28.9.-29.3.2015 </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>Award ceremony held at Sajos at 29th of March.</p>
<p>Organizer  :  Reindeer Herders' Association</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"><em type="bold"> </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Wed 25.3.2015 at 19.00  </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p><em type="bold">CHAMBER ORCHESTRA OF LAPLAND ENTERTAINMENT CONCERT: SATUJEN MAA </em></p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">- TISLATTUA TANGOA </em></p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Lauri Sallinen, clarinet</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Henrik Sandås, bandoneon</p>
<p>Well-known  Finnish  tangos  and  ballads  as a new kind  of version  à la  Lauri  Sallinen</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="smn"><em type="bold">Sun </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">15.3.2015 at 18.00  </em></p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="italic">BEAIVVÁŠ SÁMI NAŠUNÁLATEÁHTER: NJUORJU NIILA </em>    </p>
<p>Beaivváš Sámi National Theatre. Children's play, duration approx. 45 min. The play is in Sámi language (no subtitles). Ticket 12 €.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="fin"><em type="italic">ke </em><em type="italic">11.3.2015 klo 19.00 </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="italic">LAULUJA UNESTA - NIEGUID LÁVLAGAT -CONCERT - SONGS FROM A DREAM </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Amanda Martikainen, mezzosopraano / mezzosopráno, Väinö Jalkanen, piano. Music from composers: Berg, Rautavaara, Sallinen, Schubert ja Sibelius &amp; Karjalaisia kansanlauluja. Tickets 15/12/7 €.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">Tue </em><em type="italic">24.2.2015 at 10.00 </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="italic">SÁMI PARLIAMENTS PLENUM 1/2015  </em> </p>
<p>The Plenum represents the supreme authority of the Sámi Parliament. It meets 4-5 times per year. The Plenum decides mainly on the statements, proposals, and other comments. The meeting shows also as live strem</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">broadcast: <em type="italic">http://sogku.fi/live.  </em></p>
<p>The meeting can be also followed at the meetingroom.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno"><em type="italic">Sun </em> <em type="italic">22.2.2015 at 18.00 </em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">TEATRE AURORE B'S MOTION OF ANDREI MAKINEN'S BOOK VERA </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Tickets 12/10 €</p>
<p><em type="bold">Thu 12.2.2015 at 19.00  </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p><em type="italic">MILITARY BAND OF LAPLAND: OATHCONCERT </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>The concert is part of the oath events that showcase the band's own vocal skills. Eric  Ewazen  Marimba  Concerto  interprets  Tomi  Kauppila  . Conductors: Juha Ketola and Jaakko Nurila. Vocalist: Tomi Kauppila, marimba. Tickets: starting from 15 €.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno"><em type="bold">Fri </em> </p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">06.02.2015  </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="nob"><em type="bold">SÁMI NATIONAL DAY CELEBRATION </em></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>Sámi National Day will be celebrated at Sajos on February sixth.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="smn"><em type="bold">Thu 22.- Mon 26.1.2015  </em></p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="italic">INDIGENOUS PEOPLES' FILM FESTIVAL SKÁBMAGOVAT </em>  </p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p xml:lang="swe"></p>
<p>Skábmagovat – Indigenous Peoples’ Film Festival is held yearly in Janury. Skábmagovat will present Sámi films and TV programs.  Films will be shown in our Northern Lights Theater, which is rich in atmosphere: it is totally made of snow, with the sky as the roof. Films will also be presented in the auditoriums of Siida and the cultural center Sajos.  Festival homepage.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno"><em type="bold">Fri </em></p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">23.1.2015  </em></p>
<p xml:lang="deu"><em type="italic">SKÁBMA SEMINAR </em>  </p>
<p>Skábma Seminar on Friday 23 Jan. 2015, 10:30–13:00 is held at the Parliament hall Solju at Sajos. The purpose of the seminar is to exchange experiences and information between indigenous film makers. The seminar is chaired by Liisa Holmberg (Sámi Education Institute).</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Festival homepage.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">Fri 9.1.2015 at 17.00-19.30 </em> </p>
<p><em type="italic">OPENING CEREMONY OF SKOLT SÁMI STUDIES </em> </p>
<p>Skolt Sámi basic studies start at the Giellagas institute of University of Oulu at January 2015. Opening ceremony of the studies is held in Inari at Sajos 9.1.2015 at 17.00-19.30. The event is open to all.</p>
<p>Program in Finnish</p>
</body></document>