<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Invoicing Address - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2022</year><wordcount>313</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/invoicing-address/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="laskutusosoite.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="rehketbearran.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="rekigistem.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="laasktos.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">Invoicing</p>
<p type="title">Purchase invoices</p>
<p type="title">Invoicing address for e-invoices</p>
<p>Name: Samediggi/Saamelaiskäräjät Business ID: 1052535-3 VAT number: FI10525353 Invoicing address/party identification number: 003710525353 Operator code: 003708599126 E-invoicing operator: Liaison Technologies</p>
<p>Please use the above-mentioned e-invoicing address and operator code for routing your invoices.</p>
<p type="title">Purchase invoices via e-mail</p>
<p>The invoice can also be sent in PDF format by e-mail to: fennoa.FI.P.124808-7(at)docinbound.com</p>
<list><p type="listitem">The invoice is sent as an attached file.</p>
<p type="listitem">You can send multiple invoices in a single e-mail, if each invoice is attached as separate file. All files must have a different name.</p>
<p type="listitem">The invoice attachments must be attached to the same pdf file as the invoice itself.</p>
<p type="listitem">PDF files must not be locked or password protected.</p>
<p type="listitem">Allowed characters in the attachment name are common characters, a-z, A-Z, 0-9. Do not use special characters to name the attachments.</p>
</list><p type="title">Paper invoice via post</p>
<p>If you are unable to send invoice via e-mail, you can send it as a paper invoice to: Sámediggi/Saamelaiskäräjät, PL 57273, 01051 LASKUT</p>
<p>Reward invoices from companies (with business ID) can be sent electronically as an e-invoice.</p>
<p type="title">More information about e-invoicing</p>
<p>Irmeli Moilanen Sámediggi/Saamelaiskäräjät irmeli.moilanen(at)samediggi.fi +358 10 839 3130</p>
<p type="title">Reward and travel invoices</p>
<p>Without business ID, reward and travel invoices are made to the Sámi Parliament via M2 travel invoice program. You can get more detailed instructions from your contact person from the Sámi Parliament.</p>
<p>The personal data form can be filled out electronically at:</p>
<p>https://www.samediggi.fi/personaldataform/?lang=en</p>
<p>You can send a secure email to the Sámi Parliament’s financial office talous(at)samediggi.fi via the following address: https://secmail.com/send/vMJaNprX</p>
<p>Via a secure email, you can send, for example, a personal information form or a tax card in pdf-format securely.</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Personal data form</p>
</list><p type="title">Processing of personal data</p>
<p>Maintenance of personal and employment information is part of the process of calculating salaries in the Economy office. The data subjects have the right to obtain information on the processing of their personal data.</p>
</body></document>
