<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>OSCE High Commissioner on National Minorities to visit Inari - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2023</year><wordcount>208</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/2023/02/14/osce-high-commissioner-on-national-minorities-to-visit-inari/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="etyjin_vahemmistovaltuutettu_vierailee_inarissa_.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="etyj:a_vehadataittardeaddji_galleda_anaris.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="etyj_ucceeblohovaldalas_kuallee_anarist.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="etyj_minorite_ttvaldduumnek_kuo_ssai_aanrest.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">OSCE High Commissioner on National Minorities to visit Inari</p>
<p><em type="italic">The Organisation for Security and Co-operation in Europe (OSCE) High Commissioner on National Minorities Kairat Abdrakhmanov visits Inari on 15–16 February 2023. Over the course of the visit, the High Commissioner will meet representatives of the Sámi Parliament, the Truth and Reconciliation Commission, the Skolt Sámi Siida Council, Sámi organisations and Sámi homeland municipalities. </em></p>
<p>– It is great to see the OSCE show interest towards Sámi matters, in particular because the object of the visit is to discuss the Act on the Sámi Parliament and the general situation caused by it. The OSCE plays an important role in securing the rights of national minorities, says Tuomas Aslak Juuso, President of the Sámi Parliament.</p>
<p>During the visit, the High Commissioner for National Minorities will also examine economic matters and visit the Yle Sápmi editorial office and an Inari Sámi language nest.</p>
<p>The OSCE High Commissioner for National Minorities strives to prevent and mitigate tensions pertaining to national minorities within the OSCE territory. The work emphasises quiet diplomacy and supporting cooperation between various parties.</p>
<p type="title">Further information:</p>
<p>Tuomas Aslak Juuso President +358 40 687 3394 tuomas.juuso@samediggi.fi</p>
<p>Inka-Saara Arttijeff Secretary for International Affairs +358 10 839 3198 / +358 50 574 7629 inka-saara.arttijeff@samediggi.fi</p>
</body></document>
