<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>President Juuso: "The State of Norway must respect the rights of indigenous people" - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2023</year><wordcount>298</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/2023/03/02/president-juuso-the-state-of-norway-must-respect-the-rights-of-indigenous-people/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="puheenjohtaja_juuso:_norjan_valtion_kunnioitettava_alkuperaiskansaoikeuksia_.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="sagajodiheaddji_juuso:_norgga_stahta_galga_gudnejahttit_eamialbmotvuoigatvuodaid_.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="saavajodetteijee_juuso:_taaza_staata_kalga_kunnijattid_algaaalmugvuoigadvuodaid_.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="saaggjaa_dtee_jj_juuso:_taarr_riikk_algg_ci_sttjed_alggmeervuoiggadvuodid_.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">President Juuso: <span type="quote">“The State of Norway must respect the rights of indigenous people”</span></p>
<p><em type="italic">Young Sámi people have protested against wind farms at Fosen at the Ministry of Petroleum and Energy of Norway in Oslo. The protest started on Thursday 23 February, 500 days after the Supreme Court of Norway stated in its judgment that the wind farms at Fosen had been built without a valid operating licence, violating the rights of the Sámi to enjoy their own culture. The protesters demanded the enforcement of the judgment of the Supreme Court and the demolition of 150 illegal wind power plants in their area. Juuso concurs with the demands of the Sámi in Norway on the enforcement of the judgment. </em></p>
<p>President of the Sámi Parliament Tuomas Aslak Juuso understands the frustration of the Sámi in the wind farm issue well. <span type="quote">“I support the Sámi in Norway with their demands. The rights of the Sámi as an indigenous people must be respected and implemented in reality. In the Fosen case, the Government of Norway must enforce the decision of the Supreme Court without delay,”</span> says Juuso.</p>
<p>The protest started when 500 days had passed from the judgment with no measures whatsoever having been taken. In fact, President Juuso wonders why the State of Norway has not implemented the decisions of its own judicial system. <span type="quote">“I find it inconceivable, and it does not show that the State of Norway would respect the rights of indigenous people,”</span> Juuso says.</p>
<p>In its judgment, the Supreme Court of Norway found that the State of Norway violated Article 27 of the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights (ICCPR) of the UN that protects the culture of indigenous people. ICCPR is also legally valid in Finland.</p>
<p type="title">Further information:</p>
<p>Tuomas Aslak Juuso President 040 687 3394 tuomas.juuso(at)samediggi.fi</p>
</body></document>
