<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Procedure for seeking consent for research projects - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2023</year><wordcount>261</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/procedure-for-seeking-consent-for-research-projects/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="tutkimuseettinen_menettelyohje.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="tu_tkkeemeettlaz_moontoollamvua_pstos.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">Procedure for seeking consent for research projects dealing with Sámi cultural heritage and traditional knowledge</p>
<p><em type="italic">Procedure for seeking the free, prior, and informed consent of the Sámi from the Sámi Parliament in Finland for research projects dealing with Sámi cultural heritage and traditional knowledge and other activities that have or may have an impact on this heritage and knowledge. </em></p>
<p>The procedure is based on the principle of FPIC (free, prior, and informed consent) and the Akwé: Kon Guidelines (see Secretariat of the Convention on Biological Diversity 2004, CBD Guidelines, https://www.cbd.int/doc/publications/akwe-brochure-en.pdf ).</p>
<p>The objective of the procedure is to guarantee that the indigenous rights of the Sámi are realized in research dealing with Sámi cultural heritage and traditional knowledge and other measures that have or may have an impact on this heritage and knowledge; the procedure is also aimed at promoting the preservation of the cultural heritage and the traditional knowledge of the Sámi and safeguarding the self-determination of the Sámi over this heritage and knowledge.</p>
<p>The procedure will be applied to research projects dealing with Sámi cultural heritage and traditional knowledge and measures that have or may have an impact on the cultural heritage and the traditional knowledge of the Sámi.</p>
<p><em type="italic">» Procedure for seeking consent for research projects dealing with Sámi cultural heritage and traditional knowledge </em></p>
<p type="title">More information</p>
<p>Inquiries can be addressed to the Environmental Secretary of the Sámi Parliament, tel. +358 50 5999 725 or e-mail: info(at)samediggi.fi</p>
<p>Applications for prior consent should be sent to the Sámi Parliament by post to Sajos, FI-99870 INARI or by e-mail to info(at)samediggi.fi.</p>
</body></document>
