<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Sámi youth come together to fight climate change in a conference on 26 August - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2021</year><wordcount>379</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/2021/08/23/sami-youth-come-together-to-fight-climate-change-in-a-conference-on-26-august/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="saamelaisnuoret_kokoavat_voimansa_ilmastonmuutosta_vastaan_konferenssissa_26_8_.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="samenuorat_cohkkejit_famuideaset_dalkkadatrievdama_vuosta_konferanssas_26_8_.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="saminuorah_cuakkejeh_vuoimijdis_songngadahnubastus_vuasta_konferensist_26_8_.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="saa_mnuor_na_rre_vioggees_aimmosmuuttas_vuastta_konferee_nsest_26_8_.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">Sámi youth come together to fight climate change in a conference on 26 August</p>
<p><em type="italic">The Nordic Sámi Youth Conference will be organised on 26 August 2021. The theme of the conference is climate change and the conference will be organised virtually. The conference is free of charge and open to all Sámi youth. </em></p>
<p><span type="quote">“It is great that Sámi youth can once again discuss current and important matters across international borders. I believe that we will come to important realisations about climate change and how to battle it, but also realisations about how we can adapt,”</span> rejoices the chair of the Youth Council, Anni-Sofia Niittyvuopio.</p>
<p>At the conference we will hear interesting speeches from the Minister of the Environment and Climate Change, Krista Mikkonen, the Chair of the Sámi Parliamentary Council, Aili Keskitalo, young reindeer herder Jussa Seurujärvi and the Chair of the Sámi Parliament in Finland, Tuomas Aslak Juuso. The conference also includes workshops. The workshops will be held by the youth-led global organisation Youth4Nature, social media influencer Emmi Nuorgam and activist, director and screenwriter Pauliina Feodoroff.</p>
<p><span type="quote">“We hope that the young people participate boldly in the workshops. In the workshops, we will try to find everyone a suitable way of making an impact. Climate change can feel overwhelming, but we want to encourage people to find common strength and a message in the societal work against climate change,”</span> explains the project worker of the conference, Milla Pulska.</p>
<p>Arctic indigenous peoples experience climate change most drastically and Sámi youth are worried about the impacts of climate change on the traditional livelihoods and culture of the Sámi people. At the conference, we will compile a declaration against climate change and plan shared operation models for Sámi youth across borders.</p>
<p>The Youth Council, which is under the Sámi Parliamentary Council, organises the Nordic Sámi Youth Conference every two years. The conference is organised in cooperation with youth from the Sámi Parliaments of Norway, Sweden and Finland. The main organiser of the conference is the Sámi Parliament’s Youth Council. The goal of the conference is to encourage Sámi youth to develop Sámi society.</p>
<p>More information about the conference: www.nuor.fi</p>
<p type="title">More information:</p>
<p>Anni-Sofia Niittyvuopio Chair of the Sámi Parliament Youth Council 040 7082 072 anni-sofia.niittyvuopio(at)samediggi.fi</p>
<p>Milla Pulska project worker 040 669 5295 milla.pulska(at)samediggi.fi</p>
</body></document>
