<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Sámi Language Council - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>607</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/expert-committees/sami-language-council/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="saamen_kielineuvosto.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="sami_giellaraddi.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="saami_kielaraadi.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="saa_m_kiollsuavtos.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">The Sámi Language</p>
<p>The Sámi Language Council is in charge of Sámi language issues in the Sámi Parliament. The Sámi Parliament chooses its representative from amongst the Sámi Language Council for the Sámi Language Committee, which functions under the Sámi Parliamentary Council. In addition, the Sámi Language Office of the Sámi Parliament is, among other things, in charge of distributing translations related to the Sámi Language Act to the authorities, and working on improving the position of the Sámi language; it also participates in certain terminology projects.</p>
<p>SáFá – Preparatory Project Gollegiella – Pohjoismainen saamen kielen kielipalkinto (no translation available) Kieli- ja käännöspalvelut (no translation available) Saamenkieliset palvelut verkossa (no translation available)</p>
<p type="title">Sámi Language Council</p>
<p>The Sámi Language Council represents all three Sámi languages that are spoken in Finland:Northern Sámi, Inari Sámi and Skolt Sámi.</p>
<p>The activities of the Language Council include, among other things, maintaining and developing the Sámi languages used in Finland; giving instructions and recommendations on the issues concerning the correct use of language, names, and terminology; advancing language research; providing information on Sámi languages, and participating in the Nordic co-operation of linguistic issues. In addition, the Sámi Language Council, together with the Language Office, gives a report to the Sámi Parliament every electoral period. The report concerns the appliance of Sámi language legislation and the realisation of language rights, as well as the development of linguistic conditions.</p>
<p><em type="italic">The members of the Sámi Language Council for the years 2020-2023 are: </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Members: </em>Ljetoff Tauno, chair Seurujärvi-Kari Irja, vice chair Aikio Matti Jääskö Neeta Valkeapää Niko Sara Magreta Eriksen Kati </p>
<p><em type="italic">Deputies: </em>Harju Terhi <em type="bold"></em>Magga Arla <em type="bold"></em>Magga-Vars Petra Seurujärvi Jussa Pautamo Ellen Magga Juhan-Tuommá Lukkari Sammol </p>
<p>Together with the Sámi Language Office, which functions in the Sámi Parliament Secretariat, the Language Council has an important political role as a supervisor of the rights of the Sámi-speaking population and as a promoter of Sámi languages.</p>
<p>An important part of the Language Council work is co-operation with the Sámi Language Committee and other institutes working with the Sámi and other minority languages and in the field of language research, such as Kotus (Research Institute for the Languages of Finland). The Language Council also has representatives on the executive board of the Finnish department (FIBLUL) in the European Bureau for Lesser-Used Languages (EBLUL).</p>
<p type="title">Sámi Language Office</p>
<p>Personnel of the Sámi Language Office</p>
<p><em type="italic">Language Protection Secretary </em></p>
<p>Siiri Jomppanen</p>
<p>– Office Manager</p>
<p>– Supervision and monitoring of the implementation of the Sámi Language Act.</p>
<p>– Communication about the Language Act and the linguistic rights of the Sámi people.</p>
<p>– Counselling and advice for the Sámi and the authorities about the use and application of the Sámi Language Act.</p>
<p>– Responsible for monitoring the processing of matters concerning the Sámi by various authorities.</p>
<p>– Presenting official and secretary of the Sámi Language Council, and executor of decisions in matters related to this role.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Secretary for Sámi Language Affairs </em> </p>
<p>Heli Aikio</p>
<p><em type="italic">Translators </em></p>
<p>I Translator – Irma Laiti , location: Inari</p>
<p>II Translator – Anja Vest , location: Inari</p>
<p>Translator – Anneli Länsman</p>
<p>Translator – Kirsti Guttorm , location: Utsjoki</p>
<p>Translator – Seija Aikio-Järviluoma</p>
<p>Inari Sámi Linguist/Translator – Tanja Kyrö</p>
<p>Skolt Sámi Linguist/Translator – Merja Fofonoff</p>
<p>If required, translators assist in translating the Sámi documents that are needed when dealing with the authorities.</p>
<p><em type="italic">THE PERSONNEL IN THE SÁMI LANGUAGE OFFICE ARE HAPPY TO ADVISE AND HELP WITH ISSUES CONCERNING THE SÁMI LANGUAGE AND THE SÁMI LANGUAGE LAW. </em></p>
<p>If you need a Sámi translator or interpreter, you can find their contact information using the relevant link below:</p>
<p>North Sámi translators and interpreters Inari Sámi translators and interpreters Skolt Sámi translators and interpreters Sámi-English-Swedish-Finnish translators and interpreters</p>
</body></document>
