<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Social Affairs and Health - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>258</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/expert-committees/social-affairs-and-health/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="sosiaali_ja_terveys.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="sosiala-_ja_dearvvasvuohta.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="sosiaal-_ja_tiervasvuodalavdikodde.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="sosiaal_da_tiorvasvuott.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">Social Affairs and Health Committee</p>
<p>The Social Affairs and Health Committee prepares social- and health-related political presentations, bills, statements and comments for the Sámi Parliament. The purpose of the committee is to advance the rights and position of the Sámi in the social affairs and health care system of Finland.</p>
<p>The committee decides on the usage of the government subsidy, which is stated in the national budget (main category 33, Ministry of Social Affairs and Health) for guaranteeing social and health services in the Sámi language. The committee prepares a long-term plan for the Plenum concerning the provision of social and health services in Sámi. It provides an annual clarification for the Plenum and the Lapland County Administrative Board on the use of the government subsidy which is appointed to secure social and health services in Sámi.The committee manages, and is in charge of, the necessary tasks that are required for acknowledging the service needs of the Sámi. These tasks are the responsibility of the Social Affairs Learning Centre of Northern Finland (Pohjois-Suomen sosiaalialan osaamiskeskus).</p>
<p>The matters covered by the committee are prepared and implemented by the Social Affairs and Health Secretary and by the planner of the Sámi Unit in the Social Affairs Learning Centre of Northern Finland.</p>
<p>The members and deputies of the Social Affairs and Health Committee for the years 2020-2023 are:</p>
<p><em type="italic">Members: </em>Hetta Karen-Anni, chair Magga Ulla-Maarit, vice-chair Hirvasvuopio Janne Rahko Niila Eriksen Heidi Pekkala Aslak Mäkinen Anne </p>
<p><em type="italic">Deputies: </em>Äärelä Inga Länsman Aslak Uula Niittyvuopio-Lämsä Leena Itäkivi Minka Veijola Ánte Tervonen Joanna Feodoroff Veikko </p>
</body></document>
