<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The Sámi Parliament Participates in the International Week for Biological Diversity - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>468</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/2020/05/18/the-sami-parliament-participates-in-the-international-week-for-biological-diversity/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="saamelaiskarajat_osallistuu_luonnon_monimuotoisuuden_viikkoon.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="samediggi_oassalasta_luonddu_mangggahamatvuoda_vahkkui.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="samitigge_uasalist_luandu_maanggahamasasvuoda_ookon.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="saa_mte_gg_vuassaatt_luad_maangghammsazvuod_nea_ttla.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">The Sámi Parliament Participates in the International Week for Biological Diversity</p>
<p>The Sámi Parliament in Finland participates in the International Biodiversity Theme Week 18-22 May by publishing a video every day of the week related to biodiversity and Sámi culture. Themes of the week have been applied to Sámi culture, and the aim is to raise issues that are important to Sámi culture in relation to biodiversity and traditional knowledge.</p>
<p>The United Nations proclaimed May 22 as the International Day for Biological Diversity (IBD). The purpose of the day is to increase understanding and awareness of biodiversity and its significance.</p>
<p>This year, Biodiversity Day will extend to a full week. Each day of the week has its own biodiversity theme, linked to the main themes of international biodiversity work. During the week, comprehensive nature communication will take place all around the world.</p>
<p type="title">The themes of the Sámi Parliament for each day of the week are:</p>
<p><em type="italic">Mon 18th: </em>Traditional knowledge and its meaning for biodiversity. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Tue 19th: </em>Biodiversity, protected areas and traditional livelihoods. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Wed 20th: </em>Biodiversity, traditional food, fishing, and food security. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Thu 21st: </em>Biodiversity and culture: handcrafts. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Fri 22th: </em>Actions to prevent biodiversity loss from a Sámi perspective. </p>
<p>You can use tags in social media #BiodiversityDay #Biodiversity #BiologicalDiversity</p>
<p type="title">Background</p>
<p>The United Nations Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD) was opened for signature at the United Nations Conference on Environments and Development (UNCED) in Rio de Janeiro in 1992. Finland ratified the Convention on Biological Diversity in 1994. The objectives of the convention are the conservation of the biological diversity, the sustainable use of its components, and the fair and equitable sharing of the benefits arising out of the utilisation of genetic resources.</p>
<p>Article 8(j) of the Convention on Biological Diversity obliges Parties to protect indigenous peoples’ traditional knowledge relevant to biological diversity. The article requires Parties to respect, protect and maintain, in accordance with their national legislation, the knowledge, innovations and practices of indigenous people and local communities relevant for the conservation of biological diversity, and to promote their wider application with the approval of knowledge holders and to encourage equitable sharing of benefits arising out of the use of biological diversity. In Finland, the obligations outlined in the article apply to the Sámi people.</p>
<p>The year 2020 is so-called super year of the biodiversity. During the year, a new global biodiversity framework (post-2020 global biodiversity framework) will be negotiated and a UN Summit on biodiversity will be organised. In addition, a meeting of the parties of the UN Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD COP15) was to be held in China, but the conference has been postponed to the next year due to the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
<p type="title">More information</p>
<p>President Tuomas Aslak Juuso, +358 40 687 3394, tuomas.juuso(at)samediggi.fi</p>
<p>Secretary for International Affairs Inka Saara Arttijeff, +358 50 574 7629, inka-saara.arttijeff(at)samediggi.fi</p>
</body></document>
