<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The conference of Sámi Parliamentarians will be held in Inari in May - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2022</year><wordcount>229</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/2022/05/10/the-conference-of-sami-parliamentarians-will-be-held-in-inari-in-may/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="saamelaisparlamentaarikkojen_konferenssi_jarjestetaan_toukokuussa_inarissa.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="sameparlamentarihkkariid_konfereansa_lagiduvvo_miessemanus_anaris.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="samiparlamianttarij_konferens_uarnejuvvoo_vyesimaanust_anarist.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="saa_mparlamentnii_kki_konfere_nss_ja_rjstet_vue_ssmannust_aanrest.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">The conference of Sámi Parliamentarians will be held in Inari in May</p>
<p>The 6th conference of Sámi Parliamentarians is held in Inari on the 19 th of May 2022. The conference was originally meant to take place in 2020, but it was postponed due to the Covid-19 pandemic. The conference takes place over one day. The conference will have participants from the Sámi Parliaments in Sweden, Norway, and Finland. There will also be participants from a Russian Sámi organisation, who will take part as observers.</p>
<p>– It is great that the Sámi Parliamentarians can get together in Inari and discuss matters that affect us all, such as the challenges with climate change, traditional knowledge, and the latest developments of Sámi rights, says Tuomas Aslak Juuso, the President of the Sámi Parliament in Finland.</p>
<p>The themes of this year’s conference are, among other things, climate change, traditional knowledge, and the latest developments of Sámi rights. The conference will have lectures from experts in these fields, who share the latest knowledge to the Parliamentarians.</p>
<p>The conference of Sámi Parliamentarians is held every three years. The Sámi Parliamentary Council is responsible of organising the conference, and this year the responsibility is on the Sámi Parliament in Finland.</p>
<p type="title">More information:</p>
<p>Tuomas Aslak Juuso President of the Sámi Parliament in Finland 040 687 3394 tuomas.juuso@samediggi.fi</p>
<p>Saara-Maria Salonen Conference Planner +44(0) 7305 965 167 saara-maria.salonen@samediggi.fi</p>
</body></document>
