<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>The Sámi Parliament met the OSCE High Commissioner on National Minorities in Inari  - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2023</year><wordcount>313</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/2023/02/20/the-sami-parliament-met-the-osce-high-commissioner-on-national-minorities-in-inari/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="saamelaiskarajat_tapasi_etyjin_vahemmistovaltuutetun_inarissa.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="samediggi_deaivvadii_etyj_vehadataittardeaddjiin_anaris_.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="samitigge_teeivai_etyj_ucceeblohovaldalii_anarist_.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="saa_mte_gg_vuei_nnloodi_etyj_minorite_ttvaldduumnii_kkin_aanrest.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">The Sámi Parliament met the OSCE High Commissioner on National Minorities in Inari</p>
<p><em type="italic">Kairat Abdrakhmanov, OSCE High Commissioner on National Minorities, visited Inari from 15 to 16 February 2023. During the visit, the High Commissioner met President of the Sámi Parliament Tuomas Aslak Juuso, as well as 2nd Vice President Leo Aikio. Out of the bodies of the Sámi Parliament, the Advisory Board on Inari Sámi Affairs as well as the Youth Council met the High Commissioner. </em></p>
<p><span type="quote">“I wish to thank the High Commissioner on National Minorities for an important visit. We discussed matters topical to the Sámi, such as the overall situation caused by the reform of the Act on the Sámi Parliament and the resulting tensions. In addition, the High Commissioner was interested in issues such as the impact of climate change on the traditional livelihoods and Sámi culture as well as the opportunities of the Sámi Parliament to influence decision-making,”</span> says Tuomas Aslak Juuso, the President of the Sámi Parliament.</p>
<p>During the visit to Inari, the High Commissioner also met representatives of the Sámi homeland municipalities, the Truth and Reconciliation Commission and Sámi organisations. The High Commissioner also heard about the current situation of the traditional livelihoods of the Sámi.</p>
<p>In addition to the meetings, the High Commissioner visited Yle Sápmi, the Sámi language department of the Finnish Broadcasting Company, and an Inari Sámi language nest. The High Commissioner also visited Vice President Leo Aikio and learned more about reindeer husbandry.</p>
<p>The OSCE High Commissioner on National Minorities strives to prevent and mitigate tensions pertaining to national minorities within the OSCE territory. The work emphasises quiet diplomacy and supporting cooperation between various parties.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Further information: </em></p>
<p>Tuomas Aslak Juuso President +358 40 687 3394 tuomas.juuso@samediggi.fi</p>
<p>Leo Aikio 2nd Vice President +358 40 621 6505 leo.aikio@samediggi.fi</p>
<p>Inka-Saara Arttijeff Secretary for International Affairs +358 10 839 3198 / +358 50 574 7629 inka-saara.arttijeff@samediggi.fi</p>
</body></document>
