<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Welcome to participate in a Nordic online seminar: Indigenous peoples: Language, culture and life cycle - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2021</year><wordcount>247</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/2021/08/26/tave-eennamlas-webinaar-31-8-1-9-algaaalmugij-vadulij-ja-mustopyeccee-ulmui-vuoigadvuodah-ja-kulttuursensitiivliih-palvalusah/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="pohjoismainen_webinaari_31_8_-1_9:_alkuperaiskansoihin_kuuluvien_vammaisten_ja_muistisairaiden_henkiloiden_oikeudet_ja_kulttuurisensitiiviset_palvelut.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="davviriikkalas_webinari_31_8_-1_9:_eamialbmogiidda_gullevas_lamisolbmuid_ja_muitobuohcciid_vuoigatvuodat_ja_kultursensitiivvalas_balvalusat.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="tave-eennamlas_webinaar_31_8_-1_9:_algaaalmugij_vadulij_ja_mustopyeccee_ulmui_vuoigadvuodah_ja_kulttuursensitiivliih_palvalusah.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">Welcome to participate in a Nordic online seminar: Indigenous peoples: Language, culture and life cycle</p>
<p>Date and time: 31 August and 1 September 2021 at 12.30 – 16.00 EEST both days Venue: Online seminar</p>
<p>How do we respect and implement rights of indigenous peoples with disabilities in the Nordic region? What are the challenges to meet the needs of indigenous peoples with dementia in sparsely populated areas?</p>
<p>This two day online event will focus on the rights of indigenous persons with disabilities, while taking special account of people with dementia. The first day of this webinar will raise the issue of how the human rights intersect, highlighting key human rights obligations and recommendations from the perspective of both indigenous peoples and persons with disabilities. The second day of this webinar will focus on a vision and provision of future language- and culture-sensitive services particularly in sparsely populated areas, with a life cycle perspective.</p>
<p>The seminar is organised in cooperation between Nordic Welfare Centre, Nordic dementia network, Council of Nordic Cooperation on Disability, Ministry of Social Affairs and Health in Finland, Finnish Institute for Health and Welfare (THL), the Sámi Parliament in Finland, SámiSoster, Finnish Advisory Board for the Rights of Persons with Disabilities VANE and Finnish Human Rights Centre.</p>
<p>The event is open to anyone interested but registration is required (by 31 August at 12.30).</p>
<p>The program, more information and link to registration:</p>
<p>Indigenous peoples: language, culture, and life cycle (link to Nordic Welfare Centre’s website) https://nordicwelfare.org/en/evenemang/indigenous-peoples-language-culture-and-life-cycle/</p>
</body></document>
