<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Welcome to the Nordic Sámi Youth Conference - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2021</year><wordcount>280</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/2021/08/17/welcome-to-the-nordic-sami-youth-conference/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="tervetuloa_pohjoismaiseen_saamelaisnuorten_konferenssiin_.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="bures_boahtin_davviriikkalas_samenuoraid_konferansii_.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="tiervapuattim_ohtsastave-eennamlii_saminuorai_konferensan_.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="tiorvvpue_ttem_ta_vvjannmallso_zze_saa_mnuori_konferenssa_.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">Welcome to the Nordic Sámi Youth Conference</p>
<p><em type="italic">When: 26.8.2021 Finnish time from 9:00 to 15:00 </em><em type="italic"></em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Place: Zoom </em><em type="italic"></em></p>
<p>The conference is free of charge and open to all Sámi youth. We will divide the attendants into workshops and we strive to base this on their wishes. The conference will have simultaneous interpretation. All attendants will be sent a t-shirt designed by artist Arsi Keva.</p>
<p>The theme of the conference is climate change. The indigenous peoples of the Arctic are most affected by climate change. Sámi youth are especially worried about the impact of climate change on the traditional livelihoods and culture of the Sámi people. As a part of the conference, the Sámi youth will outline a common declaration against climate change and plan operation models for this.</p>
<p>The Youth Council, which is under the Sámi Parliamentary Council, organises the Nordic Sámi Youth Conference every two years. The conference is organised in cooperation with youth from the Sámi Parliaments of Norway, Sweden and Finland. The main organiser of the conference is the Sámi Parliament’s Youth Council.</p>
<p>Registration before 25.8. Finnish time 12.00: https://link.webropolsurveys.com/S/762D510FDD3DA894</p>
<p>Invitation</p>
<p type="title">Programme</p>
<p>9:00 Start</p>
<p>9:15 Speech: Chair of the Sámi Parliamentary Council, Aili Keskitalo</p>
<p>9:30 Speech: Young reindeer herder Jussa Seurujärvi</p>
<p>9:45 Speech: Minister of the Environment and Climate Change, Krista Mikkonen</p>
<p>10:00 Workshops</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Youth4Nature: Mobilising Youth to Lead for Nature and Climate, Storytelling Language: English</p>
<p type="listitem">Emmi Nuorgam: Social Media and Influencing Language: Finnish</p>
<p type="listitem">Pauliina Feodoroff: Climate Activism Sápmi Language: English</p>
</list><p>12:00 Lunch break</p>
<p>12:45 Speech: Chair of the Sámi Parliament in Finland, Tuomas Aslak Juuso</p>
<p>13:00 Declaration workshops in groups</p>
<p>14:14 Wrapping up</p>
<p>15:00 End</p>
<p type="title">Additional information:</p>
<p>project worker Milla Pulska tel. +358 40 6695295 e-mail: milla.pulska(at)samediggi.fi</p>
</body></document>
