<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Youth Council - Samediggi</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>178</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>https://www.samediggi.fi/expert-committees/nuoriso/?lang=en</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="nuorisoneuvosto.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="nuoraidraddi.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="smn" location="nuorairaadi.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sms" location="nuorisuavtos.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p type="title">Youth Council</p>
<p>The members of the Youth Council are chosen for two year term at the time. The council consists of the Chair, the Vice Chair and five other members. They all have personal deputies. Both members and the deputies have to be between age of 18 and 28 when chosen. Also five expert members are chosen for two year term. Expert members have to be between age of 15 and 17 when chosen. The Chair and the Vice Chair don’t have to be members of the Sámi Parliament.</p>
<p>The Youth Council prepares those statements, initiatives and other comments which concern Sámi youth and their living conditions. Other main functions of the Committee are to advance the language and the cultural rights of the the Sámi youth and strengthen their Sámi identity.</p>
<p type="title">Youth Council 2020-2021</p>
<p><em type="italic">Members: </em></p>
<p>Niittyvuopio Anni-Sofia, chair Mäkinen Maria, vice chair Valle Juuso Tornensis Reetta Kosonen Anette Kemi Ole-Juhan Jomppanen Harri</p>
<p><em type="italic">Deputies: </em></p>
<p>Pohjanrinne Mira Semenoff Jasmin Laiti Riku Ketola Marianne Aikio Anni-Saara Mäkinen Lassi-Olavi Seurujärvi Jussa</p>
<p><em type="italic">Expert members: </em></p>
<p>Ljetoff Helmi Ravna-Pieski Hans Siilasjoki Sunna Tenoranta Ante</p>
</body></document>
