<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Activities in Tsarmitunturi Wilderness Area - Nationalparks.fi</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>648</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>http://www.nationalparks.fi/en/tsarmitunturi/activities?inheritRedirect=true</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="aktiviteetit_inheritredirect=true_12.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="astoaiggevejolasvuodat_9.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>Skip to Content</p>
<p>Open Menu</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Suomeksi</p>
<p type="listitem">På svenska</p>
<p type="listitem">Anarâškielâ</p>
<p type="listitem">Davvisámegiella</p>
<p type="listitem">中文</p>
<p type="listitem">По-русски</p>
</list><p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p type="title">Tsarmitunturi</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Activities</p>
<p type="listitem">Directions and Maps</p>
<p type="listitem">Frequently Asked Questions</p>
<p type="listitem">History</p>
<p type="listitem">Instructions and Rules</p>
<p type="listitem">Nature</p>
<p type="listitem">Services</p>
<p type="listitem">More Information</p>
</list><p></p>
<p type="title">Destinations</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Top Natural Attractions</p>
<p type="listitem">National Parks</p>
<p type="listitem">World Heritage Sites</p>
<p type="listitem">National Hiking Areas</p>
<p type="listitem">Wilderness Areas</p>
<p type="listitem">Other Nature Sites</p>
<p type="listitem">Hiking Trails</p>
<p type="listitem">Huts</p>
<p type="listitem">Historical Sites</p>
<p type="listitem">Nature Centres</p>
<p type="listitem">Accessible Destinations</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">Hammastunturi</p>
<p type="listitem">Kaldoaivi</p>
<p type="listitem">Kemihaara</p>
<p type="listitem">Käsivarsi</p>
<p type="listitem">Muotkatunturi</p>
<p type="listitem">Paistunturi</p>
<p type="listitem">Pöyrisjärvi</p>
<p type="listitem">Pulju</p>
<p type="listitem">Tarvantovaara</p>
<p type="listitem">Tsarmitunturi</p>
<p type="listitem">Tuntsa</p>
<p type="listitem">Vätsäri</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">Activities</p>
<p type="listitem">Directions and Maps</p>
<p type="listitem">Frequently Asked Questions</p>
<p type="listitem">History</p>
<p type="listitem">Instructions and Rules</p>
<p type="listitem">Nature</p>
<p type="listitem">Services</p>
<p type="listitem">More Information</p>
</list><p></p>
<p>Tsarmitunturi Menu</p>
<p type="title">Tsarmitunturi</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Activities</p>
<p type="listitem">Directions and Maps</p>
<p type="listitem">Frequently Asked Questions</p>
<p type="listitem">History</p>
<p type="listitem">Instructions and Rules</p>
<p type="listitem">Nature</p>
<p type="listitem">Services</p>
<p type="listitem">More Information</p>
</list><p></p>
<p type="title">Activities in Tsarmitunturi Wilderness Area</p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p type="title">What can one do in Tsarmitunturi Wilderness Area?</p>
<p type="title">Go Hiking</p>
<p>There are no marked trails or other facilities in Tsarmitunturi Wilderness Area, so it is only suitable for independent hikers and hunters.For someone who is able to find his own way in the wilderness, the landscape of Tsarmitunturi offers elemental experiences.</p>
<p type="title">Ski Cross-country off Trails</p>
<p>There are no marked skiing trails or other facilities in the area, but skiers can make use of the snowmobile tracks made by the reindeer herders, where skiing is easier than in unbroken snow.</p>
<p type="title">Go Fishing</p>
<p>Angling and ice fishing are free in the lakes of the wilderness area. For lure fishing you need the fishing management fee (www.eraluvat.fi). This permit does not cover the closed areas (www.mmm.fi), which have been marked with boards on the shores.</p>
<p>The recreational fishing licence of Metsähallitus (www.eraluvat.fi), 1564 Inari fishing area, also covers the special waters mentioned above, and running waters according to the fishing area map and the permit conditions.</p>
<p>The permanent residents in the municipalities of Enontekiö, Inari and Utsjoki, who practise natural means of livelihood, fish professionally or for household use, may obtain a free fishing right for the state owned waters in the municipalities mentioned above.</p>
<p>Please note that for other methods of fishing, except angling and ice fishing, people who are 18-64 years old need to pay the fishing management fee (www.eraluvat.fi).</p>
<p>More information from Metsähallitus Customer Service in Ivalo .</p>
<p><em type="italic">The salmon parasite </em><em type="italic">(Gyrodactylus salaris) </em>has not yet spread to the valuable salmon rivers flowing to the Arctic Sea. Read more. </p>
<p type="title">Go Hunting</p>
<p>Tsarmitunturi Wilderness Area belongs to the permit area 1612 Tsarmitunturi. A limited number of small game permits a day are sold for these areas. Visitors to the wilderness area may also obtain these permits to hunt willow grouse, hare, small carnivores and water birds during the hunting season.</p>
<p>Because reindeer herding is an important source of livelihood in the area, hunting with a hound is not allowed with small game permits. There may be different restrictions in the area during different seasons due to reindeer herding work.</p>
<p>The small game permits can be obtained from Metsähallitus Customer Service in Ivalo and from Siida - Northern Lapland Nature Centre.</p>
<p>Hunting still is an important recreational activity for the local people, and the traditional game dishes are a welcome addition to the diet in many families in the north. The hills and fells of the wilderness area are a popular hunting area amoung the local people. The most important game animals for the locals in Tsarmitunturi area are the Moose <em type="italic">(Alces alces), </em>the Western Capercaillie <em type="italic">(Tetrao urogallus) </em>and the Willow Grouse <em type="italic">(Lagopus lagopus). </em>Tsarmitunturi also is a domain of the Brown bear <em type="italic">(Ursus arctos), </em>and hunters have walked countless kilometres tracing it. </p>
<p>The permanent residents of the municipalities of Enontekiö, Inari and Utsjoki have a free hunting right on the state owned lands in their municipality.</p>
<p type="title">Go Berry and Mushroom Picking</p>
<p>There are not many mires in Tsarmitunturi area, so it is not easy to find Cloudberries <em type="italic">(Rubus chamaemorus). </em>You can pick Crowberries <em type="italic">(Empetrum nigrum), </em>Lingonberries <em type="italic">(Vaccinium vitis-idaea) </em>and Blueberries <em type="italic">(Vaccinium myrtillus) </em>to add vitamins to your diet. Picking mushrooms is also allowed everywhere in the area. </p>
<p></p>
<p>© Metsähallitus 2017</p>
<list><p type="listitem"></p>
</list><p>Share This Page</p>
<p>Open Menu</p>
</body></document>
