<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>Activities In Urho Kekkonen National Park - Nationalparks.fi</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>1110</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>http://www.nationalparks.fi/en/urhokekkonennp/activities</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="aktiviteetit_inheritredirect=true_9.html"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="aktivitehtat_4.html"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>Skip to Content</p>
<p>Open Menu</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Suomeksi</p>
<p type="listitem">På svenska</p>
<p type="listitem">Anarâškielâ</p>
<p type="listitem">Davvisámegiella</p>
<p type="listitem">中文</p>
<p type="listitem">По-русски</p>
</list><p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p type="title">Urho Kekkonen National Park</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Activities</p>
<p type="listitem">Directions and Maps</p>
<p type="listitem">Frequently Asked Questions</p>
<p type="listitem">History</p>
<p type="listitem">Instructions and Rules</p>
<p type="listitem">Nature</p>
<p type="listitem">Services</p>
<p type="listitem">Sights</p>
<p type="listitem">Trails</p>
<p type="listitem">Trails from Tankavaara</p>
<p type="listitem">More Information</p>
</list><p></p>
<p type="title">Destinations</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Top Natural Attractions</p>
<p type="listitem">National Parks</p>
<p type="listitem">World Heritage Sites</p>
<p type="listitem">National Hiking Areas</p>
<p type="listitem">Wilderness Areas</p>
<p type="listitem">Other Nature Sites</p>
<p type="listitem">Hiking Trails</p>
<p type="listitem">Huts</p>
<p type="listitem">Historical Sites</p>
<p type="listitem">Nature Centres</p>
<p type="listitem">Accessible Destinations</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">Archipelago</p>
<p type="listitem">Bothnian Bay</p>
<p type="listitem">Bothnian Sea</p>
<p type="listitem">Ekenäs Archipelago</p>
<p type="listitem">Gulf of Finland</p>
<p type="listitem">Helvetinjärvi</p>
<p type="listitem">Hiidenportti</p>
<p type="listitem">Isojärvi</p>
<p type="listitem">Kauhaneva-Pohjankangas</p>
<p type="listitem">Koli</p>
<p type="listitem">Kolovesi</p>
<p type="listitem">Kurjenrahka</p>
<p type="listitem">Lauhanvuori</p>
<p type="listitem">Leivonmäki</p>
<p type="listitem">Lemmenjoki</p>
<p type="listitem">Liesjärvi</p>
<p type="listitem">Linnansaari</p>
<p type="listitem">Nuuksio</p>
<p type="listitem">Oulanka</p>
<p type="listitem">Pallas-Yllästunturi</p>
<p type="listitem">Patvinsuo</p>
<p type="listitem">Petkeljärvi</p>
<p type="listitem">Puurijärvi and Isosuo</p>
<p type="listitem">Pyhä-Häkki</p>
<p type="listitem">Pyhä-Luosto</p>
<p type="listitem">Päijänne</p>
<p type="listitem">Repovesi</p>
<p type="listitem">Riisitunturi</p>
<p type="listitem">Rokua</p>
<p type="listitem">Salamajärvi</p>
<p type="listitem">Seitseminen</p>
<p type="listitem">Sipoonkorpi</p>
<p type="listitem">Southern Konnevesi</p>
<p type="listitem">Syöte</p>
<p type="listitem">Teijo</p>
<p type="listitem">Tiilikkajärvi</p>
<p type="listitem">Torronsuo</p>
<p type="listitem">Urho Kekkonen National Park</p>
<p type="listitem">Valkmusa</p>
</list><list><p type="listitem">Activities</p>
<p type="listitem">Directions and Maps</p>
<p type="listitem">Frequently Asked Questions</p>
<p type="listitem">History</p>
<p type="listitem">Instructions and Rules</p>
<p type="listitem">Nature</p>
<p type="listitem">Services</p>
<p type="listitem">Sights</p>
<p type="listitem">Trails</p>
<p type="listitem">Trails from Tankavaara</p>
<p type="listitem">More Information</p>
</list><p></p>
<p>Urho Kekkonen Menu</p>
<p type="title">Urho Kekkonen National Park</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Activities</p>
<p type="listitem">Directions and Maps</p>
<p type="listitem">Frequently Asked Questions</p>
<p type="listitem">History</p>
<p type="listitem">Instructions and Rules</p>
<p type="listitem">Nature</p>
<p type="listitem">Services</p>
<p type="listitem">Sights</p>
<p type="listitem">Trails</p>
<p type="listitem">Trails from Tankavaara</p>
<p type="listitem">More Information</p>
</list><p></p>
<p type="title">Activities In Urho Kekkonen National Park</p>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<p>Enjoy the peace and tranquillity of fell huts, with wilderness stretching as far as the eye can see. The area's natural beauty can be experienced on long treks in the park's extensive wilderness areas, or on shorter one-day hiking or skiing trips around Saariselkä Fells. The national park is divided into the basic zone designed for daytripping, and the Saariselkä, Kemi-Sompio, and Nuortti wilderness areas suitable for longer treks.</p>
<p>Please note that hiking in the restricted areas of Pajuaapa, Repoaapa, and Lamminaapa is forbidden during the bird nesting season between 15 May and 15 July.</p>
<p type="title">Hiking</p>
<p>The extensive wilderness areas of Urho Kekkonen National Park can be explored on skis in winter and on foot in other times. Hiking outside marked trails requires wilderness and orienteering skills, and in winter the thick snow adds an additional layer of difficulty. A map and compass are necessary, since GPS devices are not always reliable in the remote wilderness. Nights can be spent at any of the many wilderness and reservation huts in the park, which are stocked with firewood. The huts are located about a day's journey apart from each other.</p>
<p>Although the routes are not marked, hikers have established trails in the park's most popular areas. Most of these trails are in terrain of average difficulty. One of the most popular unmarked routes is the Kiilopää–Suomuruoktu–Tuiskukuru–Luirojärvi–Lankojärvi–Kiilopää route (70–80 km).</p>
<list><p type="listitem">Five Days Hiking in Lapland (www.visitfinland.com)</p>
</list><p type="title">Cross-Country Skiing</p>
<p>Skiers can make day trips within a maintained ski trail network in the vicinity of Saariselkä, Kiilopää, and Kakslauttanen. The total length of maintained ski trails in the area is 200 km, of which 70 km is located in Urho Kekkonen National Park's basic zone. The length of the ski network varies depending on snowfall level. Snowfall is thickest in the early spring.</p>
<p>The network includes ski trails of various levels of difficulty to amateur skiers and serious skiing enthusiasts. Most of the ski trails are suited for both classic and skating styles. There are day trip huts and lean-tos along the routes, and these are stocked with firewood for snack breaks.</p>
<p type="title">Trekking</p>
<p>The wilderness in Urho Kekkonen National Park can also be enjoyed by hiking along marked routes. The marked hiking network (200 km) in the Saariselkä, Kiilopää, and Kakslauttanen area is good for day trips. Of the network, 70 km is located in Urho Kekkonen National Park's basic zone. Visitors can pause to rest at day trip huts and lean-tos stocked with firewood along the hiking trails. The difficulty level of the trails varies. Trails that are suitable for everyone regardless of age or level of fitness (1-7 km) are equipped with information boards that introduce local nature and culture. Nature trails are located next to Saariselkä, Kiilopää, and Tankavaara Visitor Centres. In winter, nature trails are suitable for snowshoeing.</p>
<p>Marked routes suitable for longer hikes that take several days include the Kemihaara–Korvatunturinmurusta Hiking Trail that leads towards Korvatunturi (18 km one way), Nuortti Hiking Trail that follows the Nuorttijoki canyon (a 40 km circular trail), and historical Ruijanpolku Trail (35 km one way) that passes through the Sompio Strict Nature Reserve in the south. There are wilderness huts, lean-tos, and campfire sites along the trails. The Kemihaara–Korvatunturinmurusta trail is of average difficulty, whereas the Nuortti and Ruijanpolku Trails are more demanding.</p>
<p type="title">Other Activities</p>
<list><p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Fishing: </em><list><p type="listitem"></p>
<p type="listitem"></p>
<p type="listitem"></p>
<p type="listitem"></p>
</list></p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Bird-watching: </em>Birds that can be spotted in the national park include the golden eagle, Siberian jay, willow grouse, or golden plover. There are two observation towers along the Tankavaara Nature Trails. </p>
</list><list><p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Visitor centre: </em>Tankavaara Visitor Centre Tankavaara, Saariselkä Customer Service Kiehinen and Savukoski Visitor Centre Korvatunturi provide information on the national park. Ask for hiking tips, make reservations on reservation and rental huts, and purchase fishing, hunting, and cross-country traffic permits. Permanent and temporary exhibitions, AV presentations, a shop. </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Berry and mushroom picking: </em>Berry and mushroom picking is permitted in the national park. </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Canoeing: </em>Excellent canoeing spots include Rivers Luirojoki and Kopsusjoki. There are no marked canoeing routes in the national park. </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Hunting: </em>Only local residents are allowed to hunt in Urho Kekkonen National Park within the area of the municipality of their residence, and are subject to the Hunting Act regulations. </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Sights and the views: </em>Hike to Lake Luirojärvi in the wilderness of the national park, and to Sokosti, the highest fell in the area, which rises on the eastern side of the park, Paratiisikuru or Vongoivanräystäs. Visit the clear-watered Suomujokilaakso or Korvatunturi in the border zone between Finland and Russia. There are many ways visitors can explore the local cultural heritage, for example by visiting the homesteads of the Skolt Sámi people in the northern part of the national park, the Raja-Jooseppi homestead near the Russian border, and the German defence post in Tankavaara that dates back to the Second World War. Easily reachable observation points include the top of Kiilopää and Kaunispää near the border of the national park in Saariselkä. </p>
</list><list><p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Cycling: </em>Cycling is permitted on four routes within the national park: Saariselkä–Luttotupa (Moitakuru cycling route: longer 22 km and shorter a 10 km circular route), Raja-Jooseppi‒Anteri (Anteri cycling route: 25 km one way), Kemihaara‒Mantoselkä (11 km one way), and Kemihaara‒Vieriharju (10 one way). </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Horseback riding: </em>Horseback riding is permitted in the national park on two routes: Kemihaara‒Mantoselkä (11 km one way) and Kemihaara‒Vieriharju (10 one way). </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Guided group tours: </em>Tankavaara Visitor Centre provides information on various guided tours at the visitor centre and in the wilderness. </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Swimming: </em>Swimming is permitted everywhere in the park. </p>
<p type="listitem"><em type="italic">Volunteer activities: </em>Visitors can participate in the park's operations at voluntary workers' camps, Junior Ranger camps, and various events. The park also has international volunteer activities. </p>
</list><p>© Metsähallitus 2017</p>
<list/><p>Share This Page</p>
<p>Open Menu</p>
</body></document>
