<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="science"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>359</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>orig/sme/science/uit/master/inger_dagsvold.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="inger_dagsvold.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>Summary This Master thesis concerns how to understand having cancer from how the disease is being talked, or not talked about, in Sami societies. It is in Cancer care today strongly emphasized to help those who get cancer to cope with it. Conversation; to talk about it and put word on emotions, thoughts and reactions is considered the most important method to cope with the crisis. But it is not obvious that everybody wants to talk about cancer and feelings related to that. The thesis also concerns the meetings in between the Norwegian Health Care system and Sami Cancer patients3.</p>
<p>The thesis is a qualitative study, based on a philosophical hermeneutical approach.</p>
<p>The empirical data consists of interviews with 4 Sami women, and is about their experience with and thoughts about having cancer and different ways to talk about feelings and reactions related to the disease. One of these women has experienced having cancer herself, and she has published a collection of poetry about having cancer and receive treatment for that. The collection of poetry is a part of the data material. There is also a poet and two public health workers who are interviewed about cancer and talking about cancer in Sami societies. The different data sources contribute with different perspectives on to the themes. The narrative perspective is a common theme in this thesis.</p>
<p>Having Cancer and to talk, or not to talk about it, is understood in relation to theory by the philosophers Hans-Georg Gadamer and Ludwig Wittgenstein. The focus is on understanding, historical traditions, language and the life world. In addition I make use of theory about different ways to understand disease in a historical Sami perspective.</p>
<p>The aim with the thesis is to contribute to an increased understanding on how it can feel like to experience having cancer, different ways to understand the disease and out of that, different ways to talk about and act upon having cancer in a Sami perspective.</p>
<p>Search queries: Cancer Nursing, Cancer, understanding, understanding of disease, communication, narrative, Sami, Lappish. 3</p>
<p>Because one of my informers is from Sweden, this is also about meeting the Swedish Health Care system.</p>
</body></document>
