<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>About the new coronavirus and the disease COVID-19</title><genre code="facta"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="folkhälsomyndigheten.se" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>347</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>https://www.folkhalsomyndigheten.se/contentassets/5415b804c8ac494e8abfd1b663e978da/faktablad-covid-19-engelska.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="covid_19_faktablad_finska.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="fit" location="covid_19_faktablad_meankieli.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="covid_19_faktablad_sydsamiska.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="covid_19_faktablad_nordsamiska.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="allmant_om_covid19.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 180635 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p>About the new coronavirus and the disease COVID-19 Since December 2019, a new coronavirus is spreading globally. COVID-19 is the disease caused by the new virus.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Most people experience mild illness </em>Most people experience mild symptoms such as cough and fever that will disappear on their own, but some people develop more severe illness with breathing diffi-culty and pneumonia. The virus spreads through close contact with an infected person or through respiratory droplets when an infected person coughs or sneezes. The symptoms are often mild and usually they develop about five days after exposure to the virus, but symptoms may appear earlier or later than five days. </p>
<p type="listitem">COVID-19 causes a general feeling of illness with one or more of the following symptoms:</p>
<p type="listitem">cough</p>
<p type="listitem">fever</p>
<p type="listitem">shortness of breath</p>
<p type="listitem">runny nose</p>
<p type="listitem">sore throat</p>
<p type="listitem">headache</p>
<p type="listitem">aching muscles or joints</p>
<p type="listitem">nausea.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Older people may develop more severe illness </em>Some people develop more severe symptoms, such as difficulty breathing and pneumonia. Most of those who develop severe illness are people older than 80 years of age. People with chronic heart or lung disease and people who have cancer are at higher risk of developing severe illness. </p>
<p type="listitem">Important telephone numbers</p>
<p type="listitem">Call 113 13 for general questions about COVID-19.</p>
<p type="listitem">If you are unable to care for yourself at home, please call 1177 for healthcare advice.</p>
<p><em type="bold"></em>For life-threatening situations, call 112. </p>
<p><em type="bold">Current information </em>and answers to frequently asked questions: www.folkhalsomyndigheten.se/ <em type="bold"></em>covid-19 <em type="bold"></em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Seven ways to protect yourself and others: </em>1. </p>
<p>Stay home if you are ill or have mild symptoms of disease such as sore throat, cough, or runny nose. Stay home for at least 48 hours after you have recovered. 2.</p>
<p>Wash your hands often with soap and warm water for at least 20 seconds. 3.</p>
<p>Use hand sanitiser if soap and water are not available. 4.</p>
<p>Avoid close contact with people who are ill. 5.</p>
<p>Avoid touching your eyes, nose and mouth. 6.</p>
<p>Cough and sneeze into your elbow or into a tis-sue. 7.</p>
<p>Do not visit older people if you have symptoms of illness.</p>
<p>Om det nya coronaviruset och sjukdomen covid-19 Engelska, 2020-03-13</p>
</body></document>
