<document xml:lang="eng" id="no_id"><header><title>If you are 70 or over – limit close contact with other people</title><genre code="facta"/><author><person firstname="" lastname="folkhälsomyndigheten.se" sex="unknown" born="" nationality=""/></author><year>2020</year><wordcount>512</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><origFileName>https://www.folkhalsomyndigheten.se/contentassets/0370ba3bd2cb48358e2bfc1156a32cad/faktablad-covid-19-70-ar-engelska.pdf</origFileName><parallel_text xml:lang="fin" location="faktablad_covid_19-70-ar_finska.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="fit" location="faktablad_covid_19-70-ar_meankieli.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sma" location="faktablad_covid_19-70-ar_sydsamiska.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="sme" location="faktablad_covid_19-70-ar_nordsamiska.pdf"/><parallel_text xml:lang="swe" location="faktablad_covid_19-70-ar_svenska.pdf"/><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 180635 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p>If you are 70 or over – limit close contact with other people If you are 70 or over, we recommend that you limit close contact with other people and stay at home as much as possible for a period of time. The new COVID-19 virus has developed into a pan-demic and is now spreading within Sweden. The experi-ences of China and Italy, where the virus has been spreading for a long time, show that people of 70 or over are an at-risk group.</p>
<p>It is very important that you protect yourself and others from being infected by COVID-19. By doing this, you will also be helping our medical services, which are go-ing to be under great pressure.</p>
<p><em type="bold">How to keep yourself healthy </em>We are urging people who are 70 or over to limit close contact with other people to avoid infection. You should stop using public transport and shops and stop going to places where there are lots of other people. Ask your family or neighbours to help with your food shopping or other errands. </p>
<p><em type="bold">How to avoid infecting others </em>If you are unwell, even if you only have mild symptoms, you must stay at home so that you can look after yourself and avoid infecting others. Avoid close contact with other people when you are unwell. </p>
<p><em type="bold">How to help our medical services </em>Limiting close contact with other people will mean that fewer people will fall ill, which will reduce pressure on medical services. If everyone helps by doing this, we will be supporting our medical services, which are going to have a heavy workload for a limited period of time. COVID-19 makes people feel generally unwell with one or more of the following symptoms: </p>
<p type="listitem">Keep strong – this will pass   It is normal to feel worried, uncertain, and lonely if you are having to stay away from other people.   You can help yourself feel better by doing things such as going out for walks, talking to your friends and family by phone, and keeping in touch via your computer or on so-cial media.   These restrictions on close contact with other people will be in place for a set period of time. Try to keep yourself occupied with things you enjoy doing.</p>
<p type="listitem">a cough</p>
<p type="listitem">a high temperature/fe-ver</p>
<p type="listitem">shortness of breath</p>
<p type="listitem">cold symptoms</p>
<p type="listitem">a sore throat</p>
<p type="listitem">a headache</p>
<p type="listitem">aching muscles or joints</p>
<p type="listitem">nausea</p>
<p>INFORMATION ABOUT COVID-19</p>
<p><em type="bold">Important telephone numbers </em>For general questions about COVID-19, call 113 13. For medical advice, visit Vårdguiden healthcare guide at www.1177.se or call 1177; the line is open 24 hours a day. If you feel worried, call the Äldrelinjen helpline for older people: +46 (0)20-22 22 33. Monday to Friday 0800-19.00, weekends 10.00-16.00. </p>
<p><em type="bold">At-risk groups </em>Studies relating to the COVID-19 outbreak show that the main risk factor is older age. This means that if you are 70 or over, you are in an at-risk group. Severe cases more often involve older people who also have other conditions, such as high blood pressure, cardio-vascular disease, pulmonary diseases, or diabetes. </p>
<p>Du som är 70 år eler äldre 20033-1</p>
<p>Engelska</p>
</body></document>
